<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-06-18 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-03-12 Kolbjørn: added no translation
  2005/11/03 split of from menu-layer.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-resize">
  <title>Layer Boundary Size</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Size managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Resize current layer but not its content</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer Boundary Size</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, a layer is not always the same size
    as the image it belongs to. It might be smaller or it might be larger,
    in which case some parts of it are hidden. The
    <guimenuitem>Layer Boundary Size</guimenuitem> command displays a dialog
    in which you can set the dimensions for the active layer. This command
    changes the dimensions of the layer, but it does not
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-scale">scale</link> its contents.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Layer Boundary Size</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      Description of the <quote>Layer Boundary Size</quote> dialog
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Layer Boundary Size</quote> Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/layer/boundary-size.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Layer Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Width; Height</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When the dialog is displayed, the original dimensions of
                  the active layer are shown. You can change them by using
                  the two text boxes. If these boxes are linked together
                  with a chain, the width-to-height ratio is automatically
                  maintained. If you break the chain by clicking on it, you
                  can set the dimensions independently of each other.
                </para>
                <para>
                  The default unit of measurement is pixels. You can change
                  this by using the drop-down menu. For instance, you might
                  use a <quote>%</quote> of the current size.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>X Offset; Y Offset</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  By default, the resized layer is placed in the upper left
                  corner of the image. Here, you can set the offset of the
                  upper left corner of the layer relative to the same corner
                  of the image. The default unit of measurement is pixels,
                  but you can change it by using the drop-down menu. You can
                  also place the layer in the center of the image by
                  clicking on the <guibutton>Center</guibutton> button.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
