<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-05-19 j.h: added Lanczos option
  2006-08-16 scb: revised 'en'
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-scale">
  <title>Scale Layer</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Size managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Resize current layer and its content</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Scale layer</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Scale Layer…</guimenuitem> command opens the
    <quote>Scale Layer</quote> dialog that allows you to resize the layer
    and its contents. The image loses some of its quality by being scaled.
    The command displays a dialog where you can set parameters
    concerning the size of the layer and the image quality.
  </para>
  <para>
    This command only works on a single layer.
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      Another way to scale a layer is using the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scale</link> tool with the
      <guilabel>Transform</guilabel> set to <guilabel>Layer</guilabel>.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <para>
      You can access this command
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Scale Layer…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>, you
          can access it through the <guimenuitem>Scale Layer…</guimenuitem>
          command of its context menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Description of the <quote>Scale Layer</quote> Dialog</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Scale Layer</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/layer/scale.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Layer Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you enlarge a layer, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has
            to calculate new pixels from the existing ones. This procedure
            is called <quote>interpolation</quote>. Please note that no
            matter which interpolation algorithm is used, no new information
            is added to the image by interpolation. If there are places in
            the layer which have no details, you will not get any new ones
            by scaling it. It is much more likely that the layer will look
            somewhat blurred after scaling. Similarly, when you reduce a
            layer, the image loses some of its quality when pixels are
            removed.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Width</term>
              <term>Height</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The command displays a dialog which shows the dimensions
                  of the original layer in pixels. You can set the new
                  <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and
                  <guilabel>Height</guilabel> for the layer in the two text
                  boxes. If the adjacent
                  <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-vchain.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
                      </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                  </guiicon>
                  chain icon is unbroken, the width
                  and height are automatically adjusted to hold their ratio
                  constant. If you break the chain by clicking on it, you
                  can set them separately, but this will result in
                  distorting the layer.
                </para>
                <para>
                  However, you do not have to set the dimensions in pixels.
                  You can choose different units from the drop-down menu. If
                  you choose percent as units, you can set the layer size
                  relative to its original size. You can also use physical
                  units, like inches or millimeters. However if you do that,
                  you should pay attention to the
                  <guilabel>X/Y resolution</guilabel> of the image.
                </para>
                <para>
                  If you enlarge a layer, the missing pixels are calculated
                  by interpolation, but no new details are added. The more
                  the layer is enlarged, and the more times it is enlarged,
                  the more blurred it becomes. The exact result of the
                  enlargement depends upon the interpolation method you
                  choose. After scaling, you can improve the result by using
                  the <link linkend="gimp-filter-unsharp-mask">Sharpen
                  (Unsharp Mask)</link> filter,
                  but it is much better for you to use a high resolution
                  when scanning, taking digital photographs or producing
                  digital images by other means. It is an inherent
                  characteristic of raster images that they do not scale up
                  well.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Quality</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            To change the size of the layer, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            either has to add or remove pixels. The method it uses to do
            this has a considerable impact on the quality of the result. You
            can choose the method of interpolating the colors of the pixels
            from the <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel> drop-down menu.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Interpolation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This lets you choose the interpolation method used for
                  scaling. See for details about each method the
                  <link linkend="gimp-tool-interpolation-methods">Interpolation</link>
                  documentation of the Transform tools.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
