<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-edit-cut' lang='en;de;fr'>
  <title lang="en">Cut</title>
  <title lang="de">Ausschneiden</title>
  <title lang="fr">Couper</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Cut</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Ausschneiden</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Couper</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang='en'>
    This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    or by using the keyboard shortcut
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>X</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    "Cut" deletes the contents of GIMP's selection, and
    saves them in a clipboard so that they can later be pasted using the 
    Paste , Paste Into , or Paste As New commands. If no selection is 
    made, the entire current layer will be cut.  The areas
    whose contents are cut out are left transparent if the layer has
    an alpha channel, or filled with the layer's background color
    otherwise. "Cut" only works on the current active layer. Any
    layers above or below the active one are ignored. 
  </para> 

  <para lang="de">
    Sie können Bildelemente mit dem Tastenkürzel
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Strg</keycap>
      <keycap>X</keycap>
    </keycombo> ausschneiden. 
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">Auswahlen</link> können
    sie ausschneiden und vorrübergehend von GIMP intern
    gespeichert halten. Um eine ausgeschnittene Auswahl wieder in
    ihr Bild einzufügen, benutzen Sie die <link
    linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Einfügen</link> Funktion. Haben Sie
    nichts ausgewählt, wird die gesamte Ebene ausgeschnitten.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La combinaison de
    touches 
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>X</keycap>
    </keycombo> 
    activera la fonction Couper.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    La fonction Couper permet à l'utilisateur de supprimer une 
    sélection et de la sauvegarder dans un Tampon (Buffer). 
    L'information peut-être rappelée avec les commandes Coller, Coller 
    dans, Coller en tant que nouveau. S'il n'y a pas de sélection, 
    c'est l'ensemble du calque actif qui sera coupé. 
  </para>
  <tip lang='fr'>
    Couper n'agit que sur le calque actif. Tout calque situé au-dessus 
    ou en-dessous sera ignoré. 
  </tip> 
</sect2>
