<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- Section history:

-->
<sect2 id="gimp-edit-paste" lang="cs;en;de;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>sally</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-08</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-09-09</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-09</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Vložit</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Paste</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Einfügen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Coller</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Incolla</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Lim inn</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">粘贴</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Vložit</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Paste</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Zwischenablage</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Coller</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Incolla</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Lim inn</primary></indexterm>  
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>粘贴</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> command puts whatever is in
    the Clipboard from the last <quote>Copy</quote> or <quote>Cut</quote>
    command into the current image. The pasted section becomes a
    <quote>floating selection</quote> and is shown as a separate layer in the
    Layers Dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    If there is an existing selection on the canvas, it is used to align
    the pasted data. If there is already a selection, the data is pasted
    using the selection as a center point. If you want the selection to be
    used as a clipping region for the pasted data, you should use
    the <quote>Paste Into</quote> command.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Příkaz Vložit vloží obsah schránky (schránka obsahuje data z posledního
    použití příkazu Vyjmout nebo Kopírovat) Gimpu do aktivního obrázku. Data
    jsou vložena jako plovoucí výběr, který se v dialogu Vrstvy zobrazuje jako
    samostatná vrstva.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Pokud na plátně existuje výběr, je použit k zarovnání vložených dat.
    Existující výběr je považován za střed vkládaných dat. Pokud mají být data
    vložena pouze pouze do vybrané oblasti a nikoliv mimojejí hranice, je
    nutno použít příkaz Vložit do.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Dieses Kommando fügt ein vorher kopiertes Bildobjekt aus der
    Zwischenablage in das Bild ein. Das eingefügte Objekt wird als schwebende
    Auswahl erstellt und erscheint separat im Ebenendialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Existiert eine Auswahl im aktuellen Bild, wird diese als Mittelpunkt
    benutzt, um das eingefügte Objekt zu platzieren.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La commande Coller dépose dans l'image tout ce qui est dans le
    presse-papier depuis la dernière commande Copier ou Couper. La partie
    collée sera en Sélection flottante et apparaîtra en tant que calque
    séparé dans la boîte de dialogue Calque.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    S'il y a déjà une sélection sur le canevas, le collage sera
    effectué centré sur cette sélection et il gardera sa taille. Si
    vous voulez que la sélection découpe la partie collée, utilisez la
    commande <emphasis>Copier dans</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Incolla</guimenuitem> mette qualsiasi contenuto
    degli appunti, creato dall'ultimo comando <quote>Copia</quote> o
    <quote>Taglia</quote>, nell'immagine corrente. La sezione incollata
    diventa una <quote>selezione flottante</quote> e viene mostrata come un
    livello separato nella finestra di dialogo dei livelli.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Se esiste già una selezione sull'area disegnabile, essa viene usata per
    allineare i dati incollati, usando la selezione come punto centrale. Se
    si desidera usare la selezione come area di taglio dei dati da
    incollare, è necessario usare invece il comando <quote>Incolla
    dentro</quote>.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Lim inn</guimenuitem> legg det som måtte 
    finnast på utklippstavla frå siste <quote>Kopier</quote> eller
    <quote>Klipp ut</quote> inn i biletet. Det innlimte biletet blir lagt inn som
    ei <quote>flytande markering</quote> og blir vist som eit eige lag i
    lagdialogen.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Dersom det finst ei markering i biletet frå før, vil det innlimte biletet bli
    sett inn med denne markeringa som senterpunkt. Ønskjer du at den
    eksisterande markeringa skal verke som avgrensing for det innlimte
    biletet, bruker du kommandoen <quote>Lim inn i</quote> i staden.
  </para>  

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    凡是 GIMP 剪切板上由最近一次复制或剪切命令得到的内容，都将被粘贴命令放入
    当前图像中去。粘贴部分将变为浮动选区而且作为单独的图层显示在图层对话框里。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果画布上有一个选区，它将被用来校准粘贴内容。当选择区已存在，任何粘贴部
    分将以选择区作为中心来粘贴。如果要在选择区粘贴数据，那么就得用粘贴入命令
    来完成这个工作。
  </para>

  <note>
    <para lang="en">
      You can have only <emphasis>one</emphasis> floating selection at any
      one time. You cannot work on any other layer while there is a
      floating selection; you have to either anchor it or remove it.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Současně je možno mít pouze jeden plovoucí výběr a s vrstvou není
      možno během existence plovoucího výběru pracovat.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sie können im aktuellen Bild nur <emphasis>eine</emphasis> schwebende
      Auswahl benutzen. Sobald eine schwebende Auswahl existiert, lassen sich
      keine weiteren Operationen auf andere Ebenen ausführen. Entweder
      die Auswahl wird verankert oder entfernt.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous ne pouvez avoir qu'une seule sélection flottante et vous ne
      pouvez rien faire sur un calque tant qu'il y a une sélection
      flottante.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      È possibile avere solo <emphasis>una</emphasis> selezione flottante
      alla volta. Non è possibile lavorare su qualsiasi altro livello
      quando c'è una selezione flottante; è quindi necessario prima
      áncorarla o rimuoverla.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Du kan bare ha <emphasis>ei</emphasis> flytande markering i biletet.
      Du kan heller ikkje arbeide på andre lag før du har forankra eller fjerna
      den flytande markeringa.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您只能一次有一个浮动选区。当有浮动选区时，就不能在图层上工作。
    </para>
  </note>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz je dostupný z nabídky obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem>Upravit</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Vložit...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>aste</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Bearbeite<accel>n</accel></guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>E<accel>i</accel>nfügen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Éditer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>oller</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem><accel>M</accel>odifica</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem><accel>I</accel>ncolla</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Rediger</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Lim inn</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          这个命令可以在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;编辑/粘贴</guimenuitem>找到。
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="cs">
          Klávesová zkratka
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo>
          vyvolá příkaz Vložit.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando lässt sich ebenfalls mit einem Tastenkürzel aufrufen:
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Strg</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          ou par le raccourci-clavier
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          o usando la scorciatoia da tastiera
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          eller med snarvegen
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycap>Ctrl+V</keycap>是粘贴的快捷键。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
