<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-11 KoSt: added 'no'
  2006-07-29 lexa: patch from julien that includes suggestions by Sally
  2005-09-09 de added; reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-edit-clear" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-28</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-28</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-11</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Clear</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Vymazat</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Löschen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Effacer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Cancella</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Tøm markeringa</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Очистить</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">清除</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Clear</secondary>
    <tertiary>Clear layer content</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selection</primary>
    <secondary>Clear selection content</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Clear</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Vymazat</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Löschen</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Effacer</secondary>
    <tertiary>Effacer le contenu du calque</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélection</primary>
    <secondary>Effacer le contenu de la sélection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Effacer</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Cancella</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Tøm markeringa</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Очистить</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>清除</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Clear</guimenuitem> command deletes everything
    in the current selection. If there is no current selection,
    the contents of the active layer are removed. If the active
    layer has an alpha channel, the deleted selection is made
    transparent. You can restore the original color to the transparent
    area using the Eraser tool, by setting it to Anti-Erase. If the
    layer does not have an alpha channel, the deleted area is
    filled using the current background color.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Clearing a selection does not delete the selection itself. Unlike
    <quote>Cut</quote>, <quote>Clear</quote> does not place the deleted
    contents in the Clipboard and the contents of the clipboard are unaffected.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Funkce Vymazat maže obsah aktuálního výběru. Pokud není žádný aktivní
    výběr, je odstraněn celý obsah aktivní vrstvy. Má-li aktivní vrstva
    nastavený alfa kanál, vymazaná oblast se stane transparentní. Vymazanou
    barvu lze z transaparentní oblasti obnovit gumou v opačném režimu. Pokud
    vrstva alfa kanál nemá, je vymazaná oblast vyplněna barvou pozadí.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Funkce Vymazat nesmaže výběr jako takový, ale pouze jeho obsah. Na
    rozdíl od funkce Vyjmout, funkce Vymazat neumístí vymazaný obsah do
    schránky. Původní obsah schránky zůstane nezměněn.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie den Inhalt der Auswahl im aktuellen Bild
    löschen. Falls sich im Bild keine Auswahl befindet, wird der Inhalt der
    aktuellen Ebene gelöscht. Falls die aktive Ebene einen Alphakanal
    (Transparenz) hat, wird die Stelle im Bild, an der sich die Auswahl
    befindet, nach dem Löschen transparent. Sie können die Originalfarben mit
    dem Radierer wiederherstellen, indem Sie die Eigenschaft
    <guilabel>Un-Radieren</guilabel> aktivieren. Wenn die Ebene keinen
    Alphakanal hat, wird der gelöschte Bereich mit der aktuellen
    Hintergrundfarbe gefüllt.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Dieses Kommando löscht lediglich den <emphasis>Inhalt</emphasis> der
    Auswahl, die Auswahl selbst bleibt erhalten. Der Inhalt der Zwischenablage
    wird durch die Ausführung des Kommandos nicht verändert.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La commande Effacer permet à l'utilisateur de supprimer tout ce
    qui est à l'intérieur d'une sélection active. S'il n'y a pas de
    sélection active, c'est tout le calque qui sera effacé. Si le
    calque actif possède un canal Alpha, la sélection effacée sera
    rendue transparente. La couleur d'origine peut alors être rétablie
    à l'aide de la Gomme, à condition que l'option Anti-effacement
    soit cochée. S'il n'y a pas de canal Alpha, l'aire effacée sera
    remplie avec la couleur d'Arrière-plan de la Boîte à outils.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le fait d'effacer une sélection ne touche qu'au contenu de la
    sélection et non pas à l'existence de la sélection.
    À la différence de Couper, le contenu effacé n'est pas envoyé dans
    le presse-papier.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Cancella</guimenuitem> elimina ogni contenuto
    della selezione corrente. Se non c'è una selezione, viene rimosso
    l'intero contenuto del livello attivo. Se il livello attivo possiede un
    canale alfa, la selezione cancellata viene resa trasparente. È
    possibile ripristinare il colore originale dell'area trasparente usando
    lo strumento Cancellino, impostandolo su Anti-Gomma. Se il livello non
    possiede un canale alfa, l'area decancellata viene riempita dal colore
    dello sfondo corrente.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    L'operazione di cancellazione della selezione non elimina la selezione
    in se ma solo il suo contenuto e, diversamente da <quote>Taglia</quote>,
    <quote>Cancella</quote> non piazza i contenuti cancellati negli appunti
    ed quindi i contenuti degli appunti non vengono modificati.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Tøm markeringa</guimenuitem> fjernar alt
    i den aktive markeringa. Dersom ingenting er markert, vil innhaldet i det
    aktive laget bli tatt bort. Viss det aktive laget inneheld ein alfakanal, vil
    det tømte området bli gjennomsiktig. Du kan gjenskapa originalfargen i
    det gjennomsiktige området ved å bruke viskeleret sett til <quote>Visk
    inn</quote>. Har laget ingen alfakanal, blir det tømte arealet fyllt med
    gjeldande bakgrunnsfarge.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Å tømme ei markering fjernar ikkje sjølve markeringa. I motsetnad til
    <quote>Klipp ut</quote>, legg <quote>Tøm markeringa</quote> heller
    ikkje det fjerna området på utklippstavla. Utklippstavla er uforandra.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Эта команда расположена в
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Правка</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Очистить</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Функция очистки даёт пользователю удалить всё содержимое
    внутри текущего выделения. Если выделения нет, будет
    удалено содержимое активного слоя. Если активный слой
    имеет альфа канал, удалённое выделение станет прозрачным.
    Оригинальный цвет может быть восстановлен до прозрачной области
    с помощью инструмента Ластик если он установлен в режим антиластик.
    Если слой не имеет альфа канала, удалённая область будет залита
    текущим цветом фона.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Очистка выделения не удаляет непосредственно выделение.
    В отличии от вырезания, очистка не помещает удалённое
    содержимое в буфер и содержимое буфера не изменяется.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    这个清除功能允许用户删除包含在当前选择区的任何东西。如果没有当前选区，那
    么就删除包含在激活的图层内的所有内容。如果激活的图层是 Alpha 通道，那么
    删除的选择区就是透明的。如果橡皮工具设置为反擦除，那么可以用橡皮工具将透
    明区恢复成原来的色彩。如果图层没有 Alpha 通道，删除的区域将会被当前的背
    景色填充。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    清除一个选择区不会删除选择区本身。与剪切不同，清除将不会把删除的内容放入
    剪贴板，剪贴板中的内容不受影响。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Активация команды</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Cl<accel>e</accel>ar</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
          <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz lze najít v nabídce
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Upravit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Vymazat</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Bearbeite<accel>n</accel></guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>L</accel>öschen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Cette commande se trouve dans
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>É</accel>dition</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>ffacer</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
         </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>M</accel>odifica</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canc<accel>e</accel>lla</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Rediger</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Tøm markeringa</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
         <para lang="ru">
           Эта команда доступна через меню изображения
           <menuchoice>
             <guimenu><accel>П</accel>равка</guimenu>
             <guimenuitem><accel>О</accel>чистить</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          这个命令可以在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;编辑/清除</guimenuitem>找到.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Funkci Vymazat lze vyvolat také klávesovou zkratkou
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Außerdem können Sie Bildelemente mit dem Tastenkürzel
          <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>
          löschen.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Vous pouvez aussi appeler la fonction Effacer avec le
          raccourci-clavier
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          o usando la scorciatoia da tastiera
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          eller med snarvegen
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          или с помощью клавиши быстрого доступа
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo>
          将调用撤销功能。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
