<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-edit-paste-as-new' lang="cs;en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Vložit jako nový</title>
  <title lang="en">Paste as New</title>
  <title lang='de'>Als neues Bild einfügen</title>
  <title lang="fr">Coller en tant que nouveau</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">粘贴为新图像</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">Vložit jako nový obrázek</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Paste as new</primary>
    <primary lang='de'>Als neues Bild einfügen</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Coller en tant que nouveau</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">粘贴为新图像</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect lang='cs'>
    <title>Přehled</title>
    <para>
      Tento příkaz je dostupný z nabídky obrázku volbou
      <guimenuitem>Upravit</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Vložit jako nový obrázek</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Data vložená ze schránky příkazem Vložit jako nový obrázek vytvoří nový
      obrázek v novém okně obsahující data ze schránky. Pokud vložená obrazová
      data netvoří čtverec nebo obdélník, jsou doplněna průhlednými oblastmi.
      Obrazová data musíte před použitím příkazu do schránky zkopírovat nebo
      vyjmout. Příkaz se hodí pro vytvoření nového obrázku s rozměry přesně
      odpovídasjícími rozměrům výběru.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang='en'>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Paste as <accel>N</accel>ew...</guimenuitem>.     
    </para>
    <para>
      Any data that is pasted from the Clipboard using the Paste As New 
      command will create a new image that contains the pasted data. 
      If the data that is pasted is not contained within a rectangle or 
      a square area, any regions that cannot reach the canvas boundary 
      are left transparent. Of course, you must Copy your selection 
      before using this command which allows you to get an image with 
      the same dimensions as the selection.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang='de'>
    <title>Allgemeines</title>
    <para>
      Diese Funktion erreichen Sie über das Bildmenü:
      <guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>/
      <guimenuitem>Einfügen</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Jedes Bildobjekt welches mit <guimenuitem>Als neues Bild
      einfügen</guimenuitem> aus der Zwischenablage eingefügt wird,
      bekommt ein eigenens Bildfenster.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="fr">
    <title>Vue d'ensemble</title>
    <para>
      (Révision 050601)
      On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image par 
      <guimenuitem>Éditer</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Copier en tant que <accel>N</accel>ouveau...</guimenuitem>.     
    </para>
    <para>
      Avec cette commande, tout ce qui est dans le presse-papier sera 
      collé dans une nouvelle image créée pour l'occasion. Si les 
      données collées ne remplissent pas complètement le canevas parce 
      qu'elles ne sont pas rectangulaires, les espaces vides seront 
      laissés transparents. Bien entendu, une sélection devra être 
      copiée avant d'utiliser cette commande, qui permet d'avoir une 
      image aux dimensions exactes de la sélection.          
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="zh_CN">
    <title>概述</title>
    <para>
      这个命令可以在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;编辑/粘贴为新图像</guimenuitem>找到。
    </para>         
    <para>
      粘贴为新图像命令就是将剪贴板的内容做成新图像。如果粘贴的图像不是矩形或正方形，那么底图中粘贴数据没覆盖的部分保持透明。当然，在使用这个命令前，您必须先选择您的复制区域，这样才能允许您得到一个和选择区大小一致的图像。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
