<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-edit-paste' lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Paste</title>
  <title lang='de'>Einfügen</title>
  <title lang="fr">Coller</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">粘贴</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Paste</primary>
    <primary lang='de'>Einfügen</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Coller</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">粘贴</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect lang="en">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>aste...</guimenuitem>.     
    </para>
    <para>
      The Paste command puts whatever is in The GIMP Clipboard from the 
      last Copy or Cut command into the current image. The pasted 
      section will be placed as a Floating Selection and is shown as a 
      separate layer in the Layers Dialog . 
    </para>
    <para>
      If there is an existing selection on the canvas, it will be used 
      to align the pasted data. Any data pasted when a selection 
      already exists will be pasted using the selection as a center 
      point. If the selection is to be used as a clipping region for the 
      pasted data, this can be achieved by using the Paste Into command. 
    </para>
    <note> 
      <para>
        You can only have one floating selection at any one time and 
        cannot work on a layer while there is a floating selection. 
      </para>
    </note>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang='de'>
    <title lang='de'>Allgemeines</title>
    <para>
      Diese Funktion erreichen Sie über das Bildmenü:
      <guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>/
      <guimenuitem>Einfügen</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Die "Einfügen" Funktion fügt ein vorher kopiertes Bildobjekt aus der
      Zwischenablage in das Bild ein. Das eingefügte Objekt wird als
      schwebende Auswahl erstellt und erscheint seperat im Ebenendialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      Existiert eine Auswahl im aktuellen Bild, wird diese als
      Mittelpunkt benutzt, in der das eingefügte Objekt plaziert wird.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Sie können im aktuellen Bild nur eine schwebende Auswahl
        benutzen. Sobald eine schwebende Auswahl existiert, lassen sich
        keine weiteren Operationen auf andere Ebenen ausführen. Entweder
        die Auswahl wird verankert oder entfernt.
      </para>
    </note>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="fr">
    <para>
      Cette commande se trouve dans 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Édition/C<accel>o</accel>ller...</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
      La commande Coller dépose dans l'image tout ce qui est dans le 
      presse-papier depuis la dernière commande Copier ou Couper. 
      La partie collée sera en Sélection flottante et apparaîtra en tant 
      que calque séparé dans la boîte de dialogue Calque.
    </para>
    <para>
      S'il y a déjà une sélection sur le canevas, le collage sera 
      effectué centré sur cette sélection et il gardera sa taille. Si 
      vous voulez que la sélection découpe la partie collée, utilisez la 
      commande <emphasis>Copier dans</emphasis>
    </para>    
    <note>
      <para>
        Vous ne pouvez avoir qu'une seule sélection flottante et vous ne
        pouvez rien faire sur un calque tant qu'il y a une sélection
        flottante.   
      </para>
    </note>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="zh_CN">
    <title>概述</title>
    <para>
      这个命令可以在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;编辑/粘贴</guimenuitem>找到。
    </para>
         
    <para>
      凡是 GIMP 剪切板上由最近一次复制或剪切命令得到的内容，都将被粘贴命令放入当前图像中去。粘贴部分将变为浮动选区而且作为单独的图层显示在图层对话框里。
    </para>

    <para>
      如果画布上有一个选区，它将被用来校准粘贴内容。当选择区已存在，任何粘贴部分将以选择区作为中心来粘贴。如果要在选择区粘贴数据，那么就得用粘贴入命令来完成这个工作。 
    </para>

    <note> 
      <para>
	您只能一次有一个浮动选区。当有浮动选区时，就不能在图层上工作。 
      </para>
    </note>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Shortcut</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturkürzel</title>
    <title lang="fr">Raccourcis clavier</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">快捷键</title>
      <para lang="en">
        The <keycap>Ctrl+V</keycap>
        will call the Undo function
      </para>

      <para lang='de'>
        Die Tastenkombination 
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Strg</keycap>
          <keycap>V</keycap>
        </keycombo>
        ruft die Einfügen Funktion auf.
      </para>
        
      <para lang="fr">
        La combinaison de touches <keycap>Ctrl+V</keycap>
        activera la fonction Annuler.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <keycap>Ctrl+V</keycap>是粘贴的快捷键。
      </para>

  </simplesect>

</sect2>
