<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-11-23 ciampix: added Italian translation
  2007-10-26 ude: added German translation
  2007-10-15 j.h : created (inpired from the Gimp Developers site)
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-edit-fade" lang="en;es;de;fr;it;no">
  <sect2info lang="en;es;de;fr;it;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-15</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-26</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-11-22</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-15</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="it">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-11-23</date>
        <authorinitials>ciampix</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-11-27</date>
        <authorinitials>kost</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Fade...</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Verblassen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fondu...</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Sfuma...</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Ton inn/ut</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Fade</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Verblassen</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Fondu</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Sfuma</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Tone inn/ut</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    This command is usually grayed out. It becomes active if you use the Fill
    function or the Blend tool, or if you apply some filters.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    It allows you to modify the paint mode and opacity of the
    <emphasis>last</emphasis> drawable operation (Fill, Blend, Filter) by
    creating a blend between the current state of the layer and the previous
    state. It performs the following operations: copy the active drawable,
    undo the last action, paste the copy as a new layer, set its
    <quote>Opacity</quote>, and merge both new layer and previously active
    drawable.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Dieser Befehl ist meistens inaktiv und ausgegraut. Er wird aktiv, wenn Sie
    die Werkzeuge <quote>Füllen</quote> oder <quote>Farbverlauf</quote>
    verwenden, oder nach der Anwendung bestimmter Filter auf das Bild.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Er ermöglicht Ihnen, den Modus und die Deckkraft der
    <emphasis>letzten</emphasis> Zeichenoperation (Füllen, Farbverlauf,
    Filter) zu verändern, indem ein Übergang vom vorigen zum aktuellen Zustand
    der Ebene geschaffen wird. Dabei werden folgende Operationen durchgeführt:
    die aktuelle Zeichenfläche wird kopiert und die letzte Aktion
    zurückgenommen, die Kopie wird als neue Ebene eingefügt,
    <quote>Deckkraft</quote> und <quote>Modus</quote> wird wie angegeben
    gesetzt, und schließlich wird diese Ebenen mit der vorher aktiven
    Zeichenfläche vereint.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    Este comando está normalmente deshabilitado. Se habilita cuando se usa
    las funciones de relleno o mezcla, o cuando se aplica algún filtro.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Permite modificar el modo de pintar y la opacicidad de la 
    <emphasis>última</emphasis> operación (relleno, mezcla, filtro),
    creando una mezcla entre el estado de la capa y su estado anterior.
    Realiza las siguientes operaciones: copia el dibujable activo, deshace
    la última acción, pega la copia como una capa nueva, selecciona su 
    <quote>Opacidad</quote>, y mezcla la capa nueva y el dibujable
    previamente activo.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande est habituellement en grisé. Elle s'active si vous
    utilisez la fonction Remplir ou l'outil Dégradé, ou si vous appliquez
    certains filtres.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Elle vous permet de modifier le mode de peinture et l'opacité de la
    <emphasis>dernière</emphasis> opération de peinture en réalisant une
    fusion entre l'état actuel d'un objet de dessin (calque ou sélection) et
    son état antérieur. Elle effectue en fait la série d'opérations
    suivantes : copie de l'objet de dessin, annulation de la dernière
    opération, collage de la copie en tant que nouveau calque, réglage de
    l'<quote>Opacité</quote> et fusion entre l'objet de dessin et le
    nouveau calque.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Questo comando è normalmente disabilitato e mostrato con un colore
    grigio pallido. Diventa attivo se si usa la funzione di riempimento, il
    comando sfuma o se si applicano alcuni filtri.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Esso permette di modificare la modalità di disegno e l'opacità
    dell'<emphasis>ultima</emphasis> operazione disegnabile (riempimento,
    sfumatura, filtro) creando una sfumatura tra lo stato corrente del
    livello e lo stato precedente. Effettua le seguenti operazioni:
    copiatura dell'area disegnabile, annullamento dell'ultima operazione,
    incollamento della copia come nuovo livello, impostazione della sua
    <quote>opacità</quote>, e fusione assieme del nuovo livello e della
    precedente area disegnabile.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="no">
    Denne kommandoen er bare aktivert når du bruker fyllfunksjonen,
    blandeverktøyet. Dessutan for noen av filtra.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen gjer at du kan endra teiknemodus og dekkevne for
    den <emphasis>sist</emphasis> utførte teikneoperasjonen (fyll,
    bland, filter) ved å opprette ein fargeovergang mellom den
    nåverande og den tidlegare tilstanden til laget. Dette blir gjort ved
    å kopiere det aktive teikneorådet, angre siste operasjon og lime
    inn kopien som eit nytt lag. Deretter blir dekkevna for det nye laget
    set før laget blir fletta saman med teikneområdet igjen.
  </para>

  <sect3 lang="en;es;de;fr;it;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el diálogo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Dialogaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation du dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione finestra di dialogo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      You can get to this command from the image Menu bar through:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fade...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sie können dieses Kommando über das Bildmenü aufrufen:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Verblassen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Editar</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Desvanecer...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menus de l'image par
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Édition</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fondu...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu immagine
      tramite: 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Modifica</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sfuma...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Du har tilgang til denne kommandoen frå biletmenyen via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Rediger</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ton inn/ut</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingar</phrase>
    </title>
    <para lang="en">
      This command brings up a dialog window:
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Kommando öffnet folgendes Dialogfenster:
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Este comando abre una ventana de diálogo:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cette commande ouvre une fenêtre de dialogue :
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questo comando porta in primo piano una finestra di dialogo:
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Kommandoen opnar eit dialogvindauge:
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">The <quote>Fade</quote> dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Ansicht des Dialoges <quote>Verblassen</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">El diálogo <quote>Desvanecer</quote></phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La fenêtre de dialogue <quote>Fondu</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          La finestra di dialogo <quote>sfuma</quote></phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Dialogen for <quote>Ton inn/ut</quote></phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/edit-fade-options.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/edit-fade-options.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/es/edit-fade-options.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/edit-fade-options.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/it/edit-fade-options.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/edit-fade-options.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mode</term>
        <term lang="de">Modus</term>
        <term lang="es">Modo</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
        <term lang="it">Modalità</term>
        <term lang="no">Modus</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This drop-down list allows you to choose a
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Layer merge mode</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Dieses Klappmenü ermöglicht Ihnen die Auswahl eines
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Ebenenmodus</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Esta lista desplegable permite elegir un 
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Modo de mezcla de capas</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette liste déroulante vous permet de choisir un
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Mode de fusion des
              calques</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo menu a discesa permette di scegliere tra diverse
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">modalità di fusione
            di livelli</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Denne nedtrekkslista inneheld ulike <link
            linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">lagmodus</link> som du kan
            bruke.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
        <term lang="de">Deckkraft</term>
        <term lang="es">Opacidad</term>
        <term lang="fr">Opacité</term>
        <term lang="it">Opacità</term>
        <term lang="no">Dekkevne</term>

<!-- here the english text is missing the effect of rising the slider value -->
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider value is initially set to the opacity of the color
            you used with the Fill or Blend tool, which corresponds to
            the current state. Lowering the opacity to 0 changes the drawable
            to its previous state. Intermediate values produce a mixture of
            the two according to the mode you have choosen. The effect of
            this setting is visible in real time in the image, but you have
            to click on the <guibutton>Fade</guibutton> button to validate
            it.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Dieser Schieberegler ist mit der Deckkraft der Farbe
            initialisiert, die Sie für das Werkzeug <quote>Füllen</quote> oder
            <quote>Farbverlauf</quote> verwendet haben. Das entspricht dem
            aktuellen Zustand. Wenn Sie die Deckkraft auf 0 heruntersetzen,
            haben Sie den vorherigen Zustand hergestellt. Werte dazwischen
            führen zu einer Vermischung der beiden Zustände entsprechend dem
            gewählten Modus. Die Auswirkung der jeweiligen Einstellung ist
            unmittelbar sichtbar, aber die Aktion muss noch mit einem Klick
            auf die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Verblassen</guibutton>
            abgeschlossen werden, bevor sie tatsächlich angewendet wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            El valor del deslizador inicialmente selecciona el color usado
            con la herramienta de relleno o mezcla, que se corresponde con
            el estado actual. Bajando la opacidad a 0 cambia el dibujable
            a su estado anterior. Un valor intermedio produce una mezcla
            de ambos según el modo seleccionado. El efecto de esta
            selección es visible en tiempo real en la imagen, pero se
            tiene que pulsar sobre el botón
            <guibutton>Desvanecer</guibutton> para validarlo.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La valeur initiale de ce curseur est l'opacité de la couleur
            utilisée avec l'outil Remplir ou Dégradé, correspondant à l'état
            actuel. En abaissant l'opacité à 0, on remet l'objet de dessin
            dans son état antérieur. Les valeurs intermédiaires produisent un
            mélange des deux selon le mode choisi. L'effet du réglage est
            visible en temps réel sur l'image, mais vous devez cliquer sur
            le bouton <guibutton>Fondu</guibutton> pour le valider.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il valore di questo cursore è inizialmente impostato
            all'opacità del colore utilizzato per lo strumento di
            riempimento o di sfumatura, che corrisponde allo stato
            corrente.  Abbassando l'opacità a 0 riporta l'area disegnabile
            al suo stato precedente. Valori intermedi producono un effetto
            itermedio a seconda della modalità scelta. L'effetto di questa
            impostazione è visibile in tempo reale sull'immagine ma è
            necessario fare clic sul pulsante <guibutton>sfuma</guibutton>
            per confermare la scelta.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Denne glidebrytaren styrer dekkevna til fargen brukt av
            fyll- eller fargeovergangsverktøyet. Låge verdiar gjer at den
            opphavlege teikninga blir meir synleg, medan høge verdiar gjer
            resultatet av verktøybruken meir synleg. Verknaden er avhengig
            av kva modus du har vald for flettinga. Effekten er synleg i
            førehandsvisinga, men blir ikkje overført til biletet før du
            trykker knappen <guibutton>Uttoning</guibutton>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
