<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-file-revert' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">

  <title lang='en'>Revert</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Revenir</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">恢复</title>

  <para lang='en'>
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    It does not have a default shortcut.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette commande est accessible depuis le
    menu de la fenêtre d'image
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Revenir</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    Il n'y a pas de raccourci clavier par défaut.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该命令在图像菜单的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>恢复</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>。
    它没有默认的快捷键。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    "Revert" causes the image to be reloaded from disk, so that it
    will look just like it did the last time it was saved---unless,
    that is, the file has in the meantime been overwritten by you or
    some application other than GIMP, in which case the new contents
    will be loaded.  For technical reasons, when GIMP reverts a
    file, it actually closes the existing image and creates a new
    image.  Because of this, reverting an image is not undoable, and
    causes the undo history of the image to be lost.  GIMP tries to
    protect you from losing your work in this way by asking you to
    confirm that you really want to revert the image.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Revenir fait que l'image est rechargée depuis le disque pour
    qu'elle soit réaffichée de façon identique à ce qu'elle était
    lors de la précédente sauvegarde. Pour des raisons techniques
    actuellement Gimp ferme l'image à recharger puis ouvre une
    nouvelle fenêtre avec l'image rechargée. À cause de celà
    il n'est pas possible d'annuler un tel rechargement et tout
    l'historique d'annulation sera perdu. Une confirmation vous
    sera demandée pour éviter de perdre accidentellement votre
    travail.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “恢复”使图像从磁盘被重新读取，这样它就和最后一次保存时相同---除非该文件其后又被您或 GIMP 外的其它程序改写了，这时就会载入新内容。在技术上来讲，GIMP 恢复一个文件实际是关闭已存在的图像并新建一个图像。所有恢复文件不可撤销，并且会使图像的撤销历史丢失。GIMP 为了避免您丢失成果会询问您是否确认要恢复图像。
  </para>
   
</sect2>

