<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-file-quit' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Quit</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Quitter</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">退出</title>

  <anchor id='gimp-file-quit-confirm' />

  <para lang='en'>
    This command can be accessed from the Toolbox or an image
    menubar as  
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    or by using the keyboard shortcut
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Q</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    In most environments, it can also be executed by clicking a "Close"
    button somewhere on the Toolbox window.  The location and
    appearance of this button are determined by the windowing system
    and window manager. 
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette commande est accessible depuis la boîte à outils ou le
    menu de la fenêtre d'image
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Quitter</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    ou en utilisant le raccourci clavier
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Q</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    Dans la plupart des environnements il peut aussi être exécuté en
    cliquant sur le bouton Quitter de la boîte à outils.
    L'apparence et la position de ce bouton est déterminée par
    le gestionnaire de fenêtres.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该命令在工具箱或图像菜单的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>退出</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>，或使用快捷键
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Q</keycap>
    </keycombo>。它也可以通过点击工具箱窗口某处的一个“关闭”按钮执行。该按钮的位置和外型有窗口系统和窗口管理器决定。
  </para>


  <para lang='en'>
    "Quit" causes GIMP to close all images and exit.  If there are
    any images open that are not marked as "clean", you are notified
    of this and given an opportunity to cancel the action.  (In GIMP
    2.2., you are given a list of the unsaved images and asked which
    of them, if any, you would like to save before quitting.)  Note
    that if you have a large number of images open, or are using a
    large proportion of the RAM on your system, it may take a little
    while for everything to shut down.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Quitter va fermer toutes les images et l'application Gimp. S'il
    y a des images modifiées non enregistrées vous en serez informé
    et vous pourrez annuler votre action. Depus Gimp 2.2 une liste 
    des fichiers modifiés est affichée qui vous permet de sélectionner
    indivisuellement les fichiers à enregsitrer. Notez bien que si
    avez beaucoup d'images ouvertes simultanément il peut se passer
    un temps significatif avant que tout soit enregistré.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “退出”使 GIMP 关闭所有图像并退出。如果有任何打开着的“脏的”图像，您会被提醒并给您一个取消该动作的机会。(在 GIMP 中，会提供给您一个未保存图像的列表并询问是否在退出保存它们。)要注意的是，如果有大量打开的文件，或使用了系统上大量 RAM，就需要一段时间使所有图像关闭。
  </para>
</sect2>
  
