<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<!-- 2005/09/07 de added and reviewed by axel.wernicke -->
<sect2 id='gimp-file-revert' lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang='en'>Revert</phrase>
    <phrase lang='cs'>Navrátit</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Zurücksetzen</phrase>
    <phrase lang='fr'>Revenir</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">恢复</phrase>
  </title>

  <para lang='en'>
    "Revert" causes the image to be reloaded from disk, so that it
    will look just like it did the last time it was saved---unless,
    that is, the file has in the meantime been overwritten by you or
    some application other than GIMP, in which case the new contents
    will be loaded.
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Volba "Navrátit..." způsobí, že je obrázek znovu nahrán z disku,
    takže vypadá přesně tak, jak byl naposledy uložen - kromě případu,
    kdy byl obrázek v době od posledního uložení přepsán jinou aplikací
    než GIMP - bude tedy nahrán nový obsah.
    Z technických důvodů GIMP při navracení původního obsahu uzavře 
    stávající okno a obrázek znovu otevře. Proto se nelze dále vracet
    v historii úprav a její obsah je smazán.
    Při vyvolání funkce "Navrátit" se GIMP pokouší zabránit ztrátě dat
    požadavkem potvrzení, zdali opravdu chcete navrátit původní obrázek.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie ein geöffnetes Bild neu laden, also alle
    Bearbeitungsschritte seit dem letzten Speichern rückgängig machen. Wenn
    Sie diese Aktion ausführen wird <application>GIMP</application> das
    aktuelle Bildfenster schließen und die zugehörige Bilddatei in einem
    neuen Fenster laden.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Revenir fait que l'image est rechargée depuis le disque pour
    qu'elle soit réaffichée de façon identique à ce qu'elle était
    lors de la précédente sauvegarde. Pour des raisons techniques
    actuellement Gimp ferme l'image à recharger puis ouvre une
    nouvelle fenêtre avec l'image rechargée. À cause de cela
    il n'est pas possible d'annuler un tel rechargement et tout
    l'historique d'annulation sera perdu. Une confirmation vous
    sera demandée pour éviter de perdre accidentellement votre
    travail.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “恢复”使图像从磁盘被重新读取，这样它就和最后一次保存时相同---除非该文件其后又被您或 GIMP 外的其它程序改写了，这时就会载入新内容。在技术上来讲，GIMP 恢复一个文件实际是关闭已存在的图像并新建一个图像。所有恢复文件不可撤销，并且会使图像的撤销历史丢失。GIMP 为了避免您丢失成果会询问您是否确认要恢复图像。
  </para>
  
  <warning lang="en;de">
    <para lang="en">
      For technical reasons, when <application>GIMP</application> reverts a
      file, it actually closes the existing image and creates a new
      image.  Because of this, reverting an image is not undoable, and
      causes the undo history of the image to be lost.
      <application>GIMP</application> tries to protect you from losing your
      work in this way by asking you to confirm that you really want to
      revert the image.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Bitte beachten Sie, dass dieses Kommando nicht
      rückgängig gemacht werden kann und das Journal der letzten Änderungen
      verloren geht. <application>GIMP</application> warnt Sie daher, wenn
      Sie versuchen ein Bild neu zu laden, welches ungespeicherte Änderungen
      beinhaltet.
    </para>
  </warning>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Re<accel>v</accel>ert</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          It does not have a default shortcut.
        </para>
        <para lang='cs'>
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Navrátit...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Tato volba není standardně přiřazena žádné klávese.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>urücksetzen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Cette commande est accessible depuis le
          menu de la fenêtre d'image
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>evenir</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Il n'y a pas de raccourci clavier par défaut.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>恢复</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
          它没有默认的快捷键。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
