<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-02-07 Added 'no' by KoSt
  2006-02-26 j.h:  Added Right click -> Open location-Changed left pannel en;fr
  2005/10/18 zh_CN removed by romanofski - missing translation
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-file-open">
  <sect2info role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  <title>
    <phrase>Open</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Open</secondary>
    <tertiary>Open an image</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Open</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> command activates a dialog that
    lets you load an
    existing image from your hard-drive or an external medium.  For
    alternative, and sometimes more convenient, ways of opening files,
    see the <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Files</link> section.
  </para>
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase>Activate Dialog</phrase>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access the <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> dialog
          from the toolbox window or from an image window through:
          <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can also open the Dialog by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase>File browsing</phrase>
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>Open Dialog</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/file-open-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Places</guilabel> panel is divided into two parts.
          The upper part lists your main directories and your storage
          devices; you cannot modify this list. The lower part lists your
          bookmarks; you can add or remove <emphasis>bookmarks</emphasis>. To
          add a bookmark, select a directory the middle panel   and click on
          the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button at the bottom of the left
          panel. You can also use the <guilabel>Add to bookmarks</guilabel>
          command in the context menu, which you get by clicking the
          right mouse button. You can delete a bookmark by selecting
          it and clicking on the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="open-files">
        <para>
          The middle <guilabel>Name</guilabel> panel displays a list of the
          files in the current directory. Change your current directory by
          double left clicking on a directory in this panel. Select a file
          with a single left click. You can then open the file you have
          selected by  clicking on the <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button.
          Note that a double left click opens the file directly; if you have
          selected a file different from the current one, a message warns you
          before <acronym>GIMP</acronym> overwrites your work.
        </para>
        <para><!--TODO it; v2.4-->
          Right clicking on the middle panel pops up a sub-menu with two
          options:
          <itemizedlist><listitem><para><guilabel>Add to Bookmarks</guilabel>: add the selected
                entry to the left panel.
              </para></listitem><listitem><para><guilabel>Show Hidden Files</guilabel>: some files are not
                shown, for example if their name starts with a dot
                (Unix/Linux). This command makes them visible.
              </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
          The <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          key combination toggles a <guilabel>Location</guilabel> bar under
          the path bar. If you type first letters of file name, then a list of
          files whose name begin with these letters is shown.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The selected image is displayed in the <guilabel>Preview
          </guilabel> window if it is an image created by
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. File size,
          resolution and the image's composition are displayed below
          the preview window.
        </para>
        <tip>
          <para>
            If your image has been modified by another program,
            click on the <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> window to update it.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The path of the current directory is displayed at the top of the
          dialog. You can navigate along this path by clicking on one of
          the buttons.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This button shows <guilabel>All Files</guilabel> by default. This
          means that all file types will be displayed in the middle panel,
          even if they are not images. You can <emphasis>filter</emphasis>
          the list for a particular file type.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Determine File Type</guilabel> button has a
          default of <guilabel>Automatic</guilabel>. In most cases you
          don't need to pay any attention to this, because the
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can determine the file type
          automatically. In a few rare situations, neither the file
          extension nor internal information in the file are enough to tell
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> the file type. If this happens,
          you can set it by selecting it from the list.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
