<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
-->

<sect2 id="gimp-file-revert" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-09-07</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-08</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Revert</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Navrátit</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Zurücksetzen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Revenir</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Ricarica</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Tilbakestill</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">恢复</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Revert (command)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Navrátit</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Zurücksetzen</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Revenir (commande)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Ricarica (comando)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Tilbakestill (kommando)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>恢复</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem> command reloads the image from
    disk, so that it looks just like it did the last time it was saved
    — unless, that is, you or some application other than
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> have modifed the image file, in
    which case, the new contents are loaded.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Volba "Navrátit..." způsobí, že je obrázek znovu nahrán z disku, takže
    vypadá přesně tak, jak byl naposledy uložen - kromě případu, kdy byl
    obrázek v době od posledního uložení přepsán jinou aplikací než GIMP -
    bude tedy nahrán nový obsah. Z technických důvodů GIMP při navracení
    původního obsahu uzavře stávající okno a obrázek znovu otevře. Proto se
    nelze dále vracet v historii úprav a její obsah je smazán. Při vyvolání
    funkce "Navrátit" se GIMP pokouší zabránit ztrátě dat požadavkem
    potvrzení, zdali opravdu chcete navrátit původní obrázek.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie ein geöffnetes Bild neu laden, also alle
    Bearbeitungsschritte seit dem letzten Speichern rückgängig machen. Wenn
    Sie diese Aktion ausführen, wird <acronym>GIMP</acronym> das
    aktuelle Bildfenster schließen und die zugehörige Bilddatei in einem
    neuen Fenster laden.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Revenir fait que l'image est rechargée depuis le disque pour qu'elle soit
    réaffichée de façon identique à ce qu'elle était lors de la précédente
    sauvegarde.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Ricarica</guimenuitem> ricarica l'immagine da
    disco, in maniera da riportarla allo stesso stato in cui era l'ultima
    volta che era stata salvata — a meno che, qualche altra applicazione
    non abbia modificato il file dell'immagine su disco, in tale
    eventualità verrebbero caricate queste nuove modifiche.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Tilbakestill</guimenuitem> (Bm.: Forkast)
    laster inn biletet på nytt frå harddisken. Dermed blir biletet tilbakestilt
    til slik det var siste gongen du lagra det. Dvs. dersom fila i mellomtida
    ikkje er forandra eller fjerna av andre enn
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “恢复”使图像从磁盘被重新读取，这样它就和最后一次保存时相同---除非该文件
    其后又被您或 GIMP 外的其它程序改写了，这时就会载入新内容。在技术上来讲，
    GIMP 恢复一个文件实际是关闭已存在的图像并新建一个图像。所有恢复文件不可
    撤销，并且会使图像的撤销历史丢失。GIMP 为了避免您丢失成果会询问您是否确
    认要恢复图像。
  </para>

  <warning lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
    <para lang="en">
      When <acronym>GIMP</acronym> reverts a
      file, it actually closes the existing image and creates a new
      image.  Because of this, reverting an image is not undoable, and
      causes the undo history of the image to be lost.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tries to protect you from losing your
      work in this way by asking you to confirm that you really want to
      revert the image.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Bitte beachten Sie, dass dieses Kommando nicht
      rückgängig gemacht werden kann und das Journal der letzten Änderungen
      verloren geht. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> warnt Sie daher, wenn
      Sie versuchen, ein Bild neu zu laden, welches ungespeicherte Änderungen
      beinhaltet.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Pour des raisons techniques actuellement GIMP ferme l'image à recharger
      puis ouvre une nouvelle fenêtre avec l'image rechargée. À cause de cela
      il n'est pas possible d'annuler un tel rechargement et tout l'historique
      d'annulation sera perdu. Une confirmation vous sera demandée pour éviter
      de perdre accidentellement votre travail.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Quando <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ricarica un file, esso chiude
      abbandonando l'immagine corrente e crea una nuova immagine
      caricandola dal disco.  Per questa ragione, ricaricare un'immagine è
      un'operazione non ripristinabile, che provoca anche la perdita di
      tutta la cronologia degli annullamenti.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tenta di proteggere l'utente dalla
      perdita accidentale del lavoro corrente, chiedendo di confermare
      l'operazione in modo da assicurarsi che l'utente desideri realmente
      ricaricare l'immagine.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Når <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tilbakestiller eit bilete blir det
      eksisterande biletet lukka og eit nytt bilete opna. Difor kan du ikkje
      angre denne handlinga. Også angreloggen blir borte.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> prøver å få deg til å tenke deg om
      ved å spøre om du verkeleg vil tilbakestilla biletet.
    </para>
    </warning>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Re<accel>v</accel>ert</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          There is no default keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Navrátit...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Tato volba není standardně přiřazena žádné klávese.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>urücksetzen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Cette commande est accessible depuis le
          menu de la fenêtre d'image
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ichier</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>evenir</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Il n'y a pas de raccourci clavier par défaut.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>icarica</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            Per questo comando non c'è alcuna scorciatoia
            da tastiera predefinita.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne kommandoen frå biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Tilbakestill</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>恢复</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
          它没有默认的快捷键。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
