<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:

-->

<sect2 id="gimp-file-close" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-09-07</date>
        <authorinitials>a.w</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Close</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Zavřít</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Schließen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fermer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Chiudi</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">关闭</phrase>
  </title>
  
  <anchor id="gimp-file-close-confirm" />
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Close</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Zavřít</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Schließen</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Fermer</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Chiudi</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>关闭</primary></indexterm>
  
  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem> command closes the image and
    removes its window.  Closing an image is not undoable: once it is
    closed, everything is gone, including the undo history.  If the image
    is not <quote>clean</quote> — that is, if you have changed it since the
    last time you saved it — you are asked to confirm that you really want
    to close it.  Note that an image is marked as clean when it is saved to
    a file, even if the file format chosen does not preserve all the
    information in the image, so it is a good idea to think for a moment
    about what you are doing before closing an image.  If there is the
    slightest possibility that you will regret it, it can't hurt to save a
    copy as an <link linkend="gimp-file-save-xcf">XCF</link> file.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie das Bildfenster schließen. Diesen
    Vorgang können Sie nicht über das <quote>Rückgängig</quote> Kommando
    zurück nehmen.  Wenn das Fenster einmal geschlossen ist, sind alle
    Änderungen inklusive des <quote>Journals</quote> verloren. Daher werden
    Sie, sofern das Bild ungespeicherte Änderungen enthält, von
    <application>GIMP</application> gewarnt und müssen nocheinmal extra
    bestätigen, dass Sie dieses Bildfenster wirklich schließen und alle
    Änderungen verwerfen möchten. Bitte beachten Sie auch, dass ein Bild
    nach dem Speichern als unverändert gilt, egal ob das zum Speichern
    verwendete Dateiformat alle Bildeigenschaften wie Ebenen oder
    Transparenzen vollständig erhalten konnte. Es sei Ihnen daher empfohlen
    vor dem Schließen eines Bildfensters einen Augenblick
    innezuhalten. Eine Kopie im <link
    linkend="gimp-file-save-xcf">XCF</link> Dateiformat kann nie schaden.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Fermer va fermer l'image et sa fenêtre. Fermer une image n'est
    pas annulable : une fois qu'elle est fermée tout est perdu
    y compris l'historique d'annulation. Si l'image a subi des
    modifications une confirmation vous sera demandée pour la
    fermer. Notez que l'image est considérée comme non modifiée
    dès qu'elle a été enregistrée dans un fichier même si
    le format choisi ne permettait pas de conserver toutes les
    informations possibles. Si vous souhaitez n'avoir
    aucun regret voyez d'abord comment enregistrer un fichier dans le
    format natif de Gimp
    <link linkend="gimp-file-save-xcf">XCF</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Chiudi</guimenuitem> chiude l'immagine corrente
    e elimina la sua finestra. La chiusura di un'immagine non è
    annullabile: una volta chiusa, ogni dato viene perso, inclusa la
    cronologia degli annullamenti. Se l'immagine non è
    <quote>pulita</quote> — cioè, se si è cambiato qualcosa nell'immagine
    dopo l'ultimo salvataggio — viene richiesto di confermare la chiusura.
    Notare che un'immagine viene considerata pulita quando questa viene
    salvata su file, anche se il formato del file scelto non preserva tutte
    le informazioni nell'immagine, perciò è sempre meglio fare attenzione
    riflettere attentamente a quello che si sta facendo prima di chiudere
    un'immagine. Se c'è anche una piccolissima probabilità di pentirsi
    dell'operazione, non costa nulla salvarne una copia anche in formato
    <link linkend="gimp-file-save-xcf">XCF</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “关闭”将关闭图像并移除其窗口。关闭图像不能被撤销：一旦它被关闭，所有都没
    有了，包括撤销历史。如果图像不是“干净”的---指最后一次保存后又对它进行了
    修改---它会询问您是否确认要关闭图像。需要注意的是，当图像被保存后就被标
    记为“干净”，而不管其文件格式是否保留了图像中所有信息，因此在关闭一个图像
    前最好想一下您在做什么。要将这种后悔的可能性降到最小，用<link
    linkend="gimp-file-save-xcf">XCF</link>格式保存一份副本是个不错的主意。
  </para>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>lose</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz je dostupný z menu obrázku jako
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Zavřít</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>ließen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Cette commande est accessible depuis la boîte à outils ou le
          menu de la fenêtre d'image
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ichier</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>ermer</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le nom anglais de cette commande est <quote>Close</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È poissibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>hiudi</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>关闭</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>，
        </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          nebo použitím klávesové zkratky
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Alternativ können Sie das Tastenkürzel
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Strg</keycap>
            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo> verwenden.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Ou en utilisant le raccourci clavier
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          o usando la scorciatoia da tastiera
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          或使用快捷键
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          For most systems on which the <application>GIMP</application> runs,
          you can also execute it by clicking on a
          <quote>Close</quote> button somewhere on the image window titlebar.
          The location and appearance of this button are determined by the
          windowing system and the window manager.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Ve většině prostředí může být také vykonán kliknutím na tlačítko
          "Zavřít" v liště okna obrázku. Umístění a vzhled tlačítka jsou dány
          okenním systémem a manažerem.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Auf den meisten Plattformen auf denen
          <application>GIMP</application>
          funktioniert, steht Ihnen in der Titelleiste des Bildfensters eine
          Schaltfläche zum Schließen des Fensters zur Verfügung. Wie diese
          genau aussieht und wo Sie diese finden hängt allerdings von dem
          verwendeten Betriebssystem und gegebenenfalls vom Erscheinungsbild
          der verwendeten Oberfläche ab.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Dans la plupart des environnements elle peut aussi être exécutée en
          cliquant sur le bouton Fermer de toute fenêtre de GIMP.
          L'apparence et la position de ce bouton est déterminée par
          le gestionnaire de fenêtres de votre système opératoire.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Su molti sistemi su cui gira <application>GIMP</application>, è
          possibile eseguire questo comando facendo clic su un pulsante
          <quote>chiudi</quote> generico, posizionato da qualche parte
          nella barra del titolo della finestra immagine. La collocazione e
          l'aspetto di questo pulsante sono determinati interamente dal
          sistema di finestre e dal gestore di quest'ultimo.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          在大多数环境中，它也可以通过点击图像窗口标题栏某处的一个“关闭”按钮
          执行。该按钮的位置和外型有窗口系统和窗口管理器决定。
        </para>
        <note lang="en;it">
          <para lang="en">
            If you close the image window, as described above,
            <application>GIMP</application> simply closes your image.
            However, if you close the Toolbox window by using the
            <quote>Close</quote> button, <application>GIMP</application>
            itself exits.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se si chiude la finestra immagine, come descritto in
            precedenza, <application>GIMP</application> chiude
            semplicemente l'immagine. Invece, se si chiude il pannello
            degli strumenti usando il pulsante <quote>chiudi</quote>, viene
            chiusa tutta l'applicazione <application>GIMP</application>.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
