<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
-->

<sect2 id="gimp-file-quit" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-09-07</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-22</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-08</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Quit</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Ukončit</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Beenden</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Salir</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Quitter</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Esci</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Avslutt</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">退出</phrase>
  </title>

  <anchor id="gimp-file-quit-confirm" />

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Quit GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Ukončit</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Beenden</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Salir (comando)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Fermer GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Quitter GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Esci (comando)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Avslutt (kommando)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>退出</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> command causes
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to close all images and exit. If there
    are any open images which contain unsaved changes (that is, they are
    not marked as <quote>clean</quote>),
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> notifies you and displays a list of
    the unsaved images. You can then choose which images you would
    like to save, or you can cancel the command. Note
    that if you have a large number of images open, or are using a
    large part of the RAM on your system, it may take a little
    while for everything to shut down.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Příkaz Ukončit způsobí zavření všech oken Gimpu a ukončení jeho běhu.
    Pokud jsou některé z otevřených obrázků označeny jako nečisté, tzn.
    obsahují neuložené změny, GIMP na to upozorní a nabídne možnost operaci
    přerušit. (V Gimpu 2.2 se zobrazí seznam neuložených obrázků.<!--en??-->)
    Pokud je otevřeno velkémnožství obrázků, nebo pokud se používá velká část
    operační paměti počítače, může zavírání a ukončování chvíli trvat.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie <acronym>GIMP</acronym> beenden.
    Falls es geöffnete Bildfenster gibt, die ungespeicherte Änderungen
    enthalten, werden Sie hierauf hingewiesen und haben die Möglichkeit, die
    betroffenen Bilder zu speichern oder das Kommando abzubrechen.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El comando <guimenuitem>Salir</guimenuitem> hace que el
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> cierre todas las imágenes y luego
    finalice.  Si hay alguna imagen abierta que tiene cambios no guardados
    (esto es, que no está marcada como <quote>limpia</quote>), el
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> se lo hace saber mediante una advertencia.
    Puede escoger cuáles imágenes desea guardar desde una lista, o puede
    cancelar la operación.  Note que si tiene un gran número de imágenes
    abiertas, o está usando buena parte de la RAM de su sistema, puede tomar
    un tiempo mientras todo se finaliza.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Quitter va fermer toutes les images et l'application Gimp. S'il
    y a des images modifiées non enregistrées vous en serez informé
    et vous pourrez annuler votre action. Depuis GIMP 2.2 une liste
    des fichiers modifiés est affichée qui vous permet de sélectionner
    individuellement les fichiers à enregistrer. Notez bien que si
    avez beaucoup d'images ouvertes simultanément il peut se passer
    un temps significatif avant que tout soit enregistré.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Esci</guimenuitem> fa in modo che
    l'applicazione <acronym>GIMP</acronym> chiuda tutte le immagini
    e successivamente termini la propria esecuzione. Se alcune delle
    immagini aperte dovessero contenere dei cambiamenti non salvati,
    (perciò, non marcate come <quote>pulite</quote>),
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ce lo segnala mostrando un'elenco delle
    immagini da salvare. È così possibile scegliere quali immagini salvare
    o, se si desidera, annullare il comando. Notare che se l'elenco delle
    immagini aperte è molto lungo, o se si sta usando molta memoria RAM per
    le immagini, potrebbe metterci un po' per la chiusura completa.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Trykker du på kommandoen <guimenuitem>Avslutt</guimenuitem>, vil
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> lukke alle opne vindauge og slutte av.
    Dersom det finst opne bilete det er gjort endringar i utan lagring, dvs.
    at dei ikkje er merka som <quote>reine</quote>, vil
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gjere deg merksam på dette ved å vise
    ei liste over ulagra bilete. Du kan såleis velje kva bilete du ønskjer å
    lagra, eller rett og slett avbryta avsluttinga. Dersom du har svært mange
    ulagra bilete, eller du bruker mykje RAM, kan det ta litt tid før
    kommandoen blir utført.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “退出”使 GIMP 关闭所有图像并退出。如果有任何打开着的“脏的”图像，您会被提
    醒并给您一个取消该动作的机会。(在 GIMP 中，会提供给您一个未保存图像的列
    表并询问是否在退出保存它们。)要注意的是，如果有大量打开的文件，或使用了
    系统上大量 RAM，就需要一段时间使所有图像关闭。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activación del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the Toolbox menubar or the image
          menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>Q</accel>uit</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz je dostupný z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Ukončit</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Werkzeug- und dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>eenden</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde la barra de menú de la caja de
          herramientas o desde la barra de menú de una imagen siguiendo:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>A</accel>rchivo</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>alir</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Cette commande est accessible depuis la boîte à outils ou le
          menu de la fenêtre d'image
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ichier</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>Q</accel>uitter</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dal menu della barra
          degli strumenti o della barra immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>sci</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne kommandoen frå biletmenyen og
          verktøymenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Avslutt</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在工具箱或图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>退出</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>，
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          nebo pomocí klávesové zkratky
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Alternativ können Sie das Tastenkürzel
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Strg</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo> verwenden.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          o por medio del atajo de teclado
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          ou en utilisant le raccourci clavier
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          o usando la scorciatoia da tastiera
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          eller med snarvegen
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>. (Engelsk: Quit).
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          或使用快捷键
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>。
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          For most systems on which the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> runs,
          you can also execute it by clicking on a
          <quote>Close</quote> button somewhere on the Toolbox window's
          titlebar.  The location and appearance of this button are
          determined by the windowing system and the window manager.
        </para>
        <note lang="en">
          <para lang="en">
            If you close the image window, as described above,
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> simply closes your image.
            However, if you close the Toolbox window by using the
            <quote>Close</quote> button, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            itself exits.
          </para>
        </note>
        <para lang="cs">
          Ve většine grafických prostředí lze vyvolat též kliknutím na
          zavírací tlačítko okna Panelu nástrojů. Jeho vzhled a umístění však
          nezáleží na Gimpu, nýbrž na používaném správci oken. případně na
          tématu a dalších nastaveních grafického prostředí.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Auf den meisten Plattformen, auf denen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          funktioniert, steht Ihnen in der Titelleiste des Werkzeugfensters
          eine
          Schaltfläche zum Schließen des Fensters zur Verfügung. Wie diese
          genau aussieht und wo Sie diese finden, hängt allerdings von dem
          verwendeten Betriebssystem und gegebenenfalls vom Erscheinungsbild
          der verwendeten Oberfläche ab.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Para la mayoría de los sistemas en los que el
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puede correr, puede además ejecutar
          este comando haciendo clic sobre el botón <quote>Cerrar</quote> que
          debería encontrarse en alguna parte de la barra de título de la
          ventana que contiene a la caja de herramientas.  La ubicación y la
          apariencia de este botón la determina el sistema gestor de ventanas.
        </para>
        <note lang="es">
          <para lang="es">
            Si cierra una ventana de imagen, como se describió más arriba, el
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> simplemente cierra su imagen.  En
            cambio, el hecho de cerrar la ventana que tiene a la caja de
            herramientas provoca que el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> mismo
            se cierre.
          </para>
        </note>
        <para lang="fr">
          Dans la plupart des environnements elle peut aussi être exécutée en
          cliquant sur le bouton Quitter de la boîte à outils.
          L'apparence et la position de ce bouton est déterminée par
          le gestionnaire de fenêtres.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Su molti sistemi su cui gira <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
          è possibile eseguire il comando di chiusura agendo sul pulsante
          <quote>Chiudi</quote> presente da qualche parte sulla barra del
          titolo della finestra degli strumenti. La posizione e l'aspetto
          di questo pulsante sono determinati dal sistema di finestre e dal
          suo relativo gestore.
        </para>
        <note lang="it">
          <para lang="it">
            Se si chiude la finestra immagine, come sopra descritto,
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> semplicemente chiude
            l'immagine.  Comunque, se si chiude la finestra degli strumenti
            usando il pulsante <quote>Chiudi</quote>,
            si termina anche l'esecuzione di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>
        </note>
        <para lang="no">
          I dei fleste operativsystema kan du også lukke biletet ved å klikke på
          ein <quote>Lukk</quote> knapp ein eller annan plassen i tittellinja
          for biletet. Plasseringa av ein slik knapp blir bestemt av
          operativsystemet (OS) og korleis dette er sett opp.
        </para>
        <note lang="no">
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du lukker eit biletvindauge slik som omtalt ovanfor, vil
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ganske enkelt lukke biletet.
            Dersom du derimot lukker verktøyskrinet ved å bruke
            <quote>Lukk</quote>-knappen, vil du lukke heile
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>
        </note>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          它也可以通过点击工具箱窗口某处的一个“关闭”按钮执行。该按钮的位置和
          外型有窗口系统和窗口管理器决定。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
