<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-file-close' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">

  <title lang='en'>Close</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Fermer</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">关闭</title>

  <anchor id='gimp-file-close-confirm' />

  <para lang='en'>
    This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Close</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    or by using the keyboard shortcut
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>W</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    In most environments, it can also be executed by clicking a "Close"
    button somewhere on the image window titlebar.  The location and
    appearance of this button are determined by the windowing system
    and window manager. 
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette commande est accessible depuis la boîte à outils ou le
    menu de la fenêtre d'image
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Fermer</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    ou en utilisant le raccourci clavier
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>W</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    Dans la plupart des environnements il peut aussi être exécuté en
    cliquant sur le bouton Fermer de la boîte à outils.
    L'apparence et la position de ce bouton est déterminée par
    le gestionnaire de fenêtres.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该命令在图像菜单的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>关闭</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>，或使用快捷键
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>W</keycap>
    </keycombo>。在大多数环境中，它也可以通过点击图像窗口标题栏某处的一个“关闭”按钮执行。该按钮的位置和外型有窗口系统和窗口管理器决定。
  </para>


  <para lang='en'>
    "Close" closes the image and removes its window.  Closing an
    image is not undoable:  once it is closed, everything is gone,
    including the undo history.  If the image is not clean---that
    is, if you have changed it since the last time you saved
    it---then you will be asked to confirm that you really want to
    close it.  Note that images are marked as clean when saved to a
    file even if the file format chosen does not preserve all
    information present in the image, so it is a good idea to think
    for a moment about what you are doing before closing an image.
    If there is the slightest possibility that you will regret it,
    it can't hurt to save a copy as an <link
    linkend='gimp-file-save-xcf'>XCF</link> file. 
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Fermer va fermer l'image et sa fenêtre. Fermer une image n'est
    pas annulable : une fois qu'elle est fermé tout est perdu
    y compris l'historique d'annulation. Si l'image a subi des
    modifications une confirmation vous sera demandée pour la
    fermer. Noter que l'image est considérée comme non modifiée
    dès qu'elle a été enregistrée dans un fichier même si
    le format choisi ne permet de conserver toutes les
    informations possibles. Si vous ne souhaitez n'avoir
    aucun regret voyez d'abord comment enregistrer un fichier dans le
    format natif Gimp
    <link linkend='gimp-file-save-xcf'>XCF</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “关闭”将关闭图像并移除其窗口。关闭图像不能被撤销：一旦它被关闭，所有都没有了，包括撤销历史。如果图像不是“干净”的---指最后一次保存后又对它进行了修改---它会询问您是否确认要关闭图像。需要注意的是，当图像被保存后就被标记为“干净”，而不管其文件格式是否保留了图像中所有信息，因此在关闭一个图像前最好想一下您在做什么。要将这种后悔的可能性降到最小，用<link linkend='gimp-file-save-xcf'>XCF</link>格式保存一份副本是个不错的主意。
  </para>
    
</sect2>

