<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-20 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2005/11/20 split off from menus-filter.xml; de created by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-filter-reset-all" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-28</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-10</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-06-21</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Reset All Filters</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Přenastavit všechny filtry</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Alle Filtereinstellungen zurücksetzen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Reiniciar todos los filtros</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Réinitialiser tous les filtres</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Reimposta tutti i filtri</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Tilbakestill alle filtra</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">重置所有滤镜</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Common functions</secondary>
    <tertiary>Reset all</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Reset All</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Alle zurücksetzen</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Filtros</primary>
    <secondary>Funciones comunes</secondary>
    <tertiary>Reiniciar todo</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Reiniciar todo</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Fonctions communes</secondary>
    <tertiary>Réinitialiser tous les filtres</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Réinitialiser tous les
      filtres</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary>
    <secondary>Reimposta tutti</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Tilbakestill alle filtra</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Normally, each time you run an interactive plug-in, its dialog is
    displayed with all of the settings initialized to the ones you used
    the last time you ran it. This may be a problem if you made a mistake
    setting the values and you can't remember what they were originally.
    One way to recover is to exit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and
    start again, but the <guimenuitem>Reset all Filters</guimenuitem>
    command is a slightly less drastic solution: it resets the values for
    <emphasis>all</emphasis> plug-ins to their defaults. Because it is a
    dramatic step, it asks you to confirm that you really want to do it.
    Be careful: you cannot undo this command.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Wenn Sie ein Filter mit Dialogfenster mehrfach aufrufen, werden
    normalerweise jeweils die Einstellungen wieder angezeigt, mit denen Sie
    das Filter zuletzt ausgeführt haben. Gelegentlich kann es passieren, dass
    ein Zurücksetzen auf die Werte der Standardeinstellung des Filters
    hilfreich wäre, weil Sie sich beispielsweise im Dschungel der
    Filtereigenschaften verrannt haben. Mit diesem Kommando können Sie genau
    das tun. Beachten Sie aber bitte, dass Sie mit diesem Kommando die
    Einstellungen <emphasis>aller</emphasis>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Erweiterungen zurücksetzen. Sie können die
    Ausführung dieses Kommandos nicht rückgängig machen!
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Za normálních okolností se interaktivní zásuvné moduly vždy spouští s
    dialogem s přednastavenými hodnotami tak, jak byly naposledy použity.
    Většinou je to výhodné, ale pokud hodnoty nastavíte špatně a nepamatujete
    si původní fungující hodnoty, může to být protivné. Jedním možným řešením
    je restartovat celý Gimp, ale tento příkaz nabízí méně zoufalé řešení:
    resetuje nastavení pro <emphasis>všechny</emphasis>
    zásuvné moduly na výchozí hodnoty. Protože je to závažný krok a příkaz
    nelze vrátit zpět, budete požádáni o potvrzení vašeho úmyslu.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Normalmente, cada vez que se ejecuta un complemento interactivo, se
    visualiza su diálogo con la configuración usada la última vez que se
    ejecutó. Esto puede ser un problema si seleccionó unos valores erroneos y
    no recuerda los valores originales. Una manera de recuperarlos es cerrar
    el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> y iniciarlo de nuevo, pero el comando
    <guimenuitem>Reiniciar todos los filtros</guimenuitem> es una solución
    ligeramente menos drástica: reinicia los valores de
    <emphasis>todos</emphasis> de todos los complementos a los valores
    predefinidos. Dado que es un paso importante, se le pide confirmación.
    Tenga cuidado: este comando no se puede deshacer.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Normalement, chaque fois que vous exécutez un filtre, le dialogue
    conserve vos réglages en mémoire. Il est parfois ennuyeux de ne plus se
    rappeler quels étaient les réglages par défaut d'un filtre. Cette
    commande vous permet de rétablir tous les paramètres des filtres à leurs
    valeurs par défaut. Comme il s'agit d'une opération importante une
    confirmation vous sera demandée. Faites bien attention il n'y a pas de
    retour en arrière possible.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Normalmente, ogni volta che si esegue un plug-in interattivo, la sua
    finestra di dialogo mostra tutti i valori impostati come l'ultima volta
    che si è utilizzato quello specifico filtro. Ciò potrebbe essere un
    problema se si è commesso un'errore impostando questi valori senza
    ricordarsi esattamente come erano in origine. Un modo per recuperare è
    di uscire da <acronym>GIMP</acronym> e rieseguirlo, ma il
    comando <guimenuitem>Reimposta tutti i filtri</guimenuitem> è una
    soluzione un po' meno drastica: esso reimposta i valori per
    <emphasis>tutti</emphasis> i plug-in alle impostazioni
    predefinite. Dato che questo è un passo rischioso,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> domanda conferma
    dell'operazione. Attenzione: l'operazione non è annullabile.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Til vanleg blir dialogen for programtillegga viste med dei innstillingane
    du hadde sist programmet var i bruk. Dette kan bli eit problem dersom
    har gjort ein feil og ikkje hugsar originalinnstillingane. Ein måte å
    gjere det på, er å avslutte <acronym>GIMP</acronym> og starte
    på nytt igjen. Ein enklare måte kan vere å bruke kommandoen
    <guimenuitem>Tilbakestill alle filtra</guimenuitem>. Dette kan vere
    drastisk i og med at <emphasis>alle</emphasis> programtillegga
    blir tilbakestilte til normalinnstillingane. Difor får du eit spørsmål om
    du vil gjerre dette. Denne kommandoen kan ikkje angrast.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">FIXME</para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilters</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Reset all Filters</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz je dostupný z nabídky obrázku jako
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Přenastavit všechny filtry</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>
              <accel>A</accel>lle Filtereinstellung zurücksetzen
            </guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Filt<accel>r</accel>os</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Reiniciar todos los filtros</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          La commande se trouve dans le menu
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>iltres</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Réinitialiser tous les filtres</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>iltri</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Reimposta tutti i filtri</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Tilbakestill alle filtra</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>滤镜</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>重置所有滤镜</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
