<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-06-20 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-03-12 Kolbjørn: added no tranlsation
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-menu-filters-introduction">
  <title>Introduction to the <quote>Filters</quote> Menu</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Menu</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Common functions</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduction to filters</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>The <quote>Filters</quote> menu</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/menus/filters.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    terminology, a <emphasis>filter</emphasis>
    is a plug-in that modifies the appearance of an image, in most cases just
    the active layer of the image. Not all of the entries in this menu meet
    that definition, however; the word <quote>filter</quote> is often
    mis-used to mean any plug-in, regardless of what it does. Indeed, some
    of the entries in this menu do not modify images at all.
  </para>
  <para>
    With the exception of the top three items of the
    <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu, all of the entries
    are provided by plug-ins. Each plug-in decides for itself where it would
    like its menu entry to be placed. Therefore, the appearance of this menu
    can be completely different for each user. In practice, though, the
    appearance does not vary very much, because most plug-ins come with
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> when it is installed, and of course
    they are always in the same places in the menu.
  </para>
  <para><!-- Must be rewritten for v2.4? -->
    Plug-ins are not restricted to just the <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
    menu: a plug-in can place entries in any menu. Indeed, a number of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s basic 
    functions (for example, <guimenuitem>Semi-flatten</guimenuitem>
    in the <guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu) are implemented
    by plug-ins. But the <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu is the default
    place for a plug-in to place its menu entries.
  </para>
  <para>
    For general information on plug-ins and how to use them, see the section
    on <link linkend="gimp-concepts-plugins">Plug-ins</link>. You can find
    information on the filters that are provided with
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in the
    <link linkend="filters">Filters</link> chapter. For filters you install
    yourself, please refer to the information which came with them.
  </para>
</sect2>
