<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: 
     2005/11/20 split off from menus-filter.xml; de created by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-filter-reset-all" lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-11-20</date>
        <authorinitials>a.w</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Reset All Filters</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Přenastavit všechny filtry</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Alle Filtereinstellungen zurücksetzen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Réinitialiser tous les filtres</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">重置所有滤镜</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Reset All</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Alle zurücksetzen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Réinitialiser tous</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Normally, each time you run an interactive plugin, the dialog comes up
    with settings initialized to the values you used the last time you ran it.
    Sometimes this can be very annoying, if you mess up the values and don't
    remember what they were originally. One way to recover is to exit from
    GIMP and start again, but this command provides a slightly less desperate
    solution: it resets the values for <emphasis>all</emphasis>
    plugins to their defaults. Because it is a dramatic step, it asks you to
    confirm that you really want to do it. Be careful: this command is not
    undoable.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Wenn Sie ein Filter mit Dialogfenster mehrfach aufrufen werden
    normalerweise jeweils die Einstellungen wieder angezeigt, mit denen Sie
    das Filter zuletzt ausgeführt haben. Gelegentlich kann es passieren, dass
    ein Zurücksetzen der Wert auf die Standardeinstellung des Filters
    hilfreich wäre, weil Sie sich beispielsweise im Dschungel der
    Filtereigenschaften verrannt haben. Mit diesem Kommando könne Sie genau
    das tun. Beachten Sie aber bitte, dass Sie mit diesem Kommando die
    Einstellungen <emphasis>aller</emphasis> <application>GIMP</application>
    Erweiterungen zurücksetzen. Sie können die Ausführung dieses Kommandos
    nicht rückgängig machen!
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Za normálních okolností se interaktivní zásuvné moduly vždy spouští s
    dialogem s přednastavenými hodnotami tak, jak byly naposledy použity.
    Většinou je to výhodné, ale pokud hodnoty nastavíte špatně a nepamatujete
    si původní fungující hodnoty, může to být protivné. Jedním možným řešením
    je restartovat celý Gimp, ale tento příkaz nabízí méně zoufalé řešení:
    resetuje nastavení pro <emphasis>všechny</emphasis>
    zásuvné moduly na výchozí hodnoty. Protože je to závažný krok a příkaz
    nelze vrátit zpět, budete požádáni o potvrzení vašeho úmyslu.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Normalement, chaque fois que vous exécutez un filtre, le dialogue 
    conserve vos réglages en mémoire. Il est parfois ennuyeux de ne plus se 
    rappeler quels étaient les réglages par défaut d'un filtre. Cette 
    commande vous permet de rétablir tous les paramètres des filtres à leurs 
    valeurs par défaut. Comme il s'agit d'une opération importante une 
    confirmation vous sera demandée. Faites bien attention il n'y a pas de 
    retour en arrière possible.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">FIXME</para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">How to call the command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This command can be accessed from an image menubar through 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilters</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Reset All Filters...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz je dostupný z nabídky obrázku jako
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Přenastavit všechny filtry</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>
              <accel>A</accel>lle Filtereinstellung zurücksetzen
            </guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          La commande se trouve dans le menu
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>iltres</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Réinitialiser tous les filtres</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>滤镜</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>重置所有滤镜</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
