<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2005-01-07 en;fr reviewed by j.h
     2005/10/30 reviewed, de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-print-size" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Velikost tisku</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Print Size</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Druckgröße</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Taille d'impression</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Dimensione di stampa</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Utskriftformat</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Velikost tisku</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Printing</primary>
    <secondary>Printing size and resolution</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Resolution</primary>
    <secondary>Resolution when printing</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Image size</secondary>
    <tertiary>Printing size</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Print Size</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Druckgröße</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Imprimer</primary>
    <secondary>Taille d'impression et Résolution</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Résolution</primary>
    <secondary>Résolution à l'impression</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Taille de l'image</secondary>
    <tertiary>Taille d'impression</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Résolution</secondary>
    <tertiary>Résolution à l'impression</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Taille d'impression</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Dimensione di stampa</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Bilete (menyen)</primary>
    <secondary>Utskriftformat</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Utskriftformat</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    You can use the <guimenuitem>Print Size</guimenuitem> dialog to change
    the <emphasis>dimensions of a printed image</emphasis> and its
    <emphasis>resolution</emphasis>. This command does not change the number of
    pixels in the image and it does not resample the image. (If you want
    to change the size of an image by resampling it, use the
    <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scale Image</link> command.)
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die Größe des
    <emphasis>gedruckten</emphasis>
    Bildes ändern. Hierzu wird die logische Auflösung angepasst. Beachten Sie
    bitte, dass dieses Kommando <emphasis>nicht</emphasis> die Anzahl der
    Pixel im Bild verändert. Sollte dies Ihr Ziel sein, benutzen Sie
    stattdessen
    bitte das im <xref linkend="gimp-image-scale" /> beschriebene Kommando.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Ce dialogue sert à modifier les <emphasis>Dimensions</emphasis> et la
    <emphasis>Résolution</emphasis> d'une image imprimée. Il ne modifie
    pas l'image elle-même. Si vous voulez changer la taille de l'image en
    la ré-échantillonnant, utilisez la fonction
    <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Échelle et taille de l'image</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    La finestra <guimenuitem>Dimensione di stampa</guimenuitem> serve a
    cambiare la <emphasis>dimensione dell'immagine stampata</emphasis> e la
    sua <emphasis>risoluzione</emphasis>. Questo comando non cambia il
    numero di pixel presenti nell'immagine e neanche la ricampiona (se si
    vuole cambiare la dimensione dell'immagine tramite ricampionamento,
    usare invece il comando <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scala
    immagine</link>).
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Dialogen <guimenuitem>Utskriftformat</guimenuitem> blir brukt for å setje
    <emphasis>dimensjonane</emphasis> og
    <emphasis>oppløysinga</emphasis> biletet skal ha når du skriv det ut.
    Talet på pikslar i, eller storleiken på biletet blir ikkje forandra.
    Ønskjer du å forandra storleiken, bruker du kommandoen
    <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Skaler biletet</link>.
  </para>


  <sect3 lang="de;en;fr;it;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione della finestra</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this dialog from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>rint Size</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>B</accel>ild</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>ruckgröße</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande par le menu d'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Taille de l' im<accel>p</accel>ression</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questa finestra dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mmagine</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Dimensione di stam<accel>p</accel>a</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Bilete</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Utskriftformat</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>


  <sect3 lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
    <title>
      <!-- TODO: cs  <title lang="cs">Tisková velikost</title>   -->
      <phrase lang="de">Beschreibung des Dialogfensters</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">
        Options in the <quote>Print Size</quote> Dialog
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Taille d'impression</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Opzioni della finestra <quote>Dimensione di stampa</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Innstillingane i dialogen <quote>Utskriftformat</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Print Size</quote> dialog
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Dialogfenster <quote>Bildauflösung ändern</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La fenêtre <quote>Taille de l'impression</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          La finestra <quote>Dimensione di stampa</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Dialogen <quote>Utskriftformat</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/menus-image-print-size.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/menus-image-print-size.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/it/menus-image-print-size.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/menus-image-print-size.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      The output resolution determines the number of pixels used per unit
      length for the printed image. Do not confuse the output resolution
      with the printer resolution, which is expressed in dpi (dots per
      inch); several dots are used to print a pixel.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      When the dialog is displayed, the resolution shown in the boxes is the
      resolution of the original image. If you increase the output
      resolution, the printed page will be smaller, since more pixels are
      used per unit of length. Conversely, and for the same reason,
      resizing the image modifies the resolution.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Increasing the resolution results in increasing the sharpness of the
      printed page. This is quite different from simply reducing the image
      size by scaling it, since no pixels (and no image information) are
      removed.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      La résolution de sortie détermine le nombre de pixels qui seront
      utilisés dans chaque pouce de l'image imprimée (ou dans une autre
      unité de longueur, selon votre préférence). Ne confondez pas cette
      résolution de sortie avec la résolution de l'imprimante exprimée en
      dpi (dots per inch = points par pouce): l'imprimante est capable
      d'imprimer des points très fins, et il faut plusieurs points pour
      imprimer un pixel.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez régler les dimensions dans les boîtes <guilabel>
      Hauteur</guilabel> et <guilabel>Largeur</guilabel> ainsi que la
      résolution dans la boîte <guilabel>Résolution X/Y</guilabel>. Vous
      pouvez utiliser différentes unités grâce aux listes déroulantes. La
      taille et la résolution sont réglées par défaut en constante
      proportion de leur deux dimensions, mais vous pouvez les régler
      séparément en cliquant sur l'icône Chaîne.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La résolution proposée par GIMP est la résolution de l'image originale.
      Si vous augmentez la résolution de sortie, l'image imprimée sera plus
      petite puisque plus de pixels seront utilisés dans un pouce.
      Inversement et pour la même raison, le changement de taille modifie la
      résolution.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'augmentation de la résolution aboutit à une augmentation de la
      netteté de l'image imprimée. Il s'agit ici un mécanisme différent de
      celui de la réduction de taille de l'image puisqu'aucun pixel n'est
      supprimé.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      La risoluzione di uscita determina il numero di pixel usati per unità
      di lunghezza dell'immagine stampata. Attenzione a non confondere la
      risoluzione di uscita con la risoluzione della stampante, che viene
      espressa in dpi (dots per inch, punti per pollice); molti punti
      vengono usati per stampare un punto.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Quando la finestra di dialogo appare, la risoluzione mostrata nelle
      caselle è la risoluzione dell'immagine originale. Se si incrementa la
      risoluzione finale, la pagina stampata risulterà più piccola, dato
      che verranno usati più punti per unità di lunghezza. Di conseguenza,
      e per la stessa ragione, il ridimensionamento dell'immagine modifica
      la risoluzione.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Incrementando la risoluzione del risultato si incrementa la nitidezza
      della pagina stampata. Quest'operazione è abbastanza diversa dalla
      semplice riduzione dell'immagine per scalatura, dato che nessun pixel
      (e quindi nessuna informazione grafica) viene persa.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Utskriftoppløysinga bestemmer kor mange pikslar det går på kvar
      del i måleeininga. Dette er ikkje det same som skrivaroppløysinga,
      som blir uttrykt i dpi (dots per inch = prikkar per tomme). Det
      går med fleire slike <quote>dots</quote> for å skrive ut ein piksel.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Når du opnar dialogvindauget, blir biletoppløysinga vist i tekstrutene.
      Dersom du aukar utskriftoppløysinga, vil du sjå at formatet minkar.
      Dette fordi det blir brukt fleire pikslar for å få fram ei bestemt
      lengde på biletet. Det er vel unødvendig å skrive at lågare
      oppløysing fører til at biletet blir større.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Aukar du oppløysinga, blir biletutskrifta skarpare. Verken pikslane
      eller annan informasjon om biletet blir forandra. Difor er dette ein
      heilt annan prosess enn å endre storleiken ved å skalere biletet.
    </para>

    <variablelist lang="en;de;it">
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Width; Height</term>
        <term lang="de">Breite; Höhe</term>
        <term lang="it">Larghezza; Altezza</term>
        <term lang="no">Breidde; Høgde</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can set the printing Width and Height by using the
            text boxes. You can also choose the units for these values
            from the dropdown list.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesen Eigenschaften können Sie die gewünschte Größe des
            Ausdrucks dieses Bildes einstellen. Hierzu stehen Ihnen
            Eingabefelder zur Verfügung. Außerdem können Sie aus einem
            Klappmenü die Maßeinheit auswählen, in der Sie die Einstellungen
            vornehmen möchten.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            È possibile impostare la larghezza e l'altezza di stampa usando
            le caselle di immissione testo oltre che decidere le unità di
            misura per le stesse caselle, scegliendole dal menu a discesa.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Du bestemmer breidde og høgde for utskrifta ved å skrive tal
            i dei aktuelle boksane, eller ved å bruke pilene.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            As soon as you change the Width or the Height, the X and/or
            Y resolution values automatically change accordingly. If the
            two resolution values remain linked, the relationship of the
            width to the height of the image is also automatically
            maintained. If you would like to set these values independently
            of each other, simply click on the chain symbol to break the
            link.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sobald Sie die Höhe oder Breite verändern, wird der zugehörige
            Auflösungswert automatisch angepasst. Sofern die beiden
            Auflösungswerte verknüpft sind, wird automatisch auch das
            Verhältnis von Bildbreite und Bildhöhe konstant gehalten. Sollten
            Sie dies nicht wünschen, heben Sie die Verknüpfung durch einen
            Klick auf das Kettensymbol auf.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Non appena si cambia la larghezza o l'altezza dell'immagine, il
            valore X e/o Y della risoluzione cambia automaticamente. Se i
            due valori di risoluzione rimangono collegati, viene mantenuta
            automaticamente anche la relazione tra i valori di larghezza e
            altezza dell'immagine. Se si desidera impostare questi valori
            in modo indipendente, basta fare clic sul simbolo della catena
            per spezzare il collegamento.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Du vil sjå at når du forandrar verdiane for breidde og høgde,
            vil også verdiane for X- og Y-oppløysing bli forandra. Dersom
            dei to oppløysingsverdiane er lenka saman, vil forholdet
            mellom breidde og høgde bli oppretthalde automatisk. Ønskjer
            du å setje desse verdiane uavhenge av kvarandre, må du opne
            lenka ved å klikke på henne.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">X resolution; Y resolution</term>
        <term lang="de">X Auflösung; Y Auflösung</term>
        <term lang="it">Risoluzione X; Risoluzione Y</term>
        <term lang="no">X-oppløysing; Y-oppløysing</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can set the resolution used to calculate the printed
            width and height from the physical size of the image, that is,
            the number of pixels in it.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesen Beiden Eigenschaften können Sie die Auflösung
            einstellen, welche verwendet wird, um aus der physischen Größe des
            Bildes, also der Anzahl der Pixel im Bild, die Breite und Höhe der
            Druckgröße zu berechnen.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            È possibile impostare la risoluzione usata per calcolare la
            larghezza e l'altezza di stampa per la dimensione fisica
            dell'immagine, ovvero, il numero di pixel che la compongono.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Oppløysinga som blir brukt for å rekne ut den fysiske breidda og
            høgda på utskrifta.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Use the text boxes to change these resolution values.
            They can be linked to keep their relationship constant. The
            closed chain symbol between the two boxes indicates that the
            values are linked together. If you break the link by clicking
            on the chain symbol, you will be able to set the values
            independently of each other.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie können die Auflösungswerte beliebig verändern. Hierzu stehen
            Ihnen zwei Eingabefelder zur Verfügung. Diese können verknüpft
            sein, um das Verhältnis der beiden Werte konstant zu halten. Dies
            erkennen Sie am geschlossenen Kettensymbol, welches die beiden
            Eingabefelder verbindet. Die Verknüpfung können Sie durch einen
            Klick auf das Kettensymbol auch aufheben, um das Seitenverhältnis
            frei einstellen zu können.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Usare le caselle di immissione testo per cambiare questi valori
            di risoluzione. Essi possono rimanere collegati per mantenere
            il rapporto fra loro costante. Il simbolo di catena indica
            proprio il fatto che questi valori sono collegati da un
            rapporto costante. Se si spezza il simbolo di catena, facendo
            clic sopra di esso, sarà possibile cambiare i valori
            singolarmente in maniera indipendente.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Bruk desse innskrivingsfelta for å skrive inn kor stor oppløysing
            du ønskjer for biletet. Dersom lenkesymbolet viser ei lukka lenke,
            betyr dette at verdiane er lenka til kvarandre. Dersom du bryt
            lenka ved å klikka på henne, kan du skrive inn verdiar uavhengige
            av kvarandre.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>