<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-image-canvas-size' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Velikost plátna</title>
  <title lang="en">Canvas Size</title>
  <title lang="fr">Taille du canevas</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">画布大小</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">Velikost plátna</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Canvas Size</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Taille du canevas</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">画布大小</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/cs/dialogs/dialogs-image-canvas-size.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-canvas-size.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-image-canvas-size.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-image-canvas-size.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>

    <para lang="cs">
      Plátno je oblast viditelná oblast obrázku. Ve výchozí situaci velikost
      plátna odpovídá velikosti vrstev v obrázku. Tato funkce umožňuje
      plátno zvětšit nebo zmenšit, aniž by byl změněn obsah vrstev obrázku.
      Pokud je plátno zvětšeno, vytvoří se okolo obsahu obrázku volné místo.
      Pokud je plátno naopak zmenšeno, viditelná oblast se ořízne, ale vrstvy
      stále zasahují mimo hranice plátna.
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      The canvas is the visible area of the image. By default the canvas
      coincides with layers. This function allows you to enlarge or to
      reduce the canvas size without modifying content of the layers the
      image contains. When you enlarge it you create free space around the
      image content. When you reduce it, the visible area is cropped,
      however the layers still extend beyond the canvas border.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Le canevas est la zone de travail; c'est la surface sur laquelle 
      repose l'image. Par défaut, le canevas coïncide avec les calques. 
      Cette fonction permet d'agrandir ou de réduire le canevas sans rien 
      changer aux calques qu'il contient.
      Quand vous l'agrandissez, vous créez un espace vide  autour de
      l'image. Quand vous le réduisez, la partie visible de l'image est 
      tronquée, mais les calques continuent de s'étendre au-delà des bords 
      du canevas. 
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      画布就是您作画的地方。默认图像就是画布那么大。这个功能允许您在不修改图像内容的情况下，直接增大或减小画布大小。如果您增大画布，就在图像的周围显示白边。如果您减小画布，就显示部分图像。
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Velikost plátna</title>
    <title lang="en">Canvas Size</title>
    <title lang="fr">Taille</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">大小</title>

      <para lang="cs">
        V polích <guilabel>Šířka</guilabel> a <guilabel>Výška</guilabel> lze
        nastavit požadované rozměry plátna. Výchozí jednotkou je pixel, ale
        z rozbalovací nabídky můžete zvolit jiné jednotky, například
        procenta, pokud chcete velikost nastavit relativně vůči stávající
        velikosti plátna. Pokud je ikona řetězu nepřerušená, udržují výška
        a šířka stále stejný poměr. Kliknutím na ikonu řetězu ji lze přerušit,
        oba rozměry lze pak nastavovat nezávisle.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Ať používáte jakoukoliv jednotku, pod poli pro zadání šířky a výšky je
        vždy zobrazena informace o odpovídajících rozměrech v pixelech a o
        aktuálně nastaveném rozlišení obrázku. Rozlišení nelze v tomto dialogu
        nastavit. Pokud tak chcete učinit, použijte <link
        linkend="gimp-image-print-size">dialog Velikost tisku</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="en"><!-- changed May 25, 2005 -->
        You can set the <emphasis>Width</emphasis> and the
        <emphasis>Heigth</emphasis> you want give to the canvas. Default unit
        is pixel but you can choose another one, e.g. percents, if you want
        set new dimensions relatively to the current dimensions. If the
        adjacent Chain is intact both axis will develop jointly. If you break
        it by clicking on it, then you can set every axis separately.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Whatever unit you use, there is always information about the
        matching size in pixels and currently set resolution below the
        <emphasis>Width</emphasis> and <emphasis>Heigth</emphasis> fields.
        You cannot change the resolution in this dialog, if you want to do it,
        use the <link linkend="gimp-image-print-size">Print Size dialog</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Vous pouvez fixer la <emphasis>largeur</emphasis> et la 
        <emphasis>hauteur</emphasis> que vous voulez donner au canevas, 
        par défaut en pixels, mais vous pouvez choisir une autre unité 
        de mesure. Si la chaîne adjacente est intacte, les deux axes 
        évolueront de concert. Si vous la rompez en cliquant dessus, le 
        réglage sur chaque axe devient indépendant. 
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quelle que soit l'unité choisie, l'information en pixels reste 
        indiquée sous les boîtes de saisie Largeur et Hauteur. Vous ne 
        pouvez pas changer la résolution dans ce dialogue; pour cela, 
        utilisez le dialogue <link linkend="gimp-image-print-size">
        Taille d'impression</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您可以设置您想要的<emphasis>宽度</emphasis>和<emphasis>高度</emphasis>。默认单位是像素，但您可以选择其他单位。
      </para> 
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>比例</emphasis>就是在 X、Y 轴上的初始尺寸和新尺寸的比例。默认是 1，您可以修改它。如果旁边的锁链是完整的，两个轴将同步更新。如果断开锁链，就可以分开设置两轴的比例。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang="cs">Posun</title>
      <title lang="en">Offset</title>
      <title lang="fr">Décalage</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">位移</title>

      <para lang="en">
        Offset is used to place the image on canvas. The preview displays
        the image as a frame with a thin border and the canvas, when it
        is smaller than the image, as a frame with a thin
        black border.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        X and Y parameters are the coordinates of the upper left corner
        of the image against the same corner of the canvas. They are
        negative when canvas is smaller than image. You can change them
        thanks to the text boxes. Default unit is pixel but you can
        choose another one. When the mouse pointer is in a box you can
        use the Up and Down arrow keys to change pixel value one by one.
        When Shift is pressed in change is ten by ten.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <guilabel>Center</guilabel> button allows you to place the
        image center onto the canvas center.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Le Décalage sert à placer l'image sur le canevas. Vous disposez 
        d'un aperçu où l'image est représentée par un cadre à bordure 
        grise. Le canevas est représenté par un cadre à fine bordure 
        noire quand il est différent de l'image. 
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les paramètres X et Y sont les coordonnées du coin en haut à 
        gauche de l'image par rapport au même coin du canevas. Elles 
        sont négatives quand le canevas est plus petit que l'image. Vous 
        pouvez modifier séparément ces 
        paramètres grâce aux boîtes de saisie, par défaut en pixels, mais 
        vous pouvez choisir une autre unité de mesure. Quand le pointeur 
        de la souris est dans une des boîtes, vous pouvez utiliser les 
        touches flèches Haut et Bas pour modifier la valeur pixel par 
        pixel et si vous appuyez en même temps sur Maj la modification 
        se fera par 10 pixels.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le bouton <guilabel>Centrer</guilabel> vous permet de placer le
        centre de l'image au centre du canevas.          
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        位移用来确定图像在画布上的位置。预览窗口在画布上用灰色的框来显示图像，当图像和画布不同的时候，图像显示为细黑边的框。
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        X 和 Y 轴以图像左上顶点为原点。X 轴右向为正方向，Y 轴下向为正方向。X 轴参数增大，画布右移，图像左移；Y轴参数增大，画布上移，图像下移。画布小于图像的时候，参数是负数。文本框可以用来改变参数。也可以鼠标指针点击上下箭头来一个一个的调节像素值。按住 SHIFT 键可以以十个十个像素的修改。用鼠标右键点击箭头，可以直接得到最大值或最小值。
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <guilabel>中心</guilabel>按钮允许您将图像放在画布中央。
      </para>

      <note>
        <para lang="cs">
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          When you click on the <guilabel>Resize</guilabel>, the cavas is
          resized, but the pixel information in the image is not changed and
          the drawing scale is unchanged.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Because the added part of canvas doesn't contain layers (if layers
          hadn't been extending beyond the canvas border before the change),
          it is transparent with a checker look and is not immediately
          available for painting. You can either <link
          linkend='gimp-image-flatten'>flatten</link> the image, in which case
          you will get an image with a single layer fitting the canvas exactly,
          or you can use <link linkend='gimp-layer-resize-to-image'>Layer to
          Image Size</link> command resize the active layer only, without
          changing any other layers. You can also create a new layer and fill
          it with the background you want. You create so a digital passe-partout
          (a passe-partout is a kind of glass mount whose bottom can opened so
          that you can slip a photo into it).
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Quand vous cliquez sur le bouton <guilabel>Valider</guilabel>  
          la nouvelle image prend la taille du canevas mais le dessin  
          conserve une échelle inchangée .
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          La partie de canevas ajoutée est transparente, représentée par un 
          damier et n'est pas immédiatement accessible aux outils. Pour 
          qu'elle le soit, vous devez l'
          <link linkend='gimp-image-flatten'>aplatir</link>. Vous pouvez aussi 
          créer un nouveau calque pour y déposer le fond de votre choix. Vous créez 
          ainsi un passe-partout numérique (un passe-partout est une sorte de 
          sous-verre dont le fond s'ouvre pour qu'on puisse y glisser des
          photos).
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          当您点击<guilabel>确定</guilabel>按钮，新图像将采用画布的大小，但是图像比例不会改变。
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          画布的附加部分是棋盘样式的透明。而且不能马上用来作画。您不得不进行<link linkend='gimp-image-flatten'>平整图像</link>。您也可以创造一个新图层用您想要的背景来填满它。您也可以作一个数字相框（一种底部可以插进相片的玻璃框）。
        </para>
      </note>       
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
