<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: 
     2005-01-07 en;fr reviewed by j.h
     2005/10/30 reviewed, de added by axel.wernicke 
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-print-size" lang="en;cs;de;fr">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Velikost tisku</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Print Size</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Druckgröße</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Taille d'impression</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Velikost tisku</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Print Size</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Druckgröße</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Taille d'impression</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    You can use the <guimenuitem>Print Size</guimenuitem> dialog to change
    the <emphasis>dimensions of a printed image</emphasis> and its
    <emphasis>resolution</emphasis>. This command does not change the number of
    pixels in the image and it does not resample the image. (If you want
    to change the size of an image by resampling it, use the
    <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scale Image</link> command.)
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die Größe des 
    <emphasis>gedruckten</emphasis>
    Bildes ändern. Hierzu wird die logische Auflösung angepasst. Beachten Sie
    bitte, dass dieses Kommando <emphasis>nicht</emphasis> die Anzahl der
    Pixel im Bild verändert. Sollte dies Ihr Ziel sein, benutzen Sie 
    stattdessen
    bitte das im <xref linkend="gimp-image-scale" /> beschriebene Kommando.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Ce dialogue sert à modifier les <emphasis>Dimensions</emphasis> et la 
    <emphasis>Résolution</emphasis> d'une image imprimée. Il ne modifie 
    pas l'image elle-même. Si vous voulez changer la taille de l'image en 
    la ré-échantillonnant, utilisez la fonction 
    <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Échelle et taille de l'image</link>.
  </para>
  

  <sect3 lang="de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this dialog from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>rint Size</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>B</accel>ild</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>ruckgröße</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande par le menu d'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Taille de l' im<accel>p</accel>ression</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>


  <sect3 lang="en;de;fr">
    <title>
      <!-- TODO: cs  <title lang="cs">Tisková velikost</title>   -->
      <phrase lang="de">Beschreibung des Dialogfensters</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">
        Options in the <quote>Print Size</quote> Dialog
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Taille d'impression</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Print Size</quote> dialog
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Dialogfenster <quote>Bildauflösung ändern</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La fenêtre <quote>Taille de l'impression</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
  
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/menus-image-print-size.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/menus-image-print-size.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      The output resolution determines the number of pixels used per unit
      length for the printed image. Do not confuse the output resolution
      with the printer resolution, which is expressed in dpi (dots per
      inch); several dots are used to print a pixel.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      When the dialog is displayed, the resolution shown in the boxes is the
      resolution of the original image. If you increase the output
      resolution, the printed page will be smaller, since more pixels are
      used per unit of length. Conversely, and for the same reason,
      resizing the image modifies the resolution.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Increasing the resolution results in increasing the sharpness of the
      printed page. This is quite different from simply reducing the image
      size by scaling it, since no pixels (and no image information) are
      removed.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="fr">
      La résolution de sortie détermine le nombre de pixels qui seront 
      utilisés dans chaque pouce de l'image imprimée (ou dans une autre 
      unité de longueur, selon votre préférence). Ne confondez pas cette 
      résolution de sortie avec la résolution de l'imprimante exprimée en 
      dpi (dots per inch = points par pouce): l'imprimante est capable 
      d'imprimer des points très fins, et il faut plusieurs points pour 
      imprimer un pixel. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez régler les dimensions dans les boîtes <guilabel>
      Hauteur</guilabel> et <guilabel>Largeur</guilabel> ainsi que la 
      résolution dans la boîte <guilabel>Résolution X/Y</guilabel>. Vous 
      pouvez utiliser différentes unités grâce aux listes déroulantes. La 
      taille et la résolution sont réglées par défaut en constante 
      proportion de leur deux dimensions, mais vous pouvez les régler 
      séparément en cliquant sur l'icône Chaîne. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La résolution proposée par GIMP est la résolution de l'image originale.
      Si vous augmentez la résolution de sortie, l'image imprimée sera plus 
      petite puisque plus de pixels seront utilisés dans un pouce. 
      Inversement et pour la même raison, le changement de taille modifie la 
      résolution. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'augmentation de la résolution aboutit à une augmentation de la 
      netteté de l'image imprimée. Il s'agit ici un mécanisme différent de 
      celui de la réduction de taille de l'image puisqu'aucun pixel n'est 
      supprimé. 
    </para>
    
    <variablelist lang="en;de">
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Width; Height</term>
        <term lang="de">Breite; Höhe</term>
        
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can set the printing Width and Height by using the
            text boxes. You can also choose the units for these values
            from the dropdown list.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesen Eigenschaften können Sie die gewünschte Größe des
            Ausdrucks dieses Bildes einstellen. Hierzu stehen Ihnen 
            Eingabefelder zur Verfügung. Ausserdem können Sie aus einem 
            Klappmenü die Maßeinheit auswählen, in der Sie die Einstellungen 
            vornehmen möchten.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            As soon as you change the Width or the Height, the X and/or
            Y resolution values automatically change accordingly. If the
            two resolution values remain linked, the relationship of the
            width to the height of the image is also automatically
            maintained. If you would like to set these values independently
            of each other, simply click on the chain symbol to break the
            link.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sobald Sie die Höhe oder Breite verändern, wird der zugehörige
            Auflösungswert automatisch angepasst. Sofern die beiden 
            Auflösungswerte verknüpft sind, wird automatisch auch das 
            Verhältnis von Bildbreite und Bildhöhe konstant gehalten. Sollten 
            Sie dies nicht wünschen, heben Sie die Verknüpfung durch einen 
            Klick auf das Kettensymbol auf.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">X resolution; Y resolution</term>
        <term lang="de">X Auflösung; Y Auflösung</term>
        
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can set the resolution used to calculate the printed
            width and height from the physical size of the image, that is,
            the number of pixels in it.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesen Beiden Eigenschaften können Sie die Auflösung 
            einstellen, welche verwendet wird, um aus der physischen Größe des 
            Bildes, also der Anzahl der Pixel im Bild, die Breite und Höhe der 
            Druckgröße zu berechnen.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Use the text boxes to change these resolution values.
            They can be linked to keep their relationship constant. The
            closed chain symbol between the two boxes indicates that the
            values are linked together. If you break the link by clicking
            on the chain symbol, you will be able to set the values
            independently of each other.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie können die Auflösungswerte beliebig verändern. Hierzu stehen 
            Ihnen zwei Eingabefelder zur Verfügung. Diese können verknüpft 
            sein, um das Verhältnis der beiden Werte konstant zu halten. Dies 
            erkennen Sie am geschlossenen Kettensymbol, welches die beiden 
            Eingabefelder verbindet. Die Verknüpfung können Sie durch einen 
            Klick auf das Kettensymbol auch aufheben, um das Seitenverhältnis 
            frei einstellen zu können.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>