<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-09-25 AntI: Added 'es'
  2007-03-09 alex falappa: added it translation
  2005/10/30 rewiewed, de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-flatten" lang="en;cs;es;fr;de;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-07</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-10-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-25</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-23</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-19</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Flatten Image</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Zploštit obrázek</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Bild zusammenfügen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Aplanar la imagen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Aplatir l'image</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Appiattisci immagine</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Flat ut biletet</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">平整图像</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Flatten</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Zploštit</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Bild</primary><secondary>Zusammenfügen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebenen</primary><secondary>Zusammenfügen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Aplanar</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Aplatir l'image</primary></indexterm>
  <!-- FIXME IT: indexterm not traslated during rebuild -->
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Bilete (menyen)</primary>
    <secondary>Flat ut biletet</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Flat ut biletet</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>平整图像</primary></indexterm>

  <figure lang="en;cs;es;it;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        Accessing the <guimenuitem>Flatten Image</guimenuitem> menu item
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">
        Přístup k položce <guimenuitem>Zploštit obrázek</guimenuitem>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        Acceder al elemento del menú
        <guimenuitem>Aplanar la imagen</guimenuitem>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Accesso alla voce di menu <guimenuitem>Appiattisci
        immagine</guimenuitem>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">平整图像菜单 item.</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;es">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/menus-image-flatten.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/zh_CN/menus-image-flatten.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/menus-image-flatten.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Flatten Image</guimenuitem> command merges all of the
    layers of the image into a single layer with no alpha channel. After
    the image is flattened, it has the same appearance it had before. The
    difference is that all of the image contents are in a single layer
    without transparency. If there are any areas which are transparent
    through all of the layers of the original image, the background color
    is visible.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    This operation makes significant changes to the structure of the image.
    It is normally only necessary when you would like to save an image in
    a format which does not support levels or transparency (an alpha
    channel).
 </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Příkaz Zploštit obrázek sloučí všechny vrstvy obrázku do jediné vrstvy bez
    alfa kanálu. Vzhled obrázku při pohledu shora se přitom nijak nezmění.
    Pouze pokud jsou v obrázku místa průsvitná či průhledná až na podklad,
    jsou doplněna aktuální barvou pozadí nastavenou v Panelu nástrojů. Tato
    operace je součástí exportu obrázku do formátů, které nepodporují vrstvy.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando werden alle Ebenen des Bildes zu einer Ebene
    zusammengefügt. Gegebenenfalls vorhandene Alphakanäle werden entfernt. Das
    Bild erscheint nach der Ausführung so, wie es zuletzt angezeigt wurde, nur
    dass sich dann alle Inhalte auf einer einzigen Ebene ohne Transparenz
    befinden. Stellen des Bildes, an denen die Transparenz durch alle Ebenen
    reichte, werden auf die Hintergrundfarbe des Bildes projeziert.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Dieses Kommando führt weitreichende Änderungen an der Struktur des Bildes
    durch. Dies ist normalerweise nur dann notwendig, wenn Sie das Bild in
    einem Dateiformat speichern möchten, welches weder Ebenen noch
    Transparenz (Alphakanäle) unterstützt.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El comando <guimenuitem>Aplanar la imagen</guimenuitem> mezcla todas
    las capas de la imagen en una sola capa sin canal alfa. Después de
    aplanar la imagen, tiene la misma apariencia que tenia antes. La
    diferencia es que todos los contenidos de la imagen están en una sola
    capa sin transparencias. Si hay áreas transparentes en todas las capas
    de la imagen original, el color de fondo es visible.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Esta operación hace cambios significativos en la estructura de la
    imagen. Normalmente, solo es necesario cuando se quiere guardar una
    imagen en un formato que no soporta niveles o transparencias (un canal
    alfa).
 </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    <guilabel>Aplatir l'image</guilabel> :
    permet de fusionner l'ensemble des calques dans un calque unique,
    sans canal Alpha, avec l'aspect de l'image complète vue depuis le haut
    de la pile. S'il existe des zones de transparence en allant jusqu'au bas
    de la pile, elles prendront la couleur d'arrière-plan. Cette
    opération fait aussi partie du processus d'exportation d'une image si
    vous l'enregistrez dans un format qui n'accepte pas les calques.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Appiattisci immagine</guimenuitem> fonde tutti i
    livelli dell'immagine in un unico livello senza canale alfa. Dopo
    l'appiattimento l'aspetto rimane invariato la differenza è che il
    contenuto dell'immagine è in un livello unico senza trasparenza. Aree
    trasparenti in tutti i livelli dell'immagine originale vengono riempite
    con il colore di sfondo.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Questa operazione opera cambiamenti significativi alla struttura
    dell'immagine. Normalmente è necessaria unicamente quando si vuole
    salvare l'immagine in un formato che non supporta i livelli o la
    trasparenza (un canale alfa).
 </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Flat ut biletet</guimenuitem> flettar
    saman alle laga i biletet til eitt lag, utan alfakanal. Etter at biletet er
    flata ut, er innhaldet det same som før, men nå er alt samla i eitt
    enkelt lag utan gjennomsikt. Dersom noen deler av biletet er
    gjennomsijtige gjennom heile lagstabelen, blir bakgrunsfargen
    synleg her.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Operasjonen gjer store forandringar i biletet. Til vanleg er denne
    flettinga bare nødvendig når biletet skal lagrast i eit format som
    ikkje har støtte for lag eller gjennomsikt.
 </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “平整图像”将导致图像的所有图层合并成为一个没有 Alpha 通道的单个图层，其
    外部表现和从顶部看整个图像相同。如果有任何可以看到底部图层的透明区域，它
    们会被图像的背景色填充。在导出图像为不支持图层的格式时，该操作会作为其中
    的一步被执行。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>latten Image</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz je dostupný z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Obrázek</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Zploštit obrázek</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>B</accel>ild</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Bild z<accel>u</accel>sammenfügen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Se puede acceder a este comando desde la barra de menú de la
          imagen, mediante  
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>magen</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>A<accel>p</accel>lanar la imagen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir d'un menu d'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>A<accel>p</accel>latir l'image</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mmagine</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>A<accel>p</accel>ppiattisci immagine</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Bilete</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Flat ut biletet</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>平整图像</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
