<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-07-29 lexa: patch from julien that includes suggestions by Sally
  2006-07-17 note added about the Colormap Dialog by j.h
  2005/10/25 created from image-mode.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-convert-indexed" lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-01</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-10-25</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-17</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Indexed mode</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Indexovaný režim</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Indiziert</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Le mode Indexé</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">索引</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Indexed colors</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Indiziert</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Indexé</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Couleurs indexées</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="cs">
    Viz <!--FIXME: cs <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">-->Slovníček
    pojmů<!--</link>--> pro více informací o indexovaném režimu barev.
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem> command converts your image to
    indexed mode. See
    <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">indexed colors</link> in the
    Glossary for more information about Indexed Color Mode.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie das Bild in das Farbmodell
    <quote>Indizierte Farben</quote>
    umwandeln. Weitere Informationen zu diesem Farbmodell finden Sie im
    Kapitel <xref linkend="glossary-indexedcolors" />.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande convertit votre image en mode indexé.
    Voir le <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Glossaire</link> pour
    des explications sur le modèle de couleurs indexées.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    请看<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">术语表</link>是如何解释索引模式的。
  </para>


  <sect3 lang="en;de;fr">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>ode</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>I</accel>ndexed</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>B</accel>ild</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>odus</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>I</accel>ndiziert</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à ce menu par la barre de menu de l'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>ode</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Couleurs <accel>I</accel>ndexées</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
        The <quote>Convert Image to Indexed Colors</quote> dialog
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Beschreibung des Dialogfensters
        <quote>Bild in indizierte Farben konvertieren</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        La fenêtre de dialogue <quote>Convertir l'image en couleurs
          indexées</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tato volba otevře dialog
      <guilabel>Převod indexované barvy</guilabel>:
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem> command opens the
      <guilabel>Convert Image to Indexed Colors</guilabel> dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cette option ouvre la boîte de dialogue
      <guilabel>Convertir l'image en couleurs indexées</guilabel>:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这个选项会打开
      <guilabel>将图像转换为索引颜色</guilabel>对话框：
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
          The <quote>Convert Image to Indexed Colors</quote> dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Dialogfensters
          <quote>Bild in indizierte Farben konvertieren</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La fenêtre de dialogue <quote>Convertir l'image en couleurs
            indexées</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-mode-indexed.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;de">
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-mode-indexed.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-image-mode-indexed.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-image-mode-indexed.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Obecné volby mapy barev</term>
        <term lang="en">Colormap Options</term>
        <term lang="de">Farbtabelle</term>
        <term lang="fr">Options générales de la palette</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">常规色板选项</term>

        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="cs">
                <guilabel>Generovat optimální paletu</guilabel>
                : tato volba vytvoří nejlepší možnou paletu barev s výchozím
                maximálním počtem barev 256. Toto množství můžete snížit v
                položce
                <emphasis>Maximální počet barev</emphasis>
                . Příliš nízký počet barev ale může způsobit ošklivé artefakty
                zejména v plynulých barevných přechodech. Pomocí rozptylu
                můžete tyto problémy minimalizovat.
              </para>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Generate optimum palette</guilabel>:
                This option generates the best possible palette with a
                default maximum number of 256 colors (classic GIF format).
                You can reduce this
                <emphasis>Maximum Number of Colors</emphasis>, although
                this may create unwanted effects (color banding) on smooth
                transitions. You may be able to lessen the unwanted effects
                by using dithering, however.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Optimale Palette erzeugen</guilabel>
                : Diese Auswahl erzeugt die bestmögliche Farbpalette mit einer
                maximalen Anzahl von 256 Farben. Sie können die
                <guilabel>maximale Anzahl von Farben</guilabel>
                durch Eingabe eines anderen Wertes verändern. Beachten Sie
                jedoch, dass ohne Farbrasterung eine maximale Anzahl von 256
                Farben für weiche Übergänge in einem Foto bspw. unschön
                aussehen kann.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Générer une palette optimale</guilabel>
                : Cette option génère la meilleure palette possible avec, par
                défaut, 256 couleurs (format GIF classique). Vous pouvez
                réduire ce
                <emphasis>Nombre maximum de couleurs</emphasis>
                . Cela risque d'entraîner des effets indésirables dans les
                zones nuancées que vous pouvez réduire en utilisant une option
                de tramage.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                <guilabel>生成优化色板</guilabel>
                ：这个选项生成一个最多 256 色的调色板（传统 GIF 格式），也可以减少
                <emphasis>最大色彩数量</emphasis>
                。但这可能在平滑转换的过程中产生不必要的影响，您可以用抖动选项减少影响。
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem lang="en;de;fr">
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Use web-optimized palette</guilabel>: use a
                palette that is optimized for the web.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Internet-optimierte Palette verwenden</guilabel>
                : Erstellt eine Palette mit Farben die websicher sind.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Utiliser une palette optimisée pour le
                  Web</guilabel>: Utilise une palette optimisée pour Internet.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="cs">
                <guilabel>Použít černobílou (1bitovou) paletu</guilabel>
                : Takto se vytvoří obrázky obsahující jen černou a bílou
                barvu, připomínající kresbu.
              </para>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Use black and white (1-bit) palette</guilabel>:
                This option generates an image which uses only two colors,
                black and white.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Schwarz/Weiß-Palette (1-Bit) verwenden</guilabel>
                : Diese Option reduziert das Bild auf die Verwendungen von
                zwei Farben: Schwarz und Weiß.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Utiliser la palette Noir et Blanc (1-bit)</guilabel>
                : Cette option génère une image au trait avec uniquement du
                blanc et du noir.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                <guilabel>使用黑白(1 位)色板</guilabel>
                ：这个选项通常用来产生艺术照式的图像。
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="cs">
                <guilabel>Použít vlastní paletu</guilabel>:
                Tato volba umožňuje zvolit vlastní paletu barev z nabídky
                otevřené po stisknutí tlačítka. U každé palety je uveden počet
                barev. Paleta označená jako Web (216) je bezpečná webová
                paleta navržená firmou Netscape pro zajištění stejného
                zobrazování barev na různých počítačích, např. na Windows a
                počítačích Macintosh. V dnešní době většina počítačů
                zobrazuje velké množství barev, proto tento problém není tak
                palčivý. Přesné zobrazování barev na různých platformách je
                však stále nedořešeným problémem. Na přesné zobrazení barev na
                webu nespoléhejte a držte se základního pravidla tvorby
                webových stránek: tmavý text na světlém pozadí a světlý text
                na tmavém pozadí.
              </para>
              <para lang="cs"> <!-- FIXME: cs -->
                Some colors of the palette may not be used if your image is
                poorly colored. They will be removed from the palette if the
                option
                <emphasis>
                  Remove Unused Colors from the Final Palette
                </emphasis>
                is checked.
              </para>

              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Use custom palette</guilabel>:
                This button lets you select a custom palette from a list.
                The number of colors is indicated for each palette. The
                <quote>Web</quote> palette, with 216 colors, is the
                <quote>web-safe</quote> palette. It was originally created
                by Netscape to
                provide colors that would look the same on both Macs and
                PCs, and Internet Explorer 3 could manage it. Since
                version 4, MSIE handles a 212 color palette. The problem
                of color similarity between all platforms has not been
                solved yet and it probably never will be. When designing a
                web page, you should keep two principles in mind: use light
                text on a dark background or dark text on a light
                background, and never rely on color to convey information.
              </para>
              <para lang="en">
                Some colors in the palette may not be used if your image
                does not have many colors. They will be removed from the
                palette if the <guilabel>Remove unused colors from final
                palette</guilabel> option is checked.
              </para>

              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Eigene Palette verwenden</guilabel>
                : lässt Sie Ihre eigene Palette verwenden. Per Klick auf die
                Schaltfläche öffnet sich der Palettendialog bei dem Sie
                vorinstallierte, oder eigene Paletten für die Indizierung
                verwenden können.
              </para>

              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Utiliser une palette personnalisée</guilabel>
                : Ce bouton vous permet de choisir une palette dans une liste.
                La Palette Web, 216 couleurs, est la palette de sécurité pour
                le Web. Créée à l'origine par Netscape pour fournir des
                couleurs identiques sur Mac et sur PC, Internet Explorer 3
                pouvait la gérer. mais depuis la version 4 , MSIE utilise une
                palette de 212 couleurs... Ce problème de concordance de
                couleurs entre les différentes plateformes n'est pas encore
                résolu et ne le sera probablement jamais. Vous devez donc
                respecter deux principes dans vos pages Web: texte clair sur
                fond sombre ou texte sombre sur fond clair et ne jamais
                confier une information à la couleur.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Certaines couleurs de la palette peuvent ne pas être utilisées
                si votre image est pauvre en couleurs. Vous pouvez les
                supprimer grâce à l'option
                <emphasis>
                  Enlever les couleurs non utilisées de la palette finale
                </emphasis>.
              </para>

              <para lang="zh_CN">
                <guilabel>使用自定义色板</guilabel>
                ：这个按钮允许您选择列表中的自定义色板。每种色板的色彩数已经指出。Web 色板，216 色，是 Web
                上最可靠的色板。最初，为了让 PC 和 Mac 看起来一样，同时 IE3 也能管理它。Netscape创造了这种色板。从
                IE4 以后，IE 开始处理 212
                色色板...，这个色彩问题类似于所有平台间的问题，它还没有解决，估计也不会解决了。您不得不在您的网页上保存两种原则：使用深底浅字或者浅底深字；不再给颜色指定信息。
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                如果您的图像色彩很少，可能有些颜色已不再使用。如果
                <emphasis>从最终色板中删除没有被使用的颜色</emphasis>
                选项选中了，这些颜色就会从色板中删除。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Nastavení rozptylu</term>
        <term lang="en">Dithering Options</term>
        <term lang="de">Farbrasterung</term>
        <term lang="fr">Options de tramage</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">抖动选项</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Protože indexovaný obrázek obsahuje 256 nebo méně barev, je
            pravděpodobné, že v jeho paletě chybí řada barev z originálního
            obrázku. To může způsobit nehezky vypadající přechody barev a
            další problémy v obrázku. Nastavení rozptylu tyto problémy pomáhá
            řešit.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Filtr se pokusí chybějící barvu aproximovat obarvením sousedních
            pixelů různými blízkými barvami z dostupné palety. Z dálky pak
            oblast s takovými pixely vypadá, jako by měla barvu nedostupnou v
            paletě. Více se dozvíte ve Slovníčku pojmů pod heslem
            <!--<link linkend="glossary-dithering">-->rozptyl<!--</link>-->
            .
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Dostupné jsou tři filtry pro rozptyl. Je těžké předpovídat, který
            z nich se pro konkrétní obrázek hodí nejlépe, a proto je dobré je
            postupně vyzkoušet.
            <emphasis>Umístěný</emphasis>
            se hodí pro animace.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Since an indexed image contains 256 colors or less, some colors
            in the original image may not be available in the palette. This
            may result in some blotchy or solid patches in areas which
            should have subtle color changes. The dithering options let you
            correct the unwanted effects created by the Palette Options.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            A dithering filter tries to approximate a color which is
            missing from the palette by instead using clusters of pixels
            of similar colors which are in the palette. When seen from a
            distance, these pixels give the impression of a new color. See
            the Glossary for more information on
            <link linkend="glossary-dithering">dithering</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Three filters (plus <quote>None</quote>) are available. It is
            not possible to predict what the result of a particular filter
            will be on your image, so you will have to try all of them and
            see which works best. The
            <quote>Positioned Color Dithering</quote> filter is well
            adapted to animations.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Durch die Farbreduktion treten bei weichen Farbverläufen in
            Bildern unschöne, harte Farbübergänge auf. Mittels Farbrasterung
            ist es möglich Farben so zu vermischen, die Pixel so anzuordnen,
            dass ein Farbverlauf erkennbar ist.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Drei Filter stehen zur Auswahl, die einen unterschiedlichen Effekt
            auf das Bild haben. Somit sind Sie angehalten, am besten alle drei
            Farbrasterungsarten auszuprobieren, und das beste Resultat zu
            behalten.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Comme une image indexée a 256 couleurs ou moins, un certain nombre
            de couleurs seront manquantes dans la palette. Ce qui pourra
            aboutir à un aspect de marbrures ou d'aplats dans les zones
            subtilement nuancées ou de franges sur les transitions de couleur
            douces. Ces options permettront de corriger autant que faire se
            peut ces effets indésirables induits par les Options de la
            palette.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le filtre essaiera de se rapprocher de la couleur manquante en
            dispersant des pixels de la couleur la plus proche dans la
            palette. Vus de loin, ces pixels dispersés et plus ou moins
            agglutinés donneront l'illusion d'une nouvelle couleur. Voir le
            <link linkend="glossary-dithering-fr">Glossaire</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Trois filtres sont disponibles. Il n'est pas possible de prévoir
            quel sera le résultat d'un filtre particulier et vous devrez tous
            les essayer pour trouver le meilleur résultat. Le
            <emphasis>Tramage par position</emphasis>
            est bien adapté aux animations.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            当一个索引图像包含 256
            种或更少的的颜色时，初始图像的一些颜色可能色板上没有。这就导致在精细的图像区出现噪点或纯色。这个选项允许您纠正这些由色板选项引起的不必要的影响。
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这个滤镜试图将颜色最接近丢失色彩的分散开的像素，靠着丢失色彩的地方聚集起来。这些聚起来的像素远看就象一种新颜色。请看
            <link linkend="glossary-dithering">术语表</link>
            。
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            有三种可用的滤镜。一种滤镜会产生什么结果是不可预见的，您不得不挨个试一遍才能找出最合适的滤镜。
            <emphasis>抖动色彩位置</emphasis>
            是对动画是最合适的。
          </para>

          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
                Example: full color, with no dithering
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">Beispiel alle Farben kein Dithering</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Exemple: toutes couleurs sans tramage</phrase>
            </title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/examples/dither1.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="cs">Příklad postupného barevného přechodu</para>
                <para lang="en">
                  This is an example image with a smooth transition in
                  RGB Mode.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Beispielbild mit weichen Farbverläufen im RGB-Modus.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Voici l'image d'un dégradé qui servira d'exemple.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">这里有一个平滑转换的例子：</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
                Example: four colors, with no dithering
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">Beispiel 4 Farben kein Dithering</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Exemple 4 couleurs sans tramage</phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/examples/dither2.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Stejný přechod po převodu do palety 4 barev
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The same image, after being transformed to four indexed
                  colors, without dithering.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Bild mit indizierter Farbtabelle und vier Farben.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Après transformation en GIF 4 couleurs, sans tramage.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">未使用抖动的 4 色 GIF 转换后：</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
                Example: Floyd-Steinberg (normal)
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">Beispiel Floyd-Steinberg (normal)</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Exemple de Floyd-Steinberg (normal)</phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/examples/dither3.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Stejný přechod ve 4 barvách s běžným Floydovým-Steinbergovým
                  rozptylem
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The same image, with four indexed colors and
                  <quote>Floyd-Steinberg (normal)</quote> dithering.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Bild mit indizierter Farbpalette von vier Farben und einer
                  Farbrasterung mittels Floyd-Steinberg (normal).
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  GIF 4 couleurs avec Floyd-Steinberg normal.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">使用 Floyd-Steinberg(普通)颜色抖动的 4 色 GIF：</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
                Example: Floyd-Steinberg (reduced color bleeding)
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">Beispiel Floyd-Steinberg 4 Farben</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Exemple de Floyd-Steinberg 4 couleurs</phrase>
            </title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/examples/dither4.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Stejný přechod ve 4 barvách s Floydovým-Steinbergovým
                  rozptylem se sníženým odběrem barev
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The same image, with four indexed colors and
                  <quote>Floyd-Steinberg (reduced color bleeding)</quote>
                  dithering.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Bild mit indizierter Farbpalette von vier Farben und einer
                  Farbrasterung mittels Floyd-Steinberg (reduziertes
                  Farbbluten).
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">GIF 4 couleurs avec Floyd-Steinberg-2.</para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  使用 Floyd-Steinberg(减少颜色损失)颜色抖动的 4 色 GIF：
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang="cs">
            Ve formátu GIF je průhlednost kódována jen jedním bitem
            (průhledný/neprůhledný). Pokud chcete získat iluzi částečné
            průsvitnosti, zaškrtněte volbu
            <guilabel>Povolit rozptyl průhlednosti</guilabel>
            , ale filtr Částečně zploštit dává lepší výsledky.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            In a GIF image, transparency is encoded in 1 bit: transparent
            or not transparent. To give the illusion of partial
            transparency, you can use the <guilabel>Enable dithering of
              transparency</guilabel> option. However, the
            <link linkend="plug-in-semiflatten">Semi-flatten</link>
            plug-in may give you better results.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">Les pixels sont peut-être moins agglutinés.</para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Dans une image GIF, la transparence est codée sur 1 bit: couleur
            transparente ou non transparente. Pour donner l'illusion de
            transparence partielle, vous pouvez utiliser l'option
            <guilabel>Active le tramage de la transparence</guilabel>, mais
            le filtre <link linkend="plug-in-semiflatten">Aplatir à
              moitié</link> vous donnera de meilleurs résultats.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            GIF 图像的透明度编码只有 1 位：透明或不透明。用
            <guilabel>启用透明度抖动</guilabel>
            可以给出一个局部透明的假象。但是用“半平整”插件可以得到更好的效果。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <note lang="en;fr"> <!--added 060713-->
      <para lang="en">
        You can edit the color palette of an indexed image by using the
        <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Colormap Dialog</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Vous pouvez afficher et modifier la palette de couleurs d'une
        image indexée en utilisant le
        <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Dialogue des Palettes
          indexées</link>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
