<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: 
     2006-01-07 en;fr reviewed by j.h
     2005/10/25 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
     2005/06/18 en Link added 
-->
<sect2 id='gimp-image-scale' lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Scale Image</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Velikost obrázku</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Bild skalieren</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Échelle et taille de l'image</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">缩放图像</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Scale Image</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Velikost obrázku</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Bild</primary>
    <secondary>skalieren</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Echelle et taille de l'image</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>缩放图像</primary>
  </indexterm>


  <para lang="en">
    The Scale Image function enlarges or reduces the image by changing the
    number of pixels it contains. It changes the size of the image content and
    resizes the canvas accordingly.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    It acts on the whole image. If your image has layers with different sizes,
    it is possible that making the image smaller will shrink some of them
    completely away (a layer cannot be less than 1 pixel wide or high). If
    this happens you will be warned before the operation is applied.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    If you want to scale a particular layer only, use the function
    <link linkend='gimp-layer-scale'>Scale Layer</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Funkce Velikost obrázku slouží ke zvětšování nebo zmenšování obrázku ve
    smyslu změny počtu pixelů, které obrázek obsahuje. Změní velikost obsahu
    obrázku a zároveň změní ve stejném poměru velikost plátna obrázku.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Velikost obrázku mění celý obrázek. Pokud zmenšovaný obrázek obsahuje více
    vrstev o různé velikosti, může se stát, že některá z nich bude zmenšena
    natolik, že úplně zmizí (rozměry vrstvy nemohou být menší, než 1 pixel).
    Pokud by se mělo něco takového stát, Gimp vás na to upozorní.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Pokud chcete zvětšit nebo zmenšit pouze jednu vrstvu, použijte funkci
    Změnit velikost vrstvy.<!-- TODO: cs link to do-->
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando könne Sie die physische Größe des Bildes, also die
    Anzahl der Pixel verändern. Der Inhalt des Bildes wird dabei skaliert,
    dass heißt an die neue Bildgröße angepasst.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Dieses Kommando wirkt auf das gesamte Bild. Wenn das Bild Ebenen mit
    verschiedenen Größen hat, kann es beim verkleinern des Bildes passieren,
    dass Ebenen komplett gelöscht werden, da diese nicht kleiner als 1 Pixel
    sein können. In einem solchen Fall werden Sie vor der Ausführung des
    Kommandos gewarnt.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Wenn Sie statt des Bildes nur eine Ebene skalieren möchten, steht Ihnen
    dafür das Kommando
    <link linkend='gimp-layer-scale'>Ebene skalieren</link>
    zur Verfügung.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Bei der Anwendung dieses Kommandos sollten Sie berücksichtigen, dass sie
    ein Bild an vier verschiedenen Stellen befinden kann: gespeichert in einer
    Bilddatei, geladen in den Hauptspeicher (RAM) Ihres Computers, angezeigt
    auf dem Bildschirm und ausgedruckt auf Papier. Wenn Sie das Bild skalieren
    ändert sich die Anzahl der Pixel im Bild und damit die Information die das
    Bild beinhaltet. Ausserdem wird die Größe des Platzes den das Bild im
    Hauptspeicher (geladen) und auf der Festplatte (gespeichert) benötigt
    verändert.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die gedruckte Größe des Bildes hängt neben der physischen Auflösung,
    der Anzahl von Pixeln im Bild, auch von der logischen Auflösung, also
    der Punkte pro Zoll, wie sie beim Drucken verwendet werden, ab. Wenn Sie
    die gedruckte Größe des Bildes verändern wollen, ohne die physische Größe
    des Bildes zu ändern, sollten Sie das Kommando
    <link linkend='gimp-image-print-size'>Druckgröße</link> verwenden.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    La fonction Taille de l'image agrandit ou réduit l'image en modifiant le
    nombre de pixels qu'elle contient. Le canevas est adapté à la taille de
    l'image de façon à ce que, au cas où l'image est devenu plus grande que le
    canevas, elle puisse être entièrement visible.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Elle agit sur l'ensemble de l'image. Si votre image possède des calques de
    taille différente, il se peut que certains soient réduits jusqu'à
    disparaître quand vous réduisez l'image. Le programme vous avertira.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Pour changer l'échelle d'un calque particulier, utilisez la fonction
    <link linkend='gimp-layer-scale'>Échelle et taille du calque</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    缩放图像功能用来扩大或缩小图像。为了让图像可见，这个功能缩放图像同时也改变画布大小。它也给出图像打印时的大小和分辨率。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    它是将整个图像一起操作的。如果图像包含不同尺寸的图层，它很可能让图像变得更小使得图层缩小。如果是这样，操作前，系统会警告您。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果想缩放特定的图层，可以使用缩放图层功能。<!-- TODO: zh_CN link to do -->
  </para>

  <note id='gimp-image-scale-warning'>
    <para lang="en">
      If scaling would produce an image larger than the "Maximum new image
      size" set in the
      <link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Environment</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog, you are warned and asked to confirm that
      you really want to do it. Saying yes will not necessarily have bad
      consequences, but you should give it a moment of thought, because very
      large images consume a lot of resources, and outrageously large images
      may consume more resources than you have, causing GIMP to crash or
      otherwise behave unpleasantly.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie mit dem Kommando ein Bild soweit vergrößern, dass es die maximale
      Größe für neue Bilde, die in den <application>GIMP</application>
      <link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Einstellungen</link>
      überschreitet, müssen Sie die Ausführung extra bestätigen.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour préparer votre image à être imprimée dans un format précis,
      utilisez l'outil
      <link linkend='gimp-tool-crop'>Découper et Redimensionner</link>
      en choisissant les cm comme unité de mesure: la taille affichée est la
      taille d'impression.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      准备打印图像时，用
      <link linkend='gimp-tool-crop'>剪裁</link>
      工具将要打印的图像变为一种特殊格式，用英寸作单位：这时显示的尺寸就是打印尺寸。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      如果缩放产生的新图层比首选项对话框的
      <link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>环境</link>
      里设置的“最大新建图像大小”还大。系统将询问您是否确定这样做。选“是”并不一定会有糟糕的后果，但您确实应该慎重考虑，因为大图像需要消耗许多系统资源，甚至比已有的资源还多。这将导致
      GIMP 死机或产生其它不可预料的结果。
    </para>
  </note>

  <sect3 lang="en;de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          This command can be accessed from an image menubar as
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>cale image</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>B</accel>ild</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Bild <accel>s</accel>kalieren</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          On accède à cette commande par le menu d'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>chelle et Taille de 
            l'image</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">Scale Image Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Beschreibung des Dialogfensters <quote>Bild skalieren</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        La fenêtre <quote>Échelle et Taille de l'image</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="cs;zh_CN">Dialog Image Scale</phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Scale Image</quote> dialog
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Dialogfenster <quote>Bild skalieren</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La fenêtre <quote>Échelle et Taille de l'image</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;de">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-scale-image.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-image-scale-image.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-image-scale-image.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Image Size</term>
        <term lang="de">Bildgröße</term>
        <term lang="fr">Taille d'image</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">像素尺寸</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You must remember that an image can be located in four places: In
            the image file, in the RAM after loading, on your screen when
            displayed, on paper after printing. Scaling the image changes the
            number of pixels (information) the image contains, so it directly
            changes the amount of memory the image needs (in RAM or in a
            file).
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            However print size depends also on the resolution of the image
            (which basically says, how many pixels each inch on paper
            contains). If you want to change printing size without scaling the
            image and changing the number of pixels it consist of, you should
            use the
            <link linkend='gimp-image-print-size'>Print Size dialog</link>
            . Screen size also depends not only on pixel number, but also on
            the screen resolution, zoom factor and the
            <link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>Dot for Dot</link>
            option.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie das Bild über die Originalgröße hinaus vergrößern, werden
            die neuen Pixel aus den vorhandenen berechnet. Dieser Vorgang wird
            <quote>Interpoltion</quote>
            genannt. Bitte beachten Sie, dass durch eine Interpolation, egal
            mit welchem Algorithmus nie neue Informationen in das Bild
            eingebracht werden. Wo keine Details in Ihrem Bild sind, wird auch
            eine Vergrößerung keine hinzaubern können. Vielmehr kann das Bild
            nach einer Skalierung unscharf wirken.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Eine Verringerung der Bildgröße ist beispielsweise angebracht,
            wenn Sie das Bild auf einer Webseite im Internet verwenden möchten.
            Hierbei sollten Sie beachten, dass die meisten Anwender im WWW
            mit einer Bildschirmauflösung von 1024x768 Pixel arbeiten, manche
            gar mit weniger. Ein zu großes Bild kann dann nicht vollständig 
            auf einer Bildschirmseite dargestellt werden.
          </para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en;zh_CN">Width; Height</term>
              <term lang="de">Breite; Höhe</term>
              <term lang="fr">Largeur; Hauteur</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  When you launch the Scale function GIMP displays the
                  dimensions of the original image in pixels. You can set the
                  <guilabel>Width</guilabel>
                  and the
                  <guilabel>Height</guilabel>
                  you want to give to your image by adding or removing pixels.
                  If the adjacent Chain icon is intact, width and height keep
                  their proportion. If you break it by clicking on it, you can
                  set them separately: this will result in deforming the
                  image.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  However you do not have to set dimensions in pixels, you can
                  choose different units from the drop down menu. If you 
                  choose percent as units, you can set the image size 
                  relatively to its original size. You can also use physical 
                  units like inches or millimeters. However if you do that, 
                  you should keep attention to the
                  <guilabel>X/Y resolution</guilabel>
                  fields (and set them to an appropriate value), because image
                  dimensions in pixels, which are being changed by this
                  dialog, are computed from physical units using these
                  resolution values.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  If you are enlarging an image beyond its original size,
                  missing pixels are calculated by interpolation but no new
                  detail is added. The more enlarged the image is, the more
                  blurred it becomes. The exact result of enlarging depends on
                  the chosen interpolation method. You can improve the result
                  by using the filter
                  <link linkend='plug-in-sharpen'>Sharpen</link>
                  (after scaling) but the best method is to use a high
                  resolution when scanning, taking digital photographs or
                  producing digital images by other means. Not scaling up well
                  is an inherit nature of raster images.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  Reducing your image may be necessary if you intend it to a
                  Web page. You have to take in account that most Internet
                  users have relatively small screens and that your big image
                  can't be completely displayed on them. Many of screens work
                  in 1024x768 or even smaller resolution.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  Adding or removing pixels is called "Resampling".
                </para>

                <para lang="de">
                  Wenn Sie den Dialog aufrufen, werden in den Eingabefeldern
                  <guilabel>Breite</guilabel>
                  und
                  <guilabel>Höhe</guilabel>
                  zunächst die bisherigen Ausmaße angezeigt. Sie können diese
                  beliebig verändern. Zu beachten ist dabei, dass hinter den
                  Eingabefeldern ein Kettensymbol angezeigt wird. Ist dieses
                  geschlossen,wird
                  <application>GIMP</application>
                  das Seitenverhältnis automatisch konstant halten. Wenn Sie
                  also für die Breite oder Höhe des Bildes einen neuen Wert
                  eintragen, so wird
                  <application>GIMP</application>
                  den jeweils anderen Wert automatisch anpassen. Sollten Sie
                  das Seitenverhältnis ändern wollen und für Breite und Höhe
                  des Bildes unabhängig voneinander Werte eingeben wollen, so
                  müssen Sie das Kettensymbol zunächst durch anklicken öffnen.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Neben der Eistellung der Bildgröße in Pixeln stehen Ihnen
                  noch weitere Maßeinheiten in einem Klappmenü zur Auswahl. So
                  können Sie beispielsweise sehr einfach die Bildgröße
                  prozentual einstellen. Außerdem stehen Ihnen hier physische
                  Längeneinheiten wie Millimeter oder Zoll zur Auswahl. Wenn
                  Sie diese verwenden wird die notwendige physische Auflösung
                  in Pixel von
                  <application>GIMP</application>
                  automatisch unter Berücksichtigung der im Dialogfenster
                  angegebenen
                  <guilabel>X; Y Auflösung</guilabel>
                  bestimmt.
                </para>

                <para lang="fr">
                  Retenez qu'une image peut se situer à quatre endroits: dans
                  le fichier d'image, dans la mémoire vive (RAM) après
                  chargement, sur l'écran après affichage, sur papier après
                  impression.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Cette section traite de l'agrandissement ou de la réduction
                  de votre image, des dimensions qu'elle aura en RAM et dans
                  votre fichier d'image après sauvegarde.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Quand vous ouvrez la boîte de dialogue, les dimensions
                  affichées sont celles de l'image d'origine. Sur l'écran,
                  tous les pixels du fichier d'image sont affichés et les
                  dimensions dépendent de la résolution de l'écran et de
                  l'option
                  <link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>
                    Point pour point
                  </link>
                  choisie.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Vous pouvez fixer la
                  <emphasis>largeur</emphasis>
                  et la
                  <emphasis>hauteur</emphasis>
                  que vous voulez donner à l'image, en ajoutant ou en
                  retranchant des pixels, ce qui entraînera une variation des
                  dimensions. Cliquez sur les pointes de flèche pour faire
                  varier la valeur dans la boîte de valeur et si vous avez
                  cliqué dans la boîte, vous pouvez utiliser les touches
                  flèches haut et bas pour un réglage précis. Vous pouvez agir
                  directement sur les dimensions dans l'unité de votre choix,
                  ce qui ajoutera ou retranchera des pixels. Ces dimensions
                  linéaires en mémoire ne sont guère utiles, elles dépendent
                  de la résolution et ce ne sont pas celles sur l'écran. Ce
                  qui compte, c'est le nombre de pixels, d'où le nom de cette
                  rubrique.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Le
                  <emphasis>Facteur d'échelle</emphasis>
                  est pour chaque axe X et Y le rapport entre la nouvelle
                  dimension sur l'axe et la même dimension à l'origine. Il est
                  par défaut de 1. Vous pouvez le changer. Si la chaîne
                  adjacente est intacte, les deux axes évolueront de concert.
                  Si vous la rompez en cliquant dessus, le réglage sur chaque
                  axe devient indépendant, mais vous aboutirez alors à une
                  déformation de l'image.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Vous ne pouvez agrandir une image en toute sécurité que si
                  elle possède au départ une résolution suffisante,
                  suffisamment de pixels pour qu'il ne soit pas nécessaire
                  d'en ajouter. Sinon, les pixels manquants seront calculés
                  par interpolation selon diverses méthodes mathématiques.
                  Mais ce n'est qu'un pis-aller: aucun détail nouveau
                  n'apparaît avec l'agrandissement. L'image risque d'être
                  d'autant plus floue que l'agrandissement est important et un
                  aspect en escalier peut apparaître sur les contours. Vous
                  pouvez améliorer les choses avec le filtre
                  <link linkend='plug-in-sharpen'>Augmenter la Netteté</link>
                  , (après changement d'échelle) mais le mieux est de veiller
                  à avoir une bonne résolution lors de la création du document
                  par scanneur ou appareil photo numérique.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  La réduction d'une image est souvent nécessaire si elle est
                  destinée à une page Web. Vous devez tenir compte que
                  d'autres internautes ont un écran plus petit que le vôtre,
                  et que votre grande image ne sera pas affichée en entier. La
                  plupart des écrans en activité travaillent en résolution
                  800x600 ou 1024x768.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Cette action d'ajouter (pour agrandir) ou de supprimer (pour
                  rétrécir) des pixels s'appelle
                  <emphasis>Rééchantillonnage</emphasis>
                  .
                </para>

                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  您一定记得图像的所在的四个位置：保存在图像文件里，载入后在 RAM 里，显示的时候在屏幕上，打印后在纸上。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">这部分就是处理图像在 RAM 中和保存到文件后的大小。</para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  当您打开对话框时，显示的是初始图像的参数。选中
                  <link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>点对点</link>
                  选项，屏幕上将显示所有的像素，大小依赖于屏幕分辨率。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  您可以设置
                  <emphasis>宽度</emphasis>
                  和
                  <emphasis>高度</emphasis>
                  来给图像加入或删除像素。结果就是图像的尺寸发生变化。点击文本框的箭头改变数值。如果您点在框里，也可以用上下箭头来精确调整。您可以直接用想要的单位作用在线性空间上，来增加或删除像素。这些内存中的线性空间没什么用：只有像素是重要的。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  <emphasis>比例</emphasis>
                  就是初始图像和新图像间 X、Y 轴间的比例。默认比例是
                  1，您可以修改它。如果旁边的锁链是完整的，那么两个轴一起变化。如果您点击锁链断开它，您就可以分别对两轴进行变化：这会导致图像变形。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  如果初始图像分辨率很高，像素多到可以不用增加新像素的话，您可以安全的扩大图像。否则，通过插值放大的图像会丢失细节，而且放的越大杂点越多，图像会变得乱糟糟的。您可以用<!-- <link linkend='plug-in-sharpen'> -->
                  锐化(缩放比例之后)。但是最好的办法是扫描您计划放大的图像时，采用一个高分辨率。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  如果您想要将图片放入网页时，最好给图片减减肥。要知道那些使用 15
                  寸显示器的互联网用户可能没法完整显示这些图片。大多数屏幕分辨率是 800x600 和 1024x768。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">加入或删除像素被称作“重采样”。</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en;zh_CN">X Resolution; Y Resolution</term>
              <term lang="de">X Auflösung; Y Auflösung</term>
              <term lang="fr">Résolution X; Résolution Y</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  Here you can set the print resolution for the image.
                </para>

                <para lang="de">
                  Mit diesen zwei Eigenschaften können Sie die logische
                  Auflösung des Bildes einstellen. Dies geschieht
                  üblicherweise in der Einheit
                  <quote>Pixel pro Inch</quote>
                  (dpi), Sie können aus dem Klappmenü jedoch auch andere
                  Einheiten wie
                  <quote>Pixel pro Millimeter</quote>
                  auswählen.
                </para>

                <para lang="fr">
                  Cette section traite de la taille qu'aura votre image une
                  fois imprimée. Retenez que tous les pixels de l'image seront
                  imprimés et qu'il n'y aura aucun découpage.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Quand vous lancez la fonction Taille de l'image, GIMP
                  affiche là les dimensions et la résolution de l'image
                  d'origine qui permettront d'obtenir une image sans
                  déformation lors de l'impression.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Comme au niveau de l'écran, vous pouvez augmenter ou réduire
                  la taille de l'image imprimée, avec les mêmes inconvénients.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  La Résolution est la résolution de sortie, c'est-à-dire le
                  nombre de pixels qui seront utilisés dans chaque pouce de
                  l'image imprimée. Il ne faut pas la confondre avec la
                  résolution de l'imprimante qui s'exprime en dpi (dot per
                  inch = points par pouce): il faut plusieurs points pour
                  imprimer un pixel.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Comme pour les dimensions, la résolution proposée par Gimp
                  est la résolution de l'image d'origine. Si vous augmentez la
                  résolution de sortie, la taille de l'image imprimée
                  diminuera puisque plus de pixels seront utilisés pour chaque
                  pouce. Inversement et pour la même raison, un changement de
                  taille d'impression modifiera corrélativement la résolution.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  L'augmentation de la résolution peut être intéressante pour
                  augmenter la netteté de l'image imprimée. L'image est plus
                  petite mais, contenant tous ses pixels reserrés, est plus
                  nette. Ce qui est différent d'une simple réduction de taille
                  où des pixels sont supprimés.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  La modification de résolution agit également pour le fichier
                  d'image. Ce n'est pas visible au niveau des pixels, mais ça
                  l'est au niveau des dimensions, en cm ou mm. En réduisant la
                  résolution vous diminuez les dimensions dans le fichier
                  d'image. En combinant une diminution de résolution et une
                  diminution du nombre de pixels puis en rétablissant les
                  dimensions initiales de votre image, vous disposez d'un
                  moyen de réduire le poids du fichier d'image si la
                  compression PNG ne suffit pas, en vue d'une utilisation sur
                  le Web.
                </para>

                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  这部分是处理图像在打印时候的大小和分辨率。记住，图像所有的像素都会没有分割的打印出来。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">当您启用缩放功能时，GIMP 显示图像未变形情况下的打印参数对话框。</para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">和屏幕显示图像一样，放大或缩小打印图像也有一样的风险。</para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  分辨率是指输出分辨率，就是打印图像上每英寸的像素数。不要把输出分辨率和打印分辨率混淆起来，打印分辨率用 dpi
                  表示（点每英寸）：也就是打印一个像素需要多个点。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  GIMP
                  采用的分辨率是初始图像的分辨率。因为总的像素数没变，如果您增大输出分辨率，打印的图像将变小，也就是每英寸打印的像素数增大。正因为如此，有时要重新设置修改过图像的大小。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  增大分辨率会让图像打印出来更锐利。这与单单减少图像尺寸不同。因为修改输出分辨率时没有删除像素。
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  修改分辨率也会影响图像文件大小。这种修改因为总的像素数没变所以在像素级看不出来，但是尺寸级（例如英寸）可以看出来。减小输出分辨率就减小了图像文件大小。在使用
                  PNG 压缩后图像还不够小时，可以通过结合降低分辨率和减小像素并重建图像原始尺寸的方法来减小图像文件大小。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="zh_CN">Quality</term>
        <term lang="en">Quality</term>
        <term lang="de">Qualität</term>
        <term lang="fr">Qualité</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            The
            <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel>
            drop down list provides a selection of available methods of
            interpolating the color of pixels in a scaled image:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Um eine Veränderung an der Bildgröße vorzunehmen müssen entweder
            vorhandene Pixel entfernt, oder neue Pixel zum Bild hinzugefügt
            werden. Mit welchem Verfahren dies geschieht bestimmt maßgeblich
            die Qualität des Ergebnisses.
            <application>GIMP</application>
            stellt Ihnen hierzu verschiedene Algorithmen zur Auswahl:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            C'est ici que vous choisissez la méthode qui sera utilisée pour
            l'interpolation de la couleur des pixels ajoutés, valable aussi
            bien pour l'affichage à l'écran que pour l'impression.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">这里您可以选择添加像素的颜色插入的方法，这对屏幕显示和打印都有影响。</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Interpolation Type</term>
              <term lang="de">Interpolation</term>
              <term lang="fr">Type d'interpolation</term>
              <term lang="zh_CN">插值类型</term>

              <listitem>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para lang="en">
                      <guilabel>None</guilabel>
                      : no interpolation is used. Pixels are simply enlarged
                      or removed as they are when zooming. This method is low
                      quality, but very fast.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      <guilabel>Keine</guilabel>: Mit dieser Einstellung wird
                      keine Interpolation durchgeführt. Die einzelnen Pixel
                      werden durch einfaches weglassen oder duplizieren
                      entfernt oder hinzugefügt. Das geht zwar sehr schnell,
                      die Ergebnisse sind aber von sehr geringer Qualität.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      <emphasis>Aucune</emphasis>
                      : Aucune interpolation n'est utilisée. Les pixels sont
                      simplement agrandis comme ils le sont avec le zoom.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="zh_CN">
                      <emphasis>无</emphasis>
                      ：就是不采用插值法。像素就是简单的扩大，就象放大时一样。
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para lang="en">
                      <guilabel>Linear</guilabel>
                      : this method is relativelly fast, but still provides
                      fairly good results.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      <guilabel>Linear</guilabel>: In dieser Einstellung wird
                      eine lineare Interpolationsmethode verwendet. Diese ist 
                      ein Kompromiss zwischen Geschwindigkeit und  Qualität.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      <emphasis>Linéaire</emphasis>: Cette méthode 
                      d'interpolation linéaire est relativement rapide tout 
                      en produisant de bons résultats.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="zh_CN">
                      <emphasis>线性</emphasis>：
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para lang="en">
                      <guilabel>Cubic</guilabel>
                      : The best, highest quality but also the slowest method
                      available.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      <guilabel>Kubisch</guilabel>: Mit dieser Einstellung 
                      wird eine kubische Interpolationsmethode verwendet. 
                      Diese ist zwar in der Berechnung recht aufwändig, 
                      erzeugt aber die qualitativ besten Ergebnisse.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      <emphasis>Cubique</emphasis>
                      : La meilleure méthode, mais nécessite beaucoup de
                      calcul.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="zh_CN">
                      <emphasis>立方</emphasis>
                      ：最好的插值方法，但是需要的更多计算。
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
