<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-image-merge-layers' lang='en;fr;zh_CN'>
  <title lang='en'>Merge Visible Layers</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Fusionner les calques visibles</title>
  <title lang='de'>Sichtbare Ebenen vereinen</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">合并可见图层</title>
  
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Layers</primary>
    <secondary lang='en'>Merge</secondary>
    <tertiary lang='en'>Visible</tertiary>
    <primary lang="fr">Fusionner les calques visibles</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">合并可见图层</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en;zh_CN">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-merge-visible.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-image-merge-visible.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  
    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Merge Visible Layers</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Merge Visible Layers" merges all layers of the image for which
      an "eye" symbol is shown in the Layers dialog
      into a single layer, leaving non-visible layers untouched.  It
      is useful for merging a set of layers that may be scattered
      around the layer list.  Selecting it brings up a dialog that
      asks you to choose between three options for the size of the
      final, merged layer:  "Expanded as necessary" means that it
      will be made as small as possible without losing any of the
      contents of the merged layers; "Clipped to image" means it
      will be set to the size of the image and any layer contents
      outside the image bounds will be lost; and "Clipped to bottom
      layer" means what it says.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      <emphasis>Expanded as necessary</emphasis>: The final layer 
      has the size of the largest layer of all of the visible 
      layers. (Remember that a layer in GIMP can be larger than the 
      image) 
    </para>
    <para lang='en'> 
      <emphasis>Clipped to image</emphasis> Will set the final layer 
      size equal to the image size. (Remember that layers in GIMP 
      can be larger than the image itself. If you have such a 
      visible layer it will be clipped to the image size). 
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      <emphasis>Clipped to bottom layer</emphasis>:  Will set the 
      final layer size equal to the bottom layer. If the bottom 
      layer is smaller than some of your visible layers, then 
      the final layer will be clipped and trimmed according to both 
      the size and position of the bottom layer. 
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette commande se trouve dans <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Image/Fusionner
      les ca<accel>l</accel>ques visibles...</guimenuitem>.
    </para>     
    <para lang='fr'>
      <guilabel>Fusionner les calques visibles</guilabel> : permet de
      fusionner les calques visibles, ceux qui sont marqués par l'icone
      en forme d'oeil.  Un dialogue s'ouvre.  L'option <guilabel>Étendu
      autant que nécessaire</guilabel> permet de conserver des données
      dans des calques de taille supérieures à celle du canevas.
      L'option <guilabel>Rogné à la taille de l'image </guilabel> permet
      de retailler la taille du calque final à celle du canevas l'image,
      l'option <guilabel>Rogné à la taille du calque le plus bas
      </guilabel> permet de ne conserver que les données contenues dans
      les limites du calque le plus bas. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Il y a trois façons de fusionner les calques visibles (calques
      avec un «oeil»): 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      <emphasis>Étendu autant que nécessaire</emphasis>: Le calque 
      final aura la taille du plus grand des calques visibles. 
      (Rappelez-vous que dans Gimp un calque peut être plus grand 
      que l'image).
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'> 
      <emphasis>Rogné à la taille de l'image</emphasis>: Le calque 
      final aura la taille de l'image. (Rappelez-vous que dans Gimp 
      les calques peuvent être plus grands que l'image. Si un des 
      calques visibles est dans ce cas, il sera rogné à 
      la taille de l'image). 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      <emphasis>Rogné à la taille du calque le plus bas</emphasis>: 
      Le calque final aura la taille du calque le plus bas situé. Si 
      le calque du bas est plus petit que l'un des autres calques, 
      le calque final aura cette taille.
    </para>
  
  <para lang='de'>
    <guilabel>Sichtbare <accel>E</accel>benen vereinen</guilabel>:
    vereinigt alle sichtbaren Ebenen, gekennzeichnet durch ein
    Augensymbol, zu einer Hintergrundebene. 
  </para>

    <para lang='zh_CN'>
      该命令在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>合并可见图层</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>。
    </para>
    <para lang='zh_CN'>   
      “合并可见图层”将图像所有在图层对话框中显示有“眼睛”标志的图像合并成为一个单个图层，而使不可见图层保持原状。这可以用作合并一组散布在图层列表中的图层。选择该命令将唤出一个有三个选择最终合并后图层大小的选项的对话框：“必要时扩展”会使合并后图层在不丢失其内容的前提下尽可能小;“剪切板到图像”会使它和图像大小相同，而图像边缘外的任何图层内容都会丢失;“剪切板到底部图层”其含义和它的名字相同。
    </para>
    <para lang='zh_CN'>
      <emphasis>必要时扩展</emphasis>：最终图层的大小就是最大的可见图层的大小。(记住，在 GIMP 中图层可能比图像更大。)
    </para>
    <para lang='zh_CN'> 
      <emphasis>剪贴板到图像</emphasis>：将最终图层大小设置成和图像一样大。(记住 GIMP 里的图层可能比本身的图像更大。如果您有一个这样的可见图层，它可能被省略成图像大小。)
    </para>
    <para lang='zh_CN'>
      <emphasis>剪贴板到底部图层</emphasis>：将最终图层大小设置为底部图层的大小。如果底部图层比某些可见图层小，那么最终图层可能按照底部图层的大小和位置省略或修整掉一部分。
    </para>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Shortcut</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturkürzel</title>
    <title lang="fr">Raccourcis clavier</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">快捷键</title>

    <para lang="en">
      The <keycap>Ctrl+M</keycap> key combination 
      will execute the Merge Visible Layers command.
    </para>
          
    <para lang="de">
      Sie können diese Funktion mit folgendem Tastaturkürzel
      aufrufen:
      <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>M</keycap></keycombo>
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      La combinaison de touches <keycap>Ctrl+M</keycap>
      activera la fonction Fusionner les calques visibles.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这个命令的快捷键是<keycap>Ctrl+M</keycap>。
    </para>

  </simplesect>

</sect2>
