<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-image-print-size' lang="en">
  <title lang="cs">Velikost tisku</title>
  <title lang="en">Print Size</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">Velikost tisku</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Print Size</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-print-size.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-image-print-size.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Tisková velikost</title>
    <title lang="en">Print Size</title>

    <para lang="en">
      This dialog is used for changing <emphasis>dimensions of a printed
      image</emphasis> and its <emphasis>resolution</emphasis>. It doesn't
      change the number of pixels in the image; it doesn't resample it (if
      you would like to change the size of an image by resampling it, you
      should use the <link linkend='gimp-image-scale'>Scale Image</link>
      function instead.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Output resolution determines the number of pixels that will be used in
      every inch of the printed image (or another length unit, depending on
      your preference). You must not mistake the output resolution with the
      printer resolution which is expressed in dpi (dots per inch): several
      dots are necessary to print a pixel.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can set the required dimensions in the <guilabel>Height</guilabel>
      and <guilabel>Width</guilabel> fields or the required resolution in the
      <guilabel>X/Y resolution</guilabel> fields. You can use different units
      for both printing dimensions and resolution in the dropdown lists.
      Vertical and horizontal dimensions (and resolutions) are kept in a
      constant proportion by default, you can unlink them by clicking on the
      Chain icon.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The resolution proposed by GIMP is the resolution of the original image.
      If you increase the output resolution the printed image will be smaller
      since more pixels are used for an inch. Conversely and for the same
      reason resizing modifies resolution.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Increasing resolution results in increasing the printed image sharpness.
      This is quite different from simply reducing the image size by scaling
      it since no pixels (no image information) are removed.
    </para>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
