<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-09-25 AntI: Added 'es'
  2007-02-04 added 'no' by KoSt
  2006-08-26 lexa: fixed docbook errors
  yyyy-mm-tt n.n.: added section for context menu
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-menus-introduction">
  <title>Introduction to Menus</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Menus</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <!--TODO: add image menubar screenshot instead(?)-->
  <!--
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase>The Toolbox Menu</phrase>
    </title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/toolbox-menu.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  -->

  <para>
    There are many places in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> where you can
    find menus. The aim of this chapter is to explain all the commands that
    are accessible from the menus in the Toolbox and Image windows. All the
    context menus and the menu entries for the other dialogs are described
    elsewhere in the chapters that describe the dialogs themselves.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="context-menus">
    <title>Context Menus</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Context menus</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      If you right-click on certain parts of the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> interface, a
      <quote>context menu</quote> opens, which leads to a variety of
      functions. Some places where you can access context menus are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Clicking on an image window displays the Image menu. This is useful
          when you are working in full-screen mode, without a menubar.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Clicking on a layer in the Layers Dialog or on a channel in the
          Channels Dialog displays functions for the selected layer or
          channel.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Right-clicking on the image menubar has the same effect as
          left-clicking.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Right-clicking on the title bar displays functions which do not
          belong to <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
          but to the window manager program on your computer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <!-- TODO: update (are detachable submenus removed?) -->
  <sect2 id="detachable-submenus">
    <title>Detachable Submenus</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Detachable submenus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tear-off line</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      There is an interesting property associated with some of the menus in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      These are any of the menus from the Toolbox menubar and any of their
      submenus, as well as the Image context menu you get by right-clicking on
      the image window and any of its submenus. (You can tell that a menu item
      leads to a submenu because there is an
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/menus/icon-submenu.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      icon next to it.) When you bring up any of these menus, there is a
      dotted line at the top of it (tear-off line). By clicking on this
      dotted line, you detach the menu under it and it becomes a separate window.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
        The <quote>Acquire</quote> submenu and its detached submenu
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/file-acquire-submenu.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/detached-submenu.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Detached submenus originating from the Toolbox are only visible when the
      Toolbox is active. Detached submenus originating from the Image window
      are actually independent. They are always visible, their functions
      always apply to the current image, and they persist when all of the
      images are closed. You can close a detached submenu by clicking on the
      dotted line again or closing the window from the window manager on your
      computer (often by clicking on an X icon in the upper right corner of
      the window).
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
