<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: 
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
  2005/09/03 de created by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id='gimp-layer-introduction' lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-01-12</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-25</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-04</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Introduction to Layers</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Vrstvy</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Introduction aux Calques</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Einführung in das Menü <quote>Ebene</quote></phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">图层</phrase>
  </title>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">The Layers menu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Inhalt des <guilabel>Ebene</guilabel> Menüs.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Menu des calques</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">图层菜单</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/layer.png' 
          format="PNG" lang="cs;en;zh_CN" />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/de/layer.png' 
          format="PNG" lang="de" />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/fr/layer.png'
          format="PNG" lang="fr" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    In addition to the image menubar and image right-click menu, you can also
    get the Layers menu by right-clicking on a layer thumbnail in the Layers
    dialog. Several of the operations in this menu are also available from
    buttons in the Layers dialog: resizing a layer, managing layer
    transparency, and merging layers.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    This menu can contain other entries that don't actually belong to GIMP: 
    they have been brought by some plug-ins.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Die in diesem Menü befindlichen Kommandos dienen Ihnen zur Bearbeitung
    von Ebenen.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Neben den an dieser Stelle vorgestellten Kommandos können sich weitere
    Einträge im Menü befinden. Diese gehören nicht zum Standardumfang von
    <application>GIMP</application>
    , sondern sind Programmerweiterungen (Plug-In). Eine Beschreibung der
    Funktionalität entnehmen Sie bitte der Dokumentation des Plug-In.
    <!-- de TODO: the more important plugins should be documented in the manual -->
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    En plus de la barre de menus de l'image, le menu contextuel des calques
    est accessible via un clic-droit sur la vignette d'un calque. Ce menu
    offre une bonne partie des actions déjà accessibles par les boutons du
    dialogue des calques, des possibilités de redimensionnement du calque, une
    gestion de la transparence et aussi de fusion de l'ensemble des calques.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Ce menu peut contenir d'autres entrées qui n'appartiennent pas en propre 
    à GIMP, mais qui ont été ajoutées par quelques greffons.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    除了图像菜单和图像右键菜单，您也可以用右键点击图层对话框的图层缩略图获取图层菜单。该菜单中许多操作也在图层对话框的按钮中：缩放图层，管理图层的透明度和合并图层。
  </para>
</sect2>
