<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-05-24 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-02-21 KoSt: added no
  2005/11/03 split of from menu-layer.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-merge-down" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-01</date>
        <authorinitials>wes</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-01</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-05-24</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-02</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Merge Down</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Nach unten vereinen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Combinar hacia abajo</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fusionner vers le bas</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Fondi in basso</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Flett saman nedover</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">向下合并</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Stack managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Merge current layer with the underlying layer</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Merge Down</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary>
    <secondary>nach unten vereinen</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Gestionar la pila</secondary>
    <tertiary>Combinar la capa actual con la capa subyacente</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Combinar hacia abajo</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer la pile de calques</secondary>
    <tertiary>Fusionner le calque actif avec le calque sous-jacent</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Fusionner vers le bas</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Livello</primary>
    <secondary>Gestione della pila</secondary>
    <tertiary>Fonde il livello corrente con quello sottostante</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Fondi in basso</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Flett saman nedover</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Merge Down</guimenuitem>
    command merges the active layer with the layer just below it in the stack,
    taking into account the various properties of the active layer, such as
    its opacity and layer
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">mode</link>.
    The resulting merged layer will be in Normal mode, and will inherit the
    opacity of the layer below. If the layer below is not opaque, or if it is
    in some mode other than Normal, then this command will generally change
    the appearance of the image.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The most common use of <guimenuitem>Merge Down</guimenuitem> is to
    construct a layer, by starting with a <quote>base layer</quote> (usually
    opaque and in Normal mode, so that you can see what you are doing), and
    adding a <quote>modification layer</quote> on top of it, with whatever
    shape, opacity, and layer mode you need.  In this case, merging down the
    modification layer will combine the two layers into one, without
    changing the way the image looks.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die aktive Ebene mit der darunter liegenden
    Ebene vereinen. Dabei werden die verschiedenen Eigenschaften der aktiven
    Ebene, also beispielsweise die Transparenz und der <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Ebenenmodus</link>, berücksichtigt.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    <!--TODO de:  Review, der englische Text ist irgendwie seltsam...-->
    Eine typische Anwendung dieses Kommandos ist, über einer Ebene eine
    <quote>Arbeitsebene</quote> mit beliebigen Eigenschaften zu erstellen und
    zu bearbeiten und dann im letzten Schritt die Ebenen zu vereinen. Auf
    diese Weise muss man nicht direkt auf der ursprünglichen Ebene arbeiten.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El comando <guimenuitem>Combinar hacia abajo</guimenuitem> combina la
    capa activa con la capa inmediata por debajo en la pila, teniendo en
    cuenta las propiedades de la capa activa, su opacidad y el
    <!--PENDING es: fix link
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes"-->modo de capa<!--/link-->.
    La mezcla resultante estará en modo normal, y heredará la opacidad de la
    capa subyacente. Si la capa subyacente no es opaca, o si tiene otro modo
    que el normal, este comando, generalmente, cambiará la apariencia de la
    imagen.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    El uso más común de <guimenuitem>Combinar hacia abajo</guimenuitem> es
    para construir una capa, empezando con una <quote>capa base</quote>
    (normalmente, opaca y en modo normal, para poder ver lo que está
    haciendo), y añadir una <quote>capa de modificación</quote> encima de
    ella, con la forma, opacidad y modo de capa que necesite. En este caso,
    combinar hacia abajo la capa de modificación combinará las dos capas en
    una, sin cambiar el aspecto de la imagen.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande permet de fusionner le calque actif avec le calque situé
    juste en-dessous dans la liste. Le calque résultant de la fusion devient
    le calque actif. L'opacité du calque actif initial et le
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Modes de calque</link> sont
    pris  en compte.
    Le calque fusionné résultant sera en mode Normal et héritera de l'opacité
    du calque inférieur. Si le calque inférieur n'est pas opaque, ou s'il est
    dans un mode autre que Normal, la commande altérera l'apparence de
    l'image.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'utilisation la plus courante de <guimenuitem>Fusionner vers le bas
    </guimenuitem> est de créer un <quote>calque de base</quote>
    (habituellement opaque et en mode Normal), puis d'ajouter au-dessus un
    <quote>calque de modification</quote> possédant la forme, l'opacité ou
    le mode voulus. De cette façon, la fusion du calque de base et du
    calque de modification combinera les deux calques sans changer l'aspect
    de l'image.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>fondi in basso</guimenuitem> fonde il livello
    attivo con quello subito sottostante nella pila, prendendo in
    considerazione le varie proprietà del livello attivo, come l'opacità e
    la <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">modalità di
    livello</link>. Il livello fuso risultante sarà in modalità normale, e
    erediterà l'opacità del livello sottostante. Se il livello sottostante
    non è opaco, o se dovesse avere una modalità diversa da quella normale,
    questo comando in generale avrà l'effetto ulteriore di cambiare
    l'aspetto dell'immagine.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    L'uso più comune di <guimenuitem>fondi in basso</guimenuitem> è di
    costruire un livello, cominciando con un <quote>livello base</quote>
    (normalmente opaco e in modalità normale, in modo tale da poter vedere
    cosa si sta facendo), ed aggiungendo un <quote>livello di
    modifica</quote> su di esso, con una qualsiasi forma, opacità e
    modalità di livello che si abbisogni.  In questo caso, la fusione del
    livello di modifica combinerà i due livelli in uno, senza cambiare
    l'aspetto finale dell'immagine..
  </para>
  
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Flett saman nedover</guimenuitem> fletter
    det aktive laget saman med laget like under. Det blir tatt omsyn til
    innstillingane til det aktive laget, slik som gjennomsikt og 
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">modus</link>. Det
    samansette laget vil vere i normalmodus og vil arve gjennomsikta frå
    det nedre laget. Dersom det nedre laget er gjennomsiktig eller  er i
    anna modus enn normalmodus, vil denne kommandoen til vanleg føre
    til synlege forandringer i biletet.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Den mest vanlege bruksmåten for <guimenuitem>Flett saman 
    nedover</guimenuitem> er å opprette eit ugjennomsiktig 
    <quote>basislag</quote>, som oftast einsfarga og i
    normalmodus, og bruke dette som underlag for eit 
    <quote>arbeidslag</quote>. Dermed blir det lettare å sjå kva du
    gjer på arbeidslaget, særleg om du arbeider med meir eller mindre
    gjennomsiktige område.  Når arbeidet er utført, fletter du dei to
    laga saman. Resten av biletet blir uforandra.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="zh_CN">该命令使活动图层与在图层列表中活动图层下的图层合并，并
  考虑活动图层的不透明度和组合模式。</para>


  <sect3 lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ayer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Merge Do<accel>w</accel>n</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Nach un<accel>t</accel>en vereinen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>apa</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Combinar hacia abajo</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Vous le trouverez dans
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>alque</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>usionner vers le bas</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ivello</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>ondi in basso</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Flett saman nedover</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
