<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2007-11-30 j.h: updated en;fr for v2.4. Moved from layer menu to image
     menu
     2007-06-18 Added Spanish translation by AntI
     2007-03-12 Kolbjørn: added no translation
     2006-07-31 scb: revised 'en'
     -->
<sect2 id="plug-in-align-layers" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-02</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-01</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-06-18</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-02</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Align Visible Layers</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Sichtbare Ebenen anordnen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Alinear capas visibles</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Aligner les calques visibles</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Allinea livelli visibili</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Innrett synlege lag</phrase>
  </title>
  
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Stack managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Align visible layers</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Align visible layers</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary><secondary>ausrichten</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Animation</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Gestión de la pila</secondary>
    <tertiary>Alinear capas visibles</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Alinear capas visibles</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer la pile de calques</secondary>
    <tertiary>Aligner les calques visibles</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Aligner les calques visibles</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Livello</primary><secondary>Allinea</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary><secondary>Innrett synlege lag</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Innrett synlege lag</primary></indexterm>
  
  <para lang="en">
    With the <guimenuitem>Align Visible Layers</guimenuitem> command,
    you can very precisely position the visible layers (those marked with
    the <quote>eye</quote> icon). This degree of precision is especially
    useful when you are working on animations, which typically have many
    small layers. Clicking on <guimenuitem>Align Visible
      Layers</guimenuitem> displays a dialog which allows you to choose
    how the layers should be aligned.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die im Bild sichtbaren Ebenen sehr exakt
    ausrichten. Dies kann hilfreich sein, wenn Sie an Animationen arbeiten, die
    typischerweise viele kleine Ebenen erfordern. Nach welchen Regeln die
    Ebenen ausgerichtet werden, können Sie in einem Dialogfenster einstellen,
    welches Ihnen nach dem Aufruf des Kommandos angezeigt wird.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Con el comando <guimenuitem>Alinear capas visibles</guimenuitem>, puede
    posicionar de una manera precisa las capas visibles (aquellas marcadas
    con el icono <quote>ojo</quote>). Este grado de precisión es muy útil
    cuando trabaja con animaciones, que normalmente tienen muchas capas
    pequeñas. Al pulsar sobre  <guimenuitem>Alinear capas visibles</guimenuitem>
    se muestra un diálogo que permite elegir como se alinearán las capas.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande permet de positionner les calques visibles (ceux marqués
    d'un œil) de façon très précise. Ce n'est pas utile dans le travail
    habituel sur les images, mais ça l'est beaucoup plus lors de la création
    d'animations, avec de nombreux petits calques. En cliquant sur cette
    option, vous ouvrez une fenêtre de dialogue contenant de nombreux
    paramètres d'alignement.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Con il comando <guimenuitem>allinea livelli visibili</guimenuitem>, è
    possibile posizionare in maniera precisa i livelli visibili (quelli
    marcati con l'icona a forma di <quote>occhio</quote>). Questo livello
    di precisione è utile in special modo quando si sta lavorando con le
    animazioni, che tipicamente sono formate da molti piccoli
    livelli. Facendo clic su <guimenuitem>allinea livelli
      visibili</guimenuitem> viene mostrata una finestra di dialogo che
    permette di scegliere come dovranno essere allineati i livelli.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Innrett synlege lag</guimenuitem> blir
    brukt til å setje nøyaktig possisjon for dei synlege laga, dvs. dei som
    er merkte med <quote>auge</quote>-ikonet i lagmenyen. Dette er
    særleg nyttig når du arbeider med animasjonar, som svært ofte har
    mange små lag. Klikkar du på kommandoen, opnar det seg eit
    dialogvindauge der du kan bestemme ein del verdiar for plasseringa.
  </para>
  
  
  <note>
    <para lang="en">
      In <application>GIMP 1.2</application>, the default base for the
      alignment was the top visible layer in the stack.  In
      <application>GIMP 2</application>, the default alignment base is
      the edge of the canvas. You can still align the image on the bottom
      layer of the stack, even if it is invisible, by checking
      <guilabel>Use the (invisible) bottom layer as the base</guilabel>
      in the dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Bezugsobjekt der Ausrichtung ist standardmäßig die Zeichenfläche.
      Sie können jedoch durch Aktivieren der Eigenschaft <guilabel>Die
        unterste (unsichtbare) Ebene als Basis verwenden</guilabel> auch
      eine Ebene als Bezugsobjekt der Ausrichtung verwenden.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      En el <application>GIMP 1.2</application>, la base predefinide para la
      alineación fué la capa visible de arriba en la pila. En el
      <application>GIMP 2</application>, la base de la alineación predefinida
      es el borde del lienzo. Puede alinear la imagen sobre la capa del fondo
      de la pila, marcando
      <guilabel>Usar la capa inferior (invisible) como base</guilabel>
      en el diálogo.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans Gimp-1.2, la base d'alignement par défaut était le calque visible
      supérieur dans la pile. Dans Gimp-2, cette base est maintenant le bord
      du canevas. Vous pouvez toujours aligner sur le calque du bas de la
      pile en cochant la case <guilabel>Utilisez le calque du bas
        (invisible) comme base</guilabel> dans le dialogue.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      In <application>GIMP 1.2</application>, la base di allineamento
      predefinita era il livello visibile in cima alla pila.  In
      <application>GIMP 2</application>, la base di allineamento è il bordo
      della superficie disegnabile. È ancora possibile allineare l'immagine
      sul livello in fondo alla pila, anche se invisibile, impostando
      l'opzione <guilabel>Usa il livello inferiore (invisibile) come
        base</guilabel>, presente nella finestra di dialogo.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I <application>GIMP 1.2</application> var det øverste synlege laget
      utgangspunktet for innrettinga. I <application>GIMP 2</application>
      er utgangspunktet kantane på lerretet. Du kan også bruke botnlaget
      som basis for innrrettinga, sjølv om det ikkje er synleg, ved å
      markere for <guilabel>Bruk det (usynlege) botnlaget som
        basis</guilabel> i dialogvindauget.
    </para>
  </note>
  
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Example image for layer alignment</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Beispielbild zur Ebenenausrichtung</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Imagen de ejmplo para alineación de capas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Images pour exemples</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Immagine di esempio di allineamento livelli</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på innretting</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/align-demo.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          The example image contains four layers on a large (150x150 pixel)
          canvas. The red square is 10x10 pixels, the green rectangle is
          10x20 pixels and the yellow rectangle is 20x10 pixels. The
          background layer (blue, 100x100 pixels) will not be affected by
          the command, since the <guilabel>Ignore lower layer</guilabel>
          option has been checked on the dialog. Note that the layers in the
          image seem to have a different order than their actual order in
          the stack because of their positions on the canvas. The yellow
          layer is the top layer in the image and the second one in the
          stack.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Beispielbild enthält vier Ebenen auf einer großen Zeichenfläche.
          Die rote ist 10x10 Pixel, die grüne 10x20 Pixel und die gelbe
          20x10 Pixel groß. Die Hintergrundebene (blau: 100x100 Pixel) wird
          nicht durch das Kommando beeinflusst, da die Eigenschaft
          <guilabel>Die unterste Ebene ignorieren</guilabel> aktiviert ist.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          La imagen de ejemplo contiene cuatro capas en un gran lienzo
          (150x150 píxel). El cuadro rojo es 10x10, El rectángulo verde es
          10x20 y el rectángulo amarillo es 20x10. La capa de fondo (azul,
          100x100 píxel) no se verá afectada por el comando, si la opción
          <guilabel>No considerar la capa inferior aunque esté visible
          </guilabel> está marcada en el diálogo. Note que lsa capas en la
          imagen parecen tener un orden diferente que el orden actual en la
          pila debido a sus posiciones en el lienzo. La capa amarilla es la
          capa de la cima en la imagen y la segunda en la pila.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Image pour exemple: quatre calques sur un grand canevas 150x150 (ce
          pourrait être des images): rouge est 10x10 pixels, vert est 10x20,
          jaune est 20x10. Le calque d'arrière-plan (bleu: 100x100) ne
          bougera pas, car l'option <quote>Ignorer le calque du bas</quote>
          sera cochée.
          Notez que, à cause de leur position sur le canevas, les calques
          semblent avoir un ordre différent de celui de la pile (le calque
          jaune est le calque du haut sur l'image et est le second dans la
          pile ).
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          L'immagine di esempio contiene quattro livelli su una larga
          (150x150 pixel) superficie disegnabile. Il quadrato rosso è di
          10x10 pixel, il rettangolo verde di 10x20 pixel e quello giallo
          di 20x10 pixel. Il livello di sfondo (blu, 100x100 pixel) non
          sarà modificato dal comando dato che è stata impostata l'opzione
          <guilabel>Ignora livello inferiore anche se visibile</guilabel>
          sulla finestra di dialogo. Notare che i livelli nell'immagine
          sembrano avere un ordine differente sulla pila data la loro
          posizione sulla superficie di disegno. Il livello giallo è in
          cima all'immagine e il secondo sulla pila.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Eksempelbiletet inneheld fire lag på eit 150 x 150 piksel lerret.
          Det raude kvadratet er 10 x 10 piksel, det grøne rektangelet er
          10 x 20 piksel og det gule er 20 x 10 piksel. Bakgrunnslaget,
          som er blått og på 100 x 100 pikslar, blir ikkje berørt av
          kommandoen sidan valet <guilabel>Ignorer det nederste
            laget</guilabel> er avkryssa i dialogvindauget. Legg merke til
          at på grunn av possisjonen laga har i biletet, ser det ut som dei
          har ei anna rekkefølgje på biletet enn i lagstakken. Det gule laget
          er topplaget på biletet, men det andre laget i lagstabelen.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en"><!--TODO de;es;it;no;-->
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Align Visible layers</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          There is no default keyboard shortcut. The dialog doesn't show up
          if the image holds a single layer only.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>
              <accel>S</accel>ichtbare Ebenen anordnen
            </guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>apa</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Alinear capas <accel>v</accel>isibles</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          No tiene atajo de teclado predefinido.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>
              Aligner les calques visibles
            </guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Il n'y a pas de raccourci-clavier par défaut. La fenêtre de
          Dialogue ne s'ouvre pas si l'image ne possède qu'un seul calque.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ivello</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Allinea livelli <accel>v</accel>isibili</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Non c'è una scorciatoia da tastiera.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Innrett synlege lag</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        Description of the <quote>Layer Align</quote> dialog
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Beschreibung des Dialogfensters</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        Descripción del diálogo <quote>Alinear capa</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Description de la fenêtre Aligner les calques
        visibles</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Descrizione della finestra di dialogo <quote>allinea
          livelli</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Beskriving av dialogen <quote>Innrett synlege lag</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>
    
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">The <quote>Layer Align</quote> dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Dialogfenster <quote>Sichtbare Ebenen anordnen</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">El diálogo <quote>Alinear capa</quote></phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La fenêtre de dialogue <quote>Aligner les calques visibles</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">La finestra di dialogo <quote>allinea
            livelli</quote></phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Dialogvindauget for <quote>Innrett synlege lag</quote></phrase>
      </title>
      
      <mediaobject lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no">
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/menus-layer-align.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/menus-layer-align.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/es/menus-layer-align.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/menus-layer-align.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/it/menus-layer-align.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/menus-layer-align.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Horizontal Style; Vertical Style</term>
        <term lang="de">Horizontaler Stil; Vertikaler Stil</term>
        <term lang="es">Estilo horizontal; Estilo vertical</term>
        <term lang="fr">Style Horizontal/Vertical</term>
        <term lang="it">Stile orizzontale; Stile verticale</term>
        <term lang="no">Horisontal og vertikal Stil</term>
        
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            These options control how the layers should be moved in
            relationship to each other. You can choose:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, wie die Ebenen
            aneinander ausgerichtet werden sollen. Es stehen Ihnen
            verschiedene Einstellungen zur Auswahl:
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Estas opciones controlan como se deberán mover las capas en
            relación con las otras. Puede elegir entre:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette option contrôle comment les calques visibles seront
            déplacés horizontalement / verticalement les uns par rapport aux
            autres:
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Queste opzioni controllano come i livelli debbano essere
            spostati in reciproca relazione. È possibile scegliere tra gli
            stili:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Desse vala bestemmer korleis laga skal flyttast i høve til
            kvarandre. Du har valet mellom
          </para>
          
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>None</guilabel>:
                There will be no change in the horizontal or the vertical
                position, respectively.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Kein</guilabel>:
                Es wird in dieser Orientierung keine Ausrichtung vorgenommen.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                <guilabel>Ninguna</guilabel>:
                No cambiará en la posición horizontal o vertical.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Aucun</guilabel>:
                Aucun changement ne sera apporté aux positions horizontales
                / verticales.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guilabel>Nessuna</guilabel>: non ci saranno cambiamenti
                nella posizione orizzontale o verticale dei livelli.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guilabel>Ingen</guilabel>:
                Ingen endringar i noe retning.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Collect</guilabel>:
                The visible layers will be aligned on the canvas, in the
                way that is determined by the <guilabel>Horizontal
                  base</guilabel> and <guilabel>Vertical base</guilabel>
                options. If you select a <guilabel>Horizontal
                  base</guilabel> of <guilabel>Right edge</guilabel>, layers
                may disappear from the canvas. You can recover them by
                enlarging the canvas. If you check the
                <guilabel>Use the (invisible) bottom layer as the
                  base</guilabel> option, the layers will be aligned on the
                top left corner of the bottom layer.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Zusammenfassen</guilabel>:
                Wenn Sie diese Einstellung wählen, werden die Ebenen alle an
                der Zeichenfläche ausgerichtet. Welche Kante der Zeichenfläche
                zu Einsatz kommen soll, legen Sie mit der Eigenschaft
                <guilabel>Horizontale Basis</guilabel> beziehungsweise
                <guilabel>Vertikale Basis</guilabel> fest.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                <guilabel>Recolectar</guilabel>:
                Las capas visibles se alinearán sobre el lienzo, de la manera
                que se determina en las opciones
                <guilabel>Base horizontal</guilabel> y
                <guilabel>Base vertical base</guilabel>. Si selecciona una
                <guilabel>Base horizontal</guilabel> de
                <guilabel>Borde derecho</guilabel>, las capas podrían
                desaparecer del lienzo. Puede recuperarlas agrandando el
                lienzo. Si marca la opción  <guilabel>Usar la capap inferior
                  (invisible) como base</guilabel>, las capas se alinearán en
                la esquina superior izquierda de la capa inferior.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Rassembler</guilabel>:
                Cette option aligne la «Base Horizontale / verticale»
                sélectionnée (Bord gauche, Milieu, Bord droit / Bord haut,
                Milieu, Bord bas) sur le bord gauche / haut du canevas. Si
                vous choisissez Bord Droit, les calques sortent du canevas;
                vous pouvez les retrouver en agrandissant le canevas. Si
                l'option <guilabel>Calque du bas comme base</guilabel> est
                cochée, l'alignement se fait sur le bord correspondant du
                calque du bas de la pile.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <!-- FIXME IT: Il termine è stato tradotto in maniera non
                     corretta sul programma e il manuale segue la
                     traduzione del programma per questione di
                     coerenza. Questo comando è stato eliminato nella
                     futura versione di GIMP per cui la traduzione
                     probabilmente non verrà mai corretta -->
                <guilabel>Seleziona</guilabel>: tutti i livelli visibili
                verranno allineati sulla superficie disegnabile, nella
                modalità determinata dalle opzioni <guilabel>base
                  orizzontale</guilabel> e <guilabel>base
                  verticale</guilabel>. Se si seleziona <guilabel>base
                  orizzontale</guilabel> di <guilabel>bordo
                  sinistro</guilabel>, dei livelli potrebbero sparire dalla
                superficie. È possibile ripristinarli allargando la
                superficie di disegno. Se si imposta l'opzione
                <guilabel>usa il livello inferiore (invisibile) come
                  base</guilabel>, i livelli saranno allineati all'angolo in
                alto a sinistra del livello in fondo alla pila.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guilabel>Samla</guilabel>:
                Dei synlege laga blir innretta slik det er bestemt i
                <guilabel>Horisontal basis</guilabel> og
                <guilabel>Vertikal basis</guilabel>. Dersom du set
                <guilabel>Horisontal basis</guilabel> til
                <guilabel>Høgre kant</guilabel>, kan du rissikera at laga
                forsvinn frå lerretet. Du kan hente dei fram igjen ved å
                forstørra lerretet. Dersom du har markert for
                <guilabel>Bruk det (usynlege) botnlaget som
                  basis</guilabel>, blir laga innretta på det øvre, venstre
                hjørnet av botnlaget.
              </para>
              
              <figure>
                <title>
                  <phrase lang="en">
                    Horizontal <quote>Collect</quote> alignment
                    (on the edge of the canvas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="de">
                    Horizontale, zusammenfassende Ausrichtung (Zeichenfläche)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="es">
                    Alineación horizontal <quote>Recolectar</quote>
                    (sobre el borde del lienzo)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="fr">
                    Alignement horizontal par rassemblement (sur le bord du
                    Canevas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="it">
                    Allineamento <quote>selezionato</quote> orizzontale
                    (sul bordo della superficie disegnabile)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="no">
                    Horisontal <quote>Samla</quote> innretting
                    (etter kanten av lerretet)
                  </phrase>
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/align-demo.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">Original image with the layer stack
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">Originalbild mit Ebenenstapel</para>
                    <para lang="es">Imagen original con la pila de capas</para>
                    <para lang="fr">Image d'origine avec pile des calques</para>
                    <para lang="it">Immagine originale con la pila dei
                      livelli
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">Originalbiletet med lagstabelen</para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alignHCLB-.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The layers have been moved horizontally so that their
                      left edges are aligned with the left edge of the
                      canvas.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Die Ebenen wurden horizontal an der linken Kante der
                      Zeichenfläche zusammenfassend ausgerichtet.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="es">
                      Las capas se han movido horizontalmente para que los
                      bordes izquierdos se alineen con el borde izquierdo del
                      lienzo.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Les calques se sont déplacés horizontalement pour venir
                      aligner leur bord gauche sur le bord gauche du canevas.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      I livelli sono stati spostati orizzontalmente in modo
                      tale che i loro bordi sinistri siano allineati con il
                      bordo sinistro della superficie disegnabile.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Laga er flytta slik at den venstre kanten er innretta
                      etter den venstre kanten på lerretet.
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              
              <figure>
                <title>
                  <phrase lang="en">
                    Horizontal <quote>Collect</quote> alignment
                    (on the bottom layer)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="de">
                    Horizontale, zusammenfassende Ausrichtung (Ebene)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="es">
                    Alineación horizontal <quote>Recolectar</quote>
                    (sobre la capa del fondo)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="fr">
                    Alignement horizontal par rassemblement (sur le calque
                    du bas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="it">
                    Allineamento <quote>Seleziona</quote> orizzontale
                    (sul livello di fondo)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="no">
                    Horisontal <quote>Samla</quote> innretting
                    (etter botnlaget)
                  </phrase>
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/align-demo.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">Original image with the layer stack
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">Originalbild mit Ebenenstapel</para>
                    <para lang="es">Imagen original con la pila de capas</para>
                    <para lang="fr">Image d'origine avec pile des calques</para>
                    <para lang="it">Immagine originale con la pila dei
                      livelli
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">Originalbiletet med lagstabelen
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alignHCLB+.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The layers have been moved horizontally so that their
                      left edges align with the left edge of the bottom
                      layer.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Die Ebenen wurden horizontal an der linken Kante der
                      untersten Ebene zusammenfassend ausgerichtet.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="es">
                      Las capas se han movido horizontalmente para que los
                      bordes izquierdos se alineen con el borde izquierdo de
                      la capa del fondo.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Les calques se sont déplacés horizontalement pour
                      aligner leur bord gauche sur le bord gauche du calque du
                      bas de la pile.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      I livelli sono stati spostati orizzontalmente in modo
                      tale che i loro bordi sinistri siano allineati con il
                      bordo sinistro del livello in fondo alla pila.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Laga er flytt horisontalt slik at den venstre kanten
                      fluktar med den venstre kanten til botnlaget.
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Fill (left to right)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Fill (top to bottom)</guilabel>:
                The visible layers will be aligned with the canvas
                according to the edge you selected with
                <guilabel>Horizontal base</guilabel> or
                <guilabel>Vertical base</guilabel>, respectively.
                The layers are arranged regularly, so that they do not
                overlap each other. The top layer in the stack is placed
                on the leftmost (or uppermost) position in the image.
                The bottom layer in the stack is placed on the rightmost
                (or bottommost) position of the image. The other layers
                are placed regularly between these two positions.  If the
                <guilabel>Use the (invisible) bottom layer as the
                  base</guilabel> option is checked, the layers are aligned
                with the corresponding edge of the bottom layer.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Füllen (von links nach rechts)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Füllen (von oben nach unten)</guilabel>:
                Mit dieser Einstellung werden die Ebenen an
                der Zeichenfläche ausgerichtet. Welche Kante der Zeichenfläche
                zu Einsatz kommen soll, legen Sie mit der Eigenschaft
                <guilabel>Horizontale Basis</guilabel> beziehungsweise
                <guilabel>Vertikale Basis</guilabel> fest. Dabei werden die
                Ebenen so angeordnet, dass sie einander nicht überlappen. Die
                oberste Ebene wird direkt an der gewählten Kante positioniert,
                alle anderen dann auffüllend versetzt.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                <guilabel>Rellenar (izq. a der.)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Rellenar (superior a inferior)</guilabel>:
                Las capas visibles se alinearán con el lienzo según los
                bordes que seleccione en <guilabel>Base horizontal</guilabel>
                o <guilabel>Base vertical</guilabel>, respectivamente.
                Las capas se arreglan regularmente, so that they do not
                overlap each other. La capa superior en la pila se situa en
                la  posición más a la izquierda (o más arriba) en la imagen.
                Las otras capas se situan regularmente entre estas dos
                posiciones. Si marca la opción
                <guilabel>Usar la capa inferior (invisible) como base
                </guilabel>, las capas se alinearán con el borde
                correspondiente de la capa inferior.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>
                  Remplir (de gauche à droite / de haut en bas)
                </guilabel>:
                Cette option place la base sélectionnée des calques
                visibles, régulièrement, horizontalement / verticalement sur
                l'image, dans l'ordre de haut en bas de la pile des calques.
                Le premier calque de la pile est placé sur la position
                horizontale (verticale) la plus à gauche (la plus haute). Le
                dernier calque de la pile est placé sur la position
                horizontale (verticale) la plus à droite (la plus basse). Si
                l'option <quote>calque du bas comme base</quote> est cochée,
                la base du calque du haut est alignée sur le bord
                correspondant du calque du bas de la pile.
              </para>
              <para lang="it"><guilabel>Riempi (sinistra
                  destra)</guilabel>; <guilabel>Riempi (alto basso)</guilabel>:
                i livelli visibili saranno allineati con la superficie
                disegnabile secondo il bordo selezionato con rispettivamente
                <guilabel>base orizzontale</guilabel> o <guilabel>base
                  verticale</guilabel>.  I livelli verranno disposti
                regolarmente, in modo tale da non sovrapporsi. Il livello in
                cima alla pila viene piazzato nella posizione più a sinistra
                (o più in alto) nell'immagine.  Il livello in fondo alla pila
                viene piazzato nella posizione più a destra (o più in basso)
                nell'immagine. Gli altri livelli sono disposti regolarmente
                tra queste due posizioni.  Se viene abilitata l'opzione
                <guilabel>Usa il livello inferiore (invisibile) come
                  base</guilabel>, i livelli vengono allineati al bordo
                corrispondente del livello di fondo.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">:
                <guilabel>Fyll (frå venstre til høgre)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Fyll (frå topp til botn)</guilabel>:
                Dei synlege laga blir innretta etter lerretet ut frå kva kant
                som er sett i <guilabel>Horisontal basis</guilabel> eller
                <guilabel>Vertikal basis</guilabel>. Laga blir justert slik at
                dei ikkje overlappar kvarandre. Topplaget i lagstabelen
                blir lagt lengst til venstre, eller høgst oppe, i biletet.
                Botnlaget blir lagt lengst til høgre eller nederst i biletet.
                Dei andre laga blir fordelte jamnt mellom desse. Dersom
                det er avmerka for <guilabel>Bruk det (usynlege)
                  botnlaget som basis</guilabel>, vil laga bli innretta på
                tilsvarande måte etter botnlaget.
              </para>
              
              <figure>
                <title>
                  <phrase lang="en">
                    Horizontal <quote>Fill</quote> alignment (canvas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="de">
                    Horizontale, auffüllende Ausrichtung (Zeichenfläche)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="es">
                    Alineación horizontal <quote>Rellenar</quote> (lienzo)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="fr">
                    Alignment horizontal par remplissage (canevas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="it">
                    Allineamento <quote>Riempi</quote> orizzontale
                    (superficie disegnabile)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="no">
                    Horisontal <quote>Fyll</quote> innretting (lerret)
                  </phrase>
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/align-demo.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">Original image with the layer stack
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">Originalbild mit Ebenenstapel</para>
                    <para lang="es">Imagen original con la pila de capas</para>
                    <para lang="fr">Image d'origine avec pile des
                      calques</para>
                    <para lang="it">Immagine originale con la pila dei
                      livelli</para>
                    <para lang="no">Originalbiletet med lagstabelen
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alignHFLB-.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      Horizontal filling alignment, Left to Right, with
                      <guilabel>Use the (invisible) bottom layer as the
                        base</guilabel> option not checked. The top layer
                      in the stack, the green one, is placed all the way
                      on the left. The bottom layer in the stack, the red
                      one, is placed is on the right and the yellow layer
                      is between the other two.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Horizontal auffüllende Ausrichtung von links nach
                      rechts. Die grüne Ebene, die oberste des Ebenenstapels,
                      wurde an der linken Kante ausgerichtet. Nach rechts
                      versetzt folgen die gelbe und die rote Ebene auffüllend.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="es">
                      La alineación horizontal rellenar, izquierda a derecha,
                      con la opción <guilabel>Usar la capa inferior (invisible)
                        como base</guilabel> sin marcar. La capa superior en la
                      pila, la verde, se situa toda a la izquierda, la capa
                      inferior en la pila, la roja, se situa a la derecha y
                      la capa amrilla se situa entre las otras dos.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Alignement de remplissage Horizontal, de gauche à
                      droite, <quote>Calque du bas pour base</quote> non
                      cochée. Notez l'espacement régulier entre les bases
                      des calques et l'ordre des calques qui est celui de la
                      pile des calques du Dialogue des calques. Le calque
                      vert, le premier de la pile, est placé sur la position
                      horizontale la plus à gauche, qui était celle du
                      calque jaune. Le calque rouge, le dernier de la pile,
                      occupe la position la plus à droite, qui était celle
                      du calque vert.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Allineamento a riempimento orizzontale, da sinistra a
                      destra, con l'opzione <guilabel>Usa il livello
                        inferiore (invisible) come base</guilabel> non
                      impostata. Il livello superiore nella pila, quello
                      verde, viene posizionato tutto a sinistra. Il livello
                      di fondo nella pila, quello rosso, viene piazzato a
                      destra e quello giallo rimane tra gli altri due.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Horisontal fylling, venstre til høgre, utan avmerking
                      for <guilabel>Bruk det (usynlege) botnlaget som
                        basis</guilabel>. Topplaget i lagstabelen, det grøne,
                      er sett heilt til venstre. Botnlaget i lagstabelen, det
                      raude, er sett heilt til høgre. Det gule laget er sett
                      mellom desse to.
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              
              <figure>
                <title>
                  <phrase lang="en">
                    Horizontal <quote>Fill</quote> alignment (bottom layer)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="de">
                    Horizontale, auffüllende Ausrichtung (Ebene)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="es">
                    Alineación horizontal <quote>Rellenar</quote> (capa inferior)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="fr">
                    Alignement Horizontal par remplissage (calque du bas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="it">
                    Allineamento <quote>Riempi</quote> orizzontale (livello
                    di fondo)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="no">
                    Horisontal <quote>Fyll</quote> innretting (botnlaget)
                  </phrase>
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/align-demo.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">Original image with the layer stack
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">Originalbild mit Ebenenstapel</para>
                    <para lang="es">Imagen original con la pila de capas</para>
                    <para lang="fr">Image d'origine avec pile des
                      calques</para>
                    <para lang="it">Immagine originale con la pila dei
                      livelli</para>
                    <para lang="no">Originalbiletet med lagstabelen
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alignHFLB+.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The same parameters as in the previous example,
                      but with the lowest (blue) level as the base.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Parameter wie im vorherigen Beispiel, aber mit der
                      untersten (blauen) Ebene als Bezugsobjekt.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="es">
                      Los mismos parámetros como en el ejemplo anterior,
                      pero con el nivel más bajo (azul) como base.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Alignement de remplissage Horizontal, de gauche à droite
                      avec le calque du bas de la pile (bleu) pour base.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Gli stessi parametri come nell'esempio precedente, ma
                      con il livello più basso (blu) come base.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Dei same parametra som i det førre eksemplet, men med
                      det nedre, blå, laget som basis.
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Fill (right to left)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Fill (bottom to top)</guilabel>:
                These settings work similarly to the ones described above,
                but the filling occurs in the opposite direction.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Füllen (von rechts nach links)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Füllen (von unten nach oben)</guilabel>:
                Diese Einstellung wirkt ähnlich der zuvor beschriebenen, nur
                dass in die entgegengesetzte Richtung aufgefüllt wird.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                <guilabel>Rellenar (der. a izq.)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Rellenar (inferior a superior)</guilabel>:
                Esta configuración funciona de manera similar a las descritas
                antes, pero se rellena en la dirección opuesta.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>
                  Remplir (de droite à gauche / de bas en haut)
                </guilabel>:
                Comme précédemment, cette fonction lit la pile des calques
                de haut en bas, mais affiche les calques alignés de droite à
                gauche / de bas en haut.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guilabel>Riempi (destra sinistra)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Riempi (basso alto)</guilabel>: queste
                impostazioni lavorano in maniera simile a quelle descritte
                sopra, ma lo riempimento funziona nella direzione opposta.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guilabel>Fyll (høgre til venstre)</guilabel>;
                <guilabel>Fyll (botn til topp)</guilabel>:
                Desse verkar som dei ovanfor, men i omvendt rekkefølgje.
              </para>
              
              <figure>
                <title>
                  <phrase lang="en">
                    Vertical <quote>Fill</quote> alignment (bottom layer)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="de">
                    Vertikal, auffüllende Ausrichtung (Ebene)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="es">
                    Alineación vertical <quote>Rellenar</quote> (capa inferior)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="fr">
                    Alignement Vertical par remplissage (calque du bas)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="it">
                    Allineamento <quote>Riempi</quote> verticale (livello
                    di fondo)
                  </phrase>
                  <phrase lang="no">
                    Vertikal <quote>Fyll</quote> innretting (botnlaget)
                  </phrase>
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/align-demo.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">Original image with the layer stack
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">Originalbild mit Ebenenstapel</para>
                    <para lang="es">Imagen original con la pila de capas</para>
                    <para lang="fr">Image d'origine avec pile des
                      calques</para>
                    <para lang="it">Immagine originale con la pila dei
                      livelli</para>
                    <para lang="no">Originalbiletet med lagstabelen
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alignVFBB+.png"
                               format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      Vertical <quote>Fill</quote> alignment, bottom to
                      top, bottom layer as base
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Vertikal auffüllende Ausrichtung von unten nach oben mit
                      der untersten Ebene des Stapels als Bezugsobjekt
                    </para>
                    <para lang="es">
                      Alineación vertical <quote>Rellenar</quote>, inferior
                      a superior, capa inferior como base
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Alignement de remplissage vertical, de bas en haut, avec
                      le calque du bas pour base
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Allineamento <quote>Riempi</quote> verticale, dal
                      basso in alto, livello di fondo come base
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Vertikal <quote>Fyll</quote> innretting, botn til topp.
                      Botnlaget som basis
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              
              <para lang="en">
                There must be at least three visible layers in the image to
                use the <quote>Fill</quote> options.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Um <guilabel>Füllen</guilabel> zu können, müssen mindestens
                drei Ebenen im Bild sichtbar sein.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                Debe haber al menos tres capas visibles en la imagen para
                usar las opciones <quote>Rellenar</quote>.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Les options de remplissage nécessitent trois calques visibles
                au moins.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Ci devono essere minimo tre livelli visibili nell'immagine
                per poter usare le opzioni di <quote>Riempimento</quote>.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Det må vere minst tre synlege lag i biletet for å kunne bruke
                <quote>Fyll</quote>-innstillingane.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
