<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-03-12 Kolbjørn: added no translation
  2006-09-21 lexa: added de translation
  2006-08-08: created by scb; example by j.h
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-white-balance" lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
  <sect2info role="cvs" lang="en;de;fr;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-11</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-21</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-05</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-22</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">White Balance</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Weißabgleich</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Balance des blancs</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Bilanciamento del bianco</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Fargebalanse</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Colors managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>White balance</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>White Balance</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary>
    <secondary>Farben</secondary>
    <tertiary>Weißabgleich</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Farben</primary>
    <secondary>Weißabgleich</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Weißabgleich</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer les couleurs</secondary>
    <tertiary>Équilibrer les couleurs</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Balance des blancs</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <!-- FIXME IT: indexterm not translated during rebuild -->

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Fargebalanse</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fargebalanse</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>White Balance</guimenuitem> command automatically
    adjusts the colors of the active layer by stretching the Red, Green and
    Blue channels separately. To do this, it discards pixel colors at each
    end of the Red, Green and Blue histograms which are used by only 0.05%
    of the pixels in the image and stretches the remaining range as much as
    possible. The result is that pixel colors which occur very infrequently
    at the outer edges of the histograms (perhaps bits of dust, etc.) do
    not negatively influence the minimum and maximum values used for
    stretching the histograms, in comparison with <link
    linkend="plug-in-c-stretch">Stretch Contrast</link>.  Like
    <quote>Stretch Contrast</quote>, however, there may be hue shifts in
    the resulting image.
  </para>
  <para lang="en"> <!--2007-04-21-->
    This command suits images with poor white or black. Since it tends to
    create pure white (and black), it may be useful e.g. to enhance
    photographs.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    <guimenuitem>White Balance</guimenuitem> operates on layers from RGB
    images. If the image is Indexed or Grayscale, the menu item is insensitive
    and grayed out.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Das Kommando <quote>Weißabgleich</quote> stellt die Farben automatisch
    neu ein. Dies wird durch eine Streckung der Histogramme
    <emphasis>getrennt nach den einzelnen Farbkanälen</emphasis> Rot, Grün
    und Blau erreicht. Dabei werden für jeden Farbkanal die 0,05% Pixel mit
    der niedrigsten beziehungsweise höchsten Intensität auf minimale
    beziehungsweise maximale Intensität gesetzt und die Werte dazwischen
    entsprechend angepasst. Durch die Wirkungsweise kann es zu
    Helligkeitsverschiebungen in dem Bildbereich kommen, auf den das
    Kommando angewendet wurde.
  </para>
  <para lang="de"> <!--2007-04-21-->
    Dieses Kommando ist besonders für Bilder geeignet, die ein unsauberes
    Weiß oder Schwarz enthalten. Da es dazu tendiert, daraus reine Farben zu
    erzeugen, kann es beispielsweise zur Verbesserung von Fotos verwendet
    werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    <quote>Weißabgleich</quote> lässt sich ausschließlich auf Ebenen von
    Bildern im RGB-Modus anwenden. Befindet sich das Bild in einem anderen
    Modus, ist das Kommando im Menü deaktiviert und ausgegraut.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande ajuste automatiquement les couleurs du calque actif en
    écartant les colonnes de pixels des canaux Rouge, Vert et Bleu
    séparément. Pour cela, elle rejette 0,05% des pixels présents aux deux
    extrémités de l'histogramme et étale le reste sur tout l'intervalle.
    Ainsi, quelques pixels très noirs ou très clairs, dûs à des poussières
    par example, n'influenceront pas les valeurs de maximum et de minimum
    utilisées pour l'étalement, contrairement à la commande
    <link linkend="plug-in-c-stretch">Etendre le Contraste</link>. Elle tend
    ainsi à créer un blanc bien blanc et un noir bien noir, mais comme pour
    Étendre le Contraste,, on peut avoir des changements de teintes.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande n'agit que sur les calques des images RVB. Si l'image est
    indexée ou en niveaux de gris, la commande est désactivée et grisée.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>bilanciamento del bianco</guimenuitem> regola
    automaticamente i colori del livello attivo ottimizzando separatamente
    i canali dei colori rosso, verde e blu. Per ottenere questo risultato
    esso scarta i colori dei pixel ai limiti degli istogrammi di colore
    rosso, verde e blu, usati solo dal totale di 0.05% dei pixel presenti
    nell'immagine. Inolte esse "stira", allargandone l'estensione
    spettrale, il campo rimanente il più possibile, in modo da ottimizzarne
    la distribuzione. Il risultato è che i pixel di colore che ricorrono
    molto raramente, spesso dovuti a polvere o difetti, non influenzano
    negativamente i valori minimi e massimi usati per l'ottimizzazione
    degli istogrammi di colore, come accade con il comando <link
    linkend="plug-in-c-stretch">aggiusta il contrasto</link> anche se, come
    accade con quest'ultimo comando, potrebbero verificarsi degli
    spostamenti di tonalità nell'immagine finale.  Questo comando opera su
    livelli di immagini RGB. Se l'immagine è indicizzata o in scala di
    grigi, la voce di menu viene resa in colore pallido e disabilitata.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Fargebalanse</guimenuitem> justerer
    automatisk fargane i det aktive laget ved å strekke ut kanalane for
    raud, grøn og blå kvar for seg. Dette blir gjort ved at fargar som blir
    brukte av mindre enn 0,05 % av pikslane i laget blir fjerna frå kvar ende
    av kvart av histogramma for raud, grøn og blå. Dei resterande pikslane
    blir best mogleg fordelte i det ledige området. Resultatet blir at fargar
    som bare finst i små mengder i ytterpunkta av histogramma (dette er
    kanskje støvflekkar o.l.) ikkje har noen negativ påverknad på
    maksimums- og minimumsverdiane som bli brukte for å strekke
    histogrammet. På same måten som for
    <link linkend="plug-in-c-stretch">Strekk kontrast</link>, kan du oppleva
    kulørskifte i det ferdige biletet. <quote>Kvitbalanse</quote> verkar
    på lag frå RGB- og gråskalabilete. Er biletet indeksert, er
    kommandoen uverksam.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ayer</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olors</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>W</accel>hite Balance</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>F</accel>arben</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>utomatisch</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>W</accel>eißabgleich</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>alque</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Coule<accel>u</accel>rs</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Balance des <accel>b</accel>lancs</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ivello</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olori</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>ilanciamento del bianco</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Fargar</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Fargebalanse</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        <quote>White Balance</quote> example
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Ein Beispiel für den Weißabgleich</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        Exemple de <quote>Balance des blancs</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Esempio del comando <quote>bilanciamento del bianco</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Fargebalanse</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Original image</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Originalbild</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Image d'origine</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Immagine originale</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Originalbiletet</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alice.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The active layer and its Red, Green and Blue histograms
            before <quote>White Balance</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die aktive Ebene und die zugehörigen Histogramme für den roten,
            blauen und grünen Kanal vor Anwendung des Weißabgleiches.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque actif et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert, Bleu avant
            traitement.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il livello attivo ed i suoi istogrammi di colore rosso, verde e
            blu prima del <quote>bilanciamento del colore</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå før
            bruk av <quote>Fargebalanse</quote>.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Image after the command</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Bild nach Anwendung des Weißabgleiches</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Image traitée</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Immagine dopo il comando</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Biletet etter utføringa</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/white-balance.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The active layer and its Red, Green and Blue histograms after
            <quote>White Balance</quote>.  Poor white areas in the image
            became pure white.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Histogram stretching creates gaps between the pixel columns,
            giving it a striped look.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Die Histogramme des roten, blauen und grünen Kanals nach Anwendung
            des Weißabgleichs. Die Bereiche mit einem etwas unsauberem Weiß
            sind nunmehr tatsächlich weiß.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque actif et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert, Bleu après
            traitement.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            L'étalement des histogrammes crée des vides entre les colonnes
            de pixels, lui donnant un aspect strié.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Il livello attivo e i suoi istogrammi di colore rosso, verde e
            blu dopo il <quote>bilanciamento del colore</quote>.  Le
            colonne di pixel raggiungono il limite destro dell'istogramma
            (255): viene quindi prodotto un bianco puro (255, 255, 255).
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            L'aggiustamento dell'istogramma crea dei "buchi" tra le
            colonne di pixel, dandone un'aspetto a strisce.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå etter
            bruk av <quote>Fargebalanse</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Strekkinga av histogrammet lagar opningar mellom kolonnene. Difor
            stripene.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
