<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-07 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-03-12 Kolbjørn: added no translation
  2006-09-05: created by j.h
-->
<!--TODO en de es fr it no: check if we should move this content to e.g.
  menus/colors/auto.xml--><!--Good idea...-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-stretch-commands" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;lt;no">
  <sect2info lang="en;es;fr;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-11</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-01</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-06-08</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-05</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-03-11</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Layer Color-Stretching Commands</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Farbstreckungs-Kommandos für Ebenen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Comandos de extensión de colores de la capa</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Commandes d'extension des couleurs du calque</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Comandi d'estensione colori nel livello</phrase>
    <phrase lang="lt">Sluoksnių spalvų ištempimo komandos</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Automatisk fargestrekking</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Colors managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Color-stretching commands</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Colors</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary>
    <secondary>Farben</secondary>
    <tertiary>Farbstreckung</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Farbe</primary>
    <secondary>Automatische Farbstreckung</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbstreckung</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Gestión de los colores</secondary>
    <tertiary>Comandos de extensión de colores</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Colores</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer les couleurs</secondary>
    <tertiary>Commandes d'extension des couleurs</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Couleurs</primary>
  </indexterm>

<!-- FIXME IT: indexterm missing -->

  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Sluoksnis</primary>
    <secondary>Spalvų valdymas</secondary>
    <tertiary>Spalvų ištempimo komandos</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Spalvos</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Fargar</primary>
    <secondary>Fargestrekking</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fargestrekking</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has several automatic commands for stretching
    the columns of the histogram for the color channels of the active
    layer. By pushing bright pixels to the right and dark pixels to the
    left, they make bright pixels brighter and dark pixels darker, which
    enhances the contrast in the layer.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Some of the commands stretch the three color channels equally, so that the
    hues are not changed. Other commands stretch each of the color channels
    separately, which changes the hues.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The way the stretching is done varies with the different commands and the
    results look different. It is not easy to predict exactly what each
    command will do. If you know exactly what you are doing, you can get the
    same results, and even more, with the
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels</link> tool.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Here are examples of the results of these commands, all together on one
    page, so you can compare them more easily. The most appropriate command
    depends upon your image, so you should try each of them to see which
    command works best on it.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> verfügt über einige automatische Kommandos, um
    die Säulen der Histogramme für die Farbkanäle der aktiven Ebene zu
    <quote>strecken</quote>. Indem man helle Pixel nach rechts und dunkle
    Pixel nach links schiebt, macht man helle Bildpunkte heller und dunkle
    Punkte dunkler und verbessert so den Kontrast in der Ebene.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Einige dieser Befehle strecken die drei Farbkanäle gleichermaßen, so
    dass die Farbtöne unverändert bleiben, andere strecken sie getrennt
    und ändern damit die Farbtöne.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die Art und Weise, wie gestreckt wird, ist bei jedem Befehl anders und
    führt jeweils zu einem anderen Ergebnis. Was das einzelne Kommando
    letztlich konkret macht, ist schwer vorauszusagen. Falls Sie ganz genau
    wissen, was Sie tun, können Sie dieselben Ergebnisse und noch viel mehr
    mit dem Werkzeug <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Werte</link>
    erreichen.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die folgenden Beispiele zeigen die Ergebnisse dieser Befehle. Sie sind
    alle auf einer einzigen Seite, so dass Sie sie besser vergleichen
    können. Welcher Befehl am geeignetsten ist, hängt von Ihrem Bild ab,
    also probieren Sie am besten jeden einzelnen aus und schauen, welcher
    der richtige für Ihr Bild ist.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tiene varios comandos automáticos para
    extender las columnas del histograma para los canales de color de la capa
    activa. Al desplazar los píxeles claros hacia la derecha y los oscuros
    hacia la izquierda, hacen los píxeles claros más claros y los oscuros más
    oscuros, lo que realza el contraste en la capa.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Algunos de los comandos extienden los tres canales de color por igual,
    con lo que los tonos no cambian. Otros comandos los extienden por
    separado, lo que cambia los tonos.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    La manera de en que se hace la extensión varia con los diferentes
    comandos y el resultado parece distinto. No es fácil predecir con
    exactitud lo que hará cada comando. Si sabe lo que está haciendo, puede
    conseguir el mismo resultado o,  incluso más,  con la herramienta
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Niveles</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Aquí hay ejemplos de los resultados de estos comandos, todos juntos en
    una página, con lo que los puede comparar facilmente. El comando más
    apropiado depende de su imagen, así que debería probar cada uno para ver
    que comando funcioan mejor sobre ella.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    GIMP possède plusieurs commandes automatiques permettant d'étendre (en
    anglais : <quote>Stretch</quote>) les colonnes de pixels des histogrammes
    des différents canaux de couleurs du calque actif. En déplaçant ainsi
    les pixels clairs vers la droite et les pixels sombres vers la gauche,
    elles éclaircissent les pixels clairs et assombrit les pixels sombres,
    ce qui a pour résultat d'augmenter le contraste.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette extension peut se faire de façon égale dans les trois canaux, ce
    qui ne modifie pas les teintes, ou bien de façon séparée, avec alors une
    modification des teintes.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    La manière d'étendre est particulière à chaque commande, avec bien sûr
    un résultat différent. Mais il est difficile de savoir exactement ce que
    fait chaque commande. On obtient les mêmes résultats avec l'outil
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Niveaux</link>, et plus encore,
    tout en sachant exactement ce que l'on fait.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Voici réunis les exemples concernant ces commandes pour une comparaison
    plus facile :
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> possiede molti comandi automatici che
    permettono l'allargamento delle colonne degli istogrammi nei canali di
    colore del livello attivo. Spingendo i pixel luminosi a destra e quelli
    più scuri a sinistra in questi istogrammi, si rendono i pixel luminosi
    ancora di più e quelli scuri ancora più scuri, aumentando il contrasto
    del livello.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Alcuni dei comandi allargano i tre canali di colore allo stesso modo,
    in maniera da non modificare la tonalità dell'immagine. Altri comando
    allargano ogni canale in maniera indipendente, modificando di
    conseguenza la tonalità dei colori.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il metodo per l'estensione che viene adottato varia da comando a
    comando e fornisce risultati differenti. Non è facile prevedere
    esattamente cosa farà ogni comando. Se non si sa esattamente cosa si
    sta facendo, è meglio usare lo strumento <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-levels">livelli</link> che può dare anche risultati
    migliori.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Ecco raggruppati tutti insieme in un'unica pagina degli esempi dei
    risultati di questi comandi, in modo da poter confrontarli più
    facilmente. Il comando più appropriato da utilizzare dipende anche
    dall'immagine, per cui sarebbe indicato provarli tutti per essere
    sicuri di utilizzare quello che funziona meglio su di essa.
  </para>

  <para lang="lt">
    Programa <acronym>GIMP</acronym> turi kelias automatines komandas,
    skirtas aktyvaus sluoksnio spalvų kanalų histogramos stulpelių ištempimui.
    Pastumiant šviesius pikselius į dešinę, o juodus pikselius į kairę,
    jos šviesius pikselius pašviesina, o tamsius patamsina, dėl ko
    pagerėja sluoksnio kontrastas.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Kai kurios komandos ištempia visus tris spalvų kanalus vienodai,
    kad nebūtų pakeisti atspalviai. Kitos komandos ištempia kiekvieną
    spalvos kanalą atskirai, dėl ko pasikeičia atspalviai.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Ištempimo būdas skiriasi nuo komandos, todėl rezultatai atrodo skirtingi.
    Nelengva numatyti ką kiekviena komanda tiksliai padarys. Jeigu
    tiksliai žinote ką darote, tuos pačius rezultatus, ir netgi daugiau,
    galite gauti naudodami
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Lygių</link> įrankį.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Čia yra šių komandų rezultatų pavyzdžiai, visi viename
    puslapyje, kad galėtumėte juos lengviau palyginti. Tinkamiausia
    komanda priklauso nuo jūsų paveikslėlio, todėl turėtumėte išbandyti
    jas visas, kad pamatytumėte, kuri veikia geriausiai.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> finn du fleire måtar for automatisk
    utstrekking av fargane, dvs. å strekke ut kolonnene i histogrammet for
    fargekanalane i det aktive laget. Ved å flytte lyse pikslar til høgre og
    mørke pikslar til venstre, vil lyse pikslar bli lysare og mørke pikslar
    mørkare. Dette påverkar kontrasten i biletet.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Noen av kommandoane strekker dei tre fargane likt. Dette fører til at
    kuløren blir uforandra. Andre strekker kvar av fargekanalane for seg,
    noe som fører til endringar i kuløren.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Måten strekkinga blir gjort på, skifter med dei ulike kommandoane. Difor
    blir også resultata forskjellige. Det finst ingen lett måte å vita på
    førehand korleis resultatet blir, difor vil det som oftast vere enklast å
    prøve seg fram. Dersom du veit nøyaktig kva du gjer, kan du få dei
    same resultata, eller faktisk i noen tilfelle betre, med
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">nivåverktøyet</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    For å gjere samanliknane enklare, er det her samla noen av eksempla på
    ei side. Dette er og blir eksempel. Den einaste sikre måten å finne ut av
    dette på, er å prøve ut kommandoane på eigne bilete.
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The original layer and its histograms
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Die ursprüngliche Ebene und ihre Histogramme
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          La capa original y sus histogramas
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Le calque d'origine et ses histogrammes
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il livello originale con i suoi istogrammi
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Originalus sluoksnis ir jo histogramos
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Originallaget og tilhøyrande histogram
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alice.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            This layer doesn't have any very bright or very dark pixels, so
            it works well with these commands.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese Ebene hat keine sehr hellen oder sehr dunkle Pixel, daher
            eignet sie sich gut für diese Befehle.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Esta capa no tiene píxeles muy claros o muy oscuros, así que
            funciona bien con estos comandos.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce calque ne possède pas de tons très clairs ni très sombres et
            convient bien à ces commandes.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questi comandi funzionano molto bene su questo livello, dato
            che non possiede alcun pixel molto luminoso o molto scuro.
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Šis sluoksnis neturi labai ryškių arba labai tamsių pikselių,
            todėl jis gerai veikia su šiomis komandomis.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Sidan dette laget ikkje har utprega mørke og lyse pikslar, verkar
            kommandoane fint på dette laget.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Equalize</quote> command
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Befehl <link
          linkend="gimp-layer-equalize"><quote>Egalisieren</quote></link>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El comando <quote>Ecualizar</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La commande Égaliser
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il comando <quote>equalizza</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Komanda <quote>Išlyginti</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Kommandoen <quote>Jamn ut</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/equalize.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-equalize">Equalize</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-equalize">Ecualizar</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-equalize">Égaliser</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-equalize">Equalizza</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-equalize">Išlyginti</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-equalize">Jamn ut</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>White Balance</quote> command
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Befehl <link
          linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance"><quote>Weißabgleich</quote></link>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El comando <quote>Balance de blanco</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">La commande Balance des Blancs</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il comando <quote>bilanciamento del bianco</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Komanda <quote>Baltumo balansas</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Kommandoen <quote>Kvitbalanse</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/white-balance.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">White Balance</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Balance de blanco</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Balance des Blancs</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Bilanciamento del
            bianco</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Baltumo balansas</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Kvitbalanse</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Color Enhance</quote> command
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Befehl <link
          linkend="plug-in-color-enhance"><quote>Farbverbesserung</quote></link>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El comando <quote>Realzar color</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">La commande Étendre les Couleurs</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il comando <quote>aumento del colore</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Komanda <quote>Spalvų pagerinimas</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Kommandoen <quote>Fargeforbetring</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/color-enhance.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <link linkend="plug-in-color-enhance">Color Enhance</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <link linkend="plug-in-color-enhance">Realzar color</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <link linkend="plug-in-color-enhance">Étendre les Couleurs</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <link linkend="plug-in-color-enhance">Aumento del colore</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            <link linkend="plug-in-color-enhance">Spalvų pagerinimas</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <link linkend="plug-in-color-enhance">Fargeforbetring</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Normalize</quote> command
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Befehl <link
          linkend="plug-in-normalize"><quote>Normalisieren</quote></link>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El comando <quote>Normalizar</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">La commande Normaliser</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Kommandoen <quote>Normaliser</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il comando <quote>normalizzazione</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Komanda <quote>Normalizuoti</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Kommandoen <quote>Strekk HSV</quote></phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/normalize.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalize</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalizar</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normaliser</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalizzazione</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalizuoti</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normaliser</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Stretch Contrast</quote> command
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Befehl <link
          linkend="plug-in-c-astretch"><quote>Kontrastspreizung</quote></link>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El comando <quote>Reducir el contraste</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">La commande Étendre le Contraste</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il comando <quote>estensione del contrasto</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Komanda <quote>Ištempti kontrastą</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Kommandoen <quote>Strekk kontrast</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/c-stretch.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Stretch Contrast</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Reducir el contraste</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Étendre le Contraste</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Estensione del contrasto</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Ištempti kontrastą</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Strekk kontrast</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Stretch HSV</quote> command
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Befehl <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv"><quote>HSV
          strecken</quote></link>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El comando <quote>Estirar HSV</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il comando <quote>estensione HSV</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La commande Étendre TSV
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Komanda <quote>Ištempti HSV</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Kommandoen <quote>Strekk HSV</quote></phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/stretch-hsv.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv">Stretch HSV</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv">Estirar HSV</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv">Étendre TSV</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv">Estensione HSV</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv">Ištempti HSV</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <link linkend="plug-in-autostretch-hsv">Strekk HSV</link>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </para>
</sect2>
