<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-01-13 lexa: fixed error in de
  2006-01-10 en;fr reviewed by j.h
  2005/11/11 split of from layer-mask.xml by axel.wernicke 
-->
<sect2 id='gimp-layer-alpha-selection-replace' lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="cs" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="cs">2006-03-06</date>
        <authorinitials lang="cs">jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  <title>
    <phrase lang='en'>Alpha to Selection</phrase>
    <phrase lang='cs'>Alfa do výběru</phrase>
    <phrase lang='de'>Auswahl aus Alphakanal</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Alpha vers sélection</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">Alpha 到选区</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Alpha to Selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Vrstva</primary>
    <secondary>Alfa do výběru</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Alpha vers Sélection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <para lang='en'>
    "Alpha to Selection" transforms the active layer's alpha channel (which
    encodes transparency) into the image's selection. Opaque areas become
    fully selected, transparent areas unselected, and translucent areas
    partially selected. The other operations in this group do similar things,
    except that instead of completely replacing the existing selection with
    the selection produced from the alpha channel, they either add the two
    selections, subtract the alpha-selection from the existing selection, or
    create a selection that is the intersection of the two.
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Příkaz Alfa do výběru vytvoří z alfa kanálu aktivní vrstvy (alfa kanál
    obsahuje informace o průhlednosti) výběr. Oblasti s plným krytím jsou
    úplně vybrány, zcela průhledné oblasti nejsou vybrány vůbec a průsvitné
    oblasti jsou vybrány částečně. Další příkazy v této skupině fungují
    podobně, ale nenahradí stávající výběr výběrem vytvořeným z alfa kanálu,
    nýbrž výběr z alfa kanálu přičtou, odečtou nebo vytvoří průnik se
    stávajícím výběrem.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie den Alphakanal der aktiven Eben in eine
    Auswahl für das aktuelle Bild umwandeln. Eine möglicherweise bereits im
    Bild existierende Auswahl wird dadurch ersetzt. Bereiche des Alphakanals
    mit hoher Deckkraft werden ausgewählt, transparente Bereiche befinden sich
    außerhalb der Auswahl. Die halbtransparenten Bereiche werden in weiche
    Auswahlkanten umgewandelt. Der Alphakanal selbst wird durch dieses
    Kommando nicht verändert.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    <guilabel>Alpha vers sélection</guilabel>: permet de créer une sélection 
    des pixels de l'image correspondant aux pixels non transparents du 
    calque actif: les pixels du calque actif opaques à 100% seront 
    complètement sélectionnés; les pixels du calque actif partiellement 
    opaques seront partiellement sélectionnés et les pixels du calque actif 
    complètement transparents ne seront pas sélectionnés.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette option remplace complètement une sélection existante qui disparaît.
    Mais les autres commandes du groupe permettent d'ajouter, de soustraire 
    ou de ne conserver que les pixels communs (intersection), à une 
    sélection existante.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “Alpha 到选区”将活动图层的 Alpha 通道转变为图像选区。不透明区域变为完全选中，透明区域未选中，而半透明区域变为部分选中。该组中其它命令也做相似的事，不过它们不是用从 Alpha 通道得到的选区完全替代已存在选区，而是将两个选区相加，从已存在选区中减去 Alpha-选区，或从两个选区相交部分新建一个选区。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          These commands can be accessed from an image menubar as 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Transparency</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Alpha to Selection</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice><!--commands? or command?-->
        </para>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Tyto příkazy lze vyvolat z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Vrstva</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Průhlednost</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Alfa do výběru</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Tr<accel>a</accel>nsparenz</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Aus<accel>w</accel>ahl aus Alphakanal</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Ces commandes sont accessibles depuis le menu de la fenêtre
          d'image 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Calque</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Transparence</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Alpha vers sélection</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          这些命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>图层</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>透明</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Alpha 到选区</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or from the pop-menu you get by right clicking on the active layer 
          in Layer Dialog.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          nebo z kontextové nabídky dialogu vrstvy (otevře se kliknutím
          pravým tlačítkem myši do dialogu).
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Alternativ können Sie das Kommando im Kontextmenü des Ebenendialoges
          aufrufen.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          ou par le menu local obtenu par un clic droit sur le calque actif
          dans la boîte de dialogue Calque.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          ，或从右键点击图层对话框中活动图层弹出的菜单中选取。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
