<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-6 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-02-22 KoSt: added no
  2005/11/12 split of from layer-colors.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-desaturate" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-03</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-11-12</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-06-06</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-01</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Desaturate</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Sättigung entfernen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Desaturar</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Désaturer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Desatura</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Mindre metning</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">去色</phrase>
  </title>
  
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Colors managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Convert colors to gray scale</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Desaturate</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary>
    <secondary>Sättigung</secondary>
    <tertiary>entfernen</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Gestionar los colores</secondary>
    <tertiary>Convertir los colores a escala de grises</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Desaturar</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer les couleurs</secondary>
    <tertiary>Convertir les couleurs en nuances de gris</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Désaturer</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <!-- FIXME IT: indexterm not traslated during rebuild -->

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Mindre metning</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Avmetning = Mindre metning</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <para lang="en">
    By using the <guimenuitem>Desaturate</guimenuitem> command, you can
    convert all of the colors on the active layer to corresponding shades
    of gray. This differs from converting the image to grayscale in two
    respects. First, it only operates on the active layer and second,
    the colors on the layer are still RGB values with three components. This
    means that you can paint on the layer, or individual parts of it,
    using color at a later time.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die aktuelle Ebene entfärben. Dabei werden
    alle Farbwerte in die entsprechenden Graustufen umgewandelt. Zur
    Umwandlung des gesamten Bildes in ein Graustufenbild gibt es dabei zwei
    wesentliche Unterschiede. Zum einen wirkt dieses Kommando nur auf die
    aktive Ebene, das heißt die Farben in sämtlichen anderen Ebenen bleiben
    unverändert. Zum anderen besteht die Ebene auch weiterhin aus den drei
    Kanälen Rot, Grün und Blau. Dies bedeutet, dass Sie die Ebene, oder
    einzelne Bereiche davon, jederzeit wieder einfärben können.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Al usar el comando <guimenuitem>Desaturar</guimenuitem>, puede convertir
    todos los colores de la capa activa a los correspondientes niveles de
    grises. Difiere de convertir la imagen a escala de grises en dos
    aspectos. El primero, solo funciona sobre la capa activa y el segundo,
    los colores de la capa están en valores RGB con tres componentes. Esto
    quiere decir que puede pintar sobre la capa, o partes individuales de
    ella, usando color un rato después.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande transforme toutes les couleurs du calque actif en nuances de
    gris. C'est différent du fait de convertir l'image en niveaux de gris pour
    deux raisons : la première, c'est que Désaturer n'agit que sur le calque
    actif ; la seconde, c'est que le calque reste en mode de couleur RVB et
    rien ne vous empêche de repeindre les couleurs désaturées avec une autre
    couleur.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Usando il comando <guimenuitem>desatura</guimenuitem>, è possibile
    convertire tutti i colori del livello attivo nei corrispondenti livelli
    di grigio. Ciò differisce dalla semplice conversione dell'immagine in
    scala di grigi secondo due aspetti: il primo è che esso opera solo sul
    livello attivo e per secondo, i colori sul livello sono ancora valori
    RGB con tre componenti separate. Ciò significa che è possibile ancora
    disegnare su livello o su parti di esso, usando i colori in ogni
    momento successivo all'operazione.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Mindre metning</guimenuitem> blir brukt for
    å omforma alle fargane i det aktive laget til tilsvarande grader av grått. 
    Denne metoden skil seg ut frå det å konvertere til gråskala på to måtar.
    For det første verkar han bare på det aktive laget. For det andre så er
    fargane i laget framleis i RGB-verdiar. Du kan såleis fargelegge laget
    eller deler av det, på eit seinare tidspunkt.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “去色”使活动图层中所有颜色转变为相关灰色调。它在两个方面不同将图像转变成
    灰度：第一，它只影响活动图层;第二，图层中的颜色仍然是 RGB 颜色，也可以用
    任何颜色涂画去色后的图层。去色只能在 RGB 图像的图层上使用;当图像是灰度或
    索引时，该菜单项不可用。
  </para>
  
  <note lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no">
    <para lang="en">
      This command only works on layers of RGB images. If the image is in
      Grayscale or Indexed mode, the menu entry is insensitive and
      grayed out.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Bitte beachten Sie, dass Sie dieses Kommando nur auf Bildern im <link
      linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB-Farbmodell</link> ausführen können. Sollte
      sich das aktuelle Bild in einem anderen Farbmodell befinden, so wird
      dieses Kommando im Menü ausgegraut.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Este comando solo funciona sobre capas de imágenes RGB. Si la imagen
      está en escala de grises o modo indexado, la entrada del menú está
      deshabilitada y en gris claro.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Désaturer n'agit que sur les calques des images RVB : si l'image est en
      Niveaux de gris ou Indexée, l'entrée de menu sera désactivée.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questo comando opera solo su livelli di immagini RGB. Se l'immagine è
      in modalità scala di grigi o indicizzata, la voce di menu viene resa
      in colore pallido e disabilitata.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Denne kommandoen verkar bare på lag i RGB-format. Dersom biletet er i
      gråskala eller indeksert format, er kommandoen ikkje aktivisert.
    </para>
  </note>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ayer</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olors</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>esaturate</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>F</accel>arben</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Sättigung ent<accel>f</accel>ernen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Puedes acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>apa</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olores</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>esaturar</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>alque</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Co<accel>u</accel>leurs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>ésaturer</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ivello</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olori</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>esatura</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Fargar</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mindre metning</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>图层</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>颜色</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>去色</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
