<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-21 KoSt: added no
  2005/11/03 split of from menu-layer.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-merge-down" lang="en;de;fr;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-01</date>
        <authorinitials>wes</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-11-11</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-02</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Merge Down</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Nach unten vereinen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fusionner vers le bas</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Flett saman nedover</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">向下合并</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Merge down</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary>
    <secondary>nach unten vereinen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Fusionner vers le bas</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Fusionner le calque vers le bas</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Flett saman nedover</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Merge Down</guimenuitem>
    command merges the active layer with the layer just below it in the stack,
    taking into account the various properties of the active layer, such as
    its opacity and layer
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">mode</link>.
    The resulting merged layer will be in Normal mode, and will inherit the
    opacity of the layer below. If the layer below is not opaque, or if it is
    in some mode other than Normal, then this command will generally change
    the appearance of the image.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The most common use of <guimenuitem>Merge Down</guimenuitem> is to
    construct a layer, by starting with a <quote>base layer</quote> (usually
    opaque and in Normal mode, so that you can see what you are doing), and
    adding a <quote>modification layer</quote> on top of it, with whatever
    shape, opacity, and layer mode you need.  In this case, merging down the
    modification layer will combine the two layers into one, without
    changing the way the image looks.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die aktive Ebene mit der darunter liegenden
    Ebene vereinen. Dabei werden die verschiedenen Eigenschaften der aktiven
    Ebene, also beispielsweise die Transparenz und der Ebenenmodus
    berücksichtigt.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande permet de fusionner le calque actif avec le calque situé
    juste en-dessous dans la liste. Le calque résultant de la fusion devient
    le calque actif. L'opacité du calque actif initial et le
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Modes de calque</link> sont
    pris  en compte.
    Le calque fusionné résultant sera en mode Normal et héritera de l'opacité
    du calque inférieur. Si le calque inférieur n'est pas opaque, ou s'il est
    dans un mode autre que Normal, la commande altérera l'apparence de
    l'image.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'utilisation la plus courante de <guimenuitem>Fusionner vers le bas
    </guimenuitem> est de créer un <quote>calque de base</quote>
    (habituellement opaque et en mode Normal), puis d'ajouter au-dessus un
    <quote>calque de modification</quote> possédant la forme, l'opacité ou
    le mode voulus. De cette façon, la fusion du calque de base et du
    calque de modification combinera les deux calques sans changer l'aspect
    de l'image.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Flett saman nedover</guimenuitem> fletter
    det aktive laget saman med laget like under. Det blir tatt omsyn til
    innstillingane til det aktive laget, slik som gjennomsikt og 
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">modus</link>. Det
    samansette laget vil vere i normalmodus og vil arve gjennomsikta frå
    det nedre laget. Dersom det nedre laget er gjennomsiktig eller  er i
    anna modus enn normalmodus, vil denne kommandoen til vanleg føre
    til synlege forandringer i biletet.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Den mest vanlege bruksmåten for <guimenuitem>Flett saman 
    nedover</guimenuitem> er å opprette eit ugjennomsiktig 
    <quote>basislag</quote>, som oftast einsfarga og i
    normalmodus, og bruke dette som underlag for eit 
    <quote>arbeidslag</quote>. Dermed blir det lettare å sjå kva du
    gjer på arbeidslaget, særleg om du arbeider med meir eller mindre
    gjennomsiktige område.  Når arbeidet er utført, fletter du dei to
    laga saman. Resten av biletet blir uforandra.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="zh_CN">该命令使活动图层与在图层列表中活动图层下的图层合并，并考虑活动图层的不透明度和组合模式。</para>


  <sect3 lang="en;de;fr;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ayer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Merge Do<accel>w</accel>n</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Nach un<accel>t</accel>ten vereinen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Vous le trouverez dans
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>alque</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>usionner vers le bas</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Flett saman nedover</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
