<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-22 KoSt: added no
  2006-09-02 example added by j.h
  2005-11-11 split of from layer-colors.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-equalize" lang="en;de;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-11</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-11-12</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-02</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Equalize</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Egalisieren</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Égaliser</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Equalizza</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Jamn ut</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">色调均化</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Colors managing</secondary>
    <tertiary>Equalize</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Equalize</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Ebene</primary>
    <secondary>egalisieren</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer les couleurs</secondary>
    <tertiary>Égaliser</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Egaliser</primary></indexterm>

  <!-- FIXME IT: indexterm not traslated during rebuild -->
  
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Jamn ut fargar</secondary>
  </indexterm>
<indexterm lang="no"><primary>Jamn ut fargar</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Equalize</guimenuitem>
    command automatically adjusts the brightness of colors across the active
    layer so that the histogram for the Value channel is as nearly flat as
    possible, that is, so that each possible brightness value appears at about
    the same number of pixels as every other value. You can see this in the
    histograms in the example below, in that pixel colors which occur
    frequently in the image are stretched further apart than pixel colors
    which occur only rarely. The results of this command can vary quite a bit.
    Sometimes <quote>Equalize</quote>
    works very well to enhance the contrast in an image, bringing out details
    which were hard to see before. Other times, the results look very bad. It
    is a very powerful operation and it is worth trying to see if it will
    improve your image. It works on layers from RGB and Grayscale images. If
    the image is Indexed, the menu entry is insensitive and grayed out.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie die Helligkeit der aktiven Ebene
    automatisch so einstellen, dass das Histogramm der Helligkeitswerte
    annähernd gleichverteilt ist. Das Ergebnis dieses Kommandos kann sehr
    unterschiedlich sein. Entweder der Kontrast der Ebene wird sehr gut erhöht
    und die Ebene wirkt stark verbessert, oder das Ergebnis wirkt sehr
    schlecht. In jedem Fall ist dieses Kommando sehr wirkungsvoll und einen
    Versuch zur Bildverbesserung wert.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande ajuste automatiquement les couleurs du calque actif de
    telle sorte que le canal Valeur soit aussi plat que possible, c-à-d que
    chaque colonne de pixels dans histogramme ait à peu près le même nombre de
    pixels. Dans l'exemple ci-dessous, vous pouvez constater que les couleurs
    fréquentes dans le calque sont plus espacées que les couleurs rares. Agit
    sur les calques des images RVB et Niveaux de gris. Si l'image est indexée,
    la commande est désactivée.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>equalizza</guimenuitem> regola automaticamente
    la luminosità dei colori attraverso il livello attivo in modo tale da
    rendere l'istogramma del canale del valore più piatto possibile, cioè
    in modo da far apparire ogni possibile valore di luminosità nello
    stesso numero di pixel di ogni altro valore. È possibile osservare
    questo comportamento nell'istogramma dell'esempio mostrato in basso,
    nel quale i colori dei pixel che ricorrono più frequentemente
    nell'immagine, sono allungati più di quelli che ricorrono raramente. Il
    risultato di questo comando è piuttosto variabile: alle volte
    <quote>equalizza</quote> funziona molto bene nell'aumentare il
    contrasto di un'immagine, portando alla luce dettagli che in precedenza
    erano difficili da osservare. Altre volte, i risultati possono essere
    invece di pessima qualità. È un comando molto potente che merita il
    collaudo per verificare se si riesce a migliorare la qualità
    dell'immagine. Funziona su livello di immagini RGB e in scala di
    grigi. Se l'immagine è indicizzara, la voce di menu viene resa con un
    colore pallido e disabilitata.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Jamn ut</guimenuitem> justerer automatisk
    lysverdien for fargane i det aktive laget slik at histogrammet for verdiar
    blir så flatt som mogleg. Eller med andre ord, at lysverdiane blir fordelte
    jamnast mogleg med like mykje på kvar piksel. Du kan sjå dette på 
    eksemplet nedanfor ved at pikselfargar som det er mykje av i biletet er
    strekte meir enn fargar som det er lite av. Resultatet av kommandoen er
    sterkt avhengig av originalen. Av og til er <quote>Jamn ut</quote>
    ypparleg til å forbetra kontrasten i biletet og til å henta ut detaljar som
    var vanskelege å få auge på før operasjonen. Andre gonger blir resultatet
    heilt elendig. Kommandoen er likevel verd eit forsøk. Verkar han ikkje
    slik du ønskjer det, er det bare å angra heile greia.
    <quote>Jamn ut</quote> verkar på lag frå RGB- og gråskalabilete.  Er
    biletet indeksert, er kommandoen uverksam.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “色调均化”调整活动图层颜色的亮度，使亮度通道的柱状图尽可能平，也就是每个
    可能的亮度值上显示的像素数基本相同。色调均化有时可以用作加强图像对比度。
    它是非常强大的命令，不过有时能产生奇迹，有时也能毁掉您的图像。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ayers</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olor</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>qualize</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>bene</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>F</accel>arben</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>utomatisch</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>galisieren</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>alque</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Coule<accel>u</accel>rs</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>É</accel>galiser</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Questo comando è accessibile dalla barra del menu immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>L</accel>ivello</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>C</accel>olori</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>qualizza</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Fargar</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Jamn ut</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>图层</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>颜色</guisubmenu>
            <guisubmenu>自动</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>色调均化</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
        <para lang="en">
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Page_Down</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          oder durch drücken der Tastenkombination
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Umschalt</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          ou en utilisant le raccourci clavier
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Page_Bas</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          o usando la scorciatoia da tastiera
          <keycombo><keycap>Maiusc</keycap><keycap>Pag_Giù</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          eller med snarvegen
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 lang="en;fr;it;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        <quote>Equalize Layer</quote> example
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        Exemple de <quote>Égaliser le calque</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Esempio del comando <quote>equalizza livello</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Jamn ut lag</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;fr;it;no">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Original image</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Image d'origine</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Immagine originale</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Originalbiletet</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alice.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The active layer and its Red, Green, Blue histograms before
            <quote>Equalize</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque actif et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert, Bleu avant
            <quote>Égaliser</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il livello attivo ed i suoi istogrammi di colore rosso, verde e
            blu, prima del comando <quote>equalizza</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå før
            bruk av <quote>Jamn ut</quote>.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure lang="en;fr;it;no">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Image after the command</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Image traitée</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Immagine dopo il comando</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Biletet etter utføringa</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/equalize.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The active layer and its Red, Green, Blue histograms after
            treatment.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Histogram stretching creates gaps between pixel columns giving it
            a striped look.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque actif et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert, Bleu après
            traitement.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            L'étalement des histogrammes crée des vides entre les colonnes de
            pixels, lui donnant un aspect strié.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Il livello attivo e i suoi istogrammi rosso, verde e blu, dopo
            il trattamento.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            L'estensione dell'istogramma crea dei "buchi" tra le colonne di
            pixel, dandone il caratteristico aspetto a strisce.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå etter
            bruk av <quote>Jamn ut</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Strekkinga av histogrammet lagar opningar mellom kolonnene. Difor
            stripene.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
