<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
  2005/09/03 de created by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-introduction" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-17</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-25</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-02</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-04</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-21</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">
      Introduction to the <quote>Layer</quote> Menu
    </phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Vrstvy</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Introduction aux Calques</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Einführung in das Menü <quote>Ebene</quote></phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Introducción al menú Capa</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Introduzione al menu <quote>Livello</quote></phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">
      Innleiing til menyen <quote>Lag</quote>
    </phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">图层</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image window</primary><secondary>Layer Menu</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Menus</primary><secondary>Layer</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Ventana de la imagen</primary><secondary>Menú Capa</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Menús</primary><secondary>Capa</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestra immagine</primary><secondary>Menu livello</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Menu</primary><secondary>Livello</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Biletvindauget</primary><secondary>Lagmenyen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Menyar</primary><secondary>Lag</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        The Contents of the <quote>Layer</quote> Menu
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Inhalt des <guilabel>Ebene</guilabel> Menüs</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">El contenido del menú Capa</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Menu des calques</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Il contenuto del menu <quote>Livello</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Innhaldet i menyen <quote>Lag</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">图层菜单</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs;en;es;zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/layer.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/layer.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/layer.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/layer.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/layer.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The items on the <guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu allow you to work on
    layers. In addition to accessing the <guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu from
    the Image menubar and by right-clicking on the image window, you can
    get to it by right-clicking on the thumbnail of a layer in the Layers
    dialog. You can also perform several of the operations on this menu by
    clicking on buttons in the Layers dialog, for example, resizing a layer,
    managing layer transparency and merging layers.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    This menu can contain other entries besides the ones described in this
    section. They are not part of <application>GIMP</application> itself,
    but are extensions (plug-ins). Please refer to the documentation about
    the plug-ins for more information.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Die in diesem Menü befindlichen Kommandos dienen Ihnen zur Bearbeitung
    von Ebenen.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Neben den an dieser Stelle vorgestellten Kommandos können sich weitere
    Einträge im Menü befinden. Diese gehören nicht zum Standardumfang von
    <application>GIMP</application>
    , sondern sind Programmerweiterungen (Plug-In). Eine Beschreibung der
    Funktionalität entnehmen Sie bitte der Dokumentation des Plug-In.
    <!-- TODO: de the more important plugins should be documented in the
         manual -->
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    Los elementos del menú <guilabel>Capa</guilabel> le permiten operar con
    las mismas.  Además de acceder a este menú desde la barra de menú de la
    imagen, y haciendo clic derecho sobre la ventana de la imagen, puede
    obtenerlo haciendo clic derecho sobre la miniatura de la capa en el
    diálogo de capas.  Además puede realizar varias de las operaciones de este
    menú clicando en los botones de la parte inferior del diálogo de capas.
    Por ejemplo, se puede cambiar el tamaño de una capa, su transparencia, o
    se pueden combinar varias capas en una sola.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Este menú puede tener otras entradas además de las que se describen en
    esta sección.  Éstas no son parte del GIMP mismo, sino que vienen como
    complementos (plug-ins).  Refiérase a la documentación de los complementos
    para información sobre dichas entradas.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    En plus de la barre de menus de l'image, le menu contextuel des calques
    est accessible via un clic-droit sur la vignette d'un calque. Ce menu
    offre une bonne partie des actions déjà accessibles par les boutons du
    dialogue des calques, des possibilités de redimensionnement du calque, une
    gestion de la transparence et aussi de fusion de l'ensemble des calques.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Ce menu peut contenir d'autres entrées qui n'appartiennent pas en propre
    à GIMP, mais qui ont été ajoutées par quelques greffons.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Le voci presenti nel menu <guimenu>livello</guimenu>, come suggerisce
    il nome, servono a lavorare con i livelli. Oltre a poter accedere al
    menu <guimenu>livello</guimenu> dalla barra del menu immagine e tramite
    il menu accessibile facendo clic con il tasto destro sull'immagine, è
    possibile accedere questo menu anche facendo clic con il tasto destro
    del mouse sulla miniatura del livello presente nella finestra dei
    livelli. È inoltre possibile eseguire diverse delle operazioni presenti
    nel suddetto menu direttamente premendo i pulsanti presenti nella
    finestra di dialogo dei livelli per, ad esempio, ridimensionare un
    livello, gestirne la trasparenza o fondere assieme più livelli.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Questo menu contiene altre voci oltre a quelle descritte in questa
    sezione. Queste non fanno propriamente parte di
    <application>GIMP</application>, ma sono estensioni (fornite tramite
    plug-in). Per le suddette, fare riferimento alla documentazione
    allegata al plug-in per ottenere ulteriori informazioni su di esso.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="no">
    Dei ulike vala du har på <guimenu>Lagmenyen</guimenu> blir brukte 
    når du arbeider på biletlaga. I tillegg til at du har tilgang på denne
    menyen frå biletmenyen, kan du få han fram ved å høgreklikke i 
    biletet eller på miniatyren av laget i lagdialogen. Fleire av vala i
    denne menyen kan du også få fram ved å klikke på ulike knappar
    i lagdialogen. Dette gjeld for eksempel å endre storleik på laget,
    flette saman lag eller å forandre gjennomsikt for laget.
  </para>
   <para lang="no">
    Både i hovudmenyen og i undermenyane kan du finne kommandoar som
    ikkje er omtalte her. Desse høyrer eigentleg ikkje til 
    <application>GIMP</application>, men blir lagt inn av programtillegg 
    (plug-ins). Som oftast finn du nærare omtale av desse kommandoane
    i dokumentasjonen for programtillegga.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    除了图像菜单和图像右键菜单，您也可以用右键点击图层对话框的图层缩略图获取
    图层菜单。该菜单中许多操作也在图层对话框的按钮中：缩放图层，管理图层的透
    明度和合并图层。
  </para>
</sect2>
