<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en;fr">
  <title lang="en">View</title>
  <title lang="fr">Affichage</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image menu view</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image menu affichage</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/menus/menus-view.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         Contents of the View menu
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The View menu contains commands that affect the visibility or
    appearance of the image and various elements of the interface.
  </para>

  <simplesect id='gimp-view-new_view'>
    <title lang="en">New View</title>
    <title lang="fr">Nouvelle vue</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary lang="en">New View</primary>
      <primary lang="fr">Nouvelle vue</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ew View</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      "New View" creates a new image window for the current image,
      which you can set up differently than the existing display.  You
      can create multiple displays of any image:  only the zoom level
      and other viewing options can differ, though.  Any other changes
      made in one view are reflected in any other displays that show
      the same image.  One common use for multiple views is if you are
      working on individual pixels, at a high zoom level:  it may be
      useful for you to see at the same time the effects of your
      changes on the image as it would normally be viewed.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      You can delete a new view by closing the window it creates.
      Closing the last remaining display for an image will cause the
      image itself to be closed, but if this would lead to any loss of
      data, you will be asked to confirm that you really want to do
      it.
    </para>
 
    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette commande se trouve dans 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Affichage/<accel>N</accel>ouvelle vue</guimenuitem>.
    </para>     
    <para lang='fr'>
      Elle crée une nouvelle fenêtre d'image, identique à la première. 
      Vous pouvez créer ainsi plusieurs répliques de l'image, numérotées 
      .1, .2, ...etc). 
      Seules les fonctions de zoom et d'affichage seront indépendantes 
      de la première vue; toutes les autres fonctions verront leur effet 
      répercuté sur les autres vues.  
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette fonction sert surtout quand vous travaillez au niveau du 
      pixel. Vous pouvez ainsi voir en temps réel ce que donne votre 
      travail en taille normale.
    </para>
    <note lang='fr'>
      <para>
	Cette nouvelle vue ne constitue pas un fichier séparé, ce n'est
	qu'un aspect différent du même fichier.
      </para>
    </note> 
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='gimp-view-zoom'>
    <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-out' />
    <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-in' />
    <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-100' />
    <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-fit' />
    <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-other' />
    <title lang="en">Zoom</title>
    <title lang="fr">Zoom</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary lang="en">Zoom</primary>
      <primary lang="fr">Zoom</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/menus/menus-view-zoom.png'
            format="PNG"/>
         </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
       <caption>
         <para lang='en'>
           The Zoom submenu of the View menu
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      The "Zoom" commands can be accessed from an image menubar,
      in the submenu
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Zoom</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>.
      In GIMP 2.2, you can also zoom an image using the <link
      linkend='gimp-image-window-zoom'>Zoom button</link> on the
      image window.
      Zooming means changing the magnification level of the
      image. Zooming in to an image is useful for pixel-level image  
      modifications, and zooming out can be handy for working with 
      broad effects.  Note that zooming is not undoable, because it
      does not affect the image data, only the way it is displayed.
    </para> 

    <para lang='en'>
      Here are the available Zoom commands, along with their default
      keyboard shortcuts if any:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang='en'>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Zoom Out</title>
        (Shortcut: <keycap>-</keycap>)  Each time "Zoom Out" is 
        used, the zoom factor is decreased by about 30%.  There is a
        minimum zoom level of 6%
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Zoom In</title> (Shortcut: <keycap>+</keycap>) 
        Each time Zoom In is used, the zoom level is increased by a
        factor of around 30%.  The maximum possible zoom level is
        1600%.  
      </formalpara>
      <note>
        <para>
	  The keyboard shortcut for "Zoom In" has been a subject of some
	  controversy, because this is a very commonly used operation, and
	  on English keyboards it requires the Shift key to be pressed.
	  (For European keyboards, it does not.)  If you would like to have
	  an easier shortcut, you can create a dynamic shortcut for it; see
	  the help section for <link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>User
	  Interface</link> Preferences for instructions.
        </para>
      </note>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Fit Image in Window</title>
        (Shortcut:
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
          <keycap>E</keycap>
        </keycombo>).
        This command zooms the image as large as possible while still
        keeping it completely within the window.  Padding will
        probably show on two sides of the image, but not on all four
        sides.  
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Fit Image to Window</title>
        This command zooms the image as small as possible without
        requiring any padding to be shown:  it causes the image to fit
        the window perfectly in one dimension, and extend beyond the
        window borders in the other dimension.
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>A:B</title>
        Here you have a series of menu entries for specific zoom levels,
        including, most importantly, the 100% zoom level, which has a
        simple keyboard shortcut: <keycap>1</keycap>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Other</title>
        This command brings up a dialog that allows you to choose any
        zoom level you want, within the allowed limits of 6% to 1600%.
      </formalpara>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette commande se trouve dans 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Affichage/<accel>Z</accel>oom</guimenuitem>.
    </para>     
    <para lang='fr'>
      La fonction zoom permet de modifier le grossissement de l&apos;image. Le 
      zoom avant est utile pour travailler au niveau du pixel. Le zoom 
      arrière peut vous donner une vue plus générale.  
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Les deux principales commandes sont le <guilabel>Zoom avant</guilabel> 
      et le <guilabel>Zoom arrière</guilabel>. Chaque fois que le Zoom avant 
      est utilisé, le niveau de zoom est augmenté de 100% et chaque fois que 
      le Zoom arrière est utilisé, le niveau de zoom est diminué de 
      moitié. Le niveau minimum est de 6.25% et le niveau maximum de 1600%.
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      La commande <guilabel>Autre...</guilabel> ouvre le dialogue «Choisir 
      un facteur d'échelle» qui vous donne la possibilité d'ajuster plus 
      précisément le niveau de zoom. 
    </para>    
    <para lang='fr'>
      <guilabel>Zoom ajusté à la fenêtre</guilabel>: Après avoir zoomé, 
       cette commande vous permet de revenir à la taille normale. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Raccourcis clavier:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang='fr'>   
      <listitem>
        <para>
        La touche <keycap>-</keycap> réduira l'image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        La touche <keycap>+</keycap> grossira l'image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        La combinaison de touches <keycap>Maj+Ctrl+E</keycap> reviendra à 
        la taille normale.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <tip lang='fr'>
      Quand vous travaillez au niveau du pixel, utilisez la fonction  
      <link linkend='gimp-view-new_view'>Nouvelle vue</link>.
    </tip>
    <tip lang="fr">
      Voir aussi <link linkend='gimp-view-navigation'>Fenêtre de navigation</link>
    </tip>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='gimp-view-shrink-wrap'>
    <title lang="en">Shrink Wrap</title>
    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Shrink Wrap</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      or by using the keyboard shortcut
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        <keycap>E</keycap>
      </keycombo>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      "Shrink Wrap" resizes the window so that it precisely matches
      the dimensions of the image display at the current zoom level,
      unless this would cause it to be larger than the viewable area
      of the monitor.  Note that you can make this happen
      automatically by setting the options "Resize window on zoom" and
      "Resize window on image size change" in the <link
      linkend='gimp-prefs-image-window'>Image Window</link> page of
      the Preferences dialog.  Note also that this behavior is not
      implemented by GIMP itself, but rather by the window manager, so
      it is possible that in some very broken environments it might
      not work, through no fault of GIMP's.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <xi:include href="view-dot-for-dot.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="view-infowindow.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="view-navigwindow.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="view-show-selection.xml" />
  <!-- 20040702-->
  <xi:include href="view-show-layer-boundary.xml" />
  <!--end-->
  <xi:include href="view-show-guides.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-snap-to-guides.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-show-grid.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-snap-to-grid.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-show-menubar.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-show-rulers.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-show-scrollbars.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-show-statusbar.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-shrinkwrap.xml" />
  <xi:include href="view-fullscreen.xml" />
</sect1> 
