<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<sect1 id="gimp-menus-introduction" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">GIMP Menus</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Einführung in die GIMP Menüs</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Los menús del GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Les menus de GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">I menu di GIMP</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en;fr">
    <primary>Menus</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Menús</primary>
    <secondary>Introducción</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">Toolbox Menu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Die Menüleiste im Werkzeugfenster</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Le menu de la Boîte à outils</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">El menú de la caja de herramientas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">I menu della barra degli strumenti</phrase>
    </title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/cs/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-menu.png'
            format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <!--  TODO: raw translation by axel.wernicke - please review - thnx! -->
  <!-- I've shorted the paragraph because I found it unnecessary long
  (ciampix) -->
  <para lang="en">
    There are many places in <application>GIMP</application> where you can
    find menus. The aim of this chapter is to explain all the commands that
    are accessible from the menu in the toolbox and image window. All the
    context menus and the menu entries for the other dialogs are described
    elsewhere in the chapter that describes the dialog itself.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="de">
    In <application>GIMP</application> finden Sie an verschiedensten Stellen
    Menüs. In diesem Kapitel werden die Menüeinträge des Werkzeug- sowie
    des Bildfensters beschrieben. Die in GIMP ebenfalls häufig vorhandenen
    Kontextmenüs werden dort beschrieben, wo auch der entsprechende Kontext,
    also beispielsweise der Dialog, beschrieben ist.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    En muchos lugares del <application>GIMP</application> se
    encuentran menús.  En este capítulo se explican todos los comandos
    que son accesibles desde el menú de la caja de herramientas y
    desde el menú de la imagen.  Todos los menús contextuales y las
    entradas de menú de otros diálogos se describen en los capítulos
    de los diálogos mismos.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Vous trouverez plusieurs menus dans GIMP. Le but de ce chapitre est de
    vous expliquer les commandes disponibles à partir de la Boîte à outils
    et de la fenêtre d'image. Les autres menus et entrées de menus sont
    décrites dans le chapitre décrivant chaque fenêtre de dialogue.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    I menu in <application>GIMP</application> sono presenti un po' ovunque;
    lo scopo di questo capitolo è di spiegare tutti i comandi accessibili
    dai menu della barra degli strumenti e dalla finestra immagine. Tutti
    gli altri menu contestuali e le voci di menu corrispondenti, sono
    descritti nei capitoli dedicati alle finestre relative.
  </para>

  <sect2 lang="en;es;fr" id='context-menus'>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Context menus</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Menus contextuels</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Menús contextuales</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Context menus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es">
      <primary>Menús contextuales</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Menus contextuels</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para lang="en">
      Right clicking on certain elements of the GIMP interface opens a
      <quote>Context menu</quote> which lead to a variety of functions:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            On image windows: the image menu. This is useful when working
            in full screen mode, without menu-bar.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            On a layer in the Layer Dialog or on a channel in the Channel
            Dialog: functions for the selected layer or channel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Right-cliking on the image menu bar has the same action as
            left-clicking.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Right-clicking on the a title bar: these functions does not
            belong to GIMP but to the interface management program of your
            system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Al hacer clic derecho sobre ciertos elementos de la interfaz del
      GIMP se abre un <quote>menú contextual</quote>, el que lleva a
      una variedad de funciones:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sobre ventanas de imágenes: el menú de la imagen.  Éste es
            útil al trabajar a pantalla completa, sin la barra de
            menús.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sobre una capa en el diálogo de capas o sobre un canal en
            el diálogo de canales: funciones para la capa o el canal
            seleccionado.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Hacer un clic derecho sobre la barra de menú de la imagen
            tiene el mismo efecto que hacer clic izquierdo.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Hacer clic derecho sobre la barra de título de la ventana:
            estas funciones no pertenecen al GIMP sino al gestor de
            ventanas del sistema.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Sur certains éléments de l'interface GIMP, le clic droit
      ouvre un <quote>menu contextuel</quote>, encore appelé
      <quote>menu local</quote>, donnant accès a diverses fonctions:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sur les fenêtres d'image: l'ensemble des entrées du menu d'image.
            Ce qui peut être utile si vous travaillez en mode plein écran,
            sans barre de menus.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sur un des bandeaux du Dialogue des calques et du Dialogue des
            canaux: les fonctions de gestion des calques et des canaux.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sur la barre de menus: le clic droit a la même action que le clic
            gauche.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sur la barre de titre: les fonctions développées n'appartiennent
            pas à GIMP mais au programme de gestion d'interface de votre
            système.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>      
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 lang="en;es;fr" id='detachable-submenus'>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Detachable sub-menus</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Submenús desprendibles</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Sous-menus détachables</phrase>
    </title>
    
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Detachable sub-menus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es">
      <primary>Submenús desprendibles</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Sous-menus détachables</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      The sub-menus of the image menu you get by right-clicking (this
      image menu also) and the sub-menus of the tool-box --you get them
      by clicking on the
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/icon-submenu.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      icon -- have an interesting property. At the top of their window they
      have a dotted line. When you click on this dotted line, the menu
      under is detached and becomes a separate window.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Los submenús del menú de la imagen que se obtiene haciendo clic
      derecho y los submenús de la caja de herramientas, que se
      obtienen haciendo clic sobre el icono
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/icon-submenu.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>, tienen una propiedad interesante.  En su parte
      superior tienen una línea de puntos.  Si hace clic en la misma,
      el submenú se desprende, volviéndose una ventana separada.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les sous-menus du menu d'image obtenu par clic droit (ainsi que ce
      même menu d'image) et ceux du menu de la Boîte à outils, auxquels vous
      accédez en cliquant sur
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/icon-submenu.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>,
      ont une propriété intéressante. Ils possèdent en haut de leur fenêtre
      une ligne de pointillés, la <emphasis>ligne de détachement</emphasis>.
      Si vous cliquez sur cette ligne, le sous-menu se transforme en fenêtre
      séparée que vous pouvez déplacer et garder à votre disposition.
    </para>
    
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">The Acquire sub-menu and its Detached
          sub-menu</phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">
          El submenú Adquirir dentro del menú, y desprendido del
          mismo
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Le sous-menu Acquisition et son Sous-menu
          détaché</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/acquire.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/acquire.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/detached-submenu.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/detached-submenu.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/detached-submenu.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para lang="en">
      Detached sub-menus originating from the Tool-box are visible only if
      the Tool-box is active. Detached sub-menus originating from the
      image window are actually independant: always visible, their
      functions apply to the current image and they persist when all
      images are closed.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Los submenús desprendidos de la caja de herramientas son
      visibles sólo cuando la misma se encuentra activa.  Los submenús
      desprendidos de la ventana de la imagen son independientes:
      están siempre visibles, sus funciones se aplican a la imagen
      activa, y persisten aún cuando todas las imágenes se cierran.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les sous-menus détachés issus de la Boîte à outils ne sont visibles
      que si la Boîte à outils est active. Les sous-menus détachés issus de
      la fenêtre d'image sont véritablement indépendants: visibles en
      permanence, leurs fonctions s'appliquent à l'image en cours et ils
      persistent en l'absence de toute image.
    </para>

  </sect2>
</sect1>
