<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-layer-menu' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Layers</title>
  <title lang="cs">Vrstvy</title>
  <title lang="fr">Calques</title>
  <title lang="de">Ebenenkontextmenü</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">图层</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image menu layer</primary>
    <primary lang="cs">Nabídka okna obrázku Vrstvy</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image menu calque</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像菜单图层</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title lang='en'>Main Menu</title>
    <title lang='cs'>Hlavní nabídka</title>
    <title lang='de'>Hauptmenü</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Menu principal</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">主菜单</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/menus-layer.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/menus-layer.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/de/dialogs-layer-menu.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-layer-menu.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-layer-menu.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
           <para lang='en'>
             The Layers menu
           </para>
           <para lang='de'>
             Ebenenkontextmenü
           </para>
           <para lang='fr'>
             Menu des calques
           </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            图层菜单
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      In addition to the image menubar and image right-click menu, you
      can also get the Layers menu by right-clicking on a layer
      thumbnail in the Layers dialog.  Several of the operations in this
      menu are also available from buttons in the Layers dialog:
      resizing a layer, managing layer transparency, and merging layers.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Das Ebenenkontextmenü wird durch einen rechten Mausklick auf die
      aktuelle Ebene im Ebenendialog aufgerufen. Das Kontextmenü zeigt 
      eine Reihe von Funktionen, die auf die aktuelle Ebene angewendet
      werden können.
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      En plus de la barre de menus de l'image, le menu contextuel des calques 
      est accessible via un clic-droit sur la vignette d'un calque. Ce menu 
      offre une bonne partie des actions déjà accessibles par les boutons du 
      dialogue des calques, des possibilités de redimensionnement du calque, 
      une gestion de la transparence et aussi de fusion de l'ensemble des 
      calques.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了图像菜单和图像右键菜单，您也可以用右键点击图层对话框的图层缩略图获取图层菜单。该菜单中许多操作也在图层对话框的按钮中：缩放图层，管理图层的透明度和合并图层。
    </para>

    <simplesect id='gimp-new-layer-dialog' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
      <title lang='en'>New Layer</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Nouveau calque</title>
      <title lang='de'>Neue Ebene</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">新建图层</title>

      <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject lang="en">
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-layer.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-new-layer.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              New Layer dialog
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              新建图层对话框
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

      <informalfigure lang="fr">
        <mediaobject lang="fr">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-new-layer.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="fr">
              Dialogue de Nouveau calque
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

      <para lang='en'>
        This dialog comes up when you create a new layer within an
        image.  It is activated by choosing  
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>New Layer</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        Le dialogue de Nouveau calque est activé par le menu 
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Nouveau calque</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该对话框在您新建图层时出现，可以用下列方式开启，从图像菜单中
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>新建图层</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>

      <variablelist lang='en;fr;zh_CN'>
        <title lang="en">Options</title>
        <title lang="fr">Options</title>
        <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Layer Name</term>
          <term lang='fr'>Nom du calque</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">图层名字</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>
              Here you assign the layer a name.  This does not have any
              functional significance:  it is simply a convenience to
              help you remember the role you intended the layer to play
              when you created it.  By default, the name "New Layer" is
              used.  If a layer with this name (or whatever name you
              choose) already exists, after you hit the "OK" button, a
              number will be appended to the name in order to make it
              unique, i. e., "New Layer#1".
            </para>
            <para lang='fr'>
              Ici vous donnez un nom à votre nouveau calque.
              Ça n'a pas de conséquence importante, donner une non explicite
              est le meilleur moyen que vous avez de retrouver plus tard
              votre calque s'il est mélangé dans une multitude d'autres
              calques. Par défaut le nom « Nouveau calque » sera affecté.
              Si vous utilisez le nom d'un calque déjà existant le
              nouveau calque sera suffixé par un numéro d'ordre.
             </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              在这里给图层一个名字。它并没有什么功能上的作用：它只是方便您记忆您创建该图层想要它所起的作用。默认使用“新建图层”这个名字。如果给的名字已经存在，在您按下“确定”按钮后，会在名字后添加一个数字使其名字唯一，如“新建图层#1”。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>  
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Width and Height</term>
          <term lang='fr'>Hauteur et largeur</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">宽度和高度</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>
              Here you set the dimensions of the new layer.  When the
              dialog appears, the values are initialized to the
              dimensions of the image.  You can change them, and if you
              want to use units other than pixels, you can get them
              using the Units menu to the right.  You can't set the
              position of the layer within the image here, but you can
              always move it after it has been created.
            </para>
            <para lang='fr'>
              Ici vous indiquez les dimensions qu'aura le nouveau calque.
              Quand le dialogue apparait ces valeurs sont initialisées
              à la taille de l'image. Vous pouvez les changer et
              choisir dans un menu les unités de mesure.
              Un calque peut être plus petit ou plus grand que le canevas
              de l'image et de toute façon vous pouvez toujours changer
              ultérieurement sa taille.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              在这里设定新建图层的尺寸。当对话框出现时，其值将初始为图像的尺寸。您可以改变它们，而且也能从右边单位菜单中选择单位，如果不想使用像素。您不能够在这里设置图层在图像中的位置，不过可以在创建后移动它。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>  
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Layer Fill Type</term>
          <term lang='fr'>Type de remplissage du calque</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">图层填充类型</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>
              Here you have four options for the solid color that will
              fill the layer:  the foreground or background colors as
              shown in the Main Toolbox; white; or transparent. 
            </para>
            <para lang='fr'>
              Vous avez ici le choix entre quatres options de remplissage,
              les couleurs de premier et d'arrière-plan de la boîte à
              outils ou blanc ou transparent.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              在这里有关于填充图层所有用单色的四个选项：显示在主工具箱的前景或背景色;白色;或透明。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>  
      </variablelist>

      <para lang='de'>
        <guilabel><accel>N</accel>eue Ebene</guilabel>: läßt Sie eine neue
        Ebene anlegen.
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Duplicate layer</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Dupliquer le calque</title>
      <title lang='de'>Ebene duplizieren</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">复制图层</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        This item adds to the image a new layer that is a perfect copy
        of the active layer in all respects but two:  first, if the
        active layer is the bottom layer and lacks an alpha channel, one
        will be added to the copy; second, if any layer parasites are
        attached to the active layer, they are not copied (if you don't
        understand what this means, don't worry about it).
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Dupliquer le calque</guilabel> : permet de copier le calque.
        Cette copie diffère de l'original sur deux points. D'abord, si le 
        calque ne possède pas de canal Alpha, il en sera ajouté un. Ensuite, 
        si quelque parasite de calque est attaché au calque actif, il ne sera 
        pas copié (si vous ne comprenez pas de quoi il s'agit, ne vous 
        tracassez pas).
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
  <guilabel>Ebene <accel>d</accel>uplizieren</guilabel>: legt eine
  Kopie der aktuellen Ebene an.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该命令给图像添加一个新图层，它是活动图层的完全副本，除了两种情况：第一，如果活动图层是没有 Alpha 通道的底部图层，副本中就会添加一个;第二，活动图层上的有任何“寄生”都不会复制(如果不知道我说什么，也不用担心)。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Anchor layer</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Ancrer le calque</title>
      <title lang='de'>Ebene verankern</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">固定图层</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        This item anchors the floating selection to the active layer.
        If the image does not contain a floating selection, this menu
        entry will be insensitive.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Ancrer le calque</guilabel> :
        permet de d'ancrer un calque temporaire (une sélection
        flottante) dans le calque précédemment actif. Si l'image ne contient 
        pas de sélection flottante, cette entrée de menu ne sera pas 
        disponible (en grisé).
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
  <guilabel>Ebene <accel>v</accel>erankern</guilabel>:
  vereinigt die schwebende Auswahl mit der Ebene, aus dem die
  Auswahl erstellt wurde.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该命令固定浮动选区到活动图层中。如果图像中没有活动选区，该菜单项则不可用。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id='gimp-layer-merge-down'>
      <title lang='en'>Merge down</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Fusionner vers le bas</title>
      <title lang='de'></title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">向下合并</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        This item causes the active layer to be merged with the layer
        below it in the layer list, taking into account the active
        layer's opacity and combination mode.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Fusionner vers le bas</guilabel> :
        le calque est fusionné avec le calque situé juste
        en-dessous dans la liste. Il est supprimé et le nouveau calque 
        actif est celui qui est le plus bas dans la liste. L'opacité du 
        calque actif initial et le mode de fusion sont pris en compte.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该命令使活动图层与在图层列表中活动图层下的图层合并，并考虑活动图层的不透明度和组合模式。
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        FIX ME
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Delete layer</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Supprimer le calque</title>
      <title lang='de'></title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">删除图层</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        This item removes the active layer from the image.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Supprimer le calque</guilabel> :
        permet de supprimer le calque.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        FIX ME
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该命令从图像中删除活动图层。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Edit Layer Attributes</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Éditer les attributs du calque</title>
      <title lang='de'>Ebeneneigenschaften</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">编辑图层属性</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        This item is used to change the name of the layer.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Éditer les attributs du calque</guilabel> :
        permet de changer le nom du calque.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
  <guilabel>Ebenenei<accel>g</accel>enschaften</guilabel>: läßt Sie
  den Namen der Ebene verändern.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该命令用作改变图层的名字。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id='gimp-layer-resize'>
      <title lang='en'>Layer Boundary Size</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Taille des bords du calque</title>
      <title lang='de'>Ebenengröße</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">图层边界大小</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        A layer does not always have same size as the image canvas.  It
        can be smaller (consuming less memory) or larger, in which case
        some parts are hidden.  Selecting this item will activate a
        dialog in which you can set parameters for the layer dimensions:
        these parameters are <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and
        <guilabel>Height</guilabel>, or alternatively <guilabel>Ratio X
        Y</guilabel>.   The layer ratio is maintained if the chain
        symbol has a "locked" appearance. Clicking on the chain symbol
        will toggle it between locked and unlocked states. You can
        use a menu to select the units for the new layer boundary size.
        <guilabel>Offset</guilabel> locates the upper left corner of the
        layer in the image's canvas. In addition to editing the numbers,
        you can change the X and Y offsets by dragging the mouse in the
        interactive image in the dialog. The old layer configuration
        is shown with a blurred border and the new layer
        configuration with a hard border. 
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        Rappellons qu'un calque n'a pas forcément la même taille
        que le canevas de l'image. Il peut être plus petit ce qui
        économise de la mémoire ou plus grand mais dans ce dernier cas
        il ne sera pas entièrement visible.  Un dialogue s'ouvre, il
        permet de fixer quelques paramètres pour la taille du calque. On
        peut indiquer la <guilabel>Largeur</guilabel> et la
        <guilabel>Hauteur</guilabel> ou bien encore un <guilabel>Facteur
        d'échelle</guilabel>. Le ratio du calque (le rapport largeur/hauteur) 
        est conservé tant que l'icône à côté du facteur d'échelle représente 
        une chaîne.  Il suffit de cliquer sur l'icône pour arrêter de 
        conserver le ratio, l'icône se transforme alors en une chaine brisée. 
        Le menu déroulant permet de choisir l'unité utilisée pour mesurer les
        nouveaux bords du calque.  Le <guilabel>Décalage</guilabel>
        permet de positionner le coin supérieur gauche du calque par rapport 
        au canevas de l'image. On peut ajuster les décalages X et Y en 
        utilisant la souris dans l'image interactive proposée par le dialogue. 
        L'ancienne taille du calque est représentée par un rectangle à bords 
        flous alors que la nouvelle taille du calque est représentée par un 
        rectangle à bords nets. Faites les derniers ajustements grâce aux 
        boutons indiquant une flêche ou bien entrez-les manuellement.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        <guimenuitem>Ebenen<accel>g</accel>röße</guimenuitem>: lässt Sie
        die Größe der Ebene verändern.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">   
   一个图层并不总是和图像画布有相同的大小，它可以更小(消耗更少内存)或更多(一些部分会隐藏)。该项会开启一个设置图层尺寸参数的对话框：这些参数是<guilabel>宽度</guilabel>和<guilabel>高度</guilabel>，或<guilabel>比率 X Y</guilabel>。如果锁链标志是“锁住”的，图层比率将被保持。点击锁链标志将在锁住和未锁住状态间切换。在右边的菜单选择图层新边界大小的单位。<guilabel>位移</guilabel>定位图层在图像画布中的左上角。除了可以编辑数字，也可以通过在对话框的交互图像中拖动鼠标改变 X 和 Y 位移。旧图层轮廓为模糊边界而新图层轮廓为硬质边界。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id='gimp-layer-resize-to-image'>
      <title lang='en'>Layer to Image Size</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Calque aux dimensions de l'image</title>
      <title lang='de'>Ebene auf Bildgröße</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">图层到图像大小</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        This item resizes the layer boundaries to match the image
        bounds, without moving the contents of the layer with respect to
        the image.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Calque aux dimensions de l'image</guilabel> :
        permet de ramener les contours du calque aux mêmes dimensions que le 
        canevas de l'image.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
  <guilabel>Ebene auf <accel>B</accel>ildgröße</guilabel>:
  passt die Größe der aktuellen Ebene der Grösse des Bildes an.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该项改变图层边缘大小以符合图像边缘，但不会移动图层内容。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id='gimp-layer-scale'>
      <title lang='en'>Scale Layer</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Échelle et Taille du calque</title>
      <title lang='de'>Ebene skalieren</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">缩放图层</title>

      <para lang='en'>   
        With this item you can resize the
        layer and its contents.  A dialog appears in which you can set
        parameters for the layer size. Those parameters are
        <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and <guilabel>Height</guilabel>
        or also <guilabel>Ratio X Y</guilabel>.  The layer ratio is
        retained if the icon behind the ratio values is a chain.
        When you click on this icon, the chain is broken and the
        original ratio is no longer maintained. You can use a menu to
        select the units for the new layer boundary size.  The
        <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel> menu let you choose how
        the new layer pixels will be recalculated. When you resize
        the layer content either pixels are added or removed,
        and a recalculation is necessary.  When the new size is
        smaller, the layer is cropped. When the new size is larger, a 
        transparent area (or the background color if the layer has
        no Alpha channel) is added around the previous contents of
        the layer.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        <guilabel>Étirer le calque</guilabel> : permet de
        redimensionner le calque et son contenu.  Un dialogue
        s'ouvre, il permet de fixer quelques paramètres pour la
        taille du calque. On peut indiquer la
        <guilabel>Largeur</guilabel> et la
        <guilabel>Hauteur</guilabel> ou bien encore un
        <guilabel>Facteur d'échelle</guilabel>. Le ratio du calque
        est conservé tant que l'icône à côté du facteur d'échelle
        représente une chaîne.  Il suffit de cliquer sur l'icône
        pour arrêter de conserver le ratio, l'icône se transforme
        alors en une chaine brisée. Le menu déroulant permet de
        choisir l'unité utilisée pour mesurer la nouvelle taille du
        calque et de son contenu.  Le menu <guilabel>Type
        d'interpolation</guilabel> permet de choisir comment les
        nouveaux pixels du calque seront recalculés, en effet
        lorsqu'on redimensionne le contenu d'un calque soit des
        pixels sont ajoutés, soit des pixels sont enlevés et il
        faut les recalculer.  Lors d'un rétrécissement le calque
        sera rogné. Lors d'un agrandissement une zone transparente
        (ou la couleur d'arrière-plan si le calque n'a pas de canal
        Alpha) sera ajoutée autour du contenu précédent du calque, 
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        <guilabel>Ebene <accel>s</accel>kalieren</guilabel>:
        verändert die Größe des Bildes durch Skalierung. Hierbei
        kann ein Qualitätsverlust der Bildobjekte auf der Ebene
        entstehen.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">   
        该项改变图层及其内容的大小,它会唤出一个设置图层大小参数的对话框。这些参数是<guilabel>宽度</guilabel>和<guilabel>高度</guilabel>，或<guilabel>比率 X Y</guilabel>。如果锁链标志是“锁住”的，图层比率将被保持。点击锁链标志将在锁住和未锁住状态间切换。在右边的菜单选择新图层大小的单位。<guilabel>插值</guilabel>菜单决定新图层像素如何被再次计算。当您通过添加或删除像素的方式改变了图层内容的大小，就有必要进行再次计算。新尺寸过小时，图层将被剪裁。新尺寸过大时，会在以前图层内容周围添加一个透明区域(如果图层没有 Alpha 通道则添加背景色)。
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </sect2>

  <xi:include href="menus-layer-stack.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-colors.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-mask.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-transparency.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-transform.xml" /> 
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-crop.xml" />
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-autocrop.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="menus-layer-align.xml" />
</sect1>
