<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-imagewindow-menus-image' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en;fr">Image</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">图像</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en;fr">Image menu image</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像菜单/图像</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en;zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/menus/menus-image.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>

       <caption>
         <para lang='en'>
           Contents of the Image menu
         </para>
         <para lang="zh_CN">
           图像菜单内容
         </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Image menu contains commands that use or affect the entire
    image in some way, not just the active layer or some other
    specific part of the image.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    图像菜单中是一些用某种方式使用或影响整个图像的命令，而不是对活动图层或图像的特定部分。
  </para>

  <simplesect id='gimp-image-crop'>
    <title lang='en'>Crop Image</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">剪裁图像</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Crop Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Crop Image" crops the image to the selection bounds, by
      removing any strips at the edges whose contents are all
      completely unselected.  Areas that are partially selected (for
      example, by feathering) are not cropped away.  If no selection
      exists for the image, the menu entry will be insensitive.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该命令在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>剪裁图像</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      “剪裁图像”将图像剪至图像的边缘，将边缘任何完全未选中的内容移除。那些被部分选中的区域(比如对选区羽化后得到的)则不会被裁剪掉。当图像中没有选区时，该菜单项则不可用。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='plug-in-autocrop'>
    <title lang='en'>Autocrop Image</title>
    <title lang="fr">Découpage automatique</title> 
    <title lang="zh_CN">自动剪裁图像</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Autocrop Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Autocrop Image" removes borders from an image.  It searches the
      active layer for the largest possible border area that all has
      the same color, and then crops this area from the image, just as
      though you had used the Crop tool.
    </para>
    <caution lang="en">
      <para>
        Note carefully that this command only uses the <emphasis>active
        layer</emphasis> of the image to find borders.  If other layers
        have color variations extending into the border zone of the
        active layer, they will be cropped away.
      </para>
    </caution>


    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette fonction automatise le Découpage de l'image, à la différence 
      de <link linkend='gimp-tool-crop'>l'outil Découpage</link> qui
      vous permet de définir manuellement la zone à découper.  
    </para> 
    <para lang='fr'> 
      Elle est en fait à réserver au cas où vous avez un sujet perdu 
      dans un fond uni trop grand: la nouvelle image sera recadrée aux 
      dimensions du sujet. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Dans les autres cas, le résultat risque d'être aléatoire. En 
      particulier, si votre image a plusieurs calques, le découpage se 
      basera sur le calque actif et appliquera les mêmes dimensions aux 
      autres calques, ce qui peut occasionner d'importantes pertes 
      d'informations. 
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该命令在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>自动剪裁图像</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">   
      “自动剪裁图像”从图像中删除边缘。它从活动图层中搜索有相同颜色的最大区域，并把它们从图像中裁剪出来，就像使用剪裁工具一样。
    </para>
    <caution lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        需要注意的是该命令只在图像的<emphasis>活动图层</emphasis>上搜索边缘。如果其它图层上的颜色变化延伸至活动图层的边界内，它们将被剪掉。
      </para>
    </caution>
  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Merge Visible Layers</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Fusionner les calques visibles</title>
    <title lang='de'>Sichtbare Ebenen vereinen</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">合并可见图层</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Merge Visible Layers</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Merge Visible Layers" merges all layers of the image for which
      an "eye" symbol is shown in the Layers dialog
      into a single layer, leaving non-visible layers untouched.  It
      is useful for merging a set of layers that may be scattered
      around the layer list.  Selecting it brings up a dialog that
      asks you to choose between three options for the size of the
      final, merged layer:  "Expanded as necessary" means that it
      will be made as small as possible without losing any of the
      contents of the merged layers; "Clipped to image" means it
      will be set to the size of the image and any layer contents
      outside the image bounds will be lost; and "Clipped to bottom
      layer" means what it says.
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      <guilabel>Fusionner les calques visibles</guilabel> :
      permet de fusionner les calques visibles, ceux qui sont
      marqués par l'icone en forme d'oeil.  Un dialogue s'ouvre.
      L'option <guilabel>Étendu autant que nécessaire</guilabel>
      permet de conserver des données dans des calques de taille
      supérieures à celle du canevas. L'option <guilabel>Rogné à
      la taille de l'image </guilabel> permet de retailler la
      taille du calque final à celle du canevas l'image, l'option
      <guilabel>Rogné à la taille du calque le plus bas
      </guilabel> permet de ne conserver que les données
      contenues dans les limites du calque le
      plus bas. 
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      <guilabel>Sichtbare <accel>E</accel>benen vereinen</guilabel>:
      vereinigt alle sichtbaren Ebenen, gekennzeichnet durch ein
      Augensymbol, zu einer Hintergrundebene. 
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该命令在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>合并可见图层</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">   
      “合并可见图层”将图像所有在图层对话框中显示有“眼睛”标志的图像合并成为一个单个图层，而使不可见图层保持原状。这可以用作合并一组散布在图层列表中的图层。选择该命令将唤出一个有三个选择最终合并后图层大小的选项的对话框：“必要时扩展”会使合并后图层在不丢失其内容的前提下尽可能小;“剪切板到图像”会使它和图像大小相同，而图像边缘外的任何图层内容都会丢失;“剪切板到底部图层”其含义和它的名字相同。
    </para>
  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Flatten Image</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Aplatir l'image</title>
    <title lang='de'>Bild zusammefügen</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">平整图像</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Flatten Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Flatten Image" causes all of the layers of the image to be merged
      into a single layer with no alpha channel, with the same
      appearance as the full image viewed from the top.  If there are
      any areas with transparency all the way through to the bottom of
      the layer stack, they are mixed with the image's background
      color. This operation is performed as part of the process of
      exporting an image, if you save it in a format that does not
      support layers.
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      <guilabel>Aplatir l'image</guilabel> :
      permet de fusionner l'ensemble des calques dans un
      calque unique.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      <guilabel>Bild <accel>z</accel>usammefügen:</guilabel>:
      vereinigt alle Ebenen zu einer Hintergrundebene.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该命令在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>图像</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>平整图像</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">   
      “平整图像”将导致图像的所有图层合并成为一个没有 Alpha 通道的单个图层，其外部表现和从顶部看整个图像相同。如果有任何可以看到底部图层的透明区域，它们会被图像的背景色填充。在导出图像为不支持图层的格式时，该操作会作为其中的一步被执行。
    </para>
  </simplesect>


  <xi:include href="image-mode.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-transform.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-canvas-size.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-scale.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-duplicate.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-merge-vlayers.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-flatten-image.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="image-configure-grid.xml" />
</sect1>
