<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-layer-colors-menu' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Colors</title>

  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/menus-layer-colors.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Color submenu
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Color submenu of the Layers menu contains operations that
    alter colors within the image.  The top entries give access to
    the <link linkend='gimp-tools-color'>Color tools</link>, which
    are described in the Toolbox chapter.  
  </para>

  <simplesect id='gimp-layer-desaturate'>
    <title lang='en'>Desaturate</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Desaturate</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Desaturate" causes all colors in the active layer to be
      converted to correspondingly bright shades of gray.  It differs
      from converting the image to grayscale in two respects:  first,
      it only operates on the active layer; second, the colors in the
      layer continue to be three-component RGB colors, and nothing
      prevents you from painting the desaturated layer with any colors
      you please.  Desaturate works only on layers from RGB images; if
      the image is Grayscale or Indexed, the menu entry will be
      insensitive. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='gimp-layer-invert'>
    <title lang='en'>Invert</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Invert</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Invert" causes all colors in the active layer to be
      inverted in brightness, as though the image were converted into
      a negative.  Invert works on layers from RGB and Grayscale
      images, but if the image is Indexed, the menu entry will be
      insensitive. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Submenu: Auto</title>
    <informalfigure>  
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/menus/menus-layer-colors-auto.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Colors/Auto submenu
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    <para lang='en'>
      The Layers/Colors/Auto submenu contains operations that
      automatically adjust the distribution of colors in the active
      layer, without requiring input from the user.  Several of them
      are actually implemented as plugins. 
   </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='gimp-layer-equalize'>
    <title lang='en'>Equalize</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Equalize</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Equalize" adjusts the brightness of colors across the active
      layer so that the histogram for the Value channel is as nearly
      as possible flat, that is, so that each possible brightness
      value appears at about the same number of pixels as each other
      value.  Sometimes Equalize works wonderfully at enhancing the
      contrasts in an image.  Other times it gives garbage.  It is a
      very powerful operation, which can either work miracles on an
      image or destroy it.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='plug-in-color-enhance'>
    <title lang='en'>Color Enhance</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Color Enhance</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Color Enhance" increases the saturation range of colors in the
      layer without altering brightness or hue.  It does this by
      converting the colors in HSV space, measuring the range of
      saturation values across the image, then stretching this range
      to be as large as possible, and finally converting the colors
      back to RGB.  It works on layers from RGB and Indexed images.  If the
      image is Grayscale, the menu entry will be
      insensitive. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='plug-in-normalize'>
    <title lang='en'>Normalize</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Normalize</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Normalize" scales brightness values across the active layer so that
      the darkest point becomes black, and the brightest point becomes
      as bright as possible without altering its hue.  This is often a
      "magic fix" for images that are dim or washed out.  Normalize
      works on layers from RGB, Grayscale, and Indexed images.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='plug-in-c-astretch'>
    <title lang='en'>Stretch Contrast</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Stretch Contrast</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Stretch Contrast" is somewhat similar to Normalize in its
      effects, except that it works on each color channel of the layer
      individually, rather than just the brightness values.  This
      usually leads to color shifts within the image, so it may not
      produce the result you are looking for.  Stretch Contrast
      operates on layers from RGB, Grayscale, and Indexed images.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='plug-in-autostretch-hsv'>
    <title lang='en'>Stretch HSV</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Stretch HSV</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Stretch HSV" does the same thing as "Stretch Contrast", except
      that it works in HSV color space rather than RGB color space.
      Thus, it independently stretches the hue channel, the saturation
      channel, and the value channel.  Occasionally the results are
      good, often they are a bit odd.  Stretch HSV operates on layers
      from RGB and Indexed images.  If the image is Grayscale, the
      menu entry will be insensitive.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
