<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-04 added 'no' by KoSt
  2006-08-26 lexa: fixed docbook errors
  yyyy-mm-tt n.n.: added section for context menu
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-menus-introduction" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="en;de;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-17</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-20</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-05</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-06</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <!-- FIXME: cs zh_CN headline translation missing -->
    <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">
      Introduction to Menus
    </phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Einführung in die GIMP-Menüs</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Les menus de GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">
      Introduzione ai menu di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    </phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Menyane i <acronym>GIMP</acronym></phrase>
    </title>

  <indexterm lang="en;fr">
    <primary>Menus</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Menu</primary>
    <secondary>Introduzione</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Meny</primary>
    <secondary>Innleiing</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">The Toolbox Menu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Die Menüleiste im Werkzeugfenster</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Le menu de la Boîte à outils</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">I menu della barra degli strumenti</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Menyen for verktøyskrinet</phrase>
      </title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/cs/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-menu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>


  <para lang="en">
    There are many places in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> where you can
    find menus. The aim of this chapter is to explain all the commands that
    are accessible from the menus in the Toolbox and Image windows. All the
    context menus and the menu entries for the other dialogs are described
    elsewhere in the chapters that describe the dialogs themselves.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> finden Sie an verschiedensten Stellen
    Menüs. In diesem Kapitel werden die Menüeinträge des Werkzeug- sowie
    des Bildfensters beschrieben. Die in GIMP ebenfalls häufig vorhandenen
    Kontextmenüs werden dort beschrieben, wo auch der entsprechende Kontext,
    also beispielsweise der Dialog, beschrieben ist.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Vous trouverez plusieurs menus dans GIMP. Le but de ce chapitre est de
    vous expliquer les commandes disponibles à partir de la Boîte à outils et
    de la fenêtre d'image. Les autres menus et entrées de menus sont décrites
    dans le chapitre décrivant chaque fenêtre de dialogue.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    I menu in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sono presenti un po' ovunque;
    lo scopo di questo capitolo è di spiegare tutti i comandi accessibili
    dai menu della barra degli strumenti e dalla finestra immagine. Tutti
    gli altri menu contestuali e le voci di menu corrispondenti, sono
    descritti nei capitoli dedicati alle finestre relative.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Du finn menyar mange stader i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Føremålet
    med dette kapitlet er å forklara alle kommandoane som er tilgjengelege
    frå menyane i verktøyskrinet og frå biletvindauga. Dei andre menyane
    blir forklarte under omtalar av dei respektive dialogane.
  </para>


  <sect2 lang="de;en;fr;it;no" id="context-menus">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Context Menus</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Kontextmenüs</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Menus contextuels</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">I menu contestuali</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Lokalmeny</phrase>
      </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Context menus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Kontextmenüs</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Menus contextuels</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it">
      <primary>I menu contestuali</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Lokalmeny</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Kontekstmeny = Lokalmeny</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      If you right-click on certain parts of the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> interface, a
      <quote>context menu</quote> opens, which leads to a variety of
      functions. Some places where you can access context menus are:
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      In vielen Teilen der Applikation lässt sich ein Kontextmenü durch
      einen Rechtsklick mit der Maus anzeigen. Diese Menüs sind - wie
      der Name schon sagt - abhängig von dem jeweiligen Bereich in der
      Applikation und ausgestattet mit unterschiedlichen Funktionen.
      Einige dieser Bereiche, wo ein Kontextmenü zur Verfügung steht,
      sind folgende:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Sur certains éléments de l'interface GIMP, le clic droit
      ouvre un <quote>menu contextuel</quote>, encore appelé
      <quote>menu local</quote>, donnant accès à diverses fonctions :
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se si esegue un clic con il tasto destro del mouse in certe parti
      dell'interfaccia di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, si apre un
      <quote>menu contestale</quote>, che conduce ad una moltitudine di
      funzioni. Alcune posizioni dalle quali è possibile raggiungere dei
      menu contestuali sono:
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Mange stader i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan du få fram ein
      lokalmeny ved å høgreklikka. Noen av desse plassane er:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Clicking on an image window displays the Image menu. This is useful
          when you are working in full-screen mode, without a menubar.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Im <link
          linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Bildfenster</link> wird
          das Bildmenü angezeigt. Wenn Sie im Vollbildmodus arbeiten und
          kein Bildmenü angezeigt bekommen, können sie das Menü somit
          über einen rechten Mausklick anzeigen lassen.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Sur les fenêtres d'image : l'ensemble des entrées du menu d'image. Ce
          qui peut être utile si vous travaillez en mode plein écran, sans
          barre de menus.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Facendo clic su di una finestra immagine si mette in mostra il
          menu immagine. Quest'operazione è utile quando si sta lavorando
          in modalità a pieno schermo, senza la barra dei menu.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          I <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">biletvindauget</link>
          for å få fram biletmenyen. Dette kan vere nyttig når du arbeider
          på full skjerm utan synleg biletmeny.
        </para>
        </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Clicking on a layer in the Layers Dialog or on a channel in the
          Channels Dialog displays functions for the selected layer or
          channel.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Im <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Ebenen-</link> oder <link
          linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">Kanaldialog</link> werden
          jeweils Funktionen zum Verändern oder Verwalten der jeweiligen
          Ebene oder Kanals angezeigt.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Sur un des bandeaux du Dialogue des calques et du Dialogue des
          canaux : les fonctions de gestion des calques et des canaux.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Facendo clic su un livello nella finestra di dialogo dei livelli
          o su un canale nella finestra di dialogo dei canali, si mette in
          evidenza le funzioni disponibili per il livello o per il canale
          selezionato.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          I <!--PENDING:no <link
          linkend="gimp-layer-dialog"-->Lagdialogen<!--/link--> og
          <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">Kanaldialogen</link> for
          å henta fram funksjonane til eit bestemt lag eller ein bestemt
          kanal.
        </para>
        </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Right-clicking on the image menubar has the same effect as
          left-clicking.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Rechtsklick im Bildmenü hat den gleichen Effekt wie ein
          Linksklick, nämlich das Auswählen des jeweiligen Menüpunktes.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Sur la barre de menus : le clic droit a la même action que le clic
          gauche.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Facendo clic destro sulla barra del menu immagine ha lo stesso
          effetto che fare clic con il tasto sinistro del mouse.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Høgreklikk på biletmenyen har same effekt som venstreklikk.
        </para>
        </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Right-clicking on the title bar displays functions which do not
          belong to <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
          but to the window manager program on your computer.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Mit einem Rechtsklick auf die Titelzeile eines der
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Fenster wird Ihnen das
          Kontextmenü des in Verwendung befindlichen Fenstermanagers
          angezeigt.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Sur la barre de titre : les fonctions développées n'appartiennent pas
          à GIMP mais au programme de gestion d'interface de votre système.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Facendo clic destro sulla barra del titolo vengono mostrate
          funzioni che non appartengono all'applicazione
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, ma che fanno parte dei comandi
          comuni forniti dal gestore delle finestre attualmente in uso
          (per esempio GNOME, KDE o Explorer).
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Høgreklikk på tittellinja vil vise funksjonar som ikkje tilhøyrer
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, men kjem frå
          biletbehandlaren i datamaskinen din.
        </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 lang="de;en;fr;it;no" id="detachable-submenus">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Detachable Submenus</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Abtrennbare Menüs</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Sous-menus détachables</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">I sottomenu staccabili</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Frittståande undermenyar</phrase>
      </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Detachable submenus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Tear-off line</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Abtrennbare Menüs</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Sous-menus détachables</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Ligne de détachement</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it">
      <primary>Sottomenu staccabili</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Frittståande undermenyar</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      There is an interesting property associated with some of the menus in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      These are any of the menus from the Toolbox menubar and any of their
      submenus, as well as the Image context menu you get by right-clicking on
      the image window and any of its submenus. (You can tell that a menu item
      leads to a submenu because there is an
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/icon-submenu.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      icon next to it.) When you bring up any of these menus, there is a
      dotted line at the top of it (tear-off line). By clicking on this
      dotted line, you detach the menu under it and it becomes a separate window.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Einige Menüs bieten die Möglichkeit, sich vom Menüpunkt trennen zu
      lassen und in einem eigenständigen Fenster angezeigt zu werden.
      Dazu gehören alle Untermenüs des Bildmenüs und Menüs, die im
      Werkzeugfenster angezeigt werden. Ein Untermenü erkennen Sie an dem
      Symbol
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/icon-submenu.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      rechts vom Menüeintrag. Wenn Sie solch ein Menü öffnen, sehen Sie
      oben eine gestrichelte Linie. Durch einen linken Mausklick auf diese
      Linie trennen Sie das Untermenü. Es wird Ihnen dann als eigenständiges
      Fenster angezeigt.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Les sous-menus du menu d'image obtenu par clic droit (ainsi que ce
      même menu d'image) et ceux du menu de la Boîte à outils, auxquels vous
      accédez en cliquant sur
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/icon-submenu.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>,
      ont une propriété intéressante. Ils possèdent en haut de leur fenêtre
      une ligne de pointillés, la <emphasis>ligne de détachement</emphasis>.
      Si vous cliquez sur cette ligne, le sous-menu se transforme en fenêtre
      séparée que vous pouvez déplacer et garder à votre disposition.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      C'è una proprietà interessante associata ad alcuni menu di
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Essa riguarda qualsiasi menu o
      sottomenu appartenente alla barra del menu del pannello degli
      strumenti e i menu o sottomenu contestuali all'immagine, cioè
      ottenibili con il clic destro del mouse sulla finestra immagine (si
      può capire se una voce di menu porta da un sottomenu quando c'è
      un'icona
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/icon-submenu.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      accanto ad essa). Quando si porta in primo piano uno di questi menu,
      c'è una linea tratteggiata in cima ad esso. Facendo clic su questa
      linea, è possibile staccare il menu presente sotto di essa
      trasformandolo in una finestra separata.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      I noen av menyane i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er det lagt inn
      ein interessant eigenskap. Dette gjeld hovudmenyen i verktøyskrinet
      og lokalmenyen som sprett opp når du høgreklikkar på biletvindauget
      og alle undermenyane i denne. (At ein meny inneheld undermenyar
      blir vist med symbolet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/icon-submenu.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      ).  Alle desse menyane har ei prikkelinje øvst. Når du klikkar på denne
      linja, vil menyen bli vist i eit separat, sjølvstendig vindauge.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Acquire</quote> submenu and its detached submenu
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Untermenü <quote>Holen</quote> und das zugehörige
          abgetrennte Untermenü.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Le sous-menu Acquisition et son Sous-menu détaché
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Il sottomenu <quote>Acquisizione</quote> e la sua versione staccata
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Undermenyen <quote>Hent</quote> og den frittståande Hent-menyen
        </phrase>
        </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="de;en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/acquire.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/file-acquire.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/it/acquire.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/acquire.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="de;en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/detached-submenu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/detached-submenu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/it/detached-submenu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/detached-submenu.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      Detached submenus originating from the Toolbox are only visible when the
      Toolbox is active. Detached submenus originating from the Image window
      are actually independent. They are always visible, their functions
      always apply to the current image, and they persist when all of the
      images are closed. You can close a detached submenu by clicking on the
      dotted line again or closing the window from the window manager on your
      computer (often by clicking on an X icon in the upper right corner of
      the window).
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Abgetrennte Untermenüs, die aus dem Menü des Werkzeugfensters
      stammen, werden nur angezeigt, wenn das Werkzeugfenster sichtbar
      ist. Hingegen sind vom Bildfenster abgetrennte Untermenüs immer
      sichtbar. Sie können abgetrennte Menüs durch Klicken auf die
      gestrichelte Linie schließen oder über das Schließensymbol des
      jeweiligen Fenstermanagers.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les sous-menus détachés issus de la Boîte à outils ne sont visibles que
      si la Boîte à outils est active. Les sous-menus détachés issus de la
      fenêtre d'image sont véritablement indépendants: visibles en permanence,
      leurs fonctions s'appliquent à l'image en cours et ils persistent en
      l'absence de toute image.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      I sottomenu staccati originari dal pannello degli strumenti sono
      visibili solo quando il pannello degli strumenti è attivo. I
      sottomenu staccati che sono invece originati dalla finestra immagine
      sono indipendenti; sono sempre visibili, le loro funzioni si
      applicano sempre all'immagine corrente e sono persistenti anche
      quando tutte le immagini sono chiuse. Per chiudere un sottomenu
      staccato basta fare clic nuovamente sulla linea tratteggiata o
      chiudere la finestra usando la gestione delle finestre dell'ambiente
      grafico corrente (spesso facendo clic su un'icona a forma di X
      presente nell'angolo in alto a destra della finestra).
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Frittståande undermenyar som har utspring frå verktøyskrinet er bare
      synlege når verktøyskrinet er aktivt. Dei som kjem frå biletvindauget
      er derimot uavhengige, er alltid synlege og alltid knytt til det aktive
      vindauget. Dei blir ståande sjølv om alle biletvindauga blir lukka.
      Du kan lukke menyvindauget ved å klikka på prikkelinja eller ved
      å bruke vindaugebehandlaren til datamaskinen. (Som oftast ved å
      klikke på X-en i øvre, høgre hjørne av vindauget).
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
