<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-imagewindow-menus-image' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Image</title>
  <title lang="fr">Image</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image menu image</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image menu image</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/menus/menus-image.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>

       <caption>
	 <para lang='en'>
	   Contents of the Image menu
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Image menu contains commands that use or affect the entire
    image in some way, not just the active layer or some other
    specific part of the image.
  </para>

  <simplesect id='gimp-image-crop'>
    <title lang='en'>Crop Image</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Crop Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Crop Image" crops the image to the selection bounds, by
      removing any strips at the edges whose contents are all
      completely unselected.  Areas that are partially selected (for
      example, by feathering) are not cropped away.  If no selection
      exists for the image, the menu entry will be insensitive.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='plug-in-autocrop'>
    <title lang='en'>Autocrop Image</title>
    <title lang="fr">Découpage automatique</title> 

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Autocrop Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Autocrop Image" removes borders from an image.  It searches the
      active layer for the largest possible border area that all has
      the same color, and then crops this area from the image, just as
      though you had used the Crop tool.
    </para>
    <caution lang='en'>
      Note carefully that this command only uses the <emphasis>active
      layer</emphasis> of the image to find borders.  If other layers
      have color variations extending into the border zone of the
      active layer, they will be cropped away.
    </caution>

    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette fonction automatise le Découpage de l'image, à la différence 
      de <link linkend='gimp-tool-crop'>l'outil Découpage</link> qui
      vous permet de définir manuellement la zone à découper.  
    </para> 
    <para lang='fr'> 
      Elle est en fait à réserver au cas où vous avez un sujet perdu 
      dans un fond uni trop grand: la nouvelle image sera recadrée aux 
      dimensions du sujet. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Dans les autres cas, le résultat risque d'être aléatoire. En 
      particulier, si votre image a plusieurs calques, le découpage se 
      basera sur le calque actif et appliquera les mêmes dimensions aux 
      autres calques, ce qui peut occasionner d'importantes pertes 
      d'informations. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Merge Visible Layers</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Fusionner les calques visibles</title>
    <title lang='de'>Sichtbare Ebenen vereinen</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Merge Visible Layers</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Merge Visible Layers" merges all layers of the image for which
      an "eye" symbol is shown in the Layers dialog
      into a single layer, leaving non-visible layers untouched.  It
      is useful for merging a set of layers that may be scattered
      around the layer list.  Selecting it brings up a dialog that
      asks you to choose between three options for the size of the
      final, merged layer:  "Expanded as necessary" means that it
      will be made as small as possible without losing any of the
      contents of the merged layers; "Clipped to image" means it
      will be set to the size of the image and any layer contents
      outside the image bounds will be lost; and "Clipped to bottom
      layer" means what it says.
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      <guilabel>Fusionner les calques visibles</guilabel> :
      permet de fusionner les calques visibles, ceux qui sont
      marqués par l'icone en forme d'oeil.  Un dialogue s'ouvre.
      L'option <guilabel>Étendu autant que nécessaire</guilabel>
      permet de conserver des données dans des calques de taille
      supérieures à celle du canevas. L'option <guilabel>Rogné à
      la taille de l'image </guilabel> permet de retailler la
      taille du calque final à celle du canevas l'image, l'option
      <guilabel>Rogné à la taille du calque le plus bas
      </guilabel> permet de ne conserver que les données
      contenues dans les limites du calque le
      plus bas. 
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      <guilabel>Sichtbare <accel>E</accel>benen vereinen</guilabel>:
      vereinigt alle sichtbaren Ebenen, gekennzeichnet durch ein
      Augensymbol, zu einer Hintergrundebene. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Flatten Image</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Aplatir l'image</title>
    <title lang='de'>Bild zusammefügen</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Flatten Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>   
      "Flatten Image" causes all of the layers of the image to be merged
      into a single layer with no alpha channel, with the same
      appearance as the full image viewed from the top.  If there are
      any areas with transparency all the way through to the bottom of
      the layer stack, they are mixed with the image's background
      color. This operation is performed as part of the process of
      exporting an image, if you save it in a format that does not
      support layers.
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      <guilabel>Aplatir l'image</guilabel> :
      permet de fusionner l'ensemble des calques dans un
      calque unique.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      <guilabel>Bild <accel>z</accel>usammefügen:</guilabel>:
      vereinigt alle Ebenen zu einer Hintergrundebene.
    </para>
  </simplesect>


  <xi:include href="image-mode.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-transform.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-canvas-size.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-scale.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-duplicate.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-merge-vlayers.xml" />
  <xi:include href="image-flatten-image.xml" />    
  <xi:include href="image-configure-grid.xml" />
</sect1>
