<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-view-new_view' lang='en;fr;zh_CN'>
  <title lang="en">New View</title>
  <title lang="fr">Nouvelle vue</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">新建视图</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">New View</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Nouvelle vue</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">新建视图</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para lang='en'>
    This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>View</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ew View</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    "New View" creates a new image window for the current image,
    which you can set up differently than the existing display.  You
    can create multiple displays of any image:  only the zoom level
    and other viewing options can differ, though.  Any other changes
    made in one view are reflected in any other displays that show
    the same image.  One common use for multiple views is if you are
    working on individual pixels, at a high zoom level:  it may be
    useful for you to see at the same time the effects of your
    changes on the image as it would normally be viewed.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You can delete a new view by closing the window it creates.
    Closing the last remaining display for an image will cause the
    image itself to be closed, but if this would lead to any loss of
    data, you will be asked to confirm that you really want to do
    it.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette commande se trouve dans 
    <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Affichage/<accel>N</accel>ouvelle vue</guimenuitem>.
  </para>     
  <para lang='fr'>
    Elle crée une nouvelle fenêtre d'image, identique à la première. 
    Vous pouvez créer ainsi plusieurs répliques de l'image, numérotées 
    .1, .2, ...etc). 
    Seules les fonctions de zoom et d'affichage seront indépendantes 
    de la première vue; toutes les autres fonctions verront leur effet 
    répercuté sur les autres vues.  
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette fonction sert surtout quand vous travaillez au niveau du 
    pixel. Vous pouvez ainsi voir en temps réel ce que donne votre 
    travail en taille normale.
  </para>
  <note lang='fr'>
    <para>
     Cette nouvelle vue ne constitue pas un fichier séparé, ce n'est
     qu'un aspect différent du même fichier.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该命令在图像菜单的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>查看</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>新建视图</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “新建视图”新建一个当前图像的图像窗口。可以对任何图像创建多个显示：虽然只是缩放等级和其它查看选项不同。对其中一个视图的任何变动都会反应到相同图像的其它视图上。一个使用多个视图的常见用法就是，当您在高缩放等级下对单个像素进行处理时，
可以多开几个视图来观察您所作的变动。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    关闭新建的窗口时就删除了新建视图。当图像的最后一个视图被关闭时，图像自身也就关闭了。不过如果这样会造成数据损失的话，您就会被询问是否确认要这么做。
  </para> 
</sect2>
