<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
  
<sect2 id='gimp-view-zoom' lang='cs;en;fr;zh_CN'>
  <title lang="cs">Přiblížení</title>
  <title lang="en">Zoom</title>
  <title lang="fr">Zoom</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">缩放</title>

  <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-out' />
  <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-in' />
  <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-100' />
  <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-fit' />
  <anchor id='gimp-view-zoom-other' />

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">Přiblížení</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Zoom</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Zoom</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">缩放</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure lang="cs;en;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/menus/menus-view-zoom.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/menus/zh_CN/menus-view-zoom.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <caption>
         <para lang='cs'>
           Podnabídka Přiblížení nabídky Zobrazení
         </para>
         <para lang='en'>
           The Zoom submenu of the View menu
         </para>
         <para lang="zh_CN">
           查看菜单的缩放子菜单
         </para>
       </caption>
     </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <informalfigure lang="fr">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/menus/fr/menus-view-zoom.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='fr'>
         Le sous-menu Zoom du menu Affichage
       </para>
     </caption>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Příkazy pro změnu přiblížení obrázku jsou dostupné v podabídce
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Zobrazení</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Přiblížení</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice> nabídky obrázku.
    V Gimpu 2.2 jsou příkazy pro změnu přiblížení dostupné pomocí
    <link linkend='gimp-image-window-zoom'>tlačítka Přiblížení</link>
    v okně obrázku. Přiblížení znamená zvětšení (nebo zmenšení) pohledu na
    obrázek (jako při použití fotografického objektivu vybaveného funkcí
    zoom). Jedná se skutečně o pouhou změnu pohledu na obrázek, samotná
    obrazová data se nijak nemění (proto se změna přiblížení ani nezapisuje
    do historie změn a nelze pomocí ji vrátit pomocí funkce zpět). Přiblížení
    obrázku je vhodné pro pečlivou práci na úrovni jednotlivých pixelů,
    oddálení obrázku může být naopak vhodné pro získání celkového přehledu
    o velikém obrázku, který se při zvětšení 1:1 nevejde celý do svého okna.
  </para> 
  <para lang='en'>
    The "Zoom" commands can be accessed from an image menubar,
    in the submenu
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>View</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Zoom</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice>.
    In GIMP 2.2, you can also zoom an image using the <link
    linkend='gimp-image-window-zoom'>Zoom button</link> on the
    image window.
    Zooming means changing the magnification level of the
    image. Zooming in to an image is useful for pixel-level image  
    modifications, and zooming out can be handy for working with 
    broad effects.  Note that zooming is not undoable, because it
    does not affect the image data, only the way it is displayed.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    On accède à la commande de zoom à partir de tout menu d'image, en 
    suivant 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Affichage</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Zoom</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice>.
    Vous pouvez aussi y accéder, depuis Gimp-2.2, par le <link
    linkend='gimp-image-window-zoom'>Bouton de zoom</link> de la fenêtre 
    d'image.
  </para> 
  <para lang='fr'>
    Le zoom agrandit ou réduit l'affichage de l'image, mais ne change rien 
    à sa taille réelle. Il est très utile pour travailler au niveau du pixel 
    ou pour faire une sélection précise.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “缩放”命令在图像菜单的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>查看</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>缩放</guisubmenu>
    </menuchoice>。GIMP 2.2， 也可以用图像窗口中的<link linkend='gimp-image-window-zoom'>缩放按钮</link>缩放图像。“缩放”意谓着改变图像的放大率，它在像素级修改图像时非常有用，而“缩小”在大局上操作图像时比较实用。需要注意的是“缩放”是不可撤销的，因为它只是改变图像显示方式，而不会影响图像数据。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Dostupné příkazy pro změnu přiblížení a jejich výchozí klávesové zkratky
    jsou následující:
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Here are the available Zoom commands, along with their default
    keyboard shortcuts if any:
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Voici les différentes commandes de zoom disponibles, avec leur 
    raccourci-clavier par défaut.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    下面是些可用的缩放命令及其默认快捷键。
  </para>
  
  <variablelist lang='en'>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Zoom Out</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      (Shortcut: <keycap>-</keycap>)  Each time "Zoom Out" is 
      used, the zoom factor is decreased by about 30%.  There is a
      minimum zoom level of 6%.
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Zoom In</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      (Shortcut: <keycap>+</keycap>)
      Each time Zoom In is used, the zoom level is increased by a
      factor of around 30%.  The maximum possible zoom level is
      1600%.
      </para>  
    <note>
      <para>
        The keyboard shortcut for "Zoom In" has been a subject of some
        controversy, because this is a very commonly used operation, and
        on English keyboards it requires the Shift key to be pressed.
        (For European keyboards, it does not.)  If you would like to have
        an easier shortcut, you can create a dynamic shortcut for it; see
        the help section for <link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>User
        Interface</link> Preferences for instructions.
      </para>
    </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Fit Image in Window</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          (Shortcut:
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>E</keycap>
          </keycombo>).
          This command zooms the image as large as possible while still
          keeping it completely within the window.  Padding will
          probably show on two sides of the image, but not on all four
          sides.
        </para>  
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Fit Image to Window</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This command zooms the image as small as possible without
          requiring any padding to be shown:  it causes the image to fit
          the window perfectly in one dimension, and extend beyond the
          window borders in the other dimension.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>A:B</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Here you have a series of menu entries for specific zoom levels,
          including, most importantly, the 100% zoom level, which has a
          simple keyboard shortcut: <keycap>1</keycap>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Other</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This command brings up a dialog that allows you to choose any
          zoom level you want, within the allowed limits of 6% to 1600%.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <tip lang='en'>  <!--Added 050606-->
    <para>
      When you are working at a pixel level , use the 
      <link linkend='gimp-view-new'>New view</link> command.
    </para>
    <para>
      See also <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigation Dialog
      </link>.
    </para>
  </tip>   
  
  <variablelist lang='cs'>
  
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Oddálit</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      (Zkratka: <keycap>-</keycap>)
      Každým použitím tohoto příkazu se stupeň přiblížení
      sníží o přibližně 30%. Minimální přiblížení je 6%.
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Přiblížit</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      (Zkratka: <keycap>+</keycap>)
      Každým použitím tohoto příkazu se stupeň přiblížení zvýší o přibližně
      30%. Maximální přiblížení je 1600%.
      </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Klávesová zkratka pro příkaz Přiblížit vyvolala rozsáhlé diskuse,
        protože na angloamerických klávesnicích vyžaduje stisknutí klávesy
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>, což u tak často používané funkce není
        příjemné. V případě kontinentálních evropských klávesnic (tedy i
        české) tento problém není. Pokud používáte americkou klávesnici a
        chcete pro přiblížení používat jednoklávesovou zkratku, vytvořte
        si pro funkci Přiblížit vlastní dynamickou klávesovou zkratku.
        Více se dozvíte v části věnované předvolbám pro <!--<link
        linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>-->uživatelské rozhraní<!--</link>-->.
      </para>
    </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Celý obrázek do okna</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          (Zkratka:
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>E</keycap>
          </keycombo>).
          Tento příkaz přiblíží obrázek co nejvíce, ale tak, aby se stále celý
          vešel do okna. Na dvou stranách se tak pravděpodobně objeví
          nevyužité místo, ale další dvě strany budou přesně využívat prostor
          v okně.
        </para>  
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Fit Image to Window</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tento příkaz zmenší obrázek jak je to jen možné, aniž by se v okně
          objevil nevyužitý prostor. Obrázek tak v jednom směru do okna přesně
          pasuje, v duhém směru okno pravděpodobně bude přesahovat.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>A:B (X%)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Řada položek s různými stupni přiblížení obrázku. Nejdůležitější je
          samozřejmě přiblížení 1:1 (100%), které má jednoduchou klávesovou
          zkratku: <keycap>1</keycap> <!-- some comment as in + in US to be
          added -->
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Jiné</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tento příkaz otevře dialog umožňující zadat libovolný stupeň
          přiblížení v rozsahu 6-1600 %.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist lang='fr'>
  
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Zoom Arrière</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      (Raccourci: <keycap>-</keycap>)  Chaque fois que «Zoom arrière» est 
      utilisé, le facteur de zoom est diminué d'environ 30%, le minimum 
      étant de 6%. 
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Zoom Avant</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      (Raccourci: <keycap>+</keycap>; il s'agit du signe «+» obtenu avec la 
      touche Majuscule et non pas de celui du pavé numérique). Chaque fois 
      que le «Zoom avant» est utilisé, le facteur de zoom est augmenté 
      d'environ 30%, le maximum étant 1600%. 
      </para>  
    <note>
      <para>
        Si ce raccourci ne vous convient pas, vous pouvez créer un 
        raccourci dynamique. Voyez l'aide des Préférences à la rubrique 
        <link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Interface utilisateur</link>. 
      </para>
    </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Ajuster l'image dans la fenêtre</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          (Raccourci:
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>E</keycap>
          </keycombo>). 
          Cette commande agrandit l'affichage de l'image le plus possible 
          sans la couper. Il y aura probablement un remplissage sur deux 
          côtés, mais pas sur les quatre côtés. 
        </para>  
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Ajuster l'image à la fenêtre</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Cette commande réduit l'affichage de l'image le plus possible sans 
          avoir à faire du remplissage: l'image s'adaptera parfaitement à la 
          taille de la fenêtre dans une dimension et débordera les limites 
          de la fenêtre dans l'autre dimension. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>A:B</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Vous avez là une série d'entrées pour des niveaux de zoom 
          particuliers, et surtout le niveau 100% qui est le seul à avoir 
          un raccourci: <keycap>1</keycap> (NdT:qui ne semble pas 
          fonctionner). 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Autre</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          cette commande fait apparaître une fenêtre de dialogue qui vous 
          permet de saisir le niveau de zoom que vous voulez, dans la limite 
          des 6%-1600%. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>  
  <tip lang='fr'>
    <para>
      Quand vous travaillez au niveau du pixel, utilisez la fonction  
      <link linkend='gimp-view-new'>Nouvelle vue</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Voir aussi <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Dialogue de 
      navigation</link>.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <variablelist lang="zh_CN">
    <varlistentry>
      <term>缩小</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          (快捷键：<keycap>-</keycap>) 每次使用“缩小”时，缩放比率都减少 30% 左右，最小能缩到 6%。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>    
      <term>放大</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          (快捷键：<keycap>+</keycap>) 每次使用“放大”时，缩放比率都增加 30 % 左右，最大能放到 1600%。
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            “放大”的快捷键一直有许多争议，因为它非常常用，但在英语键盘上需要按 Shift 键。(对欧洲键盘则不需要。)如果您想要更简单的快捷键，可用给它创建一个动态快捷键。创建的步骤请看<link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>用户界面</link>首选项这一节。
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>匹配窗口</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          (快捷键：<keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>E</keycap>
          </keycombo>)。该命令在保证图像在窗口内的情况下，尽量扩大图像。图像的两边可能有画布衬垫，不过不会出现四边都有的情况。
        </para>  
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>匹配窗口</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          该命令尽量缩小图像，而不需要显示任何画布衬垫：它使图像在一个方向上和窗口完美结合，而在另一个方向上超出窗口边界。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>A:B</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          这里是一组指定的缩放等级，包括最重要的 100% 缩放率，其快捷键是：<keycap>1</keycap>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>其它</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          该命令会唤出一个对话框，其中让您在 6% 到 1600% 间选择任何缩放等级。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
