<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2005/10/24 reviewed; de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-view-new" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-10</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-10-24</date>
        <authorinitials>a.w</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-01-30</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-15</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">New View</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Neue Ansicht</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Nový pohled</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Nouvelle vue</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Nuova vista</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Ny visning</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">新建视图</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>New View</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Nový pohled</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Neue Ansicht</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Nouvelle vue</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Nuova vista</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Vismenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Ny visning</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Ny visning</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>新建视图</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>New View</guimenuitem> command creates a new image
    window for the current image, which you can set up differently from
    the existing display. You can create multiple views of any image, which
    are numbered .1, .2, etc., but only the zoom factor and other viewing
    options may be different. Any changes, other than viewing changes,
    which you make in one window also appear in the other displays which
    show the same image. The new views are not separate image files; they
    are simply different aspects of the same image. You might use multiple
    views, for example, if you were working on individual pixels at a high
    zoom factor. You could then see the effects your changes would have on
    the image at a normal size.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    You can delete a view by closing its window. If you close the last
    window displaying an image, the image itself is closed. However, if
    you have made changes to the image which you have not yet saved, you
    are asked for confirmation.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Příkaz Nový pohled vytvoří nové okno obrázku zobrazující aktuální obrázek.
    Stávající okno zůstane zachováno. Obrázek tak může být zobrazen ve více
    oknech, z nichž každé může být jinak nastaveno – v každém může být
    například jiný stupeň přiblížení nebo se mohou lišit v jakémkoliv jiném
    parametru zobrazení. Obsah okna, obrázek, je však společný, a změna
    obrázku v jednom okně se ihned projeví i v dalších oknech zobrazujících
    stejný obrázek. Užitečné je to například při práci s jednotlivými pixely
    při velkém přiblížení – další pohled lze využít k celkovému pohledu na
    obrázek a pozorování změn „s nadhledem“, aniž by bylo nutno neustále měnit
    stupeň přiblížení v jednom okně.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Kterýkoliv pohled lze jednoduše zavřít zavřením okna. Zavřením posledního
    pohledu na určitý obrázek se zavře obrázek samotný. Pokud obrázek obsahuje
    neuložené změny, GIMP se samozřejmě dotáže, zda má být obrázek skutečně
    zavřen, případně, zda mají být změny v něm uloženy.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie für das aktuelle Bild eine neue
    Ansicht in einem neuen Bildfenster erzeugen. Mit der neuen Ansicht
    erzeugen Sie kein neues Bild, haben aber die Möglichkeit
    beispielsweise mit unterschiedlichen Vergrößerungsstufen auf ein
    Bild zu schauen. Alle Änderungen die Sie an dem Bild vornehmen,
    werden automatisch in allen weiteren Bildansichten dargestellt.
    Beispielsweise werden Änderungen die Sie in einer hohen
    Vergrößerungsstufe vornehmen anschaulicher, wenn sie diese in
    einer zweiten Ansicht bei <quote>normaler</quote> Vergrößerung
    verfolgen können.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Sie können eine Ansicht einfach durch schließen des entsprechenden
    Bildfensters entfernen. Das Schließen der letzten Ansicht eines Bildes
    schließt auch das Bild selbst. Sollten noch ungesicherte Änderungen
    im Bild existieren, werden Sie darauf hingewiesen und haben die
    Möglichkeit das Bild zu speichern.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande crée une nouvelle fenêtre d'image, identique à la première.
    Vous pouvez créer ainsi plusieurs répliques de l'image, numérotées
    .1, .2, ...etc).
    Seules les fonctions de zoom et d'affichage seront indépendantes
    de la première vue; toutes les autres fonctions que vous appliquerez
    verront leur effet répercuté sur les autres vues.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette fonction sert surtout quand vous travaillez au niveau du
    pixel. Vous pouvez ainsi voir en temps réel ce que donne votre
    travail en taille normale.
  </para>
  <note lang="fr">
    <para>
     Cette nouvelle vue ne constitue pas un fichier séparé, ce n'est
     qu'un aspect différent du même fichier.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Nuova vista</guimenuitem> crea una nuova
    finestra immagine dell'immagine corrente, configurabile diversamente
    dalla prima. È così possibile creare viste multiple di una stessa
    immagine, numerate .1, .2, ecc, ma che sono differenziate solo da
    alcune opzioni come il fattore di zoom. Qualsiasi modifica, a parte le
    opzioni di visualizzazione, che viene applicaca all'immagine da una
    finestra, apparirà anche nell'altra, dato che essa è solo un'altra
    vista della stessa immagine. È comodo usare le viste multiple, per
    esempio, se si sta lavorando su singoli pixel ad un alto rapporto di
    zoom. In questo modo si possono osservare in tempo reale come le
    modifiche modificano l'aspetto dell'immagine al fattore di zoom
    normale.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Per cancellare una vista basta chiudere la finestra corrispondente. Se
    si chiude l'ultima finestra di una determinata immagine, il file
    corrispondente viene chiuso.Se si è effettuato qualche cambiamento non
    ancora salvato all'immagine, quest'ultima chiusura produrrà una
    richiesta di conferma.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Ny visning</guimenuitem> oppretter eit
    nytt biletvindauge med det aktive biletet i. Du kan lage fleire visningar
    av eit bilete. Kvar visning blir nummerert automatisk med .1, .2 osv i
    tillegg til biletnamnet. Desse bileta representerer ikkje nye biletfiler,
    men ulike framsyningar av den same fila. Alle endringar du gjer i eitt
    av bileta, vil også bli viste i dei andre vindauga. Det einaste som kan
    vere forskjellig i dei ulike vindauga, er korleis dei blir viste på
    skjermen. Denne kommandoen kan vere nyttig når du arbeider på
    pikselnivå og gjerne vil ha eit auge med korleis biletet ser ut i
    normal storleik.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Du kan fjerne desse vindauga ved å lukke dei. Dersom du lukker det
    siste opne vindauget, lukker du også biletet. Har du gjort endringar
    utan lagring, blir du åtvara på vanleg måte.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “新建视图”新建一个当前图像的图像窗口。可以对任何图像创建多个显示：虽然只
    是缩放等级和其它查看选项不同。对其中一个视图的任何变动都会反应到相同图像
    的其它视图上。一个使用多个视图的常见用法就是，当您在高缩放等级下对单个像
    素进行处理时，可以多开几个视图来观察您所作的变动。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    关闭新建的窗口时就删除了新建视图。当图像的最后一个视图被关闭时，图像自身
    也就关闭了。不过如果这样会造成数据损失的话，您就会被询问是否确认要这么做。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>V</accel>iew</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ew View</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz lze vyvolat z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Zobrazení</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Nový pohled</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>An<accel>s</accel>icht</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>eue Ansicht</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de tout menu d'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>A</accel>ffichage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ouvelle vue</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>V</accel>isualizza</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>uova vista</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Vis</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Ny visning</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>查看</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>新建视图</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
