<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-12-27 lexa: reviewed for color management enhancements
  2007-05-22 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-03-18 ude: Re-arranged color proof options
  2005-12-21 julien: Created en;fr; the "profile" section needs more information
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-display-filter-dialog" lang="de;en;es;fr;it;lt;no">
  <sect2info role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-27</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-27</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-05-22</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-12-21</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="it">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>yyy-mm-dd</date>
        <authorinitials>n.n.</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-14</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Display Filters</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Ansichtsfilter</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Mostrar filtros</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Filtres d'affichage</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Mostra filtri</phrase>
    <phrase lang="lt">Rodymo filtrai</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Vis filtra</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Color</primary><secondary>Color display</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Ansichtsfilter</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbmanagement</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Farbe</primary><secondary>Sehschwäche</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Ver</primary><secondary>Mostrar fitros</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Affichage</primary><secondary>Filtres d'affichage</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Couleur</primary><secondary>Affichage des couleurs</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Visualizza</primary><secondary>Mostra filtri</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Rodymas</primary>
    <secondary>Rodymo filtrai</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Vismenyen</primary><secondary>Filter</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The images you create, we hope, will be seen by many people on many
    different systems. The image which looks so wonderful on your screen may
    look somewhat different to people with sight deficiencies or on a screen
    with different settings from yours. Some information might not even be
    visible.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Ihre Bilder werden vermutlich von vielen Menschen unter
    verschiedenen Umständen auf einem Bildschirm betrachtet.
    Naturgegeben wird der Eindruck eines Bildes immer subjektiv
    ausfallen und vor allem hauptsächlich von einem Faktor abhängen: der
    Wahrnehmung durch das menschliche Auge. So unterschiedlich wie wir
    Menschen Farben in unserer Umgebung wahrnehmen, so unterschiedlich
    werden auch ihre Bilder am Bildschirm gesehen. Der
    Informationsgehalt ihres Bildes kann also variieren, vor allem bei
    Menschen mit <ulink
    url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farbenfehlsichtigkeit">Farbenfehlsichtigkeit</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Las imágenes que cree, esperamos, que las vean mucha gente en diferentes
    sistemas. La imagen se verá muy bien en su pantalla pero podría verse
    algo diferente en una pantalla con diferentes ajustes que los suyos.
    Puede que alguna peculiaridad no sea visible.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les images que vous créez seront, nous l'espérons, vues par de
    nombreuses personnes sur des systèmes différents. Il se peut donc que
    l'image qui paraît si belle chez vous soit vue de façon différente par
    les personnes ayant un défaut de vision, ou parce que
    le moniteur sur lequel elle est affichée a des réglages différents.
    Certaines informations pourraient même devenir invisibles.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Le immagini che creiamo, si spera, possono essere viste da tanta gente
    su molti sistemi differenti. L'immagine che sembra così bella sul
    proprio schermo, potrebbe apparire differente ad altra gente con
    difetti di vista o con uno schermo impostato in maniera differente dal
    nostro. Alcuni particolari potrebbero addirittura non essere visibili.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Mes tikimės, kad jūsų sukurtus paveikslėlius pamatys daug žmonių,
    naudojančių įvairias sistemas. Paveikslėlis, atrodantis nuostabiai
    jūsų ekrane, žmonėms, turintiems nejautrumo kai kurioms spalvoms negalią,
    arba ekrane, kurio parametrai skiriasi nuo jūsų ekrano, gali atrodyti
    šiek tiek kitaip. Kai kuri informacija gali būti netgi nematoma.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Bileta dine vil vonleg bli sett av mange ulike menneske på mange ulike
    datasystem. Biletet som ser heilt perfekt ut på skjermen din, kan sjå heilt
    anleis ut for folk med synsskader, eller på ein annan skjerm innstilt litt
    anleis enn den skjermen du bruker sjølv. Deler av informasjonen kan
    till og med vere usynleg.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Die <emphasis>Ansichtsfilter</emphasis> sollen Ihnen helfen, das
    Bild wie durch die Augen eines Menschen mit Farbfehlsichtigkeit
    wahrzunehmen. Diese Filter ändern nur die Art und Weise, wie Sie das
    Bild wahrnehmen, aber niemals die Bildinformation selbst.
    Deshalb können Sie eingestellte Filter nicht über
    <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>
    rückgängig machen. Sie müssen sie ebenso deaktivieren, wie
    sie aktiviert wurden.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    <emphasis>Display Filters</emphasis> allow you to view your image as if
    it were seen by people with a sight deficiency or on a different screen.
    Don't worry, the filters display the image in a different way, but they
    never change the image. Besides that, if you save the image that is
    displayed, the original image is saved. For the same reason, you can't
    undo the action of a filter with
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    <emphasis>Mostrar filtros</emphasis> le permite ver su imagen como si la
    viera en una pantalla diferente. No se peocupe, los filtros muestran la
    imagen de una manera difernte, pero no cambian la imagen. Además, si
    guarda la imagen mostrada, se guarda la imagen original. Por eso, no
    puede deshacer la acción de un filtro con
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les <emphasis>Filtres d'affichage</emphasis> vous permettent de
    visualiser votre image comme elle le serait sur un moniteur différent
    ou par une personne à vision déficiente. Comprenez bien, ces filtres
    vous présentent l'image d'une certaine façon, mais ne modifient en rien
    l'image. D'ailleurs, si vous enregistrez l'image ainsi présentée, c'est
    l'image d'origine que vous enregistrerez. Pour la même raison, il n'est
    pas possible d'annuler l'action du filtre par
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <emphasis>Mostra filtri</emphasis> permette di visualizzare
    la propria immagine come potrebbe essere vista da gente con difetti
    visivi o con uno schermo differente. Non temete, i filtri dello schermo
    fanno in modo di visualizzare l'immagine in modo diverso ma non la
    modificano affatto. Infatti, se si salva l'immagine così com'è
    rappresentata, viene comunque salvata l'immagine originale. Per la
    stessa ragione, non è possibile annullare un'azione su di un filtro con
    la scorciatoia
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>, dato che
    l'immagine non viene modificata.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    <emphasis>Rodymo filtrai</emphasis> leidžia peržiūrėti paveiklėlį
    lyg jis būtų matomas žmonių, turinčių nejautrumo spalvoms negalią, arba
    kitame ekrane. Nebijokite, šie filtrai rodo paveikslėlį kitokiu būdu,
    tačiau jie niekada nekeičia paveikslėlio. Be to, jeigu išsaugosite
    rodomą paveikslėlį, bus išsaugotas originalus paveikslėlis. Dėl tos
    pačios priežasties negalite atšaukti filtro veiksmo klavišų kombinacija
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <emphasis>Vis filtra</emphasis> gir deg høve til å sjå på
    bileta slik folk med synsfeil gjer det, eller slik dei blir viste på andre
    datasystem. Sjølve biletet blir ikkje forandra, bare visinga. Dersom du
    lagrar biletet som blir vist, er det originalbiletet som blir lagra. Difor
    kan du heller ikkje gjere om verknaden av filteret med angreknappen
    eller med
    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Nicht nur Filter zur Simulation von
    <quote>Farbfehlsichtigkeit</quote>, sondern auch
    <quote>Gamma</quote>, <quote>Kontrast</quote> <!-- GIMP 2.4
    <quote>Farbverwaltung</quote>--> und <quote>Farbandruck</quote>
    stehen zur Verfügung.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The filters available are called
    <quote>Color Deficient Vision</quote>, <quote>Gamma</quote>,
    <quote>Contrast</quote> and <quote>Color Proof</quote>:
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Los filtros disponibles se llaman:
    <quote>Color de visión deficiente</quote>, <quote>Gamma</quote>,
    <quote>Contraste</quote> y <quote>Color seguro</quote>:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les filtres disponibles concernent la vision des couleurs, le gamma, le
    contraste et la calibration des couleurs.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    I filtri disponibili si dividono in
    <quote>Visione con deficit di colore</quote>, <quote>Gamma</quote>,
    <quote>Contrasto</quote> e <quote>Prova di colore</quote>:
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Prieinami filtrai:
    <quote>Matymas su spalvų deficitu</quote>, <quote>Gama</quote>,
    <quote>Kontrastas</quote> ir <quote>Spalvų korekcija</quote>:
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Dei tilgjengelege filtra blir kalla
    <quote>For fargesvakt syn</quote>, <quote>Gamma</quote>,
    <quote>Kontrast</quote> og <quote>Fargeprøve</quote>:
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activer le Dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Komandos aktyvavimas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>An<accel>s</accel>icht</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Ansichts<accel>f</accel>ilter</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>V</accel>iew</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Display <accel>F</accel>ilters</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>V</accel>er</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mostrar <accel>f</accel>iltros</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande par le menu d'image en suivant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>A</accel>ffichage</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>iltres d'affichage</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>V</accel>isualizza</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mostra <accel>f</accel>iltri</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="lt">
          Šią komandą galite aktyvuoti paveikslėlio meniu juostoje:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>R</accel>odymas</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Rodymo <accel>f</accel>iltrai</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Vis</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Filtra</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Beschreibung des Ansichtsfilter-Dialogs
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">
        Description of the <quote>Display Filters</quote> Dialog
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        Descripción del diálogo <quote>Mostrar filtros</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Description de la fenêtre de dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Descrizione della finestra di dialogo <quote>Mostra filtri</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">
        Dialogo <quote>Rodymo filtrai</quote> aprašymas
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Beskriving av dialogen <quote>Vis filtra</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Der Ansichtsfilter-Dialog
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The <quote>Configure Color Display Filters</quote> dialog
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          El diálogo
        <quote>Configuración de los filtros de colores de la pantalla</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">La fenêtre Configurer les filtres d'affichage
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          La finestra <quote>Configura i filtri di colore a video</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">
          Dialogas <quote>Konfigūruoti spalvų rodymo filtrus</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Dialogen <quote>Konfigurer filter for fargevising</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/es/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="lt">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/lt/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/display-filters.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="de">
      Der Dialog zeichnet sich durch zwei Auswahlbereiche aus. Der linke
      Bereich zeigt die Filter, die zur Auswahl stehen, der rechte die, die
      aktuell auf das Bild angewendet werden und ausgewählt sind. Sie
      können Filter auswählen, indem sie den Namen im linken Bereich mit
      einem Mausklick auswählen. Aktiviert wird das Filter, indem sie
      mit einem zusätzlichen Mausklick auf den Pfeil, der nach rechts
      zeigt, klicken. Im unteren Bereich des Dialoges werden Optionen
      zu aktivierten Filtern angezeigt. Klicken Sie dazu im linken
      Bereich auf einen Filternamen, um sich die Optionen anzeigen zu
      lassen.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This dialog has two small selectboxes. The left selectbox displays the
      <guilabel>Available Filters</guilabel>. You can move a filter to the
      right selectbox by selecting it and clicking on the
      <guibutton>right arrow</guibutton> button. The
      <guilabel>Active Filters</guilabel> window on the right displays
      filters you have chosen and which will be applied if the adjacent box
      is checked. You can move filters from the right selectbox to the left
      selectbox by using the <guibutton>left arrow</guibutton> button. If you
      select a filter by clicking on its name, its options are displayed
      below the two selectboxes, in the
      <guilabel>Configure Selected Filter</guilabel> area.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Este diálogo tiene dos pequeñas cajas de selección. La caja de la
      izquierda muestra los <guilabel>Filtros disponibles</guilabel>. Puede
      mover un filtro a la caja de la derecha seleccionándolo y pulsando
      sobre el botón <guibutton>flecha derecha</guibutton>. La ventana de los
      <guilabel>Filtros activos</guilabel>, a la derecha, muestra los filtros
      que ha elegido y que se  aplicarán, si la caja adyacente está marcada.
      Puede mover los filtros de la caja de selección derecha a la izquierda
      usando el botón <guibutton>flecha izquierda</guibutton>. Si selecciona
      un filtro pulsando sobre su nombre, sus opciones se muestran en las
      cajas inferiores, en el área
      <guilabel>Configurar el filtro seleccioando</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cette fenêtre comporte deux petites fenêtres. Dans la fenêtre de
      gauche sont affichés les <guilabel>Filtres disponibles</guilabel>.
      Vous pouvez les faire passer dans la fenêtre de droite en les
      sélectionnant et en cliquant sur la flèche dirigée vers la droite.
      La fenêtre de droite, dite des <guilabel>Filtres actifs</guilabel>,
      comporte donc les filtres que vous aurez choisis et qui seront
      appliqués à l'image à condition que la case adjacente soit cochée.
      Vous pouvez aussi refaire passer les filtres dans la fenêtre de gauche
      grâce à la flèche dirigée vers la gauche. Quand vous cliquez sur le
      nom d'un filtre dans la fenêtre de droite, il est sélectionné et ses
      options s'affichent sous les deux fenêtres, sous la rubrique
      <guilabel>Configurer le filtre sélectionné</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questa finestra di dialogo possiede due piccole caselle di
      selezione. Quella di sinistra mostra i <guilabel>Filtri
      disponibili</guilabel>. Selezionando e facendo clic sul pulsanta a
      forma di <guibutton>freccia a destra</guibutton> si sposta un filtro
      sulla casella di destra. La finestra <guilabel>Filtri
      attivi</guilabel> sulla destra mostra i filtri che si è scelto e che
      verranno applicati se la casella adiacente viene spuntata. Per
      riportare i filtri dalla casella di destra a quella di sinistra basta
      usare il pulsante a forma di <guibutton>freccia a
      sinistra</guibutton>. Se si seleziona un filtro facendo clic sul suo
      nome, sotto le due caselle vengono mostrate le opzioni corrispondenti
      allo stesso filtro, nell'area di <guilabel>configurazione del filtro
      selezionato</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Šiame dialoge yra du maži pasirinkimo laukai. Kairiajame lauke rodomi
      <guilabel>Prieinami filtrai</guilabel>. Filtrą galite perkelti į
      dešinįjį pasirinkimo lauką jį pasirinkdami ir spustelėdami
      <guibutton>rodyklės į dešinę</guibutton> mygtuką. Dešinėje esančiame
      lauke <guilabel>Aktyvūs filtrai</guilabel> rodomi filtrai, kuriuos
      jūs pasirinkote ir kurie bus pritaikyti, jeigu pažymėta šalia esantis
      žymimasis langelis. Galiter perkelti filtrus iš dešinės į kairę
      naudodami <guibutton>rodyklės į kairę</guibutton> mygtuką. Jeigu
      pasirenkate filtrą spustelėdami jo pavadinimą, jo parinktys yra
      rodomos po dviem pasirinkimo laukais, srityje
      <guilabel>Konfigūruoti pasirinktą filtrą</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Denne dialogen har to tekstvindauge. Det til venstre viser
      <guilabel>Tilgjengelege filter</guilabel>. Du kan flytte eit filter frå
      dette vindauget og over til <guilabel>Aktive filter</guilabel> ved først
      å klikke på ønskt filter for å markere det, og deretter på pila som
      peikar mot høgre. Du kan flytte filtra andre vegen ved å bruke pila
      som peiker mot venstre. Filtra i vindauget <guilabel>Aktive
      filter</guilabel> blir aktiverte eller deaktiverte ved at du klikkar på
      det lille merket framføre filternamnet. Klikkar du på namnet til filteret,
      blir innstillingane for filteret vist nadanfor i området under
      <guilabel>Sett opp vald filter</guilabel>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-deficient-vision">
    <title>
      <!-- de: Farbenfehlsichtigkeit (fixed in GIMP 2.3.x) -->
      <phrase lang="de">Farbenblindheit</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Color Deficient Vision</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Color de visión deficiente</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Vision des couleurs déficiente</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Visione con deficit di colore</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Regėjimas su spalvų deficitu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">For fargesvakt syn</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Deficient vision</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Couleur</primary>
      <secondary>Vision déficiente</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="lt">
      <primary>Spalva</primary>
      <secondary>Regėjimas su trūkumais</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="de">
            Simulation von <quote>Farbenfehlsichtigkeit</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="en">
            Description of the <quote>Color Deficient Vision</quote> dialog
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="es">
            Descripción del diálogo <quote>Color de visión deficiente</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">
            La fenêtre de dialogue Vision des couleurs déficiente
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="it">
            Descrizione della finestra di dialogo <quote>Visione con
            deficit di colore</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="lt">
            Dialogo <quote>Matymas su spalvų deficitu</quote> aprašymas
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="no">
            Beskriving av dialogen <quote>For fargesvakt syn</quote>
          </phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject lang="en">
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-vision.png"
                      format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="de">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/display-filters-vision.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="es">
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/menus/es/display-filters-vision.png"
                      format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="fr">
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/menus/fr/display-filters-vision.png"
                      format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="it">
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-vision.png"
                      format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="lt">
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/menus/lt/display-filters-vision.png"
                      format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="no">
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/menus/no/display-filters-vision.png"
                      format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title>
        <!-- de: Art der Fehlsichtigkeit (Gimp 2.3.x) -->
        <phrase lang="de">Art der Sehschwäche</phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">Color Deficiency Type</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Tipo de deficiencia de color</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Type de déficience des couleurs</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Tipo di deficienza di colore</phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt">Spalvų deficito tipas</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Type fargesynssvikt</phrase>
      </title>

      <para lang="de">
        In diesem Auswahlmenü können sie zwischen folgenden
        Optionen wählen:
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In this drop-down menu you can select from among:
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        En este menú desplegable puede seleccionar entre:
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans cette liste déroulante, vous pouvez choisir entre :
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        In this drop-down menu you can select from among:
      </para>
      <para lang="lt">
        Šiame žemyn išskleidžiamame sąraše galite pasirinkti iš:
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        I denne nedtrekksmenyen kan du velje mellom:
      </para>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Protanopia (insensitivity to red)</term>
        <term lang="de">
          Protanopie<footnote><para>
            Aus griech.: <foreignphrase>proto</foreignphrase>: erste
            (RGB-Farbe); <foreignphrase>an</foreignphrase>: Negation;
            <foreignphrase>op</foreignphrase>: Auge, Sehfähigkeit.
          </para></footnote>
          (Rotblindheit)
        </term>
        <term lang="es">Protanopia (desviado al rojo)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Protanopie</term>
        <term lang="it">Protanopia (insensibilità al rosso)</term>
        <term lang="lt">Protanopija (nejautrumas raudonai)</term>
        <term lang="no">Protanopi (raudblind)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Protanopen können weder Rot noch Grün erkennen. Ihre Umwelt
            nehmen sie gelb-blau schattiert wahr.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Do not be afraid of this odd name. It is made up from three
            Greek roots: <quote>op</quote> for eye, vision; <quote>an</quote>
            for negation; <quote>proto</quote> for first, the first color in
            the <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">RGB Color System</link>.
            So, protanopia is a visual deficiency of the color red. It's the
            well-known daltonism (red-green color blindness).
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            No se deje intimidar por este extraño nombre. Viene de tres
            raices griegas:<quote>op</quote> para ojo, visión; <quote>an</quote>
            para negación; <quote>proto</quote> para el primero, el primer
            color del
            <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Sistema de color RGB</link>.
            Así que protanopia es una deficiencia visual del color rojo. Es
            el conocido daltonismo (cegera del rojo-verde).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce mot barbare ne doit pas vous effayer. Il est constitué de
            trois racines grecques : <quote>op</quote> pour œil, vision ;
            <quote>an</quote> pour la négation ; <quote>proto</quote> pour
            premier, c'est-à-dire la première couleur
            du <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">système de couleur RVB
            </link>. La protanopie est donc l'absence de vision du rouge.
            C'est le fameux <quote>daltonisme</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Non bisogna essere intimoriti dallo strano nome. La parola è
            formata da tre radici greche: <quote>op</quote> per occhio,
            visione; <quote>an</quote> per negazione; <quote>proto</quote>
            per primo, il primo colore nel <link
            linkend="glossary-colormodel">sistema di colori RGB</link>.
            Per cui, protanopia è la deficienza visiva del colore rosso. In
            pratica il famoso daltonismo (cecità di colore rosso-verde).
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Neišsigaskite šio neįprasto pavadinimo. Jį sudaro trys graikų
            kalbos šaknys: <quote>op</quote> – akis, regėjimas;
            <quote>an</quote> – neigimas; <quote>proto</quote> – pirmas,
            pirma spalva
            <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">RGB spalvų sistemoje</link>.
            Taigi protanopija yra raudonos spalvos regėjimo deficitas.
            Tai žinomas daltonizmas (aklumas raudonai – žaliai spalvai).
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dette flotte namnet er sett saman av fleire greske ord:
            <quote>op</quote> for auge, syn; <quote>an</quote>
            for negasjon; <quote>proto</quote> for første, dvs. den første
            fargen i <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB
            fargesystemet</link>. Så, ein person som er utsett for protanopi,
            har rett og slett nedsett følsemd for raud. Betre kjend som
            raud-grøn-fargeblind.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Protanopia is actually more complex than this; a person with this
            problem cannot see either red or green, although he is still
            sensitive to yellow and blue. In addition, he has a loss of
            luminance perception and the hues shift toward the short
            wavelengths.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Protanopia es, actualmente, algo más complejo; una persona con
            este problema no puede ver el rojo ni el verde, aunque es
            sensible al amarillo y al azul. Además, tiene una perdida de
            percepción de la luminancia y cambios en las tonalidades hacia
            las longitudes de ondas cortas.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La protanopie est en fait plus complexe : le rouge, mais aussi le
            vert ne sont pas vus. Le protanope reste sensible au jaune et au
            bleu. En outre, il existe une perte de luminance et un décalage
            des courbes de teintes vers les ondes courtes du spectre.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La protanopia è però un poco più complicata; una persona con
            questo problema non può vedere rosso o verde, malgrado sia
            comunque sensibile al giallo e al blu. Inoltre, essa ha una
            perdita di percezione della luminosità, e le tonalità che
            osserva si spostano verso le lunghezze d'onda inferiori.
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Iš tikro protanopija yra sudėtingesnė, nei tai; asmuo, turintis
            šią problemą, negali matyti raudonos arba žalios, nors jis
            tebėra jautrus geltonai ir mėlynai. Be to, jis nesuvokia skaisčio
            ir atspalviai pasislenka link trumpų bangų ilgių.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Protanopi er eigentleg litt meir komplisert enn dette. Ein
            person med dette problemet ser ikkje korkje raudt eller
            grønt, men ser likevel gult og blått. I tillegg har han mindre
            følsemd for lysstyrke og kuløren han ser skifter mot dei
            korte bølgjelengdene, dvs. blått.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Deuteranopia (insensivity to green)</term>
        <term lang="de">Deuteranopie (Grünblindheit)</term>
        <term lang="es">Deuteranopia (desviado al verde)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Deutéranopie</term>
        <term lang="it">Deuteranopia (insensibilità al verde)</term>
        <term lang="lt">Deuteranopija (nejautrumas žaliai)</term>
        <term lang="no">Deuteranopia (grønblind)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Deuteranopen haben Defizite in der Wahrnehmung von Grün.
            Wie bei der Protanopie nehmen sie kaum Rot und Grün wahr.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            With deuteranopia, the person has a deficiency in green vision.
            Deuteranopia is actually like protanopia, because the person has a
            loss of red and green perception, but he has no luminance loss or
            hue shift.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Con deuteranopia, la persona tiene una deficiencia en la visión
            del verde. Actualmente es como la protanopia, porque la persona
            tiene una perdida de la percepción del rojo y del verde, pero no
            tiene la perdida de luminancia o cambios tonales.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Absence de vision du vert. En fait, la deutéranopie ressemble à la
            protanopie, avec une perte de la vision du vert et du rouge,
            conservation de la vision du jaune et du bleu, mais sans la perte
            de luminance ni le décalage de la courbe des teintes.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La persona affetta da deuteranopia ha un deficit nella visione
            del verde.  Deuteranopia è simile la protanopia, dato che c'è una
            perdita di percezione del rosso e del verde, ma non c'è perdità
            di luminosità, né spostamento di tonalità.
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Asmuo su deuteranopija turi žalių spalvų regėjimo deficitą.
            Iš tikro deuteranopija yra panaši į protanopiją, kadangi
            asmuo nematos raudonos ir žalios spalvos, tačiau neturi
            škaisčio regėjimo arba atspalvių pasislinkimo sutrikimų.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Deuteranopi er nokså likt protanopi, med nedsett følsemd for
            raudt og grønt. Skilnaden er at ein persom med deuteranopi
            ikkje har redusert følsemd for lysmengde og heller ikkje
            fargeskifte mot korte bølgelengder.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="de">Tritanopie (Blaublindheit)</term>
        <term lang="en">Tritanopia (insensitivity to blue)</term>
        <term lang="es">Tritanopia (desviado al azul)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Tritanopie</term>
        <term lang="it">Tritanopia (insensibilità al blu)</term>
        <term lang="lt">Tritanopija (nejautrumas mėlynai)</term>
        <term lang="no">Tritanopia (blåblind)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Tritanopen haben Defizite in der Wahrnehmung von Blau und
            Gelb.
            <!--TODO: de  Stimmt die folgende Aussage überhaupt?-->
            Dafür ist die Wahrnehmung von Rot und Grün verbessert.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            With tritanopia, the person is deficient in blue and yellow
            perception, although he is still sensitive to red and green. He
            lacks some perception of luminance, and the hues shift toward the
            long wavelengths.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Con la tritanopia, la deficiencia está en la percepción el azul
            y el amarillo, aunque todavia es sensible al rojo y al verde.
            Algunas carencias en la percepción de la luminancia y cambios en
            las tonalidades hacia las longitudes de ondas largas.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Absence de vision du bleu. En fait, il y a perte de la vision du
            bleu et du jaune, conservation de la vision du rouge et du vert,
            perte de luminance et décalage des courbes d'intensité vers les
            grandes longueurs d'onde.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La persona affetta da tritanopia ha un deficit nella percezione
            dei colori blu e giallo, anche se è comunque sensibile al rosso
            e al verde. Il soggetto presenta carenze nella sensibilità, e
            le tonalità che osserva sono spostate verso le frequenze ad
            onda lunga.
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Asmuo su tritanopija nesuvokia mėlynos ir geltonos spalvų, tačiau
            jis tebėra jautrus raudonai ir žaliai. Jo škaisčio suvokimas yra
            šiek tiek sumažėjęs, o atspalviai yra pasislinkę link ilgų
            bangų ilgių.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Ein person med tritanopi har redusert følsemd for blått og gult,
            men har normalt syn når det gjeld raudt og grønt. Som oftast har
            han også redusert følsemd for lysstyrke og fargeskifte mot dei
            lange bølgjelengdene, dvs. raudt.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="de">Beispiele</term>
        <term lang="en">Examples</term>
        <term lang="es">Ejemplos</term>
        <term lang="fr">Exemples</term>
        <term lang="it">Esempi</term>
        <term lang="lt">Pavyzdžiai</term>
        <term lang="no">Eksempel</term>

        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="de">Beispiel für Protanopie</phrase>
              <phrase lang="en">Example of protanopia with some text</phrase>
              <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo de protanopia con texto</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Exemple de protanopie sur texte</phrase>
              <phrase lang="it">Esempio di protanopia con del testo</phrase>
              <phrase lang="lt">Protanopijos pavyzdys su tekstu</phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på protanopi</phrase>
            </title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/protanopia.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>

              <caption>
                <para lang="de">
                  Das rechte Bild verdeutlicht, wie Menschen mit einer
                  Rotblindheit das linke Bild sehen: sie können den roten
                  Text auf schwarzem Hintergrund nicht wahrnehmen.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  As you can see, a red-blind person cannot see the red
                  (255,0,0) text on a black (0,0,0) background. You have to
                  change the text color. Daltonism occurs fairly frequently in
                  the population.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Como puede ver, una persona ciega al rojo no puede ver
                  texto rojo (255,0,0) sobre un fondo negro (0,0,0). Tiene
                  un cambio en el color del texto. El daltonismo ocurre con
                  cierta frecuencia en la población.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Comme vous pouvez le constater, un daltonien ne verra pas
                  votre texte écrit en rouge (255;0;0) sur fond noir (0;0;0).
                  Il vous faudra changer la couleur du texte. Sans être aussi
                  caricatural, le daltonisme est fréquent dans la population.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Come si può vedere, una persona cieca del colore rosso
                  non può vedere del testo rosso (255,0,0) su sfondo nero
                  (0,0,0). Si rende necessario cambiare il colore del
                  testo. Il daltonismo è un difetto visivo abbastanza
                  comune.
                </para>
                <para lang="lt">
                  Kaip galite matyti, raudonai spalvai aklas asmuo negali
                  matyti raudono (255,0,0) teksto juodame (0,0,0) fone.
                  Turite pakeisti teksto spalvą. Žmonių populiacijoje
                  daltonizmas sutinkamas gana dažnai.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Ein raudblind person kan ikkje sjå den raude (255,0,0)
                  skrifta på svart (0,0,0) bakgrunn. Du må endra
                  tekstfargen.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;it;lt;no">
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Examples of the three types of vision deficiencies in one
                image
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Beispiele für die drei Arten der Fehlsichtigkeit in einem
                Bild
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="es">
                Ejemplos de los tres tipos de deficiencias de la visión en
                una imagen
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">
                Exemples des trois défauts de vision sur une image
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="it">
                Esempio dei tre tipi di deficienze visive in un'immagine
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="lt">
                Trijų regėjimo deficitų tipų pavyzdžiai viename paveikslėlyje
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">
                Eksempel på dei tre synsdefektane
              </phrase>
            </title>

            <!--sight-defect.xcf exists for translators-->
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en;de;es">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/sight-defects.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/sight-defects.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="it">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/it/sight-defects.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="lt">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/lt/sight-defects.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="no">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/sight-defects.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>

              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  From top to bottom: normal vision, protanopia, deuteranopia,
                  and tritanopia. It appears that the filters don't give a
                  fair reflection of medical data. In deuteranopia, yellow is
                  shifted toward red. In tritanopia, green is slightly
                  represented in the blue range...
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Von oben nach unten: normale Sehfähigkeit, Protanopie,
                  Deuteranopie, Tritanopie. Allerdings geben die Filter nicht
                  ganz genau die Realität, wie sie sich aus den medizinischen
                  Daten ergibt, wieder. Bei der Deuteranopie wird Gelb nach
                  Rot verschoben, bei der Tritanopie Grün durch Blau
                  dargestellt.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  De arriba a abajo: visión normal, protanopia, deuteranopia
                  y tritanopia. Parece que los filtros no reflejan bien los
                  datos médicos. En deuteranopia, el amarillo varia hacia el
                  rojo. En tritanopia, el verde se represena ligeramente en
                  el rango del azul...
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  De haut en bas : vision normale, protanopie, deutéranopie,
                  tritanopie. Il semble bien que le filtre ne reflète pas bien
                  les données médicales. Dans la deutéranopie, le jaune est
                  décalé vers le rouge. Dans la tritanopie le vert apparaît
                  légèrement au sein du bleu...
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Dall'alto al basso: visione normale, protanopia,
                  deuteranopia e tritanopia. I filtri non rendono bene
                  l'idea dei dati medici.  In deuteranopia, il giallo è
                  spostato verso il rosso. In tritanopia, il verde viene
                  parzialmente rappresentato nel campo del colore blu...
                </para>
                <para lang="lt">
                  Nuo viršaus į apačią: normalus regėjimas, protanopija,
                  deuteranopija ir tritanopija. Atrodo, kad filtrai
                  nepakankamai tiksliai perteikia medicininius duomenis.
                  Esant deuteranopijai geltona yra paslenkama link raudonos.
                  Esant tritanopijai žalia yra šiek tiek atvaizduota
                  mėlyname rėžyje...
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Desse eksempla viser korleis personar med normalsyn,
                  protanopi, deuteranopi og tritanopi oppfattar fargane. Det ser
                  ut til at filtera ikkje gir eit heilt korrekt bilete av dei
                  medisinske data. I deuteranopi er gult skifta mot raudt,
                  i tritanopi er grønt lite representert i det blå området osv.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-gamma-dialog">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de;en;es;fr;it;lt;no">Gamma</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Gamma proof</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Couleur</primary>
      <secondary>Tester le gamma</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="lt">
      <primary>Spalva</primary>
      <secondary>Gamma korekcija</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="de">Der Gamma-Dialog</phrase>
          <phrase lang="en">The <quote>Gamma</quote> dialog</phrase>
          <phrase lang="es">El diálogo <quote>Gamma</quote></phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">La fenêtre de dialogue Gamma</phrase>
          <phrase lang="it">La finestra di dialogo <quote>Gamma</quote></phrase>
          <phrase lang="lt">Dialogas <quote>Gamma</quote></phrase>
          <phrase lang="no"><quote>Gamma</quote>-dialogen</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject lang="en">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-gamma.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="de">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/display-filters-gamma.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="es">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/menus/es/display-filters-gamma.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="fr">
            <imagedata
                fileref="../images/menus/fr/display-filters-gamma.png"
                format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="it">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-gamma.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="lt">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/menus/lt/display-filters-gamma.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="no">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/menus/no/display-filters-gamma.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Da Unterschiede zwischen der Erzeugung und Anzeige von Farben am
      Monitor bestehen, gibt es die <quote>Gammakorrektur</quote>. Der
      <quote>Gamma</quote>-Wert ist ein Koeffizient, mit dessen Hilfe dieser
      Unterschied minimiert wird. Der Anzeigefilter <guilabel>Gamma</guilabel>
      bietet die Möglichkeit, die Anzeige des Bildes in
      sehr hellen oder sehr dunklen Umgebungen zu simulieren.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The correspondence between electrical intensity and color brightness
      is not exact and it depends upon the device (the camera, the scanner,
      the monitor, etc.). <quote>Gamma</quote> is a coefficient used to
      correct this correspondence. Your image must be visible in both dark
      and bright areas, even if it is displayed on a monitor with too much
      luminence or not enough. The <quote>Gamma</quote> Display Filter
      allows you to get an idea of the appearance of your image under these
      conditions.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      La correspondencia entre la intensidad eléctrica y el brillo del color
      no es exacta y depende del dispositivo (la cámara, el escaner,
      el monitor, etc.). <quote>Gamma</quote> es un coeficiente que se usa
      para corregir esta correspondencia. En su imagen deben verse las áreas
      claras y oscuras, igual si se muestra en un monitor con mucha
      luminosidad o con poca. El filtro <quote>Gamma</quote> le permite
      tener una idea de la apariencia de su imagen bajo esas condiciones.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La correspondance entre l'intensité électrique et l'intensité
      lumineuse des couleurs n'est pas exacte et dépend de l'appareil
      de saisie (appareil photo, caméra, scanner...) ou de
      reproduction (moniteur). Le <quote>gamma</quote> est un coefficient
      destiné à corriger cette correspondance. Votre image doit rester
      visible dans ses zones d'ombres ou de pleine lumière même si elle est
      affichée sur un moniteur peu ou trop lumineux. Le filtre
      d'affichage <quote>gamma</quote> vous permet de vous faire une idée de
      l'aspect de votre image dans ces conditions.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      La corrispondenza tra intensità elettrica e brillantezza di colore
      non è esatta e dipende dal dispositivo usato (macchina fotografica,
      scanner, monitor, ecc.). <quote>Gamma</quote> è un coefficiente usato
      per correggere questa corrispondenza. L'immagine deve essere visibile
      sia nelle aree scure che quelle chiare, anche se visualizzata su un
      monitor con troppa o insufficiente luminosità. Il filtro a monitor
      <quote>Gamma</quote> permette di rendere l'immagine al meglio, anche
      in queste condizioni.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Atitikimas tarp elektrinio intensyvumo ir spalvos šviesumo nėra tikslus
      ir jis priklauso nuo įrenginio (fotoaparato, skenerio, vaizduoklio,
      ir t. t.). <quote>Gamma</quote> – tai koeficientas, naudojamas
      pataisyti šį atitikimą. Jūsų paveikslėlis turi būti matomas ir
      tamsiose ir šviesiose srityse, netgi jeigu jis rodomas vaizduoklyje,
      su per dideliu arba nepakankamu skaisčiu. <quote>Gamma</quote>
      rodymo filtras jums leidžia suprasti kaip jūsų paveikslėlis atrodytų
      esant šioms sąlygoms.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Samanhengen mellom elektrisitet og fargestyrke er på ingen måte eksakt,
      men er avhengig av kva utstyr, dvs. kamera, skanner, skjerm osv, du
      bruker. <quote>Gamma</quote> er ein konstant som blir brukt til å
      korrigera denne samanhengen. Både mørke og lyse område av biletet
      ditt skal verre synlege sjølv om det blir vist på ein for mørk eller for
      lys skjerm. Filtervisinga <quote>Gamma</quote> kan gi deg ein ide
      om korleis biletet ditt vil sjå ut i slike tilfelle.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-contrast-dialog">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Kontrast</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Contrast</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Contraste</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Contraste</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Contrasto</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Kontrastas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Kontrast</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Contrast proof</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Couleur</primary>
      <secondary>Tester le contraste</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="lt">
      <primary>Spalva</primary>
      <secondary>Kontrasto korekcija</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="de">
            Der Kontrast-Dialog
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="en">
            The <quote>Contrast</quote> dialog
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="es">
            El diálogo <quote>Contraste</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">La fenêtre de dialogue Contrast</phrase>
          <phrase lang="it">
            La finestra di dialogo <quote>Contrasto</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="lt">
            Dialogas <quote>Kontrastas</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="no">
            Dialogvindauget for <quote>Kontrast</quote>
          </phrase>
        </title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject lang="en">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-contrast.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="de">
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../images/menus/de/display-filters-contrast.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="es">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/es/display-filters-contrast.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="fr">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/menus/fr/display-filters-contrast.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="it">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-contrast.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="lt">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/lt/display-filters-contrast.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="no">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/display-filters-contrast.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Here, we are back in the medical domain.
      <quote>Contrast Sensitivity</quote>
      is the capacity of the visual system to distinguish slight differences
      in contrast. Some people with cataracts (which means that the lens has
      opaque crystals that scatter light over the retina) or retinal disease
      (for instance, due to diabetes, which destroys the rods and cones) have
      a deficiency in sensitivity to contrast: for example, they would have
      difficulties distinguishing spots on a dress.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      <quote>Kontrastempfindlichkeit</quote> ist die Fähigkeit des visuellen
      Systems, auch geringe Kontrastunterschiede in einem Bild zu erkennen.
      Manche Menschen haben Probleme, Kontraste wahrzunehmen (z.B. durch
      eine Krankheit), beispielsweise können sie nur schwer Flecken auf
      Kleidungsstücken erkennen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Aquí, volvemos al campo médico. La
      <quote>Sensibilidad al contraste</quote>
      es la capacidad del sitema visual para distinguir ligeras diferencias
      en el contraste. Algunas personas con cataratas ( significa que la
      lente tiene un cristal opaco que dispersa la luz sobre la retina) o
      con la enfermedad de la retina (por ejemplo, debido a la diabetes, que
      destruye conos y bastoncillos de la retina) tienen una deficiencia en
      la sensibilidad al contraste: por ejemplo, tendrían dificultad para
      distinguir puntos en un vestido.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Nous voici à nouveau dans le domaine médical. La
      <emphasis>sensibilité au contraste</emphasis>
      est la capacité du système visuel à distinguer les faibles différences
      de contraste. Certaines personnes, souffrant de cataracte (l'opacité du
      cristallin éparpille la lumière sur la rétine) ou de maladie de la
      rétine (due au diabète par exemple, qui détruit cônes et bâtonnets de la
      rétine), ont un déficit de cette sensibilité au contraste : il leur est
      difficile de distiguer des taches sur un habit par exemple.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Qui si ritorna nel dominio della medicina. La <quote>sensibilità al
      contrasto</quote> è la capacità del sistema visivo di distinguere
      leggere differenze di contrasto. Alcune persone con cataratta
      (malattia che porta alla perdita di trasparenza del cristallino, la
      lente naturale sita nell'occhio che porta la luce alla rètina) o con
      malattie della rètina (per esempio, dovuta al diabete, che distrugge
      i coni e i bastoncelli nell'occhio) hanno una deficienza nella
      sensibilità al contrasto: per esempio, esse hanno difficoltà a
      distinguere una macchia su un vestito.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Vėl sugrįžome į medicinos sritį. <quote>Jautrumas kontrastui</quote>
      yra regėjimo sistemos sugebėjimas atskirti nedidelius kontrasto
      pokyčius. Kai kurie žmonės, turintys kataraktas (tai reiškia, kad
      lęšiuke yra nepermatomų kristalų, kurie išsklaido šviesą tinklainėje)
      arba tinklainės sutrikimą (pavyzdžiui, dėl diabeto) turi jautrumo
      kontrastui nepakankamumą: pavyzdžiui, jiems gali būti sunku atskirti
      taškus suknelėje.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Nå er vi tilbake i medisinen att. <quote>Kontrastfølsemd</quote>
      er evna til å oppfatte små skilnader i kontrastar. Det kan vere mange
      årsakar til at denne evna kan bli svekka. Augesjukdommen
      <quote>grå stær</quote>, er ein tilstand der det blir utvikla
      ugjennomsiktige krystallar i augelinsa. Desse spreier lyset over
      netthinna og gjer synet uklart. Ein annan årsak kan vere skader
      på stavane og tappane t.d. som følgje av diabetes. Folk med
      nedsett evne til å sjå kontrastar, kan t.d. ha  problem med å
      sjå prikkane på ein kjole.
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      With the <quote>Contrast</quote> Filter, you can see the image as if
      you were suffering from cataracts. You may have to increase the
      contrast of the image so that your grandmother can see it well. In
      most cases, only very low values of the <guilabel>Contrast
      Cycles</guilabel> parameter are of interest. Higher values create a
      side-effect which doesn't interest us here: if you increase the
      luminosity value above 255, the complementary color appears.
   </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter bietet eine Möglichkeit, diese Fehlsichtigkeit zu
      simulieren.  In den meisten Fällen sind kleine Kontrastwerte, also eine
      geringe <guilabel>Kontrastverstärkung</guilabel>, von Interesse. Große
      Kontrastwerte haben einen unschönen Nebeneffekt: Bei einer Leuchtkraft
      mit einem Wert größer als 255 wird die Komplementärfarbe angezeigt.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Con el filtro <quote>Contraste</quote>, Puede ver la imagen como si
      sufriera cataratas. Puede subir el contraste de forma que se pudiera
      ver bien. En la mayoria de los casos, solo pocos valores bajos del
      parámetro de <guilabel>Ciclos de contraste</guilabel> son de interes.
      Los valores más altos crean un efecto lateral que no nos interesa
      aquí: si incrementa el valor de la luminosidad a 255, aparece el color
      complementario.
   </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre d'affichage <quote>Contraste</quote> vous fait voir l'image
      comme si vous aviez une cataracte. Vous pouvez être amené à
      augmenter le contraste de votre image pour que votre grand-mère
      puisse en profiter pleinement. Dans la plupart des cas, seules les
      très faibles valeurs du paramètre <guilabel>Cycles de contraste
      </guilabel> sont intéressantes. Les valeurs élevées entraînent
      un effet collatéral sans intérêt ici : l'augmentation de la
      luminosité, quand elle dépasse la valeur 255, fait apparaître la
      couleur complémentaire.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Con il filtro <quote>Contrasto</quote>, è possibile vedere l'immagine
      come se si fosse malati di cataratta. Per esempio si potrebbe
      desiderare di incrementare il contrasto dell'immagine in modo da
      poterla mostrare alla propria nonna. Spesso sono utili solo valori di
      molto bassi del parametro <guilabel>Cicli di contrasto</guilabel>
      dato che i valori alti creano un effetto collaterale non utile in
      questo ambito: se si aumenta i valori di luminosità sopra il valore
      255, appaiono i colori complementari.
   </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Naudodami filtrą <quote>Kontrastas</quote> galite matyti paveikslėlį
      taip lyg turėtumėte kataraktą. Jums gali reikėti padidinti kontrastą,
      kad jūsų senelė gerai matytų jūsų paveikslėlį. Daugeliu atvejų
      aktualios yra tik labai mažos parametro <guilabel>Kontrasto
      ciklai</guilabel> reikšmės. Naudojant didesnes reikšmes gaunamas
      pašalinis poveikis, kuris čia mūsų nedomina: jeigu padidinsite
      škaisčio reikšmę virš 255, atsiras papildomų spalvų.
   </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Filteret <quote>Kontrast</quote> gjer at du kan få ei førestiling om
      korleis biletet ser ut for ein med grå stær. Kan hende må du auke
      kontrasten i biletet slik at også bestemor ser biletet godt. I dei
      fleste tilfella har du bare bruk for små verdiar for
      <guilabel>Kontrastsyklusar</guilabel>. Høge verdiar fører med seg
      ein sideeffekt: Aukar du verdien over 255, vil
      komplimentærfargane kome fram.
   </para>

    <para lang="en">
      If you are interested in this subject, you can browse the Web for
      <quote>contrast sensitivity</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Si está interesado en esto, puede explorar en la web buscando
      <quote>sensibilidad al contraste</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Si le sujet vous intéresse, explorez le Web français sur le
      thème <quote>sensibilité au contraste</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se si è interessati all'argomento, cercare sul web informazioni
      relative alla <quote>sensibilità al contrasto</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Jeigu jus domina ši tema, žiniatinklyje galite paieškoti
      <quote>jautrumo kontrastui</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Skulle dette ha vekt interesse, kan du søke på Internett på
      <quote>contrast sensitivity</quote> eller noe liknande.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-color-proof">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Farbandruck</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Color Proof</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Color seguro</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Calibration des couleurs</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Prova di colore</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Spalvų korekcija</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Sikre fargar</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Color proof</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Profile</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Profile</primary></indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Couleur</primary>
      <secondary>Calibration</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Couleur</primary>
      <secondary>Profil</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Profil</primary></indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="lt">
      <primary>Spalva</primary>
      <secondary>Spalvų korekcija</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="lt">
      <primary>Spalva</primary>
      <secondary>Profilis</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="lt"><primary>Profilis</primary></indexterm>

    <!-- This section needs more informations about profiles-->
    <para lang="de">
      Mit den meisten Systemen lassen sich nicht alle Farben physisch
      ausgeben, wenn sie auf dem Bildschirm dargestellt werden. Mit
      diesem Filter können sie die Ansicht der Ausgabe simulieren.
      Farb<guilabel>profile</guilabel> erlauben es, die Ausgabe z.B.
      systemabhängig anzupassen.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The various systems for reproducing colors cannot represent the
      infinity of colors available. Even if there are many colors in
      common between the various systems and nature, some of the colors
      will not be the same. The <quote>gamut</quote> is the color range of
      a system. <emphasis>Color Profiles</emphasis> allow you to compensate
      for these differences.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Los distintos sistemas para reproducir colores no pueden representar
      la infinidad de colores disponibles. Igual que hay muchos colores
      comunes entre estos sistemas y la naturaleza, algunos no son iguales.
      La <quote>gama (gamut)</quote> es le rango de color de un sistema. Los
      <emphasis>Perfiles de color</emphasis> permiten compersar estas
      diferencias.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les différents systèmes de reproduction des couleurs ne peuvent pas
      représenter l'infinité des couleurs disponibles. Même s'ils ont
      beaucoup de couleurs communes dans leur intervalle de couleurs,
      certaines seront différentes. On appelle <quote>gamut</quote>
      l'ensemble, la gamme
      des teintes que peut produire un système. Les <emphasis>Profils
      colorimétriques</emphasis> permettent de compenser ces différences.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      I vari sistemi di riproduzione del colore non possono rappresentare
      l'infinità di colori disponibili in natura. Molti tra i colori
      riproducibili con in vari sistemi corrispondono ai colori naturali,
      altri colori invece non sono riprodotti perfettamente e quindi
      appaiono diversi. Il <quote>gamut</quote> è il campo di colori, la
      gamma, di un sistema. I <emphasis>profili di colore</emphasis>
      permettono di compensare queste differenze.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Įvairios spalvų atkūrimo sistemos negali atvaizduoti begalybės
      galimų spalvų. Netgi jeigu tarp įvairių sistemų ir gamtos yra daug
      bendrų spalvų, kai kurios spalvos nebus tokios pat. <quote>Gama</quote>
      – tai sistemos spalvų rėžis. <emphasis>Spalvų profiliai</emphasis>
      leidžia jums kompensuoti šiuos skirtumus.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dei ulike systema som blir brukte for å reprodusera fargar, kan ikkje
      behandla uendeleg med fargenyansar. Difor hender det at dei
      naturlege fargane og dei som blir vist med fargesystemet, ikkje er
      heilt dei same. Filteret <emphasis>Fargeprofil</emphasis> gir deg
      ein sjanse til å prøve ut noen kompenseringar for manglande fargar.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Um Bilder zu drucken, mag es sinnvoll sein, das Farbprofil in
      Verbindung mit dem Filter zu benutzen. So bekommen Sie einen
      Eindruck von dem Bild, das sie bearbeiten, wie es letztendlich vom
      Drucker ausgegeben wird.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Before you print an image, it may be useful for you to see if you
      will get the result you want by applying a profile. The <quote>Color
      Proof</quote> filter shows you how your image will look after a color
      profile has been applied.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Antes de imprimir una imagen, será útil ver el resultado que se
      obtiene al aplicar un perfil de color. El filtro
      <quote>Color seguro</quote> muestra como se verá su imagen después de
      aplicar el perfil.
    </para>
     <para lang="fr">
      Il peut être utile de voir avant impression si l'application d'un
      profil colorimétrique donne bien les résultats escomptés. Le filtre
      <quote>calibration des couleurs</quote> vous permet de voir comment
      votre image sera rendue après application d'un profil colorimétrique.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Prima di stampare un'immagine, è utile verificare se si riesce ad
      ottenere il risultato sperato applicando un profilo. Il filtro
      <quote>Prova di colore</quote> mostra come apparirà un'immagine dopo
      che sia stato applicato un determinato profilo di colore.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Prieš spausdinant paveikslėlį gali būti naudinga pažiūrėti, ar
      gausite norimą rezultatą, pritaikant profilį. Filtras <quote>Spalvų
      korekcija</quote> parodo kaip jūsų paveikslėlis atrodys pritaikius
      spalvų profilį.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Før du skriv ut eit bilete, kan det vere greitt å kontrollera om
      resultatet blir slik du håper det skal bli. Filteret
      <quote>Fargeprofil</quote> kan gi eit inntrykk av korleis biletet blir
      sjåande ut med ulike fargeprofilar.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
          <phrase lang="en">The <quote>Color Proof</quote> dialog</phrase>
          <phrase lang="de">Der Farbandruck-Dialog</phrase>
          <!--TODO  it no  Check this title, it's just cut & pasted-->
          <phrase lang="en">El diálogo <quote>Color seguro</quote></phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">
            La fenêtre de dialogue Calibration des couleurs
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="it">
            La finestra di dialogo <quote>Prova di colore</quote>
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="lt">Dialogas <quote>Spalvų korekcija</quote></phrase>
          <phrase lang="no">
            Dialogvindauget for <quote>Fargeprofil</quote>
          </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/de/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/es/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/fr/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="lt">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/lt/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/no/display-filters-proof.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">The <quote>Color Proof</quote> options</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Die Eigenschaften des Farbandruck-Filters</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Las opciones de <quote>Color seguro</quote></phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Les options Calibration des couleurs</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Le opzioni di <quote>Prova di colore</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="lt"><quote>Spalvų korekcijos</quote> parinktys</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for <quote>Fargeprofil</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Intent</term>
        <term lang="de">Absicht</term>
        <term lang="es">Intento</term>
        <term lang="fr">Rendu des couleurs</term>
        <term lang="it">Intento</term>
        <term lang="lt">Tikslas</term>
        <term lang="no">Føremål</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can apply the filter you have selected in one of four ways:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie können dieses Filter auf vier verschiede Arten anwenden:
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Puede aplicar el filtro seleccionado de una de estas cuatro
            maneras:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous pouvez appliquer le filtre que vous choisirez selon quatre
            méthodes :
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il filtro è applicabile in uno dei seguenti quattro metodi:
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Galite pritaikyti pasirinktą filtrą keturiais būdais:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Du kan legge til det valde filteret på fire måtar:
          </para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Perceptual</term>
              <term lang="de">Wahrnehmung</term>
              <term lang="es">Perceptible</term>
              <term lang="fr">Perceptuelle</term>
              <term lang="it">Percettivo</term>
              <term lang="lt">Percepcinis</term>
              <term lang="no">Perseptuell</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die <guilabel>Wahrnehmung</guilabel> ist eine gute Methode,
                  um einen Eindruck zu bekommen, wie das Bild von einem
                  Drucker ausgegeben wird.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The <guilabel>Perceptual</guilabel> method is the best way
                  to reproduce photographs on ink-jet printers. The
                  adjustment is minimal and visual relationships between
                  colors are preserved so that they are perceived in a
                  natural way by the human eye.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  El método <guilabel>Perceptible</guilabel> es la mejor
                  manera de reproducir las fotografias en las impresoras de
                  tinta. Los ajustes son mínimos y la relación visual entre
                  colores se preserva con los que percive en la naturaleza
                  el ojo humano.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  La méthode Perceptuelle est la mieux adaptée à la
                  reproduction de photographies sur les imprimantes à jet
                  d'encre. Les teintes peuvent être légèrement modifiées mais
                  les relations visuelles entre les couleurs sont préservées
                  de façon à être perçues de façon naturelle par l'œil humain.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Il metodo <guilabel>Percettivo</guilabel> è il metodo migliore
                  per di riprodurre le fotografie su stampanti a getto
                  d'inchiostro. Gli aggiustamenti sono minimi e le relazioni
                  visuali tra i colori vengono mantenute in modo da rendere la
                  percezione naturale per l'occhio umano.
                </para>
                <para lang="lt">
                  <guilabel>Percepcinis</guilabel> metodas yra geriausias
                  nuotraukų atkūrimo būdas rašaliniuose spausdintuvuose.
                  Pakoregavimas yra minimalus, o vaizdiniai ryšiai tarp
                  spalvų yra išsaugomi, kad jie galėtų būti žmogaus akies
                  suvokiami natūraliu būdu.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Metoden <guilabel>Perseptuell</guilabel> er den beste
                  metoden for å imitere blekkskrivarar. Det er lite å justera
                  og den visuelle samanhengen mellom fargane blir bevart slik
                  at fargane ser naturlege ut.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Relative Colorimetric</term>
              <term lang="de">Kolometrisch (relativ)</term>
              <term lang="es">Métrica de color relativa</term>
              <term lang="fr">Colorimétrie relative</term>
              <term lang="it">Colorimetrico relativo</term>
              <term lang="lt">Santykinis kolorimetrinis</term>
              <term lang="no">Relativ (Kolometrisk)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="de">
                  Diese Methode vergleicht die weißen und schwarzen Punkte
                  einer Farbpalette mit denen der Ausgabefarbpalette und
                  passt den Farbton entsprechend an. Diese Methode ist vor
                  allem geeignet, um einen Eindruck für die Druckausgabe von
                  Fotos auf Tintenstrahldruckern zu bekommen. Das Filter
                  neigt dazu, das Bild abzudunkeln. Daher muss unter
                  Umständen ein zusätzlicher
                  <guilabel>Schwarzpunkt-Abgleich</guilabel> erfolgen.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  This method compares the white and black points of the source
                  gamut with those of the destination gamut and scales the hues
                  accordingly. It is well suited for printing photographs on
                  ink-jet printers. It tends to darken the image, so it may be
                  necessary to compensate the black point.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Este método compara los puntos blancos y negros de la gama
                  con los de la gama destino y escala los tonos en
                  concordancia. Está indicado para la impresión fotográfica
                  en impresoras de tinta. Tiende a oscurecer la imagen, por
                  lo que podría ser necesario compensar el punto negro.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  La méthode de Colorimétrie relative compare les points blanc et
                  noir de la source à ceux de la gamme de couleur de la
                  destination et échelonne les teintes selon le résultat. Elle
                  convient bien aussi à l'impression des photographies sur
                  imprimante à jet d'encre. Les couleurs hors-gamme sont
                  reproduites aussi fidèlement que possible. Elle a tendance à
                  assombrir l'image, ce qui peut nécessiter une compensation du
                  noir.
                 </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Questo metodo confronta i punti bianchi e neri del gamut
                  sorgente con quelli del gamut di destinazione e scala la
                  tonalità di conseguenza. È indicato per la stampa di fotografie
                  su stampanti a getto d'inchiostro. Tende a rendere le immagini
                  più scure, perciò è consigliabile compensare il punto del nero.
                </para>
                <para lang="lt">
                  Šis metodas palygina šaltinio gamos baltą ir juodą taškus
                  su paskirties gama ir atitinkamai ištempia atspalvius.
                  Jis gerai tinka nuotraukų spausdinimui rašaliniais
                  spausdintuvais. Tai paprastai patamsina paveikslėlį, todėl
                  gali būti būtina kompensuoti juodą tašką.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Denne metoden samanliknar dei svarte og kvite punkta i
                  originalen med dei tilsvarande punkta i det endelege biletet og
                  skalerer kuløren i høve til dette. Metoden passar svært godt
                  for blekkskrivarar. Han har ein tendens til å gi litt mørke
                  bilete, så det kan bli nødvendig å kompensere for dette.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en;fr">Saturation</term>
              <term lang="de">Sättigung</term>
              <term lang="es">Saturación</term>
              <term lang="it">Saturazione</term>
              <term lang="lt">Sodrumas</term>
              <term lang="no">Metning</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="de">
                  Diese Option bewahrt die Sättigungswerte des Bildes. Die
                  Sättigungsoption ist nicht empfehlenswert für Fotos, jedoch
                  für Bilder, bei denen es um einen hohen, gleichmäßigen
                  Sättigungsgehalt der Farben geht (z.B. Logos).
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  This method preserves the saturation values of the original
                  pixels. The original pixels which are outside of the range are all
                  represented at the same saturation. This method is not very useful
                  for photographs. It is used for documents where color punch is
                  more important than accuracy, such as for reproducing logos.
                  Colors which should have a continuous change are not represented
                  very well, since there are jumps in the colors.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Este método preserva los valores de saturación originales
                  de los píxeles. Los píxeles originales que están fuera del
                  rango se representan con la misma saturación. Este método
                  no es muy útil para los fotógrafos. Se usa con documentos
                  donde los colores agresivos son más importante que la
                  exactitud, como para reproducir logos. Los colores con un
                  cambio continuo no se representan muy bien, hay saltos de
                  color.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Préserve les valeurs de saturation des pixels originaux. Les
                  pixels originaux hors-gamme sont également représentés avec leur
                  saturation. Cette méthode intéresse peu les photographes. Elle
                  sert surtout aux documents où l'aggressivité des couleurs compte
                  plus que leur exactitude, comme dans les logos. Les tons en
                  variation continue sont mal représentés, avec des sauts de
                  tonalité.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Questo metodo conserva i valori di saturazione dei pixel
                  originali. I pixel originali che sono fuori campo sono tutti
                  rappresentati con la stessa saturazione. Questo metodo non è
                  molto utile per le fotografie. Viene usato per i documenti dove
                  l'aggressività del colore è più importante dell'accuratezza,
                  come per riprodurre i logotipi. I colori che hanno cambiamenti
                  continui come le sfumature, non sono riprodotti molto bene,
                  dato che si verificano discontinuità nella tinta.
                </para>
                <para lang="lt">
                  Šis metodas išsaugo originalių pikselių sodrumo reikšmes.
                  Originalūs pikseliai, kurie yra už rėžio, yra atvaizduojami
                  tokiu pačiu sodrumu. Šis metodas nelabai naudingas
                  nuotraukoms. Jis naudojamas dokumentams, kur spalvų
                  štampavimas yra svarbiau už tikslumą, pavyzdžiui,
                  logotipų atkūrimui. Spalvos, kurios turėtų kisti tolygiai,
                  neatkuriamos labai gerai, kadangi yra spalvų šuolių.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Denne metoden tar vare på metningsverdiane i originalen.
                  Pikslar som er utanfor metningsområdet blir sett til same
                  metningsverdien. Metoden er lite brukbar til fotografiar, men
                  høver bra for dokument der fargemetninga er viktigare enn
                  nøyaktig farge, t.d. for å reprodusera logoar. Metoden er heller
                  ikkje eigna til å vise kontinuerlege fargeovergangar sidan han
                  fører til <quote>hopp</quote> i fargen.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Absolute Colorimetric</term>
              <term lang="de">Kolometrisch (absolut)</term>
              <term lang="es">Colorimetria absoluta</term>
              <term lang="fr">Colorimétrie absolue</term>
              <term lang="it">Colorimetrico assoluto</term>
              <term lang="lt">Absoliutinis kolorimetrinis</term>
              <term lang="no">Absolutt (Kolometrisk)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="de">
                  Diese Option entfernt unbenutzte Farben der Farbpalette des
                  ausgewählten Profils.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  This method leaves the colors of the source which are
                  within the gamut of the destination unchanged and discards
                  the colors outside of the gamut. There is no stretching of
                  the colors on the white point. The accuracy of the colors
                  is preserved, but not their relationships, and different
                  colors may be represented in the same way.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Este método deja los colores de la fuente que están en la
                  gama del destino sin cambiar, y descarta los colores fuera
                  de la gama. No hay extensión de los colores en el punto
                  blanco. Se preserva la exactitud del color, pero no su
                  relación, y los colores diferentes se representan de la
                  misma manera.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Cette méthode laisse les couleurs de la gamme de
                  destination inchangées et les couleurs hors-gamme sont
                  rejetées. Il n'y a pas d'échelonnement des couleurs sur le
                  point blanc. L'exactitude des couleurs est préservée, mais
                  pas leurs relations et des couleurs différentes risquent
                  d'être représentées de la même façon.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Questo metodo lascia invariati i colori della sorgente che
                  rientrano nel gamut di destinazione, mentre elimina i colori
                  fuori da questi parametri. Non viene eseguita nessuna
                  estrapolazione dei colori sul punto di bianco. L'accuratezza
                  dei colori viene mantenuta, ma non la loro relazione, e colori
                  differenti potrebbero essere rappresentati allo stesso modo.
                </para>
                <para lang="lt">
                  Šis metodas palieka šaltinio spalvas, kurios yra
                  paskirties gamoje, nepakeistas ir pašalina į gamą
                  nepatenka į gamą. Spalvos neištempiamos baltame taške.
                  Spalvų tikslumas yra išsaugomas, tačiau ne jų ryšiai,
                  o skirtingos spalvos gali būti perteiktos tokiu pat
                  būdu.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Denne metoden bevarer dei fargane som kan reproduserast av
                  fargesystemet uendra. Fargar som ikkje kan reproduserast, blir
                  fjerna. Her er det alstå ikkje noe tilnærming til næraste farge.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry> <!-- end of "Intent" -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Profile</term>
        <term lang="de">Profil</term>
        <term lang="es">Perfil</term>
        <term lang="fr">Profil</term>
        <term lang="it">Profilo</term>
        <term lang="lt">Profilis</term>
        <term lang="no">Profil</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Hier können Sie das Farbprofil eines Gerätes von einem
            Datenträger laden.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            This text box and its browser button allow you to select the
            profile you want from a location on a storage device.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Esta caja de texto y su botón de navegación permite seleccionar
            el perfil desde la localización de almacenaje.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette boîte de texte et son bouton de navigation vous permettent
            de choisir le profil voulu sur un périphérique de stockage
            quelconque.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questa casella di testo ed il suo pulsante di navigazione
            permettono di selezionare il profilo desiderato in una
            posizione qualsiasi su disco.
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Šis teksto laukelis ir jo naršymo mygtukas leidžia jums
            pasirinkti jūsų pageidaujamą profilį, esantį jūsų kaupiklyje.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her kan du hente inn ein fargeprofil frå andre lagringsmedia.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Black Point Compensation</term>
        <term lang="de">Schwarzpunkt-Abgleich</term>
        <term lang="es">Compensación del punto negro</term>
        <term lang="fr">Compensation du point noir</term>
        <term lang="it">Compensazione del punto nero</term>
        <term lang="lt">Juodo taško kompensacija</term>
        <term lang="no">Svartpunktkompensering</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Der Schwarzpunkt-Abgleich gleicht den Farbton zum
            Schwarzpunkt des Bildes an.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Black point compensation resamples the image to scale the hues
            from the black point of the original image, if the result is too
            different from the original.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Compensación del punto negro remuestrea la imagen para escalar
            los tonos del punto negro de la imagen original, si el resultado
            es demasiado diferente del original.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La compensation du point noir permet de rééchantillonner l'image
            en renforçant la prise en compte de l'image originale quand le
            résultat est trop différent de l'original.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La compensazione del punto nero ricampiona l'immagine per
            scalarne le tonalità dal punto di nero dell'immagine originale
            se il risultato dovesse differire troppo dall'originale.
          </para>
          <para lang="lt">
            Juodo taško kompensacija pertvarko paveikslėlį, kad ištemptų
            originalaus paveikslėlio atspalvius nuo juodo taško, jeigu
            rezultatas per daug skiriasi nuo originalo.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom resultatet blir for langt frå originalen, blir biletet sett
            saman på nytt. Verdiane for kulør blir justerte med verdien
            for svartpunktet i originalen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist> <!-- end of "Options" -->
  </sect3>

</sect2>
