<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-view-dot-for-dot' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Dot for Dot</title>
  <title lang="fr">Point pour point</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">点对点</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dot for Dot</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Point pour point</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">点对点</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    This command is found at
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>View</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Dot for Dot</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Turns &quot;Dot for Dot&quot; viewing on or off. When turned on, 
    every pixel in the image is shown as one pixel on the screen, on 
    condition that the zoom ratio is 1:1. 
  </para> 
  <para lang="en">
    Actually, it is set at a general level in the Preferences menu. 
    Here, you can set it for your image.     
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Another condition for the Dot-for-Dot to be effective is that the 
    image resolution is set to the screen resolution in the 
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-display">Preferences menu</link>.  
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    If your image is intended for a Web site, this option is suitable 
    but not if it is intended for printing.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande se trouve dans 
    <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Affichage/<accel>P</accel>oint pour point</guimenuitem>.
  </para>     
  <para lang="fr">
    Si cette option est activée (marquée par une coche), chaque pixel de 
    l'image correspondra à un pixel de l'écran, à condition bien sûr que 
    le rapport de zoom soit à 1:1. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    En fait, elle est réglée au niveau général dans le menu Préférences. 
    Ici, vous pouvez la régler pour votre image.  
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Une autre condition pour que le point-pour-point soit effectif, est 
    que la résolution des images soit réglée à la résolution de l'écran 
    dans le <link linkend="gimp-prefs-display">menu Préférences</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette option convient si votre image est destinée aux sites Web car ils sont 
    réglés par défaut à 72 dpi, mais pas si vous devez l'imprimer.
  </para>         

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该命令在
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>查看</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>点对点</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>。
  </para>     
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    切换是否以&quot;点对点&quot;方式查看。打开时，当缩放比率为 1:1 时，图像上每个像素都显示为屏幕上一个像素大小。
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    实际上，要使所有图像都使用，需要在首选项菜单中设置它。这里只是让当前图像使用点对点。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    另外一种使用点对点将比较有效的情况是在<link linkend="gimp-prefs-display">首选项菜单</link>设置了图像分辨率和屏幕分辨率相同。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当设计为网站使用的图像时，适合使用该选项，但不适合于打印。
  </para>
</sect2>
