<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-brush-dialog' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Brushes dialog</title>
  <title lang="cs">Dialog Stopy</title>
  <title lang='de'>Pinsel Dialog</title>
  <title lang="fr">Le dialogue des brosses</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">画笔对话框</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang="cs">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang='de'>Dialoge</primary>
    <primary lang='fr'>Dialogue</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Brushes</secondary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Stopy</secondary>
    <secondary lang='de'>Pinsel</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Brosses</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">画笔</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-brushes.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Brushes dialog
        </para>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Dialog Stopy
        </para>
        <para lang='zh_CN'>
          画笔对话框
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Ansicht des Pinseldialogs.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le dialogue des brosses
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Brushes dialog is used to select a brush, for use with
    painting tools:  see the <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-brushes'>Brushes</link> section for basic
    informmation on brushes and how they are used in GIMP.  The dialog
    also gives you access to several functions for 
    manipulating brushes.  You can select a brush by clicking on
    it in the list:  it will then be shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  A few dozen basic
    brushes come pre-installed with GIMP, along with a few assorted
    bizarre ones that mainly serve to show you the range of
    possibilities.  You can also create custom brushes using the Brush
    Editor, or by saving images in a special brush file format.
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Dialog Stopy slouží k výběru stopy pro kreslící nástroje,
    viz FIXME
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le dialogue des brosses sert à choisir une brosse pour l'utiliser 
    avec un des outils de peinture: voyez la section  <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-brushes'>Brosses</link> pour plus de détails.  Il 
    vous offre diverses fonctions de manipulation des brosses. Vous 
    sélectionnez une brosse en cliquant dessus; elle apparaît alors 
    dans la zone Brosse/Motif/Dégradé de la Boîte à outils. Une petite 
    douzaine de brosses sont fournies avec Gimp, certaines d'aspect 
    bizarre pour vous donner un exemple des possibilités offertes. 
    Vous pouvez aussi créer vos propres brosses avec l'Éditeur de 
    brosses, ou en enregistrant des images dans un format spécial. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    画笔对话框用作在使用涂画工具时选择一个画笔：请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-brushes'>画笔</link>这节以便了解画笔的基本信息以及如何在 GIMP 中使用。该对话框也提供对画笔进行处理的许多功能。通过在列表中点击来选择一个画笔：然后它将显示在工具箱的 画笔/图案/渐变 区域。GiMP 自带了一些基本画笔和少数主要是示范其可能性的怪异画笔。您也可以通过画笔编辑器或保存图像为特定的画笔格式来创建自定义画笔。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Brushes dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Dialog Stopy je dokovatelný; viz část
    <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dokování dialogů</link>.
    Lze ho vyvolat několika různými způsoby:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le dialogue des brosses est un dialogue attachable: voyez la 
    section <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogues et attachements</link>.
    Il peut être activé de différentes manières:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    画笔对话框是一个可停靠对话框；请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>。有多种方式开启它：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brus<accel>h</accel>es</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Z nabídky Panelu nástrojů:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogy</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Stopy</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        A partir du menu de la Boîte à outils:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogues</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>rosses</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">    
        在工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>画笔</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Create New Dock</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brushes, Patterns, and Gradients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        This gives you a dock containing three dialogs, with the
        Brushes dialog one of them.
      </para>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Z nabídky Panelu nástrojů:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogy</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Vytvořit nový dok</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Stopy, vzorky a přechody</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        Tímto příkazem se otevře dok se třemi dialogy, mezi nimiž
        jsou i Stopy.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        A partir du menu de la Boîte à outils:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogues</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Nouvelle fenêtre attachable</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brosses, Motifs et Dégradés</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        ce qui vous donne une fenêtre avec trois dialogues attachés 
        sous forme d'onglet, dont celui des brosses.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">    
        在工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>创建新停靠栏</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>画笔，图案和渐变</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
        将出现一个带三个对话框停靠栏，画笔对话框是其中一个。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>      
      <para lang='en'>    
        From the Toolbox, by clicking on the brush symbol in the
        Brush/Pattern/Gradient area.
      </para>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Z Panelu nástrojů kliknutím na ikonu aktivní stopy v části
        zobrazující aktivní stopu, vzorek a přechod.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        A partir de la Boîte à outils en cliquant sur le symbole de 
        brosse dans la zone Brosse/Motif/Dégradé.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        在工具箱的 画笔/图案/渐变 区域点击画笔标志。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>      
      <para lang='en'>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brus<accel>h</accel>es</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Z nabídky obrázku:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogy</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Stopy</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        A partir du menu image:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogues</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>rosses</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">    
        在图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>画笔</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>


    <listitem>      
      <para lang='en'>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brus<accel>h</accel>es</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang='cs'>    
        Z nabídky odrážky jakéhokoliv dokovatelného dialogu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Přidat odrážku</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Stopy</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        A partir du menu d'onglet, dans toute fenêtre attachable:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Ajouter un onglet</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>rosses</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">    
        在任何可停靠对话框的页签菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>添加页签</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>画笔</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>      
      <para lang='en'>    
        From the Tool Options dialog for any of the paint tools, by
        clicking on the Brush icon button.  Note that, depending on your
        Preferences, a brush selected in this way may only apply
        to the currently active tool, not to other paint tools.  See
        the <link linkend='gimp-prefs-tool-options'>Tool Option
        Preferences</link> section for more information.   
      </para>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Z dialogu Volby nástrojů kteréhokoliv kreslícího nástroje kliknutím na
        ikonu aktivní stopy. Uvědomte si ale, že v závislosti na nastavení
        vašeho Gimpu, může být takto vybraná stopa přiřazena jen aktivnímu
        nástroji a nikoliv nástrojům ostatním. Viz FIXME
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        A partir du dialogue Options de l'outil, pour tous les outils 
        de peinture, en cliquant sur l'icône Brosse. Notez que, selon 
        le réglage de vos Préférences, une brosse choisie de cette 
        façon ne s'appliquera qu'à l'outil en cours et non pas à tous.
        Voyez <link linkend='gimp-prefs-tool-options'>Préférences des
        outils</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        在任何涂画工具的工具选项对话框中点击画笔图标按键。注意，根据您的首选项，通过这样的方式选择一个画笔可能只应用在当前活动画笔，而不是包括其它涂画工具上。请看<link linkend='gimp-prefs-tool-options'>工具选项参数</link>来获取更多信息。
     </para>
   </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>
    <title lang="cs">Režim mřížky a seznamu</title>
    <title lang="fr">Mode Grille et Mode Liste</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">阵列/列表模式</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the brush shapes are laid out in a rectangular
      array, making it easy to see many at once and find the one you
      are looking for.  In List mode, the shapes are lined up in a
      list, with the names beside them.  
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      V nabídce odrážky můžete pomocí položek
      <guimenuitem>Zobrazit jako seznam</guimenuitem> a
      <guimenuitem>Zobrazit jako mřížku</guimenuitem>
      přepínat mezi dvěma režimy zobrazení. V režimu mřížky jsou tvary stop
      zobrazeny v pravidelné pravoúhlé síti, což šetří místo a usnadňuje
      orientaci. V režimu seznamu jsou tvary stop zobrazeny i se svými jmény.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans le menu d'onglet du Dialogue des brosses, vous pouvez 
      choisir entre <guimenuitem>Voir comme une liste</guimenuitem> 
      et <guimenuitem>Voir comme une grille</guimenuitem>. En mode 
      grille, les brosses sont affichées dans une grille, permettant 
      une vue d'ensemble. En mode Liste, les brosses sont alignées 
      verticalement avec leur nom.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在页签菜单中，您能在<guimenuitem>以阵列方式列查看</guimenuitem>和<guimenuitem>以列表方式查看</guimenuitem>间选择。阵列模式中，画笔形状按矩形阵列排列，这样一次能看到多个并容易寻找。列表模式中，形状在列表中排成一列，其名字对应地列在一旁。
    </para>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Brushes dialog (Grid mode)</title>
    <title lang="cs">Použití dialogu Stopy (režim mřížky)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Utilisation du dialogue des brosses (en mode grille)</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用画笔对话框(阵列模式)</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      At the top of the dialog appears the name of the currently
      selected brush, and its size in pixels.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      V horní části dialogu je zobrazeno jméno aktivní stopy a její velikost v
      pixelech.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En haut de la fenêtre apparaît le nom de la brosse sélectionnée 
      avec sa taille en pixels.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在对话框上方显示当前选择画笔的名字和画笔的像素大小。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the center appears a grid view of all available brushes, with
      the currently selected one outlined.  If you see a little "+" to
      the right of a brush, it means the brush is actually larger than
      it appears.  If you see a little red triangle, it means the
      brush is an animated brush, also known as an "image hose".
      Clicking on a brush causes it to be selected as GIMP's current
      brush.  Double-clicking activates the Brush Editor.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Ve střední části jsou zobrazeny všechny dostupné stopy (možná budete
      ale muset používat posuvník), aktivní stopa je orámována. Pokud je u
      stopy zobrazeno malé plus znamená to, že je stopa větší, než v dialogu
      vypadá. Pokud je u stopy zobrazen malý červený trojúhelníček, znamená
      to, že se jedná o animovanou stopu, tzv image hose (FIXME). Kliknutím na
      stopu ji aktivujete. Dvojitým kliknutím otevřete editor stop.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Au centre se trouve une grille contenant toutes les brosses 
      disponibles. En cliquant sur l'une d'elles, vous en faites la 
      brosse active qui apparaît dans la zone Brosse/Motif/Dégradé de 
      la Boîte à outils.  
      </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      正中则是所有可用画笔以阵列方式排列，用方框显示当前被选中的画笔。如果在画笔右边看到一个小“+”，表示实际中画笔比显示的要大。如果看到一个红色三角，表示这是一个动画画笔，也被叫作“图像管”。点击一个画笔使其成为 GIMP 当前画笔，而双击则开启画笔对话框。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Below the grid appears a scale entry for "Spacing", which is the
      distance between consecutive brush marks when you trace out a
      brushstroke with the pointer.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Pod stopami je posuvník <guilabel>Rozestup</guilabel>, který umožňuje
      nastavitvzdálenost mezi jednotlivými otisky stopy při malování.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En dessous de la grille se trouve un curseur d'
      <emphasis>Espacement</emphasis>, permettant de régler la 
      distance entre les «coups de tampons» successifs de la brosse 
      quand vous peignez (une brosse peint en fait par coups de tampon 
      successifs). 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      阵列下方的是输入“间隔”值的地方，它表示用光标画一个连续笔划时相邻画笔印记间的距离。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The buttons at the bottom of the dialog allow you to operate on
      brushes in several ways:
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Tlačítka v dolní části dialogu umožňují rozličné operace se stopami:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les boutons en bas de la fenêtre vous permettent d'agir sur la 
      brosse de différentes façons:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      对话框底部的按钮允许您用多种方式操作画笔：
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Edit Brush</term>
        <term lang="cs">Upravit stopu</term>
        <term lang="fr">Édition</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">编辑画笔</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This activates the <link linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Brush
            Editor</link>.  Pressing the button will open the Editor
            for any brush.  It only works, however, for parametric
            brushes:  for any other type, the Editor will show you the
            brush but not allow you to do anything with it.  
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            FIXME
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce bouton active l' <link 
            linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Éditeur de brosses</link>.
            En fait, il ne marche qu'avec les brosses paramétriques. 
            Avec les autres, l'éditeur vous montre la brosse mais ne 
            vous permet pas d'agir dessus.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            它将开启<link linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>画笔编辑器</link>。按下按钮将开启对任何画笔的编辑器。不过它只对参数画笔有作用：对于其它类型，编辑器只显示画笔而您不能对它做任何事。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">New Brush</term>
        <term lang="cs">Nová stopa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Nouveau</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">新建画笔</term>

        <listitem>
          <anchor id='gimp-brush-new' />
          <para lang="en">
            This creates a new parametric brush, initializes it with a 
            small fuzzy round shape, and opens the Brush Editor so
            that you can modify it.  The new brush is automatically
            saved in your personal <filename>brushes</filename> folder.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Vytvoří novou parametrickou stopu a otevře Editor stop, ve kterém
            ji můžete nastavit. Nová stopa bude automaticky uložena ve vašem
            oѕobním adresáři <filename>brushes</filename>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce bouton crée une nouvelle brossse paramétrique, 
            initialisée par un petit cercle noir, plein et flou, et 
            ouvre l'Éditeur de brosses pour le modifier. La nouvelle 
            brosse sera automatiquement enregistrée dans votre dossier 
            parsonnel «brushes».
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            它将新建一个初始的带模糊边缘圆形的参数画笔，并开启画笔编辑器让您修改。新建的画笔将自动保存在您的个人 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Duplicate Brush</term>
        <term lang="cs">Duplikovat stopu</term>
        <term lang="fr">Dupliquer</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">复制画笔</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id='gimp-brush-duplicate' />
          <para lang="en">
            This button is only enabled if the currently selected
            brush is a parametric brush.  If so, the brush is
            duplicated, and the Brush Editor is opened so that you can
            modify the copy.  The result is automatically
            saved in your personal <filename>brushes</filename> folder.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Toto tlačítko je aktivní pouze tehdy, pokud je právě vybraná
            parametrická stopa. FIXME
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce bouton n'est actif que s'il s'agit d'une brosse 
            paramétrique. La brosse est alors dupliquée et l'Éditeur 
            de brosse est ouvert pour la modifier. Le résultat est 
            enregistré automatiquement dans votre dossir personnel 
            de brosses.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该按钮只有在当前选中画笔是一个参数画笔时才有效。此时，画笔被复制，并且画笔编辑器打开让您修改其拷贝。然后自动保存在您个人的 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Delete Brush</term>
        <term lang="cs">Odstranit stopu</term>
        <term lang="fr">Supprimer</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">删除画笔</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id='gimp-brush-delete' />
          <para lang="en" >
            This removes all traces of the brush, both from the dialog
            and the folder where its file is stored, if you have
            permission to do so.  It asks for confirmation before
            doing anything.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Odstraní stopu z dialogu, ale i z adresáře, ve kterém je uložena
            (pokud máte patřičná oprávnění). Před skutečným smazáním stopy
            budete požádáni o potvrzení vašeho úmyslu.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Supprime la brosse, de la fenêtre et du disque dur. 
            Confirmation vous est demandée.  
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            它从对话框和保存文件的文件夹中将画笔删除，当然您要有相应的权限。在执行任何动作之前，它会要您确认。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Refresh Brushes</term>
        <term lang="cs">Aktualizovat stopy</term>
        <term lang="fr">Rafraîchir</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">刷新画笔</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id='gimp-brush-refresh' />
          <para lang="en" >
            If you add brushes to your personal
            <filename>brushes</filename> folder or any other folder in
            your brush search path, by some means
            other than the Brush Editor, this button
            causes the list to be reloaded, so that the new entries
            will be available in the dialog.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud do vašeho osobního adresáře <filename>brushes</filename>
            nebo jakéhokoliv jiného adresáře ve kterém jsou hledány stopy
            přidáte nové stopy jinak, než pomocí Editoru stop, musíte
            tímto tlačítkem stopy aktualizovat, aby se načetly do dialogu.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce bouton vous permet d'inclure dans la fenêtre de 
            dialogue la ou les brosses que vous avez ajoutées, sans 
            qu'il soit besoin de re-démarrer Gimp.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该按钮使列表被重新加载，这样您在个人 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹或任何画笔搜索路径添加的画笔，就会立即在对话框中可用。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <para lang='en'>
      The functions performed by these buttons can also be accessed
      from the dialog pop-up menu, activated by right-clicking
      anywhere in the brush grid/list, or by choosing the top item,
      <guisubmenu>Brushes menu</guisubmenu>, from the dialog Tab menu..  
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Funkce těchto tlačítek jsou dostupné také z kontextového menu dialogu
      Stopy, které můžete vyvolat kliknutím pravého tlačítka myši kdekoliv
      v seznamu (či mřížce) stop, nebo volbou první položky
      <guisubmenu>Menu Stopy</guisubmenu> z nabídky odrážky dialogu
      Stopy.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      On peut également accéder aux fonctions de ces boutons par le 
      menu local obtenu par clic droit sur la fenêtre ou par le 
      sous-menu Brosse du menu d'onglets.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      通过这些按钮实现的功能也可以在对话框中弹出菜单中得到：在画笔阵列/列表中用右键点击其中，或在对话框页签菜单中选最上方的<guisubmenu>画笔菜单</guisubmenu>...
    </para>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Brushes dialog (List mode)</title>
    <title lang="cs">Použití dialogu Stopy (režim seznamu)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Utilisation du Dialogue des brosses (en mode Liste)</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用画笔对话框(列表模式)</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-brushes-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The Brushes dialog (List view)
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject lang="cs">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-brushes-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para>
            Dialog Stopy (režim seznamu)
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject lang="fr">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-brushes-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para>
      Le Dialogue des brosses (mode Liste)	    
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-brushes-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para>
	    画笔对话框(列表查看)
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      For the most part, the dialog works the same way in List mode as
      in Grid mode, with one exception:
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Dialog Stopy pracuje v režimu seznamu stejně, jako v režimu mřížky, s
      jednou výjimkou:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En mode Liste, ce dialogue fonctionne comme en mode Grille, avec 
      une exception:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在大部分情况下，对话框在列表模式下的工作方式和在阵列模式下相同，不过有一种例外：
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      If you <emphasis>double-click</emphasis> on the name of a brush,
      you will be able to edit it.  Note, however, that you are only
      allowed to change the names of brushes that you have created
      or installed yourself, not the ones that come pre-installed with
      GIMP.  If you try to rename a pre-installed brush, you will be
      able to edit the name, but as soon as you hit return or click
      somewhere else, the name will revert to its original value.  It
      is a general rule that you cannot alter the resources that GIMP
      pre-installs for you: brushes, patterns, gradients, etc; only
      ones that you create yourself.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Pokud <emphasis>dvojitě kliknete</emphasis> na jméno stopy, můžete ho
      upravit. Můžete však měnit jen jména těch stop, které jste sami
      vytvořili nebo nainstalovali, nikoliv stop, které jsou součástí
      instalace Gimpu. Pokud se pokusíte změnit jméno takové stopy, nepodaří
      se vám to, vrátí se automaticky k původnímu jakmile editaci jména
      ukončíte. Je to obecným pravidlem Gimpu: nelze měnit zdroje (stopy,
      vzorky, přechody atd.), které jsou součástí instalace, ale pouze ty,
      které sami vytvoříte.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un double clic sur le nom d'une brosse permet d'éditer et de 
      modifier ce nom, à condition qu'il s'agisse d'une brosse 
      personnelle.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      如果<emphasis>双击</emphasis>画笔的名字，您可以编辑它。注意，您只允许改变您自己创建或安装的画笔的名字，GIMP 自带的则不行，如果您尝试给自带的画笔重命名，您虽然可以编辑它的名字，不过当敲下回车或点其它地方时，其名字就会回到原来的名字。不能更改 GIMP 自带的资源是一个基本原则：画笔，图案，渐变等；只能改变您自建的。
    </para>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='gimp-brush-editor-dialog' >
    <title lang="en">Brush Editor</title>
    <title lang="cs">Editor stop</title>  
    <title lang="fr">L'Éditeur de brosse</title>  
    <title lang="zh_CN">画笔编辑器</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      FIXME: Writing of this section is deferred until the user
      interface for this dialog stabilizes.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      FIXME
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Rédaction en attente de stabilisation de l'interface utilisateur 
      de cet éditeur. 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      FIXME
    </para>

  </simplesect>
</sect1>
