<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-buffers-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Buffers dialog</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Buffers</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-buffers.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Buffers dialog
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    Buffers are temporary repositories for image data, created when
    you cut or copy part of a drawable (a layer, layer mask, etc.).
    When you use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    or
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    the data goes into the Global Buffer.  When you use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Buffer</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem></guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Buffers dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tool Options for the Text tool.  If you click on the
      "Font" button, a Font-selector pops up.  In the lower right
      corner is a button that, if pressed, brings up the Fonts
      dialog. 
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-buffers-grid.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Buffers dialog (Grid View)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu for the Buffers dialog, you can choose between
      <guimenuitem>View as Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as
      List</guimenuitem>.   In Grid mode, the buffers are laid out in a
      rectangular array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically,
      with each row showing an example of the appearance of the font
      ("Aa"), followed by the name of the font.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Buffers dialog</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a buffer by clicking
      on it:  this font will then be used by the Text tool.  If
      instead of clicking and releasing, you hold down the 
      left mouse button with the pointer positioned over the font
      example ("Aa"), a window showing a larger text example will
      pop up ("Pack my box with five dozen liquor jugs.").
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Pressing the button at the bottom of the dialog causes the
      system font list to be rescanned.  This may be useful if you add
      new fonts while GIMP is running, and want to make them
      accessible for the Text tool.  You can also cause the font list
      to be rescanned by right-clicking in the font display, and
      selecting "Rescan Font List" from the menu that pops up (it is
      actually the only option in the menu).
    </para>

    <note lang='en'>
      You can change the size of the buffer previews in the dialog using
      the "Preview Size" submenu of the dialog's Tab menu.
    </note>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
