<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-buffer-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Buffers dialog</title>
  <title lang="fr">Tampon</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Buffers</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Tampon</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-buffers.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Buffers dialog
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    Buffers are temporary repositories for image data, created when
    you cut or copy part of a drawable (a layer, layer mask, etc.).
    When you use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    or
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    the data goes into the Global Buffer.  When you use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Buffer</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Copy Named</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    or
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Buffer</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Copy Named</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    a dialog pops up asking you to name a buffer to store the data
      in.  There is no hard limit on the number of named buffers you
      can create, although, of course, each one consumes a share of
      memory. 
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Le Tampon est un presse-papier perfectionné qui permet de 
    conserver plusieurs documents, en général des sélections ou des 
    calques et de les récupérer ensuite. Il est commun à toutes les 
    images ouvertes. Il disparaît quand Gimp est fermé.
  </para>  

  <para lang='en'>
    The Buffers dialog shows you the contents of all existing named
    buffers, and allows you to operate on them in several ways.  It
    also shows you, at the top, the contents of the Global Buffer, but
    this is merely a display:  you can't do anything with it.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Buffers dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tool Options for the Text tool.  If you click on the
      "Font" button, a Font-selector pops up.  In the lower right
      corner is a button that, if pressed, brings up the Fonts
      dialog. 
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <caution lang='en'>
    Named buffers are not saved across sessions.  The only way to save
    their contents is to paste them into images.
  </caution>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-buffers-grid.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Buffers dialog (Grid View)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu for the Buffers dialog, you can choose between
      <guimenuitem>View as Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as
      List</guimenuitem>.   In Grid mode, the buffers are laid out in a
      rectangular array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically,
      with each row showing a preview of the contents of the buffer,
      its name, and its pixel dimensions.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Buffers dialog</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-buffers-menu.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Buffers Menu
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      Clicking on a buffer in the display area makes it the active
      buffer, i. e., the one that will be used for paste commands
      executed with the Buffers Menu or the buttons at the bottom of
      the dialog.  Double-clicking on a buffer causes its contents to
      be pasted to the active image; this is a quick way of executing
      the "Paste Buffer" command.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      At the bottom of the dialog are four buttons.  The operations
      they perform can also be accessed from the Buffers Menu, and
      from the 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Buffer</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      submenu in the image menu.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id='gimp-buffer-paste' />
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Paste Buffer</title>
          This command pastes the contents of the selected buffer into
          the active image, as a floating selection.  The only
          difference between this and the ordinary <link
          linkend='gimp-edit-paste'>Paste</link> command is
          that it uses the selected buffer rather than the global
          clipboard buffer.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id='gimp-buffer-paste-into' />
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Paste Buffer Into</title>
          This command pastes the contents of the selected buffer into
          the active image's selection, as a floating selection.
          The only difference between this and the ordinary <link
          linkend='gimp-edit-paste-into'>Paste Into</link>
          command is that it uses the selected buffer rather
          than the global clipboard buffer.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <anchor id='gimp-buffer-paste-as-new' />
       <formalpara lang='en'>
           <title>Paste Buffer as New</title>
          This command creates a new single-layer image out of the
          contents of the selected buffer. 
          The only difference between this and the ordinary <link
          linkend='gimp-edit-paste-as-new'>Paste as New</link>
          command is that it uses the selected buffer rather
          than the global clipboard buffer.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <anchor id='gimp-buffer-delete' />
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Delete Buffer</title>
          This command deletes the selected named buffer, no questions
          asked.  You cannot delete the Global Buffer.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note lang='en'>
      You can change the size of the buffer previews in the dialog using
      the "Preview Size" submenu of the dialog's Tab menu.
    </note>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
