<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-02-20 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-04-29 lexa: made docbook compliant
  2006-02-25 romanofski fixed broken image references
-->
<sect3 id="gimp-channel-mask">
  <title>Selection masks</title>
  <anchor id="dialogs-selection-masks" xreflabel="Selection masks"/>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Masks</primary>
    <secondary>Selection mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selection</primary>
    <secondary>Selection mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Masks</primary>
    <secondary>Channel mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Channel</primary>
    <secondary>Channel mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Masks</primary>
    <secondary>Quick mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>A selection composed out of channels.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/channel-masks-example-dialog.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/channel-masks-example-example.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    Channels can be used to save and restore your selections.
    In the Channels dialog you can see a thumbnail representing the selection.
    Selection Masks are a graphical way to build selections into a gray level
    channel where white pixels are selected and black pixels are not selected.
    Therefore gray pixels are partially selected. You can think of them as
    feathering the selection, a smooth transition between selected and not
    selected. This is important to avoid the ugly pixelization effect when you
    fill the selection or when you erase its content after isolating a subject
    from background.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Creating Selection Masks</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There are several ways to initialize a selection mask.
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                From the main menu
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Save to Channel</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                if there is an active selection.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                In the image window the bottom-left
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-quick-mask-off-symbolic.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                button creates a
                <link linkend="gimp-quick-mask">Quick Mask</link>; the content
                will be initialized with the active selection.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                From the Channels dialog, when you click on the
                <guilabel>New channel</guilabel> button or from the context
                menu. When created, this Selection mask appears in the
                Channels dialog, named <quote>Selection maskcopy</quote> with
                a queuing number. You can change this by using the context
                menu that you get by right-clicking on the channel.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect4>
    <title>Using Selection Masks</title>
    <para>
      Once the channel is initialized, selected (highlighted in blue), visible
      (eye-icon in the dialog), and displayed as you want (color and opacity
      attributes), you can start to work with all the paint tools. The colors
      used are important. If you paint with some color other than white, gray,
      or black, the color Value (luminosity) will be used to define a gray
      (medium, light, or dark). When your mask is painted, you can transform
      it to a selection by clicking on the
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      button (<link linkend="gimp-channel-selection-replace">Channel to
      Selection</link>) or from the
      <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">context menu</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can work in selection masks not only with the paint tool but also
      with other tools. For instance, you can use the selection tools to fill
      areas uniformly with gradients or patterns. By adding many selection
      masks in your list you can easily compose very complex selections. One
      can say that a selection mask is to a selection as a layer is to an
      image.
    </para>
    <caution>
      <para>
        As long as a selection mask is activated you are working in the mask
        and not in the image. To work in the image you have to deactivate all
        selection masks. Don't forget also to stop displaying masks in the
        image by removing the eye icon. Check also that all RGB and Alpha
        channels are activated and displayed in the image.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>
</sect3>
