<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-20 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-04-29 lexa: made docbook compliant
  2006-02-25 romanofski fixed broken image references
-->
<sect3 id="dialogs-selection-masks" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;lt;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect3info lang="en;de;es;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-27</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-25</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-20</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-27</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect3info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Selection masks</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Masky výběru</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Auswahlmasken</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Máscaras de selección</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Masques de sélection</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Maschere di selezione</phrase>
    <phrase lang="lt">Pažymėjimo kaukės</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Markeringsmasker</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Маски выделения</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">选区蒙板</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Masks</primary><secondary>Selection mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selection</primary><secondary>Selection mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Masks</primary><secondary>Channel mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Channel</primary><secondary>Channel mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Masks</primary><secondary>Quick mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Auswahlmaske</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Kanalmaske</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Schnellmaske</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Auswahl</primary></indexterm>


  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Máscaras</primary><secondary>Máscaras de selección</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Masques</primary><secondary>Masque de sélection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélection</primary><secondary>Masque de sélection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Masques</primary><secondary>Masque de canal</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Canal</primary><secondary>Masque de canal</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Masques</primary><secondary>Masque rapide</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Kaukės</primary><secondary>Pažymėjimo kaukė</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Pažymėjimas</primary><secondary>Pažymėjimo kaukė</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Kaukės</primary><secondary>Kanalo kaukė</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Kanalas</primary><secondary>Kanalo kaukė</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Kaukės</primary><secondary>Greita kaukė</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Маски</primary><secondary>Маска выделения</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Masker</primary><secondary>Markeringsmasker</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;lt;ru;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">A selection composed out of channels.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Eine Auswahl erstellt aus verschiedenen Kanälen
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Una selección compuesta por varios canales.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Une sélection composée de plusieurs canaux</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Iš kanalų sudarytas pažymėjimas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Ei markering laga av kanalar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Составленное вне каналов выделение</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;de;es;fr;it;lt;no;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    Channels can be used to save and restore your selections. Clicking on the
    <guilabel>Quick mask</guilabel> button on the
    <link linkend="gimp-image-window">Image window</link>
    automatically creates a new channel called <guilabel>Qmask</guilabel>
    and saves the displayed active selection to a thumbnail in front of the
    channel.There are many selection tools in GIMP like rectangular
    selection tool or fuzzy selection for continuous selections. Selection
    Masks are a graphical way to build selections into a gray level channel
    where white pixels are selected and black pixels are not selected.
    Therefore gray pixels are partially selected. You can think of them as
    feathering the selection, a smooth transition between selected and not
    selected. This is important to avoid the ugly pixelization effect when you
    fill the selection or when you erase its content after isolating a subject
    from background.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Kanály lze používat k ukládání výběrů. Kliknutí na tlačítko rychlé masky
    v <link linkend="gimp-image-window">Okně obrázku</link> automaticky
    vytvoří nový kanál nazvaný <guilabel>Rychlá maska</guilabel>. Ikona
    před jménem kanálu zobrazuje náhled výběru. V gimpu je k dispozici řada
    nástrojů pro výběr, jako je výběr obdélníku nebo volný výběr. Maky výběru
    jsou grafickým znázorněním výběru v podobě šedého kanálu, kde bílé pixely
    jsou vybrané a černé nikoliv. Šedé pixely jsou vybrány částečně. Lze si je
    představit jako prolnutí výběru, plynulý přechod mezi vybranými a
    nevybranými oblastmi. To je důležitá obrana proti ošklivým artefaktům při
    vyplňování výběru barvou nebo jeho vymazáním.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Kanäle können benutzt werden, um Auswahlen zu speichern und wieder
    herzustellen. Es gibt zahlreiche
    <link linkend='gimp-tools-selection'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link>
    in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, mit denen neue Auswahlen erstellt werden
    können. Auch <link linkend='gimp-qmask'>Schnellmasken</link>
    können in einen Kanal gespeichert werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Los canales se pueden emplear para conservar selecciones.  Al hacer clic
    sobre el botón <guilabel>Máscara rápida</guilabel> de la <link
    linkend="gimp-image-window">ventana de la imagen</link>, se crea
    automáticamente un nuevo canal llamado <guilabel>Máscara rápida</guilabel>
    y la selección que había antes se muestra como una miniatura en el
    diálogo.  Hay varias herramientas de selección, como la selección
    rectangular, o la varita mágica para seleccionar áreas contiguas de color.
    Las máscaras de selección proporcionan una manera gráfica para construir
    selecciones sobre un canal a escala de grises, en donde el blanco
    significa seleccionado, el negro deseleccionado, y los distintos niveles
    de gris son selecciones parciales.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les canaux peuvent être utilisés pour sauvegarder, restituer et modifier
    vos sélections. Les Masques de sélection, ou masques de canaux, créés dans
    la partie basse de la Fenêtre des canaux, sont une représentation d'une
    sélection en niveaux de gris, où les pixels blancs sont sélectionnés et
    les pixels noirs ne le sont pas. Les pixels gris sont partiellement
    sélectionnés. Nous allons voir comment créer et utiliser ces masques de
    sélections.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    I canali si possono utilizzare per salvare e poi ripristinare le selezioni.
    Facendo un clic sul pulsante della <guilabel>Maschera veloce</guilabel>
    nella <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="gimp-image-window" -->finestra immagine<!--/link-->
    viene creato automaticamente un nuovo canale chiamato <guilabel>Maschera
      veloce</guilabel> e la selezione attiva visualizzata viene salvata in una
    miniatura prima del canale. Per creare delle selezioni continue ci sono
    molti strumenti in Gimp, come la selezione rettangolare o la bacchetta
    magica. Le maschere di selezione rappresentano un modo di costruire le
    selezioni graficamente all'interno di un canale in scala di grigi, dove i
    pixel bianchi sono selezionati ed i pixel neri sono quelli non selezionati.
    Quindi i pixel grigi sono parzialmente selezionati. Si può pensare ad essi
    come ad una sfumatura della selezione, una transizione graduale tra ciò che
    è selezionato e ciò che non lo è. Questo è importante per evitare il brutto
    effetto scalinato dei pixel quando si riempie una selezione o quando si
    cancella il suo contenuto dopo aver isolato un soggetto dallo sfondo.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Kanalus galima naudoti norint išsaugoti ir atkurti savo pažymėjimus.
    Spustelėjus
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Paveikslėlio lange</link>
    esantį mygtuką <guilabel>Greita kaukė</guilabel> automatiškai
    sukuriamas naujas kanalas <guilabel>Greita kaukė</guilabel> ir rodomas
    aktyvus pažymėjimas išsaugomas miniatiūroje, rodomoje prieš kanalą.
    Programoje GIMP yra daug pažymėjimo įrankių, pvz., stačiakampio
    pažymėjimo įrankis arba neaiškaus pažymėjimo įrankis, skirtų
    vientisiems pažymėjimams. Pažymėjimo kaukės – tai grafinis būdas sukurti
    pažymėjimus pilkumo lygių kanale, kur balti pikseliai yra pažymėti, o
    kur juodi – nepažymėti. Taigi pilki pikseliai yra dalinai pažymėti.
    Juos galite įsivaizduoti kaip pažymėjimo kraštų išliejimą, vientisą
    perėjimą tarp pažymėtų pikselių ir nepažymėtų. Tai yra svarbu norint
    išvengti negražaus pikseliavimo efekto, kai užpildote pažymėjimą arba,
    kai ištrinate jo turinį atskyrę subjektą nuo fono.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Du kan bruke kanalar for å lagre og henta fram igjen markeringar. Når du
    klikkar på knappen <guilabel>Snarmaske</guilabel> i <link
    linkend="gimp-image-window">Biletvindauget</link>, blir det
    automatisk oppretta ein ny kanal med namnet
    <guilabel>Snarmaske</guilabel>. Denne blir vist i kanaldialogen som
    ein miniatyr framføre kanalen. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har mange
    markeringsverktøy som kan brukast for å lage ulike former for
    markeringar.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Markeringsmaskene blir brukte for å bestemma kor mykje markeringa skal
    vere markert. Kanskje ei merkeleg formulering, men det betyr kort og godt
    at alle område av maska som er kvite blir fullstendig markerte. Svarte
    område er område som er fullstendig umarkerte, og grå område er meir eller
    mindre markerte. Du kan altså bruke ulike grader av grått for å lage mjuke
    overgangar mellom markert og umarkert. Dette kan vere til hjelp for å
    unngå merkverdige effektar når du fyller ei markering eller når du viskar
    ut innhaldet etter å ha isolert eit objekt frå bakgrunnen.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Выделение областей можно сохранять в канале. При нажатии на кнопку
    <guilabel>Быстрая маска</guilabel>, которая находится в
    <link linkend="gimp-image-window">окне изображения</link>,
    автоматически создается новый канал, который называется
    <guilabel>Быстрая маска</guilabel>. В нем сохраняется текущее выделение
    области. В GIMP есть много инструментов для выделения области -
    прямоугольное выделение, свободное выделение и т.п. Маски выделения
    - это инструмент для графического отображения обасти выделения: белые
    пикселы соответствуют выделенной области, черные - невыделенной, а
    серые - частично выделенной (например, при размытом выделении).
    Таким образом, выделение области отображается в канале градациями
    серого.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    通道可以保存和恢复您的选区。点击<link linkend="gimp-image-window">图像窗口</link>的<guilabel>快速蒙板</guilabel>按键会自动新建一个叫作<guilabel>Qmask</guilabel>的通道，并将显示的当前选区保存为通道前的一个缩略图上。GIMP 中有很多像矩形选择或模糊选择这样的选择工具。选区蒙板是一种能将选区放入一个灰阶通道的方法，其中选中的为白色像素，未选中的为黑色像素，而灰色像素则表示部分选中。您可以把它们看作被羽化的选区，是选中和未选中之间的过渡。这对在您填充选区或在从背景中分离一个物体后删除其内容时，避免产生的丑陋的格删化现象非常重要。
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Creating Selection Masks</term>
      <term lang="cs">Vytvoření masky výběru</term>
      <term lang="de">Erstellen von Auswahlmasken</term>
      <term lang="es">Creación de una máscara de selección</term>
      <term lang="fr">Création d'un masque de sélection</term>
      <term lang="it">Creazione delle maschere di selezione</term>
      <term lang="lt">Pažymėjimo kaukių kūrimas</term>
      <term lang="no">Å opprette markeringsmasker</term>
      <term lang="ru">Создание маски выделения</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">创建选区蒙板</term>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          There are several ways to initialize a selection mask.  From the
          image window menu
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>S</accel>elect</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Save to <accel>C</accel>hannel</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          if there is an active selection.  From the image window
          the bottom-left button creates a <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quick
            Mask</link>; the content will be initialized with the active
          selection.  From the channel dialog, when you click on the
          <guilabel>New channel</guilabel> button or from the context menu.
          When created, this Selection mask appears in the Channel dialog,
          named <quote>Selection mask copy</quote> with a queuing number.
          You can change this by using the context menu that you get by
          right-clicking on the channel.
        </para>

        <para lang="cs">
          Existuje řada způsobů, jak vytvořit masku výběru. Z nabídky obrázku
          můžete, pokud existuje aktivní výběr, zvolit
          <guimenuitem>Vybrat</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>Uložit do
            kanálu</guimenuitem>. Tlačítko v levém dolním rohu okna obrázku
          vytvoří <link linkend="gimp-qmask">rychlou masku</link>, jejíž obsah
          je vytvořen z aktivního výběru. Z dialogu kanálů kliknutím na
          <guilabel>Nový kanál</guilabel> nebo kontextové nabídky.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Erstellen Sie eine Auswahl mit einen <link
          linkend='gimp-tools-selection'>Auswahlwerkzeug</link>.  Danach
          überführen Sie die erstellte Auswahl in einen Kanal.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Benutzen Sie dafür über das Bildmenü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>In <accel>K</accel>anal speichern</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Danach erscheint ein neuer Kanal mit einem Miniaturbild im
          Kanaldialog.  Standardmäßig ist die erstellte Auswahlmaske nicht
          sichtbar; dem Kanal fehlt das gesetzte <link
          linkend='channel-attributes'>Augensymbol</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Möchten Sie die gespeicherte Auswahl aus dem Kanal wiederherstellen,
          benutzen Sie dazu die Schaltfläche
          <link linkend='gimp-channel-selection-add'>Auswahl aus Kanal</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          Hay varias maneras de crear una máscara de selección.  Desde el menú
          de la ventana de la imagen, siguiendo
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>S</accel>eleccionar</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Guardar en c<accel>a</accel>nal</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          si hay una selección activa.  Desde el botón que se halla en la
          esquina inferior izquierda de la ventana de la imagen, se crea la
          <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Máscara rápida</link>, y su contenido se
          inicializa con la selección activa.  Desde el diálogo
          <quote>Canales</quote>, haciendo clic sobre el botón <guilabel>Canal
          nuevo</guilabel>, o desde su menú contextual.  Una vez creada, la
          máscara aparece en el diálogo <quote>Canales</quote>, con el nombre
          <quote>Copia de Máscara de selección</quote>, posiblemente seguido
          de un número.  Puede cambiarle el nombre desde el menú contextual
          que se obtiene haciendo clic derecho sobre el canal.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Il existe plusieurs méthodes pour initialiser un masque de
          sélection.  Depuis le menu d'image
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Sélection</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Enregistrer dans un canal</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          disponible si vous avez une sélection active. Depuis le bouton au
          bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image qui va créer un <link
          linkend="gimp-qmask">Masque rapide</link> dont le contenu sera
          initialisé avec la sélection active. Depuis le dialogue des
          canaux en cliquant sur le bouton <guibutton>Nouveau
            canal</guibutton> ou depuis le menu contextuel obtenu par
          clic-droit sur un canal. Une fois créé, le masque de sélection
          apparaît dans la fenêtre de dialogue des canaux avec le nom
          <quote>Copie de masque de sélection</quote> et un numéro d'ordre.
          Vous pouvez changer ce nom en utilisant le menu contextuel obtenu
          par clic droit sur le bandeau du canal.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Ci sono diversi modi per creare una maschera di selezione. Se è
          attiva una selezione, nel menu della finestra immagine è
          disponibile la voce:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>S</accel>eleziona</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Salva nel <accel>C</accel>anale</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
          Il pulsante in basso a sinistra nella finestra dell'immagine crea una
          <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Maschera veloce</link>; il cui contenuto
          iniziale sarà quello della selezione attiva. Dalla finestra dei
          canali quando si fa clic sul pulsante <guilabel>Nuovo canale</guilabel>
          o dal menu contestuale.
        </para>

        <para lang="lt">
          Pažymėjimo kaukę galima inicializuoti keliais būdais. Spustelėjus
          paveikslėlio lango meniu esančią komandą
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Žy<accel>m</accel>ėjimas</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Išsaugoti į <accel>k</accel>analą</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
          jeigu yra aktyvus pažymėjimas. Spustelėjus paveikslėlio lango
          apatiniame kairiajame kampe esantį mygtuką sukuriama
          <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Greita kaukė</link>; turinys bus
          inicializuotas su aktyviu pažymėjimu. Kanalų dialoge,
          spustelėjus mygtuką <guilabel>Naujas kanalas</guilabel>, arba
          kontekstiniame meniu. Sukūrus ši Pažymėjimo kaukė rodoma
          Kanalų dialoge, pavadinimu <quote>Pažymėjimo kaukės kopija</quote>
          bei gale pridėtu skaičiumi. Tą galite pakeisti naudodamiesi
          kontekstiniu meniu, kurį gaunate dešiniuoju pelės mygtuku
          spustelėję kanalą.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          Det er fleire måtar å opprette ei markeringsmaske på. Dersom det er
          ei aktiv markering i biletet, kan du anten bruke
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Marker</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Lagre til kanal</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          i biletmenyen eller  knappen <link
          linkend="gimp-qmask">Snarmaske</link> nedst i biletvindauget.
          Dersom biletet er utan aktiv markering, kan du gå inn på
          kanaldialogen og trykke på knappen merka <guilabel>Ny
          kanal</guilabel> eller kopiere ein eksisterande kanal med knappen
          <guilabel>Kopier kanal</guilabel>. Dersom namnet på den nye kanalen
          ikkje passar, kan du bruke menyen som dukkar opp når du
          høgreklikkar på kanalen i kanaldialogen.
        </para>

        <para lang="ru">
          Есть несколько способов создания маски выделения. Если выделенная
          область уже существует, можно воспользоваться пунктом меню окна
          изображения
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem>Выделение</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Сохранить в канале</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          Кроме того, в окне изображения есть кнопка
          <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Быстрая маска</link>
          (она находится в левом нижнем углу окна) - при ее нажатии
          будет создан канал, содержащий активное выделение. Еще один
          метод - создать новый канал при помощи кнопки <guilabel>Новый
          канал</guilabel>, находящейся в диалоге каналов.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          有多种方法初始化一个选区蒙板。如果有一个活动选区，可以在图像窗口菜单中
          <guimenuitem>选择</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>保存到通道</guimenuitem>。用图像菜单左下方按钮产生一个<link linkend="gimp-qmask">快速蒙板</link>，它将用活动选区初始化其内容。在通道对话框中，点击<guilabel>新建通道</guilabel>按钮或通过通道菜单。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect4>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Using Selectionmasks</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Používání masek výběru</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Auswahlmasken benutzen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Empleo de las máscaras de selección</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Utilisation des masques de sélection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Utilizzo delle maschere di selezione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Pažymėjimo kaukių naudojimas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å bruke markeringsmasker</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Использование масок выделения</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用选区蒙板</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      Once the channel is initialized, selected (highlighted in blue), visible
      (eye-icon in the dialog), and displayed as you want (color and opacity
      attributes), you can start to work with all the paint tools. The colors
      used are important. If you paint with some color other than white, grey,
      or black, the color Value (luminosity) will be used to define a gray
      (medium, light, or dark). When your mask is painted, you can transform
      it to a selection by clicking on the
      <guilabel>Channel to selection</guilabel>
      button or from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can work in selection masks not only with the paint tool but also
      with other tools. For instance, you can use the selection tools to fill
      areas uniformly with gradients or patterns. By adding many selection
      masks in your list you can easily compose very complex selections. One
      can say that a selection mask is to a selection as a layer is to an
      image.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Jakmile je kanál vytvořen, aktivní (barevně zvýrazněn v dialogu Kanály),
      viditelný (je zobrazena ikona oka v dialogu Kanály) a zobrazen
      vyhovujícím způsobem (barva, průhlednost), můžete na něm začít pracovat
      s pomocí kreslících nástrojů. Důležité jsou použité barvy. Pokud zvolíte
      něco jiného než černou, bílou či odstín šedi, bere se v potaz hodnota
      barvy (jas). Když jste s úpravami hotovi, můžete masku převést zpět na
      výběr kliknutím na tlačítko
      <guilabel>Kanál do výběru</guilabel>
      nebo pomocí kontextové nabídky.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Sobald Sie eine Auswahl in einen Kanal gespeichert haben, können Sie
      diese Auswahl bearbeiten. Die Bearbeitung des Kanals erfolgt vorrangig
      mit <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>Malwerkzeugen</link>.
      Die ausgewählten Farben spielen hier eine besondere Rolle.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Benutzen Sie die Farbe Weiß, um die erstellte Auswahl zu vergrößern, und
      die Farbe Schwarz, um die Auswahl zu verkleinern. Indem Sie nur diese
      beiden Farben benutzen, können Sie eine Auswahl mit harten Kanten
      erzeugen, d.h. das Ende der Auswahl wird durch die schwarze Farbe
      beziehungsweise die laufenden Ameisen gekennzeichnet.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Möchten Sie die Auswahl langsam ausblenden, benutzen Sie Farben, die
      sich zwischen Schwarz und Weiß befinden, also Grautöne. Je höher der
      Anteil von Weiß im Grau ist, desto durchsichtiger ist die Auswahl.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Una vez que el canal haya sido inicializado, seleccionado, y hecho
      visible (con el icono del ojo en el diálogo), puede comenzar a trabajar
      con cualquiera de las herramientas de pintado. El valor (la luminosidad)
      del color empleado es lo que importa: si pinta con cualquier color que
      no sea blanco ni negro, se utiliza un gris equivalente. Cuando haya
      terminado de pintar la máscara, puede transformarla en selección
      haciendo clic sobre el botón <guilabel>Canal a selección</guilabel>
      desde el menú contextual.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      También puede trabajar las máscaras de selección con otras herramientas,
      no sólo con las herramientas de pintado.  Por ejemplo, puede usar las
      herramientas de selección para rellenar áreas con degradados o con
      patrones.  Se pueden componer selecciones muy complejas añadiendo varias
      máscaras de selección a la lista.  Se puede decir que una máscara de
      selección es a la selección lo que una capa es a la imagen.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Une fois le canal initialisé, activé (surligné en bleu), visible
      (l'icône en forme d'oeil dans le dialogue) et affiché à votre convenance
      (attributs de couleur et d'opacité) il devient possible de travailler
      dedans avec tous les outils de dessin classiques. Les couleurs utilisées
      sont évidemment importantes. Si vous utilisez autre chose que du blanc,
      du noir ou du gris ce sera la valeur (luminosité) de la couleur qui sera
      utilisée pour définir un gris plus ou moins clair. Une fois votre masque
      dessiné vous pouvez le transformer en sélection depuis le bouton
      <guilabel>Canal vers sélection</guilabel>
      ou depuis le menu contextuel.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il est tout à fait possible de travailler avec d'autres outils que les
      outils de dessin dans les masques de sélection. Par exemple vous pouvez
      utiliser les outils de sélection pour remplir des zones uniformément,
      avec des motifs ou avec des dégradés. En cumulant ainsi plusieurs
      masques de sélection dans votre liste vous pouvez arriver à composer des
      sélections vraiment complexes avec beaucoup de souplesse, on peut dire
      qu'un masque de sélection est à une sélection ce qu'un calque est à une
      image.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Una volta che il canale è stato creato, è selezionato (evidenziato in
      blu), è visibile (icona con l'occhio nella finestra), ed è visualizzato
      nel modo desiderato (attributi di colore ed opacità), si può iniziare a
      lavorarci con tutti gli strumenti di disegno. I colori utilizzati sono
      importanti. Se si dipinge con colori diversi dal bianco, dal grigio o
      dal nero, il valore del colore (luminosità) sarà usato per definire un
      grigio (medio, chiaro o scuro). Quando la maschera è stata dipinta la si
      può trasformare in una selezione facendo clic sul pulsante
      <guilabel>Canale a selezione</guilabel>
      o dal menu contestuale.
    </para>

    <para lang="lt">
      Kai kanalas inicializuotas, pažymėtas (paryškintas mėlyna spalva),
      matomas (dialoge esanti akies piktograma) ir rodomas taip, kaip jūs
      pageidaujate (spalvos ir nepermatomumo savybės), galite pradėti
      dirbti visais piešimo įrankiais. Naudojamos spalvos yra svarbios.
      Jeigu piešiate kitokia spalva nei balta, pilka arba juoda, spalvos
      Reikšmė (šviesumas) bus naudojama apibrėžti pilką spalvą
      (vidutinė, šviesi arba tamsi). Nupiešę kaukę galite ją transformuoti
      į pažymėjimą spustelėdami kontekstiniame meniu esantį mygtuką
      <guilabel>Kanalas į pažymėjimą</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="lt">
      Pažymėjimo kaukėse galite dirbti naudodami ne tik piešimo įrankį,
      bet ir kitus įrankius. Pavyzdžiui, norėdami vienodai užpildyti sritis
      gradientais arba raštais, galite naudoti pažymėjimo įrankius.
      Sąraše pridėdami daug pažymėjimo kaukių galite lengvai sukurti labai
      sudėtingus pažymėjimus. Galima sakyti, kad pažymėjimo kaukė
      pažymėjimui yra tas pats, kas sluoksnis yra paveikslėliui.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Når kanalen er oppretta og markert i kanaldialogen (med
      uthevingsfarge), er synleg (vist med augeikonet) og blir vist slik du
      ønskjer det ut frå eigenskapane du har sett i dialogvindauget, kan du
      endeleg byrja å arbeida på kanalen med teikneverktøya. Du bør bruke
      fargane kvit, grå eller svart. Bruker du andre fargar, vil fargeverdien
      bli brukt for å definera ein gråverdi. Dette blir ikkje alltid slik du trur
      det skal bli. Når maska er ferdig, kan du omforma ho til ei markering
      med knappen <guilabel>Kanal til markering</guilabel> i kanaldialogen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Du kan arbeide på markeringsmaska med andre verktøy enn teikneverktøya.
      Du kan for eksempel bruke markeringsverktøya for å fylle eit område med
      fargeovergangar eller mønsterelement. Det er råd å komponera svært
      komplekse markeringar ved å kombinera ulike markeringsmasker. Du kan
      gjerne tenke på at markeringsmaskene er for ei markering det eit lag er
      for biletet.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Перед тем, как работать с маской выделения, необходимо удостовериться,
      что канал, в котором сохранена выделенная область, является на данный
      момент активным (он подсвечен другим цветом, каким - зависит от темы
      оконного менеджера) и видимым (слева от иконки канала есть иконка
      глаза). Кроме того, вы можете настроить параметры цвета и прозрачности
      отображения маски. После этого можно приступать к редактированию области
      выделения, используя любые инструменты для рисования. Цвет, который
      используется при работе, имеет большое значение. Если вы рисуете любым
      цветом, отличным от белого, черного и серого, то во внимание принимается
      только информация о яркости цвета. Таким образом, маска воспринимает
      любой не белый и не черный цвет как серый. По окончании рисования маски
      ее можно преобразовать в выделенную область, воспользовавшись пунктом
      меню каналов <guilabel>Канал->Выделение</guilabel>
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      При редактировании маски выделения не обязательно использовать только
      инструменты для рисования. Например, можно воспользоваться любым
      инструментом для выделения, а потом заполнить выделенную область
      заливкой или градиентом. Создавая большое количество масок выделения вы
      создадите достаточно сложную выделенную область без особого труда. В
      конечном итоге маска выделения для выделенной области является тем же,
      чем слой является для всего изображения.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      一旦通道被初始化，选中(用蓝色高亮表示)可见(对话框中的眼睛图标)，让它如您所愿显示(颜色和不透明度属性)，然后您就能用任何涂画工具来使用它了。使用的颜色很重要，假如您用白，灰或黑以外的颜色涂画，颜色的亮度将被用来定义一个灰色(中等，明亮或阴暗)。当蒙板被涂画后，就可以通过点击通道菜单中<guilabel>通道到选区</guilabel>按钮将其转换为一个选区。
    </para>

    <tip lang="cs;it">  <!--TODO it: Please translate to 'en' if it's still usefull.-->
      <para lang="cs">
        Masky výběru můžete upravovat nejen pomocí kreslících nástrojů, ale i
        dalšími nástroji. Můžete například používat nástroje pro výběr a
        vybrané oblasti vyplňovat jednolitou barvou nebo přechody či vzorky.
        Pomocí většího množství masek můžete vytvořit velmi složité výběry.
        Masky výběru jsou pro výběr zhruba tím, co vrstvy pro obrázek.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Sulle maschere di selezione si può lavorare non solo con gli strumenti
        di disegno, ma anche con altri strumenti. Per esempio, si possono
        usare gli strumenti di selezione per riempire uniformemente delle zone
        con dei gradienti o con dei motivi. Aggiungendo alla lista diverse
        maschere di selezione si possono facilmente comporre delle selezioni
        complesse. Si può affermare che una maschera di selezione rappresenta
        per le selezioni quello che un livello rappresenta per un'immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您不光可以用涂画工具，而且可以用其它工具来在选区蒙板上进行处理。比如，可以用带渐变或图案的选择工具统一地填充区域。在列表中添加许多选区蒙板能很容易地生成非常复杂的选区。可以这么说，一个选区蒙板对一个选区就好比一个图层对一个图像。
      </para>
    </tip>

    <caution>
      <para lang="en">
        As long as a selection mask is activated you are working in the mask
        and not in the image. To work in the image you have to deactivate all
        selection masks. Don't forget also to stop displaying masks in the
        image by removing the eye icon. Check also that all RGB and Alpha
        channels are activated and displayed in the image.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Dokud je maska výběru aktivní, pracujete s maskou a nikoliv s
        obrázkem. Chcete-li opět pracovat s obrázkem, musíte deaktivovat
        všechny masky výběru. Nezapomeňte také zakázat zobrazování masek v
        obrázku odstraněním ikon oka. Také si zkontrolujte, že jsou aktivovány
        a zobrazovány všechny barevné a alfa kanály.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Solange die Auswahlmaske aktiviert ist (gekennzeichnet durch das
        gesetzte Augensymbol des Kanals), haben die eingesetzten Werkzeuge nur
        auf die Auswahlmaske einen Effekt.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Una vez que la máscara de selección se ha activado, se trabaja sobre
        ésta y no sobre la imagen. Para volver a trabajar en la imagen, debe
        desactivar todas las máscaras de selección. Tampoco olvide ocultar las
        máscaras desactivando el icono con forma de ojo. También chequee que
        todos los canales RGB y alfa estén activados y visibles.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Tant qu'un masque de sélection est activé vous travaillez dans le
        masque et non pas dans l'image. Pour travailler à nouveau dans l'image
        vous devez impérativement désactiver tous les masques de sélection.
        N'oubliez pas aussi de désactiver l'affichage des masques dans l'image
        en enlevant l'icône en forme d'oeil. Vérifiez aussi que vos canaux RVB
        et Alpha sont bien actifs et affichés dans l'image.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Fintanto che una maschera di selezione è attiva si lavora sulla
        maschera e non sull'immagine. Per lavorare sull'immagine è necessario
        disattivare tutte le maschere di selezione. Non va dimenticato anche
        di disabilitare la visualizzazione delle maschere nell'immagine,
        eliminando l'icona con l'occhio. Va anche controllato che tutti i
        canali RGB e alfa sia attivi e visualizzati nell'immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="lt">
        Kol pažymėjimo kaukė yra aktyvuota, dirbate kaukėje, o ne
        paveikslėlyje. Norėdami dirbti paveikslėlyje, turite išjungti visas
        pažymėjimo kaukes. Taip pat nepamirškite išjungti kaukių
        rodymą paveikslėlyje pašalindami akies piktogramą. Taip pat
        patikrinkite ar paveikslėlyje įjungti ir rodomi visi RGB ir Alfa
        kanalai.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Så lenge markeringsmaska er aktiv, arbeider du på denne og ikkje på
        biletet. Skal du arbeide på biletet, må du deaktivere alle
        markeringsmaskene. Gløym heller ikkje å skjule maskene ved å klikke på
        augeikonet. Det er også ein god ide å kontrollera at alle RGB- og
        alfakanalane er aktiverte og viste i biletet.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        До тех пор, пока маска выделения активна, все изменения происходят
        только с маской, не касаясь самого изображения. Чтобы перейти к
        редактированию изображения надо сделать маску неактивной. Не забывайте
        так же о том, что маску надо сделать невидимой, нажав на иконку глаза
        слева от иконки маски. Обратите внимание на то, что все RGB и
        альфа-каналы должны быть активными и видимыми.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当一个选区蒙板被激活后，您就对蒙板进行处理了，而不是对图像。如果要对图像处理就必须使所有选区蒙板不活动，另外不要忘记关闭眼睛图标使蒙板停止在图像中显示，然后还要检查所有的
        RGB 和 Alpha 通道是否是活动和是否显示在图像上。
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>
</sect3>
