<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<!-- 2006-02-25 romanofski fixed broken image references -->
<sect3 id="dialogs-selection-masks" lang="de;cs;en;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <sect3info lang="en;de;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="en">2006-02-27</date>
        <date lang="de">2006-02-25</date>
        <date lang="fr">2006-02-27</date>
        <authorinitials lang="en">j.h</authorinitials>
        <authorinitials lang="de">romanofski</authorinitials>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect3info> 
  
  <title lang="en">Selection masks</title>
  <title lang="cs">Masky výběru</title>
  <title lang="de">Auswahlmasken</title>
  <title lang="fr">Masques de sélection</title>  <!--050511-->   
  <title lang="it">Maschere di selezione</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">选区蒙板</title>
  
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Masks</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Masques</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Selection mask</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Masque de sélection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <figure lang="de;en;fr">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        A selection composed out of channels.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Eine Auswahl erstellt aus verschiedenen Kanälen
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        Une sélection composée de plusieurs canaux
      </phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata 
                   fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks.png" 
                   format="PNG" lang="de;en;fr;it" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <para lang="en"> 
    Channels can be used to save and restore your selections.  Clicking
    on the <guilabel>Quick mask</guilabel> button on the <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Image window</link> automatically
    creates a new channel called <guilabel>Qmask</guilabel> and saves the
    displayed active selection to a thumbail in front of the
    channel.There are many selection tools in the Gimp like rectangular
    selection tool or fuzzy selection for continuous selections.
    Selection Masks are a graphical way to build selections into a gray
    level channel where white pixels are selected and black pixels are
    not selected. Therefore gray pixels are partially selected. You can
    think of them as feathering the selection, a smooth transition
    between selected and not selected. This is important to avoid the
    ugly pixelization effect when you fill the selection or when you
    erase its content after isolating a subject from background.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Kanály lze používat k ukládání výběrů. Kliknutí na tlačítko rychlé masky  
    v <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Okně obrázku</link> automaticky
    vytvoří nový kanál nazvaný <guilabel>Rychlá maska</guilabel>. Ikona
    před jménem kanálu zobrazuje náhled výběru. V gimpu je k dispozici řada
    nástrojů pro výběr, jako je výběr obdélníku nebo volný výběr. Maky výběru
    jsou grafickým znázorněním výběru v podobě šedého kanálu, kde bílé pixely
    jsou vybrané a černé nikoliv. Šedé pixely jsou vybrány částečně. Lze si je
    představit jako prolnutí výběru, plynulý přechod mezi vybranými a
    nevybranými oblastmi. To je důležitá obrana proti ošklivým artefaktům při
    vyplňování výběru barvou nebo jeho vymazáním.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Kanäle können benutzt werden um Auswahlen zu speichern und wieder
    herzustellen. Es gibt zahlreiche <link
    linkend='gimp-tools-selection'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> im
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym>, mit denen neue Auswahlen erstellt werden
    können. Auch <link linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMasks</link> können in
    einen Kanal gespeichert werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">     
    Les canaux peuvent être utilisés pour sauvegarder, restituer et 
    modifier vos sélections. Les Masques de sélection, ou masques de 
    canaux, créés dans la partie basse de la Fenêtre des canaux, sont 
    une représentation d'une sélection en niveaux de gris, où les 
    pixels blancs sont sélectionnés et les pixels noirs ne le sont pas. 
    Les pixels gris sont partiellement sélectionnés. Nous allons voir 
    comment créer et utiliser ces masques de sélections.
  </para>
  <para lang="it"> 
    I canali si possono utilizzare per salvare e poi ripristinare le selezioni.
    Facendo un clic sul pulsante della <guilabel>Maschera veloce</guilabel> 
    nella <!--link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window" FIXME -->finestra immagine<!--/link--> 
    viene creato automaticamente un nuovo canale chiamato <guilabel>Maschera 
      veloce</guilabel> e la selezione attiva visualizzata viene salvata in una
    miniatura prima del canale. Per creare delle selezioni continue ci sono 
    molti strumenti in Gimp, come la selezione rettangolare o la bacchetta 
    magica. Le maschere di selezione rappresentano un modo di costruire le 
    selezioni graficamente all'interno di un canale in scala di grigi, dove i 
    pixel bianchi sono selezionati ed i pixel neri sono quelli non selezionati.
    Quindi i pixel grigi sono parzialmente selezionati. Si può pensare ad essi
    come ad una sfumatura della selezione, una transizione graduale tra ciò che
    è selezionato e ciò che non lo è. Questo è importante per evitare il brutto 
    effetto scalinato dei pixel quando si riempie una selezione o quando si 
    cancella il suo contenuto dopo aver isolato un soggetto dallo sfondo.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN"> 
    通道可以保存和恢复您的选区。点击<link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">图像窗口</link>的<guilabel>快速蒙板</guilabel>按键会自动新建一个叫作<guilabel>Qmask</guilabel>的通道，并将显示的当前选区保存为通道前的一个缩略图上。GIMP 中有很多像矩形选择或模糊选择这样的选择工具。选区蒙板是一种能将选区放入一个灰阶通道的方法，其中选中的为白色像素，未选中的为黑色像素，而灰色像素则表示部分选中。您可以把它们看作被羽化的选区，是选中和未选中之间的过渡。这对在您填充选区或在从背景中分离一个物体后删除其内容时，避免产生的丑陋的格删化现象非常重要。
  </para>
  
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Creating Selection Masks</term>
      <term lang="cs">Vytvoření masky výběru</term>
      <term lang="de">Erstellen von Auswahlmasken</term>
      <term lang="fr">Création d'un masque de sélection</term>
      <term lang="it">Creazione delle maschere di selezione</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">创建选区蒙板</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          There are several ways to initialize a selection mask.  From the
          image window menu
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>S</accel>elect</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Save to <accel>C</accel>hannel</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>            
          if there is an active selection.  From the image window
          the bottom-left button creates a <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quick
            Mask</link>; the content will be initialized with the active
          selection.  From the channel dialog, when you click on the
          <guilabel>New channel</guilabel> button or from the context menu. 
          When created, this Selection mask appears in the Channel dialog, 
          named <quote>Selection mask copy</quote> with a queuing number. 
          You can change this by using the context menu that you get by 
          right-clicking on the channel.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="cs">
        <para>
          Existuje řada způsobů, jak vytvořit masku výběru. Z nabídky obrázku
          můžete, pokud existuje aktivní výběr, zvolit
          <guimenuitem>Vybrat</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>Uložit do
            kanálu</guimenuitem>. Tlačítko v levém dolním rohu okna obrázku
          vytvoří <link linkend="gimp-qmask">rychlou masku</link>, jejíž obsah
          je vytvořen z aktivního výběru. Z dialogu kanálů kliknutím na
          <guilabel>Nový kanál</guilabel> nebo kontextové nabídky.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Erstellen Sie eine Auswahl mit einen <link
          linkend='gimp-tools-selection'>Auswahlwerkzeug</link>.  Danach
          überführen Sie die erstellte Auswahl in ein Kanal.
        </para>
        <para>
          Benutzen Sie dafür über das Bildmenü
          <guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>In
            <accel>K</accel>anal speichern</guimenuitem>. Danach erscheint
          ein neuer Kanal mit einem Miniaturbild im Kanaldialog.
          Standardmässig ist die erstellte Auswahlmaske nicht sichtbar; dem
          Kanal fehlt das gesetzte <link
          linkend='channel-attributes'>Augensymbol</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Möchten Sie die abgespeicherte Auswahl aus dem Kanal wieder
          herstellen, benutzen Sie dazu die <link
          linkend='gimp-channel-selection-add'>Auswahl aus Kanal</link>
          Schaltfläche.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">       
        <para>
          Il existe plusieurs méthodes pour initialiser un masque de
          sélection.  Depuis le menu d'image
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Sélection</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Enregistrer dans un canal</guimenuitem> 
          </menuchoice>
          disponible si vous avez une sélection active. Depuis le bouton au
          bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image qui va créer un <link
          linkend="gimp-qmask">Masque rapide</link> dont le contenu sera
          initialisé avec la sélection active. Depuis le dialogue des
          canaux en cliquant sur le bouton <guibutton>Nouveau
            canal</guibutton> ou depuis le menu contextuel obtenu par 
          clic-droit sur un canal. Une fois créé, le masque de sélection 
          apparaît dans la fenêtre de dialogue des canaux avec le nom 
          <quote>Copie de masque de sélection</quote> et un numéro d'ordre. 
          Vous pouvez changer ce nom en utilisant le menu contextuel obtenu 
          par clic droit sur le bandeau du canal.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="it">
        <para>
          Ci sono diversi modi per creare una maschera di selezione. Se è
          attiva una selezione, nel menu della finestra immagine è
          disponibile la voce:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>S</accel>eleziona</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Salva nel <accel>C</accel>anale</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
          Il pulsante in basso a sinistra nella finestra dell'immagine crea una 
          <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Maschera veloce</link>; il cui contenuto
          iniziale sarà quello della selezione attiva. Dalla finestra dei 
          canali quando si fa clic sul pulsante <guilabel>Nuovo canale</guilabel> 
          o dal menu contestuale.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          有多种方法初始化一个选区蒙板。如果有一个活动选区，可以在图像窗口菜单中
          <guimenuitem>选择</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>保存到通道</guimenuitem>。用图像菜单左下方按钮产生一个<link linkend="gimp-qmask">快速蒙板</link>，它将用活动选区初始化其内容。在通道对话框中，点击<guilabel>新建通道</guilabel>按钮或通过通道菜单。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect4 lang="en">
    <title lang="en">Using Selectionmasks</title>
    <para>
      Once the channel is initialized, selected (highlighted in blue),
      visible (eye-icon in the dialog), and displayed as you want
      (color and opacity attributes), you can start to work with all
      the paint tools.  The colors used are important. If you paint
      with some color other than white, grey, or black, the color Value
      (luminosity) will be used to define a gray (medium, light, or
      dark).  When your mask is painted, you can transform it to a
      selection by clicking on the <guilabel>Channel to
        selection</guilabel> button or from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
        You can work in selection masks not only with the paint tool
        but also with other tools. For instance, you can use the
        selection tools to fill areas uniformly with gradients or
        patterns.  By adding many selection masks in your list you can
        easily compose very complex selections. One can say that a
        selection mask is to a selection as a layer is to an image.
    </para>
    <caution>
      <para>
        As long as a selection mask is activated you are working in the
        mask and not in the image. To work in the image you have to
        deactivate all selection masks. Don't forget also to stop
        displaying masks in the image by removing the eye icon. Check
        also that all RGB and Alpha channels are activated and
        displayed in the image.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 lang='cs'>
    <title lang="cs">Používání masek výběru</title>
    <para>
      Jakmile je kanál vytvořen, aktivní (barevně zvýrazněn v dialogu Kanály),
      viditelný (je zobrazena ikona oka v dialogu Kanály) a zobrazen
      vyhovujícím způsobem (barva, průhlednost), můžete na něm začít pracovat
      s pomocí kreslících nástrojů. Důležité jsou použité barvy. Pokud zvolíte
      něco jiného než černou, bílou či odstín šedi, bere se v potaz hodnota
      barvy (jas). Když jste s úpravami hotovi, můžete masku převést zpět na
      výběr kliknutím na tlačítko <guilabel>Kanál do výběru</guilabel> nebo
      pomocí kontextové nabídky.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        Masky výběru můžete upravovat nejen pomocí kreslících nástrojů, ale i
        dalšími nástroji. Můžete například používat nástroje pro výběr a
        vybrané oblasti vyplňovat jednolitou barvou nebo přechody či vzorky.
        Pomocí většího množství masek můžete vytvořit velmi složité výběry.
        Masky výběru jsou pro výběr zhruba tím, co vrstvy pro obrázek.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Dokud je maska výběru aktivní, pracujete s maskou a nikoliv s
        obrázkem. Chcete-li opět pracovat s obrázkem, musíte deaktivovat
        všechny masky výběru. Nezapomeňte také zakázat zobrazování masek
        v obrázku odstraněním ikon oka. Také si zkontrolujte, že jsou
        aktivovány a zobrazovány všechny barevné a alfa kanály.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 lang='de'>
    <title lang="de">Auswahlmasken benutzen</title>
    <para>
      Sobald Sie eine Auswahl in einen Kanal gespeichert haben, können
      Sie diese Auswahl bearbeiten. Die Bearbeitung des Kanals erfolgt
      vorranging mit <link
        linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>Malwerkzeugen</link>. Die
      ausgewählten Farben spielen hier eine besondere Rolle.
    </para>
    <para>
      Benutzen Sie die Farbe Weiss um die erstellte Auswahl zu
      vergrössern und die Farbe Schwarz um die Auswahl zu verkleinern.
      Nur durch die Benutzung der beiden Farbarten, können erzeugen Sie
      eine Auswahl mit harten Kanten, d.h. das Ende der Auswahl wird
      durch die Schwarze Farbe bzw. der laufenden Ameisen
      gekennzeichnet.
    </para>
    <para>
      Möchten Sie die Auswahl langsam ausblenden, benutzen Sie Farben
      die sich zwischen Schwarz und Weiss befinden, also Grautöne. Je
      höher der Anteil von Weiss im Grau ist, desto durchsichtiger ist
      die Auswahl.
    </para>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Solang die Auswahlmaske aktiviert ist (gekennzeichnet durch das
        gesetzte Augensymbol des Kanals), haben die eingesetzten
        Werkzeuge nur auf die Auswahlmaske einen Effekt.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>
  
  <sect4 lang='fr'>
    <title lang='fr'>Utilisation des masques de sélection</title>
    <para>
      Une fois le canal initialisé, activé (surligné en bleu), visible
      (l'icône en forme d'oeil dans le dialogue) et affiché à votre
      convenance (attributs de couleur et d'opacité) il devient
      possible de travailler dedans avec tous les outils de dessin
      classiques. Les couleurs utilisées sont évidemment importantes.
      Si vous utilisez autre chose que du blanc, du noir ou du gris ce
      sera la valeur (luminosité) de la couleur qui sera utilisée pour
      définir un gris plus ou moins clair. Une fois votre masque
      dessiné vous pouvez le transformer en sélection depuis le bouton
      <guilabel>Canal vers sélection</guilabel> ou depuis le menu
      contextuel.
    </para>
    <para>
        Il est tout à fait possible de travailler avec d'autres
        outils que les outils de dessin dans les masques de sélection.
        Par exemple vous pouvez utiliser les outils de sélection pour
        remplir des zones uniformément, avec des motifs ou avec des
        dégradés.  En cumulant ainsi plusieurs masques de sélection
        dans votre liste vous pouvez arriver à composer des
        sélections vraiment complexes avec beaucoup de souplesse, on
        peut dire qu'un masque de sélection est à une sélection ce
        qu'un calque est à une image.
    </para>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Tant qu'un masque de sélection est activé vous travaillez
        dans le masque et non pas dans l'image. Pour travailler à
        nouveau dans l'image vous devez impérativement désactiver
        tous les masques de sélection.  N'oubliez pas aussi de
        désactiver l'affichage des masques dans l'image en enlevant
        l'icône en forme d'oeil.  Vérifiez aussi que vos canaux RVB et
        Alpha sont bien actifs et affichés dans l'image.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 lang='it'>
    <title lang="it">Utilizzo delle maschere di selezione</title>
    <para>
      Una volta che il canale è stato creato, è selezionato (evidenziato in blu),
      è visibile (icona con l'occhio nella finestra), ed è visualizzato nel 
      modo desiderato (attributi di colore ed opacità), si può iniziare a 
      lavorarci con tutti gli strumenti di disegno. I colori utilizzati sono
      importanti. Se si dipinge con colori diversi dal bianco, dal grigio o dal
      nero, il valore del colore (luminosità) sarà usato per definire un grigio
      (medio, chiaro o scuro). Quando la maschera è stata dipinta la si può 
      trasformare in una selezione facendo clic sul pulsante <guilabel>Canale a 
      selezione</guilabel> o dal menu contestuale.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        Sulle maschere di selezione si può lavorare non solo con gli strumenti
        di disegno, ma anche con altri strumenti. Per esempio, si possono usare
        gli strumenti di selezione per riempire uniformemente delle zone con dei
        gradienti o con dei motivi. Aggiungendo alla lista diverse maschere 
        di selezione si possono facilmente comporre delle selezioni complesse.
        Si può affermare che una maschera di selezione rappresenta per le 
        selezioni quello che un livello rappresenta per un'immagine.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Fintanto che una maschera di selezione è attiva si lavora sulla maschera
        e non sull'immagine. Per lavorare sull'immagine è necessario disattivare
        tutte le maschere di selezione. Non va dimenticato anche di disabilitare
        la visualizzazione delle maschere nell'immagine, eliminando l'icona con
        l'occhio. Va anche controllato che tutti i canali RGB e alfa sia attivi
        e visualizzati nell'immagine.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect4>
  
  <sect4 lang='zh_CN'>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用选区蒙板</title>
        <para>
          一旦通道被初始化，选中(用蓝色高亮表示)可见(对话框中的眼睛图标)，让它如您所愿显示(颜色和不透明度属性)，然后您就能用任何涂画工具来使用它了。使用的颜色很重要，假如您用白，灰或黑以外的颜色涂画，颜色的亮度将被用来定义一个灰色(中等，明亮或阴暗)。当蒙板被涂画后，就可以通过点击通道菜单中<guilabel>通道到选区</guilabel>按钮将其转换为一个选区。
        </para>
        <tip>
    <para>
      您不光可以用涂画工具，而且可以用其它工具来在选区蒙板上进行处理。比如，可以用带渐变或图案的选择工具统一地填充区域。在列表中添加许多选区蒙板能很容易地生成非常复杂的选区。可以这么说，一个选区蒙板对一个选区就好比一个图层对一个图像。
    </para>
        </tip>
        <caution>
    <para>
      当一个选区蒙板被激活后，您就对蒙板进行处理了，而不是对图像。如果要对图像处理就必须使所有选区蒙板不活动，另外不要忘记关闭眼睛图标使蒙板停止在图像中显示，然后还要检查所有的 RGB 和 Alpha 通道是否是活动和是否显示在图像上。
    </para>
        </caution>
  </sect4>
</sect3>

