<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-23 j.h: no change for 2.8
  2008-12-13 j.h: updated to v2.6
  2007-08-29 j.h : link to glossary Alpha Channel added
  2006-03-06 lexa: made docbook compliant
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-channel-dialog">
  <title>Channels Dialog</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Channels</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Channel</primary>
    <secondary>Dialog</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>The Channels dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/channels-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Channels dialog is the main interface to edit, modify and manage your
    channels. Channels have a double usage. This is why the dialog is divided
    into two parts: the first part for color channels and the second part for
    <link linkend="gimp-channel-mask">selection masks</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Color channels</emphasis> apply to the image and not to a
    specific layer. Basically, three primary colors are necessary to render
    all the wide range of natural colors. As other digital software,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses Red, Green, and Blue as primary colors. The
    first and primary channels display the <guilabel>Red</guilabel>,
    <guilabel>Green</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Blue</guilabel> values of each
    pixel in your image.
  </para>
  <para>
    Next to the channel name is a thumbnail displaying a grayscale
    representation of each channel, where white is 100% and black is
    0% of the primary color. Alternatively, if your image is not a colored but
    a Grayscale image, there is only one primary channel called
    <guilabel>Gray</guilabel>. For an Indexed image with a fixed number of
    known colors there is also only one primary channel called
    <guilabel>Indexed</guilabel>.
  </para>
  <para>
    Then there is an optional channel called <guilabel>Alpha</guilabel>. This
    channel displays transparency values of each pixel in your image
    (See <link linkend="glossary-alpha-channel">Alpha Channel</link> in
    Glossary). In front of this channel is a thumbnail displaying a grayscale
    representation of the transparency where white is opaque and visible, and
    black is transparent and invisible. If you create your image without
    transparency then the Alpha channel is not present, but you can add it
    from the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link> context
    menu.
    Also, if you have more than one layer in your image,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> automatically creates an Alpha channel.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>GIMP doesn't support CMYK or YUV color models.</para>
  </note>
  <figure>
    <title>Representation of an image with channels</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-red.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Red channel</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-green.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Green channel</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-blue.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Blue channel</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-alpha.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Alpha channel</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-combined.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para><!-- All channels combined -->All channels</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The right image is decomposed in three color channels (red, green, and
    blue) and the Alpha channel for transparency. On the right image the
    transparency is displayed as a gray checkerboard. In the color channel
    white is always white because all the colors are present and black is
    black. The red hat is visible in the red channel but quite invisible in
    the other channels. This is the same for plain green and blue which are
    visible only in their own channels and invisible in others.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gimp-channel-dialog-calling">
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      This dialog is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can access it:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog by clicking on
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon> and selecting
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      In the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> menu, there is a list of
      <link linkend="gimp-dockable-menu">detached windows</link> which exists
      only if at least one dialog remains open. In this case, you can raise
      the <quote>Channels</quote> dialog from the main menu:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-channel-dialog-using">
    <title>Using the Channels Dialog</title>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-overview">
        <term>Overview</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Channels Dialog consists of a list of color channels and the
            optional Alpha channel.
            Below that is a list of selection mask channels.
            A right-click in a channel list entry opens the
            <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">channel context menu</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The color channels are always organized in the same order. They
            cannot be removed. You can only change their visibility and
            select or unselect them. By default, all of these channels are
            visible and selected.
          </para>
          <para>
            To select a channel, click on a color channel in the list.
            This toggles the selection of the channel, meaning a selected
            channel will become unselected and vice versa.
            The selected color channels appear highlighted in the dialog.
          </para>
          <caution>
            <para>
              Unselecting one of the color channels red, blue, or green has
              severe consequences. For instance if you disable the blue channel,
              all pixels from now on added to the image will not have a blue
              component, and so a white pixel will have the yellow complementary
              color.
            </para>
            <para>
              Making one of the color channels invisible does not influence how
              tools work and only changes what is currently displayed on your
              screen. For example, a brush will continue to paint as usual, and
              the eraser will change the alpha value of pixels also when the
              alpha channel is set to be not visible.
            </para>
            <para>
              The selected color channels define which parts of a tool's action
              are applied to the layer. For example, the eraser will not change
              your image if the alpha channel is not selected.
            </para>
          </caution>
          <note>
            <para>
              The duplicate and selection commands documented below can also
              be used on the color channels. However, this only works when
              accessing the command from the right-click context menu, and
              only for one channel at a time.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Selecting multiple channels</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to select multiple selection mask
            channels and perform actions on them. You can e.g. move them to a
            different location in the channels stack, and convert them to
            selections.
            Selecting multiple channels is done by using the mouse and
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> key, for adding a range of channels, or
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key, for adding or removing the clicked
            channel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Channel list header</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Directly above the list of selection masks is the header bar. On
            the left you see the icons that identify the visibility and lock
            columns. In the middle a text label will tell you how many channels
            are currently selected if it is more than one.
          </para>
          <!-- Searching on channels and paths is temporarily disabled in GIMP.
               Since it is intended to come back later, we comment it out here.
          <para>
            On the right you see the search entry. Clicking here will allow you
            to search for and select one or more channels. You will also be
            able to save this search for future use.
          </para>
          <para>
            For more details about searching see
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-search">Search layers and Saved searches</link>.
          </para>
          -->
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-attributes">
        <term>
            <!-- Old anchor which is probably not used anymore -->
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-linked"/>
          <phrase>Channel attributes</phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Every channel is shown in the list with its own attributes, which are
            very similar to the <link linkend="gimp-layer-attributes">layer
            attributes</link>:
          </para>
          <variablelist id="channel-attributes">

            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-visible">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-visible.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Channel visibility</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  By default, all color channels are visible, and color mask
                  channels are invisible.
                  Clicking on the eye-symbol, or the empty space if the channel
                  is not visible, will toggle the visibility of the channel.
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>-clicking on the icon causes
                  all <emphasis>other</emphasis> channels to be hidden.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-locks">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-lock.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Channel lock attributes</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Each selection mask channel has lock attributes. If one of its
                  attributes is set, the respective lock icon will show up in front
                  of the thumbnail.
                </para>
                <para>
                  When multiple attributes are set, a double lock icon will
                  show here. Clicking in this column allows you to change
                  these attributes.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-lock-pixels">
                    <term>
                      <guiicon>
                        <inlinemediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-lock-content.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject>
                      </guiicon>
                      <phrase>Lock pixels</phrase>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This icon shows when <quote>lock pixels</quote> is
                        enabled for the current channel. When this is enabled,
                        the channel is locked for any action that changes
                        pixels, meaning there will be no changes done to this
                        channel.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-lock-position">
                    <term>
                      <guiicon>
                        <inlinemediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-lock-position.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject>
                      </guiicon>
                      <phrase>Lock position and size</phrase>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This icon shows when <quote>lock position and size</quote>
                        is enabled for the current channel. When this is enabled,
                        the channel is locked for any action that changes its
                        position or size.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-lock-visibility">
                    <term>
                      <guiicon>
                        <inlinemediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-lock-visibility.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                          </imageobject>
                        </inlinemediaobject>
                      </guiicon>
                      <phrase>Lock visibility</phrase>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This toggle button controls the <quote>Lock</quote>
                        setting for the visibility of the channel. If this is
                        enabled, the channel visibility cannot be changed until
                        you disable the lock.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <!--Preview image-->
              <term>Thumbnail</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A small preview icon represents the effect of the channel. This
                  preview can be enlarged by holding down the left mouse button
                  on it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Channel name</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The name of the channel, which must be unique within the image.
                  Double-clicking on the name of a selection mask channel will
                  allow you to edit it. The names of the primary channels (Red,
                  Green, Blue, Alpha) can not be changed.
                  Double-clicking on the preview icon will open a dialog where
                  you can set all channel attributes.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-managing">
        <term>Managing channels</term>

        <listitem>
        <!--TODO: check: do we really need so many indexterms?-->
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
          <secondary>Edit Channel Attributes</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
          <secondary>Create a New Channel Mask</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
          <secondary>Move Channel Mask</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
          <secondary>Duplicate Channel Mask</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
          <secondary>Delete Channel Mask</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
          <secondary>Channel to Selection</secondary>
        </indexterm>

          <para>
            The button bar at the bottom offers the following functionality:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-new">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/document-new.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>New Channel</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This creates a new channel. A dialog will open where you can set
                  the <guilabel>Channel name</guilabel>, the
                  <guilabel>Color tag</guilabel>, the
                  <link linkend="channel-attributes">channel attributes</link> and
                  <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog-using-locks">lock attributes</link>,
                  and finally the <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> and color used for
                  the mask in the image window. A click on the color button
                  displays the GIMP color selector where you can change the mask
                  color.
                </para>
                <para>
                  If you press the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while clicking the
                  <guibutton>New Channel</guibutton> button, the New Channel
                  dialog will not be opened. Instead the new channel will be
                  created with the same settings as used previously.
                  This new channel is a selection mask applied over the image.
                  See for more details
                  <link linkend="gimp-channel-mask">Selection Mask</link>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-raise">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/go-up.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Raise Channels</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <anchor id="gimp-channel-raise-to-top"/>
                <para>
                  This moves the selected channels up in the list.
                  Press the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key to move the selected
                  channels to the top of the list.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-lower">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/go-down.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Lower Channels</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <anchor id="gimp-channel-lower-to-bottom"/>
                <para>
                  This moves selected channels down in the list.
                  Press the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key to move the selected
                  channels to the bottom of the list.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-duplicate">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-duplicate.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Duplicate Channels</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This creates a copy of the selected channels. The name
                  of the new channels is suffixed with a number.
                </para>
                <tip>
                  <para>
                    You can also duplicate color channels or the Alpha channel.
                    It's an easy way to keep a copy of them and to use them later
                    as a selection in an image.
                    Note that you can only duplicate one color channel at a
                    time, and only using the right-click context menu.
                  </para>
                </tip>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-selection-replace">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Replace the Selection with Selected Channels</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This transforms the selected channels to become a selection. By
                  default the selection derived from channels replaces the
                  active selection. You can change this by using control keys.
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem id="gimp-channel-selection-add"
                    xreflabel="Add to Selection">
                    <para>
                      <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                      the selection derived from a channel is added to the
                      active selection. The final selection is merged from both.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem id="gimp-channel-selection-subtract"
                    xreflabel="Subtract from Selection">
                    <para>
                      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                      the final selection is the subtraction of the selection
                      derived from a channel from the active selection.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem id="gimp-channel-selection-intersect"
                    xreflabel="Intersect with Selection">
                    <para>
                      <keycombo>
                        <keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                      </keycombo>:
                      the final selection is the intersection of the selection
                      derived from a channel with the active one. Only the
                      selected parts common to both are kept.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-channel-delete">
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/edit-delete.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Delete Channels</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This deletes the selected channels.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
  <xi:include href="channel-menu.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="channel-selection-mask.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="qmask.xml"/>
</sect2>
