<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-03-06 lexa: reviewed and made docbook compliant
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-channel-dialog" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">

  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-09</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-25</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-10-23</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-10</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-28</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Channels dialog</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Dialog Kanály</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Der Dialog <quote>Kanäle</quote></phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Diálogo de canales</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Dialogue des canaux</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Finestra canali</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Kanaldialogen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Диалог каналов</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">通道对话框</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary><secondary>Channels</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Channel</primary>
    <secondary>Dialog</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Dialog</primary><secondary>Kanály</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Kanály</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Dialog</primary><secondary>Kanäle</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Kanal</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Diálogos</primary><secondary>Canales</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Canales</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogues</primary>
    <secondary>Canaux</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Canal</primary>
    <secondary>Dialogue</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestre</primary><secondary>Canali</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Canali</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Dialogar</primary><secondary>Kanalar</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Kanalar</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru" >
    <primary>Диалог</primary><secondary>Каналы</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Каналы</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary><secondary>通道</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>通道</primary></indexterm>


  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">The Channel dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Ansicht des Dialoges <quote>Kanäle</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">La fenêtre de dialogue des Canaux</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">El diálogo de canales</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">La finestra dei canali</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Kanaldialogen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Диалог каналов</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/de/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="es">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/it/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/no/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/ru/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-channel.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Channels dialog is the main interface to edit, modify and manage your
    channels. Channels have a double usage. This is why the dialog is divided
    into two parts: the first part for color channels and the second part for
    selection masks.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Color channels: Color channels apply to the image and not to a specific
    layer. Basically, three primary colors are necessary to render all the
    wide range of natural colors. As other digital software, the
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    uses Red, Green, and Blue as primary colors. The first and primary
    channels display the <guilabel>Red</guilabel>, <guilabel>Green</guilabel>,
    and <guilabel>Blue</guilabel>
    values of each pixel in your image. In front of each channel is a
    thumbnail displaying a grayscale representation of each channel, where
    white is 100% and black is 0% of the primary color. Alternatively, if your
    image is not a colored but a Grayscale image, there is only one primary
    channel called <guilabel>Gray</guilabel>.
    For an Indexed image with a fixed number of known colors there is also
    only one primary channel called <guilabel>Indexed</guilabel>.
    Then there is a optional channel called <guilabel>Alpha</guilabel>.
    This channel displays transparency values of each pixel in your image.
    In front of this channel is a thumbnail displaying a grayscale
    representation of the transparency where white is opaque and visible, and
    black is transparent and invisible. If you create your image without
    transparency then the Alpha channel is not present, but you can add it
    from the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers dialog menu</link>.
    Also, if you have more than one layer in your image, GIMP automatically
    creates an Alpha channel.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Dialog Kanály je hlavním rozhraním pro úpravy a správu kanálů. Smysl
    kanálů je dvojí. Proto je dialog rozdělen do dvou částí. První je určena
    pro barevné kanály a druhá je určena pro masky výběru.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Barevné kanály: Barevné kanály se týkají obrázku a nikoliv určité vrstvy.
    K zobrazení celého přirozeného barevného spektra jsou potřeba tři základní
    barvy. GIMP používá jako základní barvy červenou, zelenou a modrou (režim
    RGB). První tři kanály představují tyto základní barvy a jejich hodnoty v
    každém bodu obrázku ( <guilabel>Červená</guilabel>,
    <guilabel>Zelená</guilabel> a <guilabel>Modrá</guilabel>
    ). Před každým kanálem je malý náhled zobrazující v šedé škále daný kanál,
    bílá představuje 100% dané základní barvy, černá představuje 0% dané
    základní barvy. V případě, že váš obrázek není barevný, ale ve stupních
    šedi, existuje pouze jeden primární kanál zvaný <guilabel>Šedá</guilabel>.
    Pokud se jedná o obrázek v indexovaných barvách, existuje také jediný
    kanál, který se jmenuje <guilabel>Indexovaná</guilabel>.
    Dále existuje volitelný sekundární kanál zvaný <guilabel>Alfa</guilabel>.
    Ten nese informace o průhlednosti jednotlivých pixelů v obrázku. V jeho
    náhledu značí bílá barva neprůhledné a černá průhledné oblasti. Pokud
    obrázek vytvoříte bez průhlednosti, není alfa kanál přítomný. Můžete ho
    však přidat pomocí
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">nabídky dialogu vrstvy</link>.
    Pokud máte v obrázku více než jednu vrstvu, GIMP vytvoří alfa kanál
    automaticky.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Der Kanaldialog dient der Verwaltung der Kanäle. Der Dialog is in zwei
    Bereiche aufgeteilt. Der obere Bereich zeigt die Farbkanäle des jeweiligen
    Bildes und der untere Bereich angelegte Auswahlmasken. Die Bedienung
    gestaltet sich ähnlich dem
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Ebenendialog</link>.
    In der linken Spalte befinden sich Augensymbole, die für die
    Sichtbarkeit des jeweiligen Kanales zuständig sind. Daneben befinden sich
    graustufige Miniaturbilder, bei denen weiße Bereiche 100% und schwarze
    Bereiche 0% der Primärfarbe ausmachen. Bilder mit einem Alphakanal
    besitzen einen Eintrag, der <guilabel>Alpha</guilabel>
    heißt. Dieser Kanal repräsentiert Transparenzwerte des Bildes, wobei auch
    hier wiederum gilt: weiß heißt hundertprozentige Deckkraft der Pixel und
    schwarz völlige Durchsichtigkeit (Transparenz).
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die Farbkanäle des Bildes basieren auf dem RGB-<link
    linkend="glossary-colormodel">Farbmodell</link>. So kann das
    Gesamtbild jeweils in einen roten, grünen und blauen Kanal aufgeteilt
    werden, so dass jeder Kanal einen entsprechenden Farbwert pro Pixel im
    Bild repräsentiert. Indizierte Bilder besitzen nur einen Kanal, der den
    Namen <guilabel>Indiziert</guilabel> trägt. Bei Bildern, die von Grund auf
    keinen Alphakanal besitzen, wird dieser im Kanaldialog nicht angezeigt.
    Er kann jedoch aus dem
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Ebenendialog</link> hinzugefügt werden.
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> erstellt bei einem Bild mit mehreren Ebenen
    automatisch einen Alphakanal.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El diálogo Canales proporciona la principal interfaz para editar,
    modificar y administrar sus canales.  Los canales tienen un doble
    propósito.  Es por esto qe el diálogo se divide en dos partes: la primera
    parte es para los canales de color, y la segunda es para las máscaras de
    selección.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Los canales de color se aplican a la imagen y no a una capa es especial.
    Básicamente, hay tres colores primarios necesarios para representar todo
    el espectro de colores de la naturaleza.  Como los demás programas, el
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> usa rojo, verde y azul como colores primarios.
    Los tres primeros canales representan los colores primarios de cada píxel
    de la imagen.  Delante de cada canal hay una miniatura que muestra una
    representación en escala de grises, en las que el blanco representa al
    color primario.  Alternativamente, si su imagen no es a color, sino que es
    a escala de grises; sólo habrá un canal primario, llamado
    <guilabel>Gris</guilabel>.  Para una imagen indexada con un número fijo de
    colores conocidos, también habrá un solo canal primario, llamado
    <guilabel>Indexado</guilabel>.  También habrá un canal opcional llamado
    <guilabel>Alfa</guilabel>.  Este canal representa los valores de
    transparencia de cada píxel de su imagen.  Delante de este canal hay una
    miniatura que muestra una representación a escala de grises de la
    transparencia de la imagen, en la que el blanco puro representa a lo
    completamente opaco y visible, y el negro puro representa a lo
    completamente transparente e invisible.  Si crea una imagen sin
    transparencia, el canal alfa no estará presente, pero lo puede añadir
    desde el <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">menú del diálogo Capas</link>.
    Además, si tiene más de una capa en su imagen, el GIMP crea
    automáticamente un canal alfa.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Le dialogue des Canaux est l'interface principale pour éditer, modifier et
    gérer vos canaux. Les canaux ont un double usage, c'est pourquoi le
    dialogue est divisé en 2 parties, la première partie contient les canaux
    chromatiques et la deuxième partie les masques de sélection.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les canaux chromatiques : les canaux chromatiques s'appliquent à
    l'ensemble de l'image et pas à un calque particulier.  Fondamentalement
    il y a besoin de trois couleurs primaires pour rendre l'ensemble
    complet des couleurs naturelles. Comme les autres logiciels numériques,
    GIMP utilise le Rouge, le Vert et le Bleu comme couleurs primaires.
    Les premiers canaux primaires affichent les valeurs
    <guilabel>Rouge</guilabel>, <guilabel>Vert</guilabel> et
    <guilabel>Bleu</guilabel> de chaque pixel contenu dans votre image.
    Devant chaque canal se trouve une vignette qui montre une
    représentation en noir et blanc de celui-ci où le blanc est 100% et le
    noir 0% de la couleur primaire.  Alternativement si votre image n'est
    pas composée de couleurs mais une image en Niveaux de gris il n'y a
    plus qu'un canal appelé <guilabel>Gris</guilabel>. Pour les images
    Indexées avec un nombre fixe de couleurs connues il n'y a plus qu'un
    canal primaire appelé <guilabel>Couleurs indexées</guilabel>.  Ensuite
    il y a un canal secondaire optionnel appelé canal
    <guilabel>Alpha</guilabel>. Ce canal affiche les valeurs de
    Transparence pour chaque pixel contenu dans l'image. Devant ce canal il
    y une vignette qui montre une représentation en noir et blanc de
    celui-ci où le blanc est opaque et visible et le noir transparent et
    invisible. Si vous créez votre image sans transparence alors le
    canal Alpha ne sera pas présent ; vous pouvez l'ajouter depuis le menu
    du <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">dialogue des calques</link>.
    Également si vous avez plus d'un calque dans votre image
    GIMP créé automatiquement un canal Alpha.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    La finestra dei canali è l'interfaccia principale per alterare, modificare
    e gestire i canali. I canali hanno un duplice uso, per questo motivo la
    finestra è divisa in due parti: la prima parte per i canali dei colori e
    la seconda parte per le maschere di selezione.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Canali dei colori: i canali dei colori si riferiscono all'immagine e non
    ad uno specifico livello. Fondamentalmente per generare l'intera gamma dei
    colori naturali sono necessari tre colori primari. Come altri programmi
    digitali, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> usa come colori primari il rosso, il verde
    ed il blu. I primi che troviamo sono i canali primari e mostrano il valore
    del <guilabel>Rosso</guilabel>, del <guilabel>Verde</guilabel>, e del
    <guilabel>Blu</guilabel> di ogni pixel dell'immagine.
    Prima di ogni canale c'è una miniatura che visualizza una rappresentazione
    in scala di grigio di ogni canale, nella quale il bianco equivale al 100%
    ed il nero allo 0% del colore primario.
    In alternativa, quando l'immagine non è a colori, ma in scala di grigio,
    ci sarà solo un colore primario il <guilabel>Grigio</guilabel>.
    Anche per un'immagine indicizzata, con un numero fisso di colori noti, ci
    sarà un solo canale primario chiamato <guilabel>Indicizzato</guilabel>.
    Poi esiste un canale secondario opzionale chiamato <guilabel>Alfa</guilabel>.
    Questo canale rappresenta i valori della trasparenza di ogni pixel
    dell'immagine. Prima di questo canale c'è una miniatura che visualizza una
    rappresentazione della trasparenza dove il bianco è opaco e visibile,
    il nero è trasparente ed invisibile. Se si crea un'immagine senza
    trasparenza il canale alfa non è presente, ma può essere aggiunto dal
    <!--link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog" FIXME it -->menu dei livelli<!--/link-->.
    Inoltre, se l'immagine ha più di un livello, GIMP crea automaticamente
    un canale alfa.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kanaldialogen er hovudinngangen for å redigere, gjere endringar i og
    anna arbeid med kanalar. Kanalane blir brukte på to måtar. Det er
    difor dialogen er delt i to. Den første delen for fargekanalar og den
    andre for markeringsmasker.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Fargekanalane: Desse høyrer til heile biletet og ikkje til eit bestemt
    lag. I utgangspunktet er det nødvendig med tre primærfargar for å
    lage alle dei naturlege fargane. Som andre digitale biletprogram,
    bruker også <acronym>GIMP</acronym> raud, grøn og blå som
    primærfargane. Primærkanalane viser pikselverdiane for
    <guilabel>Raud</guilabel>, <guilabel>Grøn</guilabel> og
    <guilabel>Blå</guilabel> som ein miniatyr av kanalen. Kvit syner
    område med 100 % og svart område med 0 % dekninga av
    primærfargen. Dersom biletet er i gråskala, er det bare ein
    primærkanal, naturleg nok kalla <guilabel>Grå</guilabel>. Også
    indekserte bilete med eit bestemt tal faste fargar, har bare ein
    kanal, kalla <guilabel>Indeksert</guilabel>. Endeleg er det ein
    valfri kanal, den såkalla <guilabel>Alfakanalen</guilabel>. Denne
    kanalen viser gjennomsikt for kvar piksel i biletet i form av gråtoner.
    Kvit representerer ein ugjennomsiktig og altså synleg piksel, medan
    svart representerer ein gjennomsiktig, og altså usynleg piksel. Dersom
    du har laga biletet utan gjennomsikt, altså utan alfakanal, vil denne
    sjølvsagt heller ikkje bli vist i dialogen. Skulle du ha ønskje om å
    legge til ein alfakanal seinare, kan dette gjerast frå menyen for
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Lagdialogen</link>. Dersom du har
    meir enn eitt lag i biletet, vil <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opprette ein
    alfakanal automatisk.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Этот диалог является основным инструментом для редактирования
    и управления каналами изображения. Каналы используются в двух
    целях, поэтому диалог каналов разделён надве части: первая
    часть для цветовых каналов и вторая для масок выделения.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Цветовые каналы применяются ко всему изображению, а не  к отдельному
    слою. По существу, три основных цвета необходимы  для отображения
    всего спектра натуральных цветов. Как и  другое программное
    обеспечение <acronym>GIMP</acronym>  использует красный, зеленый и
    синий в качестве основных  цветов. Первые и главные каналы
    отображают значения  <guilabel>Красного</guilabel>,
    <guilabel>Зеленого</guilabel>,  и <guilabel>Синего</guilabel> для
    каждого пиксела в  изображении. Слева от названия канала расположена
    миниатюра,  где в градациях серого отображается содержимое канала.
    Белый в данном случае равен 100% цвета канала, а черный - 0%.  Если
    изображение в градациях серого, то будет доступен  единственный
    канал с именем <guilabel>Серый</guilabel>.  Для индексированного
    изображения с фиксированным количеством  цветов так же доступен один
    канал -  <guilabel>Индексированный</guilabel>. Под цветовыми
    каналами  располагается <guilabel>Альфа-канал</guilabel>. Этот канал
    отображает значение прозрачности каждого пиксела изображения. В
    миниатюрном изображении, находящемся слева от названия  канала,
    представлено значение прозрачности, где белый цвет  это непрозрачное
    и видимое, а чёрный - прозрачное и невидимое.  Изображение без
    прозрачности не содерижт альфа-канала,  однако вы можете добавить
    его через  <!--link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog"-->Меню слоёв<!--/link-->.
    Также если в изображении больше одного слоя, то GIMP автоматически
    создаст альфа-канал.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    通道对话框是编辑，修改和管理通道的主界面。通道有两种有法，这也是其对话框要分成两部分的原因：一部分是颜色通道，另一部分是选区通道。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    颜色通道：颜色通道应用到图像而不是一个特定的图层。一般来说，三原色足够渲染所有的自然色。与其它数码处理软件一样，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 使用红，绿和蓝这三原色。主通道显示图像中每个像素的<guilabel>红色</guilabel>，<guilabel>绿色</guilabel>和<guilabel>蓝色</guilabel>值。在每个通道前是表现每个通道的灰度缩略图，白色代表 100% 的该原色而黑色代表 0%。但如果您的图像不是彩色而是黑白(灰度)的，就只有一个叫作<guilabel>灰度</guilabel>的主通道。而对于只有一些特定颜色的索引图像而言，就只有一个叫作<guilabel>索引</guilabel>的主通道。另外，还有一个可选的次通道叫作 <guilabel>Alpha</guilabel>，它显示图像中每个像素的透明度值。在这个通道前是表现透明度的灰度缩略图，其中白色表示不透明和可见，黑色表示透明和不可见。假如创建的是没有透明度的图像，那么就没有 Alpha 通道，不过可以在<link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">图层对话框菜单</link>中添加，而且当您的图像中有多个图层，GIMP 将自动新建一个 Alpha 通道。
  </para>

  <note>
    <para lang="en">GIMP doesn't support CMYK or YUV color models.</para>
    <para lang="cs">GIMP nepodporuje barevné režimy CMYK a YUV.</para>
    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> unterstützt noch keine CMYK- und YUV-Farbmodelle.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">El GIMP no admite los modelos de color CMYK y YUV.</para>
    <para lang="fr">
      GIMP ne peut pas utiliser un modèle de couleur de type CMJN ou YUV.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      GIMP non supporta (ancora) i modelli di colore CMYK o YUV.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">GIMP har ikkje støtte for fargemodellane CMYK og YUV</para>
    <para lang="ru">
      GIMP не поддерживает цветовые модели CMYK или YUV.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">GIMP 不支持 CMYK 或 YUV 颜色模型。</para>
  </note>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Representation of an image with channels</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Příklad kanálů v obrázku</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bildkomposition durch die Farbkanäle</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Representación de una imagen con canales</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Représentation d'une image avec les canaux</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Rappresentazione di un'immagine con canali</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Biletkomposisjon  med kanalar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Представление изображения с помощью каналов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">一个带通道图像的表现</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/wilber-channels-red.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption><!-- Problem to center captions  under images and text length too  -->
        <para lang="en">Red channel</para>
        <para lang="cs"></para>
        <para lang="de">Rot-Kanal</para>
        <para lang="es"></para>
        <para lang="fr">Canal Rouge</para>
        <para lang="it"></para>
        <para lang="no">Raudkanal</para>
        <para lang="ru"></para>
        <para lang="zh_CN"></para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/wilber-channels-green.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption><!-- Problem to center captions  under images and text length too  -->
        <para lang="en">Green channel</para>
        <para lang="cs"></para>
        <para lang="de">Grün-Kanal</para>
        <para lang="es"></para>
        <para lang="fr">Canal Vert</para>
        <para lang="it"></para>
        <para lang="no">Grønkanal</para>
        <para lang="ru"></para>
        <para lang="zh_CN"></para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/wilber-channels-blue.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption><!-- Problem to center captions  under images and text length too  -->
        <para lang="en">Blue channel</para>
        <para lang="cs"></para>
        <para lang="de">Blau-Kanal</para>
        <para lang="es"></para>
        <para lang="fr">Canal Bleu</para>
        <para lang="it"></para>
        <para lang="no">Blåkanal</para>
        <para lang="ru"></para>
        <para lang="zh_CN"></para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/wilber-channels-alpha.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption><!-- Problem to center captions  under images and text length too  -->
        <para lang="en">Alpha channel</para>
        <para lang="cs"></para>
        <para lang="de">Alpha-Kanal<!-- (Transparenz) --></para>
        <para lang="es"></para>
        <para lang="fr">Canal alpha</para>
        <para lang="it"></para>
        <para lang="no">Alfakanal</para>
        <para lang="ru"></para>
        <para lang="zh_CN"></para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/wilber-channels-combined.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption><!-- Problem to center captions  under images and text length too  -->
        <para lang="en"><!-- All channels combined -->All Chanels</para>
        <para lang="cs"></para>
        <para lang="de"><!-- Das aus allen Kanälen zusammengesetzte Bild -->Alle Kanäle</para>
        <para lang="es"></para>
        <para lang="fr">Tous Canaux</para>
        <para lang="it"></para>
        <para lang="no">Resultatbiletet</para>
        <para lang="ru"></para>
        <para lang="zh_CN"></para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The right image is decomposed in three color channels (red, green, and
    blue) and the Alpha channel for transparency. On the right image the
    transparency is displayed as a gray checkerboard. In the color channel
    white is always white because all the colors are present and black is
    black. The red hat is visible in the red channel but quite invisible in
    the other channels. This is the same for plain green and blue which are
    visible only in their own channels and invisible in others.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Obrázek vpravo je rozložen do tří barevných kanálů (červený, zelený a
    modrý) a alfa kanálu pro průhlednost. Na obrázku vpravo je průhlednost
    znázorněna jako šachovnice (jakoby prosvítající zpoza obrázku). V
    barevných kanálech, bílá je vždy bílá, neboť jsou v ní přítomny všechny
    barvy, a černá je vždy černá. Červená čepička je jasně viditelná v
    červeném kanálu ale v ostatních barevných kanálech není téměř patrná.
    Totéž platí pro čistě zelenou a čistě modrou, které jsou také viditelné
    jen ve svých vlastních kanálech.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Das rechte Beispielbild besteht aus den vier Kanälen auf der linken Seite
    (Rot, Grün, Blau und Alpha). Hervorzuheben ist hier die rote Nikolausmütze
    des Wilber. Diese ist nur im roten Kanal sichtbar. In den anderen Kanälen
    taucht sie nicht auf.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    La imagen derecha está compuesta de tres canales de color (rojo, verde y
    azul) y del canal alfa para la transparencia.  Sobre la imagen derecha la
    transparencia se muestra como un tablero de ajedréz.  En el canal de
    color, el blanco es siempre blanco porque todos los colores se hayan
    presentes, y el negro es negro.  El sombrero rojo es visible en el canal
    rojo pero casi invisible en los otros dos canales.  Pasa lo mismo con el
    verde puro y con el azul puro, los que se hayan visibles sólo en sus
    propios canales, e invisibles en los otros.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'image de droite est décomposée en trois canaux chromatiques rouge, vert
    et bleu auxquels s'ajoute le canal Alpha pour la transparence. Sur l'image
    de droite la transparence est artificiellement représentée par un damier
    gris. Dans les canaux chromatiques le blanc est toujours blanc car toutes
    les couleurs sont présentes alors que le noir est noir. Le chapeau rouge
    apparaît dans le canal rouge mais est presque invisible dans les autres
    canaux. Il en est de même pour le vert et le bleu purs qui apparaîtront
    respectivement dans le canal vert et le canal bleu et seront absents dans
    les autres.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    L'immagine di destra viene scomposta nei canali dei tre colori primari
    (rosso, verde, e blu) oltre al canale alfa per la trasparenza.
    Nell'immagine di destra la trasparenza viene visualizzata a scacchi grigi.
    Nei canali dei colori il bianco è sempre bianco, perchè sono presenti
    tutti i colori, ed il nero è nero. Il capello rosso è distinguibile nel
    canale rosso, ma è quasi impercettibile negli altri canali. Questo vale
    anche per le parti completamente verdi e blu che sono distinguibili solo
    nei loro rispettivi canali ed impercettibili negli altri.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Biletet heilt til høgre er sett saman av dei fire kanalane, raud, grøn, blå
    og alfa. Sjakkbrettmønsteret viser gjennomsiktige område. Sidan kvit
    farge i den brukte fargemodellen er sett saman av alle primærfagane,
    vil kvit vere kvitfarga (100 %) i alle kanalane. Svart er mangel på
    farge, og vil difor visast som svart (0 %) i alle kanalane. Den raude
    hatten er synleg i raudkanalen, men ikkje i dei andre. Dette gjeld for alle
    reine grøne eller blå fargar også. Dei er bare synlege i respektive
    kanalar.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Рисунок, который вы видите справа, состоит из трех цветовых
    каналов (красный, зелёный, синий) и альфа-канала. Прозрачные области
    рисунка отображаются в виде серых клеток. В цветовых каналах белый
    всегда является белым, поскольку он состоит из всех основных цветов в их
    максимальном значении, а чёрный - чёрным, т.к. значение всех основных
    цветов в нем равно нулю. Красная шляпа видна в красном канале, но совсем
    не видна в других. То же самое происходит и с другими чистыми зелёным и
    синим цветами, которые видны только в своих каналах и невидимы в других.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    右边的图像分解为三个颜色通道(红，绿和蓝)和表示透明度的 Alpha
    通道。右边图像其透明部分用一个灰色棋盘格子表示。颜色通道中白色总是显示为白色，因为它包括所有颜色，而黑色则总是黑色。红帽在红色通道中可见，但在其它通道中就看不到，对没有杂色的绿和蓝也是一样，只在自己通道中可见。
  </para>


  <sect3 id="gimp-channel-dialog-calling">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Calling the Dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Vyvolání dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Dialogaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Apertura del diálogo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Lancement du dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Visualizzazione della finestra</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering av dialogen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Вызов диалога</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">唤出对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">The Channel dialog can be activated in many ways :</para>
    <para lang="cs">Dialog Kanály lze vyvolat několika způsoby:</para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der Kanaldialog kann auf verschiedenen Wegen erreicht werden:
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El diálogo de canales puede ser activado de varias maneras:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le dialogue des canaux peut être appelé de plusieurs façons :
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      La finestra dei canali può essere richiamata in molti modi:
    </para>
    <para lang="no">Kanaldialogen kan hentast fram på mange måtar:</para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Диалог управления каналами может быть вызван различными способами:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">有多种方法唤出通道对话框：</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          from the toolbox-menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          z nabídky Panelu nástrojů:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dialogy</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kanály</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          aus dem Werkzeugfenstermenü:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>D</accel>ialoge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>K</accel>anäle</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          desde el menú de la caja de herramientas:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Archivo</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Diálogos</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canales</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          depuis le menu de la boîte à outils :
          <guimenuitem>Fichier</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>Dialogues</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>Canau<accel>x</accel></guimenuitem>
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          dal menu della barra degli strumenti:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Finestre</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canali</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          frå menyen i verktøyskrinet:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dialogar</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kanalar</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Через меню панели инструментов:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Файл</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Диалоги</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>К</accel>аналы</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          在工具箱菜单：
          <guimenuitem>文件</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>对话框</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>通道</guimenuitem>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          from the image-menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          z nabídky obrázku:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Dialogy</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kanály</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          aus dem Bildmenü:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>ialoge</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>K</accel>anäle</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Diálogos</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canales</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          depuis le menu de la fenêtre d'image :
          <guimenuitem>Dialogues</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>Canau<accel>x</accel></guimenuitem>
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          dal menu della finestra dell'immagine:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Finestre</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canali</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          frå biletmenyen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Dialogar</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kanalar</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Через меню изображения:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Диалоги</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Каналы</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          在图像菜单：
          <guimenuitem>对话框</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>通道</guimenuitem>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          from another dialog-menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          z nabídky jiného dialogu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Přidat kartu</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kanály</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          aus einem anderen Dialogmenü:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Reiter <accel>h</accel>inzufügen</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>K</accel>anäle</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          desde otro menú de diálogo:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Añadir solapa</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canales</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          depuis le menu d'un autre dialogue :
          <guimenuitem>Ajouter un onglet</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>Canau<accel>x</accel></guimenuitem>
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          dal menu delle altre finestre:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Aggiungi scheda</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Canali</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          eller frå ein annan dialogmeny:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Legg til fane</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kanalar</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Через меню любого другого диалога:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Добавить закладку</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Каналы</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          在其它的对话框菜单：
          <guimenuitem>添加页签</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>通道</guimenuitem>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3> <!-- end Dialog call -->


  <sect3 id="gimp-channel-dialog-using">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Using the Channel dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Použití dialogu kanály</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Aufbau und Benutzung des Dialoges <quote>Kanäle</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Empleo del diálogo de canales</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Utilisation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Utilizzo della finestra dei canali</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å bruke kanaldialogen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Использование диалога каналов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用通道对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <sect4 id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-overview">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Přehled</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Übersicht</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Generalidades</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Oversyn</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">概述</phrase>
      </title>

      <para lang="en">
        The top channels are the color channels and the optional Alpha
        channel. They are always organized in the same order and they cannot
        be erased. Selection masks are described below and displayed as a list
        in the dialog. Every channel appears in the list in form of a
        thumbnail. A right-click in a channel thumbnail opens the
        <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">channel menu</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        nahoře jsou barevné kanály a případně volitelný alfa kanál. jsou vždy
        ve stejném pořadí a není možné je smazat. Masky výběru jsou popsané
        níže a jsou zobrazeny v dialogu jako seznam. Každý kanál je v seznamu
        zobrazen jako náhled. Kliknutím pravým tlačítkem myši na dialog kanálu
        otevře <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">nabídku kanálu</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die Farbkanäle und der Alphakanal können über diesen Dialog nicht
        gelöscht werden. Jeder Kanal erscheint in der Liste in Form eines
        Vorschaubildes. Ein Rechtsklick hierauf öffnet das
        <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">Kanalmenü</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Los primeros canales son los canales de color y el canal alfa,
        opcional.  Están siempre organizados en el mismo orden, y no se pueden
        borrar.  Las máscaras de selección se describen debajo, y se muestran
        como una lista en el diálogo.  Cada canal aparece en la lista en forma
        de miniatura.  Un clic derecho sobre la miniatura de un canal abre el
        <!-- PENDING: ES link linkend="gimp-channel-menu"-->menú del
        canal<!--/link-->.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les canaux supérieurs sont les canaux chromatiques et le canal Alpha
        optionnel. Ils sont toujours présents dans le même ordre et ils ne
        peuvent pas être effacés. Les masques de sélection apparaissent
        en-dessous sous la forme d'une liste dans le dialogue. Chaque canal
        apparaît dans la liste sous la forme d'une vignette. En cliquant-droit
        sur la vignette d'un canal on fait apparaître le menu des canaux (voir
        au chapitre Menu).
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        I canali in cima sono quelli dei colori ed il canale alfa opzionale.
        Sono sempre disposti nello stesso ordine e non possono essere
        cancellati. Le maschere di selezione vengono descritte e visualizzate
        in una lista subito sotto. Nella lista ogni canale appare in forma di
        miniatura. Facendo clic con il tasto destro del mouse sulla miniatura
        di un canale si apre il<!--link linkend="gimp-channel-menu" FIXME it -->
        menu dei canali<!--/link-->.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Den øvre delen av dialogvindauget inneheld fargekanalane og eventuelt
        alfakanalen. Dei er alltid sett opp på same måten og kan ikkje fjernast.
        Under desse finn du eventuelle markeringsmasker. Kvar kanal blir vist
        i lista som ein miniatyr. Du kan høgreklikka på denne miniatyren for
        å få fram <!--PENDING:no
        <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu"-->kanalmenyen<!--/link-->.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        В верхней части списка каналов расположены цветовые каналы и
        дополнительный альфа-канал для прозрачности. Они всегда располагаются
        в одном и том же порядке и не могут быть удалены. Ниже следуют маски
        выделения. Каждый канал представляется в списке в виде
        изображения-миниатюры Щелчок правой кнопкой мыши по миниатюре канала
        открывает <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">Меню канала</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        最上面的通道是颜色通道和可选的 Alpha
        通道，它么总是保持这样的排列并且不能被删除。选区蒙板在下面有描述，它在对话框中也列表形式显示。列表中的每个通道则以缩略图的形式出现。在一个通道缩略图上右键点击则打开
        <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">通道菜单</link>。
      </para>
    </sect4><!-- end Overview -->

    <sect4 id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-attributes">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Channel attributes</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Atributy kanálu</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Kanalattribute</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Atributos de los canales</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Attributs d'un canal</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Proprietà dei canali</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Kanaleigenskapane</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Атрибуты канала</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">通道属性</phrase>
      </title>

      <para lang="en">
        Every channel is shown in the list with its own attributes. The main
        attribute is the name of the channel itself. You can edit selection
        masks by double-clicking on their name. A double_click on the
        thumbnail opens a full dialog where you can also set the visual aspect
        of the channel in the image window. In front of the thumbnail there is
        an eye icon:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        by clicking on it you define whether the channel is visible or not. As
        a result of this visibility, the view of the image changes in the
        image window and a white image becomes yellow if you remove the view
        of the blue because yellow is the complementary color for blue. If you
        remove the view of the Alpha channel, everything becomes transparent
        and nothing else than a grey checkerboard is visible. The aspect of
        this virtual background can be changed in the
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Preferences</link>. The chain icon
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        enables grouping of channels for operations on multiple channels.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        Každý kanál zobrazený v seznamu má své atributy. Hlavním atributem je
        jméno kanálu. Jméno masek výběru můžete upravit po dvojitým kliknutím.
        Dvojité kliknutí na náhled otevře celý dialog, ve kterém můžete kromě
        jména nastavit i vizuální aspekty zobrazení kanálu v okně obrázku.
        Před náhledem může být ikona oka:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        Kliknutím na ikonu oka se přepíná viditelnost kanálu v okně obrázku.
        Pokud například učiníte modrá kanál neviditelným, bílá barva v obrázku
        zežloutne, protože žlutá barva je vůči modré doplňková. Pokud
        zneviditelníte alfa kanál, stane se vše zcela průhledným a uvidíte jen
        šachovnici představující pozadí za obrázkem. Toto pozadí lze nastavit
        v <!-- FIXMECS<link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">-->Předvolbách<!--</link>-->.
        Ikona řetězu
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        umožňuje seskupování kanálů pro operace nad více kanály současně.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Jeder Kanal hat drei Attribute, die ähnlich wie die Ebenenattributen
        verwendet werden können.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Cada canal que muestra en la lista con sus propios atributos. El
        atributo principal es el nombre mismo del canal. Puede editar el
        nombre de las máscaras de selección haciendo doble clic sobre su
        nombre. Un clic doble sobre su miniatura abre todo un diálogo en donde
        puede además cambiar el aspecto visual del canal en la ventana de la
        imagen. Delante de la miniatura hay un icono en forma de ojo:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        haciendo clic sobre éste puede definir si el canal está visible o no.
        Como resultado de su visibilidad, la vista de la imagen cambia en su
        ventana. Si quita la visibilidad del canal azul, la imagen se vuelve
        amarilla porque el amarillo es el color complementario del azul. Si
        quita la visibilidad del canal alfa, todo se vuelve transparente y
        sólo queda visible un tablero de ajedrez. El aspecto de este fondo
        virtual se puede cambiar en las
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">preferencias</link>.
        El icono en forma de cadena
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        activa la agrupación de canales para operar sobre varios a la vez.
      </para>

      <variablelist lang="de">
        <anchor id="channel-attributes" />

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                            fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            <phrase lang="de">Augensymbol</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="de">
              Standardmäßig ist jeder Kanal und somit jeder Farbanteil eines
              Bildes für den Benutzer sichtbar. Um die Sichtbarkeit eines
              Kanals zu verändern, genügt ein Linksklick auf das Augensymbol.
              Hierdurch wird der entsprechenden Farbanteil des Bildes
              ausgeblendet, und das Augensymbol verschwindet aus der Spalte.
              Durch wiederholtes Klicken in den Leerraum wird der Farbanteil
              des Kanals im Bild wieder sichtbar.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="de">Kanalname</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="de">
              Die Namen der Primärkanäle (Rot, Grün, Blau, Alpha) können nicht
              verändert werden. Kanäle, die im unteren Bereich des Kanaldialogs
              angelegt werden, lassen sich durch einen Doppelklick umbenennen.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            <phrase lang="de">Kettensymbol</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="de">
              Neu angelegte Kanäle in der unteren Hälfte des Dialogs können
              mit Hilfe des Kettensymbols gruppiert werden. Hierdurch lassen
              sich auf die gruppierte Kanäle simultan Operationen ausführen.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Für die Primärkanäle gibt es ebenfalls eine
              Gruppierungsmöglichkeit. Standardmäßig werden Operationen auf
              allen Kanälen ausgeführt, da jeder Kanal selektiert (farbig
              hinterlegt) ist. Sie können einzelne Kanäle aus der Gruppierung
              entfernen, indem Sie mit der linken Maustaste auf den Namen des
              Kanals klicken und somit die Auswahl aufheben. Klicken sie
              nochmals auf den Namen, ist der Kanal wieder mit auszuwählen.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para lang="fr">
        Chaque canal apparaît dans la liste accompagné de ses attributs. Le
        principal attribut est bien entendu le nom dudit canal. Pour les
        masques de sélection on peut facilement l'éditer en double-cliquant
        sur son nom. Un double-clic sur la vignette ouvre un dialogue plus
        complet qui permet aussi de régler l'apparence visuelle du canal dans
        la fenêtre d'image. Devant la vignette il y a une icône en forme
        d'œil
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        , en cliquant dessus on définit si le canal est visible ou non.
        L'affichage de l'image change en conséquence dans la fenêtre d'image
        et une image blanche deviendra jaune si vous enlevez l'affichage du
        bleu car le jaune est le complémentaire du bleu. Si vous enlevez
        l'affichage du canal Alpha tout devient transparent et plus rien
        d'autre qu'un damier gris n'apparaît. L'apparence de ce fond fictif
        représentatif de la transparence peut être modifié dans les
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Préférences</link>.
        Une autre icône en forme de chaîne
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        permet de grouper des canaux des masques de sélection pour effectuer
        une opération simultanément sur plusieurs masques.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Nella lista ogni canale viene visualizzato assieme alle sue proprietà.
        La proprietà principale è il nome del canale stesso. Si può modificare
        il nome delle maschere di selezione facendo un doppio clic sul loro
        nome. Il doppio clic sulla minatura fa comparire una finestra dove si
        può impostare l'aspetto visivo che assume il canale nella finestra
        dell'immagine. Prima della miniatura c'è un'icona che raffigura
        un'occhio:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        facendo clic su quest'occhio si attiva o disattiva la visibilità del
        canale. La visualizzazione dell'immagine nella finestra principale
        cambia, come conseguenza di questa visibilità, e, ad esempio,
        un'immagine bianca diventa gialla se viene rimossa la visibilità del
        blu, dato che il giallo è il colore complementare al blu. Se si
        rimuove la visibilità del canale alfa, tutto diventa trasparente e non
        sarà visibile altro che una scacchiera grigia. L'aspetto di questo
        sfondo virtuale può essere modificato nelle
        <!--link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog" FIXME it -->Preferenze<!--/link-->
        . L'icona a forma di catena
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        abilita il raggruppamento dei canali per operazioni da eseguire su più
        di essi.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        I tillegg til miniatyren, blir det også vist ein del andre eigenskapar
        for kvar kanal. Den viktigaste er kanalnamnet. Du kan redigera
        markeringsmasker, i praksis bare forandra namnet på kanalen, ved
        å dobbeltklikka på namnet. Dobbelklikkar du på miniatyren vil du
        derimot få opp eit dialogvindauge der du i tillegg kan bestemma
        dekkevna for kanalen. Framføre miniatyren finn du eit bilete av eit
        auge:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>.
        Ved å klikka på dette ikonet, kan du bestemma om kanalen skal vere
        synleg eller ikkje. Gjer du t.d. blåkanalen usynleg, vil alt som er kvitt
        i bilete bli gult. Dette fordi gul er koplimentærfargen til blå. Gjer du
        alfakanalen usynleg, vil alt i biletet bli gjennomsiktig og det einaste du
        ser er sjakkbrettmønsteret. (Du kan forandre mønsteret som viser
        gjennomsikt i menyen for <!--PENDING:no <link
        linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog"-->Innstillingar<!--/link-->). Mellom auget og
        miniatyren finn du eit ikon som viser ei lenke:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>.
        Du gjer lenka synleg eller usynleg ved å klikka på symbolet. Alle
        kanalane som har synleg lenke, er grupperte saman slik at du kan
        arbeida på alle samstundes.
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        Каждый отображаемый в списке канал имеет свои атрибуты. Основной
        атрибут канала - название. У масок выделения название можно изменить,
        нажав на них дважды левой кнопкой мыши. Двойной щелчок по строке
        канала открывает полный диалог, в котором устанавливается цвет и
        значение прозрачности при отображении канала в окне изображения. Перед
        миниатюрой находится значок глаза:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        Щёлкая по нему вы указываете, является канал видимым или нет. В
        результате этого в окне изображения изменяется вид рисунка. Например,
        если в белом изображении отключить видимость синего канала, то
        картинка станет желтой, а если отключить просмотр альфа-канала, то все
        изображение станет прозрачным и ничего, кроме клетчатого фона, не
        будет видно. Кстати, вид этого виртуального фона можно изменить
        диалоге <!--link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog"-->Настройки<!--/link-->
        . Пиктограмма в виде цепочки
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        разрешает группировку каналов. В результате последующие изменения
        будут применяться ко всем сгруппированным каналам.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        列表中显示的每个通道都有自己的属性。最主要的属性就是通道自己的名字，双击它们的名字就可以更改选区蒙板的名字，而双击缩略图则会打开一个完整对话框，在其中还能设置通道在图像窗口中视觉方面的选项。在缩略图前则有一个眼睛图标：
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-eye.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        通过点击它，您就定义该通道是否可见。调整该可见性的结果就是，改变图像窗口中图像显示，比如去掉蓝色显示，一个白色图像将变为黄色，因为黄色是蓝色的补色。假如去掉
        Alpha 通道的显示，所有图像都变为透明，只能看到一个灰色的棋盘格子。该虚拟背景可以在
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">首选项</link>
        中更改。链条图标
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-vchain.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        组合多个通道，可以对它们一起操作。
      </para>

      <caution lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="en">
          Activated channels appear highlighted (generally) in blue in the
          dialog. If you click on a channel in the list you toggle activation
          of the corresponding channel. Disabling a color channel red, blue,
          or green has severe consequencies. For instance if you disable the
          blue channel, all pixels from now on added to the image will not
          have blue component, and so a white pixel will have the yellow
          complementary color.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Aktivierte Kanäle sind im Dialog hervorgehoben (üblicherweise
          blau). Wenn Sie auf einen Eintrag in dieser Liste klicken, wird der
          Zustand des zugehörigen Kanals (aktiv / nicht aktiv) umgeschaltet.
          Das Deaktivieren eines der drei Farbkanäle Rot, Grün oder Blau hat
          schwerwiegende Folgen. Wenn Sie beispielsweise den blauen Kanal
          deaktivieren, verfügen alle Pixel, die Sie später dem Bild
          hinzufügen, nicht mehr über eine Blaukomponente, so dass ein weißer
          Pixel in der Komplementärfarbe Gelb erscheint.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Aktivované kanály jsou v dialogu zvýrazněny (barevně vysvíceny).
          Kliknutím na kanál v seznamu přepnete jeho aktivaci. Deaktivace
          barevného kanálu mívá vážné důsledky. Pokud například zakážete modrý
          kanál, všem pixelům přidávaným do obrázku bude chybět modrá složka a
          proto se například bílá bude jevit jako k modré doplňková žlutá
          barva.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Los canales activos aparecen resaltados en el diálogo (en general en
          azul).  Si hace clic sobre un canal de la lista, se cambia su
          activación.  La desactivación de un canal primario trae aparejada
          severas consecuencias.  Por ejemplo, si desactiva el canal azul,
          todos los píxeles que se añadan a la imagen desde ahora en adelante
          no tendrán componente azul, y por lo tanto un píxel blanco tendrá
          color amarillo (el complementario del azul).
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Les canaux actifs apparaissent surlignés (en général en bleu) dans
          le dialogue.
          Si vous cliquez sur un canal dans la liste vous (dés)activez le
          canal correspondant. Désactiver un canal chromatique rouge, vert ou
          bleu n'est pas sans conséquence. Par exemple si vous désactivez le
          canal bleu tous les pixels qui seront ultérieurement ajoutés
          n'auront pas de composante bleue, c'est à dire qu'un pixel blanc
          prendra la couleur complémentaire jaune.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          I canali attivi nella finestra appaiono evidenziati in blu. Se si fa
          un clic su di un canale nella lista si attiva o disattiva il canale
          corrispondente. Disabilitare uno dei canali dei colori rosso, verde
          o blu porta numerose conseguenze. Ad esempio, se si disabilita il
          canale del blu, da quel momento in poi tutti i pixel aggiunti
          all'immagine non avranno la componente blu, pertanto un pixel bianco
          assumerà il colore complementare, ossia il giallo.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Aktive kanalar blir markerte i dialogen med ein eller annan farge,
          ofte blå eller grøn. Klikkar du på kanalen, kan du slå aktiveringa
          av eller på. Dersom du slår av ein av fargekanalane, kan dette få
          uventa konsekvensar. Dersom du t.d. slår av blåkanalen, vil alle
          pikslane som blir teikna på biletet mangla blåfarge. Ein kvit piksel
          vil såleis bli gul, som er komplimentærfargen til blå.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          В диалоге активные каналы подсвечены синим. При нажатии на строке
          канала активный канал становится неактивным и наоборот. Отключение
          цветовых каналов (красного, синего, зеленого) влечет за собой
          серьезные последствия. Например, если вы отключили синий канал, все
          пиксели, добавляемые с этого момента к изображению, не будут иметь
          синего компонента. В результате белый пиксель будет выглядеть желтым
          и т.п.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          通道被开启后用蓝色高亮表示。在列表中点击一个通道切换相应通道是否开启。关闭一个红色，蓝色或绿色的颜色通道会产生严重的后果。比如假如您关闭蓝色通道，那从现在起，任何添加到图像上的像素将没有蓝色成分，因此一个白色像素就变为黄色。
        </para>
      </caution>
    </sect4><!-- end Attributs -->


    <sect4 id="gimp-channel-dialog-using-managing">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Managing channels</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Správa kanálů</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Kanäle verwalten</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Gestión de los canales</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Gestion des canaux</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Gestione dei canali</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Handtering av kanalane</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Управление каналами</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">管理通道</phrase>
      </title>

      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Channel</primary>
        <secondary>Edit Channel Attributes</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Channel</primary>
        <secondary>Create a New Channel mask</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Channel</primary>
        <secondary>Move Channel mask</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Channel</primary>
        <secondary>Duplicate Channel mask</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Channel</primary>
        <secondary>Delete Channel mask</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Channel</primary>
        <secondary>Channel to Selection</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Canal</primary>
        <secondary>Éditer les Attributs du canal</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Canal</primary>
        <secondary>Créer un nouveau canal de sélection</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Canal</primary>
        <secondary>Déplacer un canal de sélection</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Canal</primary>
        <secondary>Dupliquer un canal de sélection</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Canal</primary>
        <secondary>Effacer un canal de sélection</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Canal</primary>
        <secondary>Canal vers sélection</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para lang="en">
        Under the channel list is a set of buttons allowing you to perform
        some basic operations on channel list.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pod seznamem kanálů je sada tlačítekumožňujících provádět s kanály
        základní operace.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Im unteren Bereich des Kanaldialogs befinden sich Schaltflächen, die
        der Verwaltung der Kanäle dienen. Bitte denken Sie daran, dass sich
        die Verwaltung der Kanäle auf neu angelegte Kanäle im unteren
        Dialogbereich bezieht.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Debajo de la lista de canales hay un conjunto de botones que le
        permiten realizar algunas operaciones básicas con los mismos.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        En dessous de la liste des canaux une série de boutons permet
        d'effectuer quelques opérations sur la liste des canaux.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Al di sotto della lista un insieme di pulsanti permette di eseguire
        alcune operazioni basilari sui canali.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Under kanallista finn du eit sett med knappar som kan brukast til
        ulike operasjonar på lista.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Под списком каналов располагается набор кнопок, позволяющих
        выполнять основные действия со списком.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">通道列表下方是一些可以对通道列表进行基本操作的按钮。</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-edit" />
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-edit.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">Edit channel attributes,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Upravit atributy kanálu,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Kanaleigenschaften bearbeiten</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Editar los atributos del canal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Éditer les attributs du canal,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Modifica attributi del canale,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Rediger kanaleigenskapane</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Редактирование атрибутов канала,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">编辑通道属性，</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              only available for selection masks. Here you can change the
              <guilabel>Channel name</guilabel>. The other two parameters
              affect channel is visibility in the image window; they control
              <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> and color used for the mask in the
              image window. A click on the color button displays the Gimp
              color selector and then you can change the mask color.
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              je aktivní jen pro
              masky výběru. Umožňuje změnit <guilabel>Název kanálu</guilabel>
              a viditelnost kanálů v okně obrázku – průhlednost a barvu masky
              kanálu v okně obrázku. Kliknutím na barevnou oblast se otevře
              klasický dialog pro výběr barev v GIMPu.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Diese Schaltfläche bietet die Möglichkeit, den Namen des Kanals,
              die Deckkraft und die Indikatorfarbe zu verändern. Die
              Veränderung der Deckkraft ist analog zur
              <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog-opacity-scale">
                Deckkraft von Ebenen</link> einzustellen.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Sólo disponible para las máscaras de selección.  Aquí puede
              cambiar el <guilabel>nombre del canal</guilabel>.  Los otros dos
              parámetros afectan a la visibilidad del canal en la ventana de
              la imagen.  Controlan la <guilabel>opacidad</guilabel> y el
              color empleado por la máscara en la ventana de la imagen.  Un
              clic sobre el botón del color abre el selector de colores del
              GIMP, y ahí puede escoger el color de la máscara.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              ce dialogue n'est disponible que pour les Masques de sélection.
              Vous pouvez changer le <guilabel>Nom du canal</guilabel>.
              Les deux autres paramètres concernent la façon dont le canal est
              visible dans la fenêtre d'image, ils permettent de contrôler l'
              <guilabel>Opacité</guilabel>
              et la couleur du masque affiché dans l'image. Un clic dans la
              couleur représentée dans le dialogue ouvre le sélecteur de couleur
              de GIMP et vous pouvez alors changer la couleur du masque.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              disponibile solo per le maschere di selezione. Da qui si può
              modificare il <guilabel>nome del canale</guilabel>.
              Gli altri due parametri influenzano la visibilità del canale
              nella finestra immagine; controllano rispettivamente l'
              <guilabel>Opacità</guilabel>
              ed il colore utilizzato per la maschera nella finestra
              dell'immagine. Un clic sul pulsante del colore fa apparire il
              selettore dei colori di GIMP dal quale è possibile cambiare il
              colore della maschera.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              er bare tilgjengeleg for markeringsmasker, og blir brukt for å
              gi kanalen eit nytt <guilabel>kanalnamn</guilabel>. Dei to
              andre kontrollane påverkar korleis kanalen blir vist i
              vindauget. Den eine er <guilabel>Dekkevne</guilabel> og den
              andre opnar fargeveljaren slik at du kan endra maskefargen.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              доступен только для масок выделения. Здесь вы можете изменить
              <guilabel>Имя канала</guilabel>. Два других парамера
              влияют на видимость канала в окне изображениия.
              Это <guilabel>Непрозрачность заливки</guilabel> и
              цвет, используемый для маски в окне изображения. Щелчок
              по кнопке цвета вызывает диалог выбора цвета GIMP.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              只对选区蒙板有效。在其中可以改变
              <guilabel>通道名字</guilabel>，另外两个参数影响通道在图像窗口中的可见度；它控制
              <guilabel>不透明度</guilabel> 和在图像窗口中蒙板的颜色。单击颜色按钮，会显示 GIMP 颜色选择器，然后改变蒙板颜色。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-new" />
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-new.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">New channel</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Nový kanál</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Neuer Kanal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Canal nuevo</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Nouveau canal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Nuovo canale</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Ny kanal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Новый канал</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">新建通道</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <!--TODO cs es it no ru zh_CN-->
            <para lang="en"> <!--changed 070612-->
              You can create here a new channel. The displayed dialog lets
              you set <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> and mask color used in
              the image to represent the selection. (If you use the
              <guibutton>New Channel</guibutton> button in Channel Menu,
              you can create this new channel with the options previously
              used by pressing the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key when clicking).
              This new channel is a channel mask (a selection mask) applied
              over the image. See
              <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Selection Mask</link>
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              umožňuje vytvořit nový kanál pro uložení výběru. V zobrazeném
              dialogu můžete měnit krytí a barvu pro reprezentaci kanálu v
              okně obrázku.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Durch Klicken auf die Schaltfläche wird ein neuer Kanal angelegt,
              der eine Deckkraft von 50% besitzt und einen Standardnamen trägt.
              Möchten Sie einen Dialog zur Erstellung eines neuen Kanals
              sehen, halten Sie die <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste
              gedrückt, während Sie auf die Schaltfläche klicken. Sie
              können in dem jetzt erscheinenden Dialog einen
              <guilabel>Kanalnamen</guilabel> und die
              <guilabel>Deckkraft</guilabel> bestimmen.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Puede crear aquí un nuevo canal, disponible para guardar una
              selección.  El diálogo que se abre le permite cambiar la
              <guilabel>opacidad</guilabel> y el color de la máscara que va a
              usarse en la imagen para representar a la selección.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              En cliquant sur cette option, vous ouvrez la fenêtre
              <quote>Options de Nouveau Canal</quote>qui vous
              permet de donner un <guilabel>Nom au canal</guilabel>
              et de régler l' <guilabel>Opacité</guilabel>
              et la couleur du masque qui sera affichée dans l'image pour
              représenter la sélection. (Si vous utilisez le bouton
              <guibutton>Nouveau Canal</guibutton>, vous pouvez créer ce
              nouveau canal avec les options déjà utilisées pour cela en
              appuyant sur la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> lors du clic). Ce
              nouveau canal est un masque de canal (un masque de sélection)
              appliqué sur l'image. Voyez
              <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Masque de
                sélection</link>
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              da qui è possibile creare un nuovo canale per salvarvi una
              selezione. La finestra che viene visualizzata permette di
              modificare l' <guilabel>Opacità</guilabel>
              ed il colore della maschera usato nell'immagine per
              rappresentare la selezione.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              blir brukt for å oppretta ein ny kanal å lagra ei markering i.
              Du kan bruke visingsdialogen ovanfor for å endre
              <guilabel>Dekkevne</guilabel> og farge som blir brukt i
              biletet for å vise markeinga.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              вы можете создать новый канал для сохранения выделения.
              Отображаемый диалог позволяет изменить
              <guilabel>Непрозрачность заливки</guilabel> и цвет маски.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              这里您能新建一个可以保存选区的通道。其对话框让您改变
              <guilabel>不透明度</guilabel> 和在图像中蒙板用作表现选区的颜色。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-raise" />
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-raise.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">Raise channel,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Kanál výš</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Kanal anheben</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Elevar canal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Remonter le canal,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Alza il canale,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Løft kanalen</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Поднять канал</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">升高通道，</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              only available for selection masks : you can here put the
              channel up a level in the list. Press <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              key to move channel to top of the list.
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              je dostupný pouze pro masky výběru. Umožňuje přesunout kanál v
              seznamu o příčku výše. Spolu s klávesou <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              umožňuje přesunout seznam až na vrchol seznamu.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Der Kanal kann um einen Schritt in der Kanalliste nach oben
              verschoben werden. Um den Kanal an den Anfang der Liste (oben)
              zu verschieben, halten Sie bitte die
              <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste gedrückt.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Sólo se haya disponible para las máscaras de selección.  Con
              éste puede subir al canal en un nivel en la lista.  Presione la
              tecla <keycap>Shift</keycap> para mover el canal a la cima de la
              lista.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              uniquement disponible pour les Masques de sélection :
              permet de remonter le canal d'un rang dans la liste. Appuyez sur
              <keycap>Maj</keycap> pour monter le canal tout en haut de la
              liste.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              disponibile solo per le maschere di selezione: da qui è
              possibile spostare il canale in su di una posizione all'interno
              della lista. Premendo il tasto <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
              si sposta il canale in cima alla lista.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              er bare tilgjengeleg for markeringsmasker, og blir brukt for å
              løfta kanalen eitt hakk oppover, eller til topps om du held nede
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten samstundes.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              эта функция  доступна только для масок выделения:
              вы можете перемещать канал вверх по списку
              Нажатие совместно с клавишей <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              перемещает канал в начало списка.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              只对选区蒙板有效：这里您可以将通道在列表中向上移动一位。按住
              <keycap>Shift</keycap> 则移动通道到列表最顶部。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-lower" />
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-lower.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">Lower channel</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Kanál níž</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Kanal absenken</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Bajar el canal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Descendre le canal,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Abbassa il canale</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Senk kanalen</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Опустить канал</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">降低通道</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              You can here put the channel down a level in the list. Press the
              <keycap>Shift</keycap> key to move the channel to bottom of the
              list.
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              Umožňuje přesunout kanál v seznamu o příčku níže. Spolu s
              klávesou <keycap>Shift</keycap> přesune kanál až naspod seznamu.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Der Kanal kann um ein Schritt nach unten verschoben werden.
              Möchten Sie den Kanal an das Ende der Liste (unten) verschieben,
              halten Sie bitte die <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste gedrückt.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Con éste puede bajar al canal en un nivel en la lista.  Presione
              la tecla <keycap>Shift</keycap> para mover al canal al fondo de
              la lista.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              uniquement disponible pour les Masques de sélection : permet de
              descendre le canal d'un rang dans la liste. Appuyez sur
              <keycap>Maj</keycap> pour descendre le canal tout en bas de la
              liste.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              da qui è possibile spostare il canale in giù di una posizione
              all'interno della lista. Premendo il tasto
              <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> si sposta il canale in fondo alla lista.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              er bare tilgjengeleg for markeringsmasker, og blir brukt for å
              senke kanalen eitt hakk nedover, eller til botnen om du held
              nede <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten samstundes.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              с помощью этой функции можно перемещать канал вниз
              по списку. Нажатие совместно с клавишей
              <keycap>Shift</keycap> перемещает канал в конец списка.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              这里您可以将通道在列表中向下移动一位。按住 <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              则移动通道到列表最底部。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-duplicate" />
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-duplicate.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">Duplicate channel</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Duplikovat kanál</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Kanal duplizieren</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Duplicar el canal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Dupliquer le canal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Duplica il canale</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Kopier kanalen</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Создать копию канала</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">复制通道</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              You can create here a copy of the active channel. Name of new
              channel is suffixed with a number.
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              Umožňuje vytvořit kopii aktivního kanálu. Jméno kanálu je
              doplněno číslem.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Erstellen Sie eine Kopie des aktuell ausgewählten Kanals,
              indem Sie auf die Schaltfläche klicken.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Con éste puede crear una copia del canal activo.  El nombre del
              nuevo canal se obtiene agregando un número como sufijo del canal
              original.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              permet de créer une copie du canal actif. Le nom du nouveau
              canal est suffixé par un chiffre.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              da qui è possibile creare una copia del canale attivo. Al nome
              del nuovo canale viene aggiunto un numero.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              blir brukt for å lage ein kopi av kanalen. Kopien får same
              namnet som originalen med <quote>Kopi av</quote>
              framføre.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              С помощью этой функции вы можете создать копию
              активного канала. К имени нового канала добавляется
              суффикс с номером.
              <!--FIXME: ru добавляется слово 'копировать'! -->
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">这里您可以创建当前通道的一份拷贝。新通道名字由源通道名字后面再加一个数字构成。</para>

            <tip>
              <para lang="en">
                You can also duplicate a color channel or the Alpha channel.
                It's an easy way to keep a copy of them and to use them later
                as a selection in an image.
              </para>
              <para lang="cs">
                Duplikovat můžete i barevný nebo alfa kanál. Je to zajímavý
                způsob, jak si vytvořit jejich kopii a použít ji později jako
                výběr v obrázku.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Farbkanäle und der Alphakanal aus dem oberen Bereich des
                Dialogs können ebenfalls dupliziert werden.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                Además puede duplicar un canal primario o el canal alfa.  Es
                una manera fácil de mantener una copia de ellos y usarlos más
                adelante como una selección en la imagen.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Vous pouvez aussi Dupliquer un canal primaire de couleur ou le
                canal Alpha. C'est une façon simple de les mémoriser pour
                pouvoir les réutiliser ultérieurement en tant que sélection
                dans une image.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                E' possibile duplicare anche il canale di un colore o il
                canale alfa. E' un modo semplice per conservare una loro copia
                da usare in seguito come selezione all'interno dell'immagine.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Du kan også kopiere ein fargekanal eller alfakanalen. Denne
                kopien kan du så bruke som ei markering i biletet.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Также вы можете дублировать цветовой канал или альфа-канал.
                Это простой способ сохранить их копию для использования
                позднее в качестве маски выделенной области.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                您也可以复制一个颜色通道或 Alpha 通道，这是保留它们的一个拷贝并在以后把它们作为一个图像的选区的简单方法。
              </para>
            </tip>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-selection-replace" />

            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-selection.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">Channel to selection</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Kanál do výběru</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Auswahl aus Kanal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Canal a selección</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Canal vers sélection</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Canale a selezione</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Kanal til markering</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Канал в выделение</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">通道到选区</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              here you can transform the channel to become a selection. By
              default the selection derived from a channel replaces any
              previous active selection. It's possible to change this by
              clicking on control keys.
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              umožňuje přeměnit kanál na výběr. Ve výchozím nastavení výběr
              odvozený z kanálu nahradí jakýkoliv stávající výběr. Lze to však
              změnit pomocí modifikačních kláves.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Aus dem aktuellen Kanal kann eine neue Auswahl erstellt werden.
              Sie können durch Tastendruck beeinflussen, wie die neu erstellte
              Auswahl Auswirkung auf bereits angelegten Auswahlen hat:
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Con éste puede hacer que el canal se convierta en selección.  Si
              no se especifica otra cosa, la selección derivada del canal
              reemplaza a cualquier selección anterior.  Es posible cambiar
              este comportamiento con las teclas de control.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              permet de transformer le canal en sélection. Par défaut la
              sélection issue du canal remplace toute sélection précédemment
              active. Il est possible de changer ceci en appuyant sur des
              touches de contrôle.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              da qui è possibile trasformare il canale in una selezione.
              Normalmente la selezione derivata da un canale sostituisce
              qualsiasi selezione precedentemente attiva. E' possibile
              modificare questo comportamento premendo un tasto modificatore.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              blir brukt til å omforma kanalen til ei markering. Normalt vil
              den nye markeringa erstatta den eksisterande, men dette kan du
              forandra på ved hjelp av kontrolltastane.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              вы можете трансформировать канал в выделение области.
              По умолчанию выделение, полученное из канала, заменяет все
              предыдущие активные выделения. Такое поведение можно изменить
              c помощью модифицирующих клавиш:
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              这里您可以转换通道变为一个选区。从一个通道生成的选区默认值是替代以前的活动选区，不过可以通过按控制键来改变这种情况。
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem id="gimp-channel-selection-add">
                <para lang="en">
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                  the selection derived from a channel is added to the
                  previous active selection. The final selection is merged
                  from both.
                </para>
                <para lang="cs">
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                  výběr odvozený z kanálu se přičte ke stávajícímu aktivnímu
                  výběru. Výsledkem je sjednocení výběrů.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>: Die Auswahl aus dem Kanal wird zur
                  vorhandenen Auswahl hinzugefügt.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                  La selección que se deriva del canal se agrega a la
                  selección previa.  La selección resultante es la unión de
                  ambas.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <keycap>Maj</keycap> :
                  la sélection issue du canal s'ajoute à la sélection
                  précédemment active. La sélection finalement obtenue est
                  donc la fusion des deux.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>:
                  la selezione derivata da un canale viene aggiunta alla
                  selezione precedentemente attiva. La selezione risultante è
                  data dall'unione di entrambe.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                  Gjer at den nye markeringa blir lagt til den eksisterande.
                  Resultatet blir ei samanfletting av begge markeringane.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                  выделение, полученное из канала добавляется к
                  предыдущему активному выделению.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
                  从一个通道生成的选区添加到以前的活动选区中，最终选区是它们的结合。
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem id="gimp-channel-selection-subtract">
                <para lang="de">
                  <keycap>Strg</keycap>: Die Auswahl aus dem Kanal wird von
                  der vorhandenen Auswahl abgezogen.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  the final selection is the substraction of selection derived
                  from a channel from the previously active one.
                </para>
                <para lang="cs">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  výběr odvozený z kanálu se od stávajícího výběru odečte.
                  Výsledkem je rozdíl.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  la selección resultante es la resta de la selección derivada
                  del canal a la selección previa.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> :
                  la sélection finalement obtenue est la soustraction de la
                  sélection issue du canal à celle précédemment active.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  la selezione finale è data dalla sottrazione della selezione
                  derivata dal canale da quella precedentemente attiva.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  Gjer at den nye markeringa blir trekt frå den eksisterande.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  выделение из канала вычитается из предыдущего
                  активного выделения.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
                  最终选区是以前的活动选区减去从一个通道生成的选区。
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem id="gimp-channel-selection-intersect">
                <para lang="en">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  the final selection is the intersection of selection derived
                  from a channel with the previously active one. Only common
                  parts are kept.
                </para>
                <para lang="cs">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  výsledkem je průnik výběru odvozeného z kanálu a stávajícího
                  výběru. Jsou zachovány pouze společné části.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>
                    <keycap>Strg</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  Es wird eine neue Auswahl erstellt, die aus der
                  Schnittmenge der Kanalauswahl und der vorhandenen Auswahl
                  besteht.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  la selección resultante es la intersección de la selección
                  derivada del canal con la selección previa.  Sólo quedan las
                  partes que tienen en común.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Maj</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo> :
                  la sélection finalement obtenue est l'intersection de la
                  sélection issue du canal avec la sélection précédemment
                  active. Seules les parties communes sont conservées.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  la selezione finale è data dall'intersezione della selezione
                  derivata dal canale con quella precedentemente attiva.
                  Vengono mantenute solo le parti in comune.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  Den nye markeringa blir eit snitt av begge markeringane. Bare
                  det som er felles i begge blir tatt med.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  Полученное выделение является результатом пересечения
                  выделения из канала с предыдущим активным.
                  Сохраняются только общие части.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  </keycombo>:
                  最终选区是从一个通道生成的选区与以前的活动选区相交，只保留相同的部分
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <anchor id="gimp-channel-selection-delete" />
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-icon-delete.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>

            <phrase lang="en">Delete channel</phrase>
            <phrase lang="cs">Odstranit kanál</phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">Kanal löschen</phrase>
            <phrase lang="es">Delete channel</phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Effacer le canal,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">Elimina canale,</phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">Slett kanal</phrase>
            <phrase lang="ru">Удалить канал</phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">删除通道,</phrase>
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              only available for selection masks: you can here delete the
              active channel.
            </para>
            <para lang="cs">
              je dostupný pouze pro masky výběru. Umožňuje smazat aktivní
              kanál.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Über diese Schaltfläche wird der aktuell ausgewählten Kanal
              gelöscht.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Sólo se encuentra disponible para las máscaras de selección.
              Con éste puede borrar el canal activo.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              uniquement disponible pour les Masques de sélection : permet
              de supprimer le canal.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              disponibile solo per le maschere di selezione: da qui è
              possibile cancellare il canale attivo.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Fjernar kanalen frå lista. Denne er bare tilgjengeleg for
              markeringsmasker.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Доступно только для масок выделения:
              с помощью неё вы можете удалить активный канал.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">只对选区蒙板有效：这里您可以删除活动通道。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect4><!-- end Managing -->

    <xi:include href="channel-menu.xml" />

  </sect3> <!-- end Using -->

  <xi:include href="channel-selection-mask.xml" />
  <xi:include href="qmask.xml" />


</sect2>
