<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<sect2 id="dialogs-selection-masks" lang="de;cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Selection masks</title>
  <title lang="cs">Masky výběru</title>
  <title lang="de">Auswahlmasken</title>
  <title lang="fr">Masques de sélection</title>   
  <title lang="zh_CN">选区蒙板</title>

  <mediaobject lang="en" >
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="de" >
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="fr" >
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="zh_CN" >
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  
  <para lang="en"> 
    Channels can be used to save and restore your selections.  Clicking
    on the <guilabel>Quick mask</guilabel> button on the <link
      linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Image window</link> automatically
    creates a new channel called <guilabel>Qmask</guilabel> and saves the
    displayed active selection to a thumbail in front of the
    channel.There are many selection tools in the Gimp like rectangular
    selection tool or fuzzy selection for continuous selections.
    Selection Masks are a graphical way to build selections into a gray
    level channel where white pixels are selected and black pixels are
    not selected. Therefore gray pixels are partially selected. You can
    think of them as feathering the selection, a smooth transition
    between selected and not selected. This is important to avoid the
    ugly pixelization effect when you fill the selection or when you
    erase its content after isolating a subject from background.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Kanály lze používat k ukládání výběrů. Kliknutí na tlačítko rychlé masky
    v <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Okně obrázku</link> automaticky
    vytvoří nový kanál nazvaný <guilabel>Rychlá maska</guilabel>. Ikona
    před jménem kanálu zobrazuje náhled výběru.
    výběr
    and saves the
    displayed active selection to a thumbail in front of the
    channel.There are many selection tools in the Gimp like rectangular
    selection tool or fuzzy selection for continuous selections.
    Selection Masks are a graphical way to build selections into a gray
    level channel where white pixels are selected and black pixels are
    not selected. Therefore gray pixels are partially selected. You can
    think of them as feathering the selection, a smooth transition
    between selected and not selected. This is important to avoid the
    ugly pixelization effect when you fill the selection or when you
    erase its content after isolating a subject from background.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Kanäle können benutzt werden um Auswahlen zu speichern und wieder
    herzustellen. Es gibt zahlreiche <link
      linkend='gimp-tools-selection'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> im
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym>, mit denen neue Auswahlen erstellt werden
    können. Auch <link linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMasks</link> können in
    einen Kanal gespeichert werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">     
    Les canaux peuvent être utilisés pour sauvegarder et restituer vos
    sélections. Cliquer sur le bouton du <guilabel>Masque
    rapide</guilabel> dans la <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">Fenêtre d'image</link> créé
    automatiquement un nouveau canal appelé <guilabel>Qmask</guilabel>
    et sauvegarde la sélection active affichée dans une vignette
    devant le canal. Cette fonctionnalité de Gimp est détaillée
    ci-dessous aux chapitres Masque Rapide et Masque de sélection.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN"> 
    通道可以保存和恢复您的选区。点击<link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-window">图像窗口</link>的<guilabel>快速蒙板</guilabel>按键会自动新建一个叫作<guilabel>Qmask</guilabel>的通道，并将显示的当前选区保存为通道前的一个缩略图上。GIMP 中有很多像矩形选择或模糊选择这样的选择工具。选区蒙板是一种能将选区放入一个灰阶通道的方法，其中选中的为白色像素，未选中的为黑色像素，而灰色像素则表示部分选中。您可以把它们看作被羽化的选区，是选中和未选中之间的过渡。这对在您填充选区或在从背景中分离一个物体后删除其内容时，避免产生的丑陋的格删化现象非常重要。
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Creating Selection Masks</term>
      <term lang="de">Erstellen von Auswahlmasken</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">创建选区蒙板</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          There are several ways to initialize a selection mask.  From the
          image window menu
          <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>elect</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>Save to <accel>C</accel>hannel</guimenuitem> is
          available if there is an active selection.  From the image window
          the bottom-left button creates a <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quick
            Mask</link>; the content will be initialized with the active
          selection.  From the channel dialog, when you click on the
          <guilabel>New channel</guilabel> button or from the context menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Erstellen Sie eine Auswahl mit einen <link
            linkend='gimp-tools-selection'>Auswahlwerkzeug</link>.  Danach
          überführen Sie die erstellte Auswahl in ein Kanal.
        </para>
        <para>
          Benutzen Sie dafür über das Bildmenü
          <guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>In
            <accel>K</accel>anal speichern</guimenuitem>. Danach erscheint
          ein neuer Kanal mit einem Miniaturbild im Kanaldialog.
          Standardmässig ist die erstellte Auswahlmaske nicht sichtbar; dem
          Kanal fehlt das gesetzte <link
            linkend='channel-attributes'>Augensymbol</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Möchten Sie die abgespeicherte Auswahl aus dem Kanal wieder
          herstellen, benutzen Sie dazu die <link
            linkend='gimp-channel-selection-add'>Auswahl aus Kanal</link>
          Schaltfläche.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">       
        <para>
          Il existe de nombreux outils de sélection dans Gimp tels que
          l'outil de sélection rectangulaire ou la baguette magique pour
          les sélections contiguës.  Les Masques de sélection sont une
          façon graphique de construire les sélections dans un canal en
          niveaux de gris où les pixels blancs sont les sélectionnés et
          les pixels noirs ne le sont pas. Les pixels gris sont donc
          partiellement sélectionnés, il faut entendre pas là
          l'équivalent d'un adoucissement de sélection, une transition
          entre ce qui est pleinement sélectionné et ce qui ne l'est pas.
          Cette notion de transition dans une sélection est très
          importante pour éviter les effets de pixelisation lorsqu'on va
          remplir la sélection ou bien lorsqu'on va effacer son contenu
          après un détourage.
        </para>
        <para>
          Il existe plusieurs méthodes pour initialiser un masque de
          sélection.  Depuis le menu d'image
          <guilabel>Sélection/Enregistrer dans un canal</guilabel>
          disponible si vous avez une sélection active. Depuis le bouton au
          bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image qui va créer un <link
            linkend="gimp-qmask">Masque rapide</link> dont le contenu sera
          initialisé avec la sélection active. Depuis le dialogue des
          canaux en cliquant sur le bouton <guilabel>Nouveau
            canal</guilabel> ou depuis le menu clic-droit sur un canal.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          有多种方法初始化一个选区蒙板。如果有一个活动选区，可以在图像窗口菜单中
          <guimenuitem>选择</guimenuitem>/
          <guimenuitem>保存到通道</guimenuitem>。用图像菜单左下方按钮产生一个<link linkend="gimp-qmask">快速蒙板</link>，它将用活动选区初始化其内容。在通道对话框中，点击<guilabel>新建通道</guilabel>按钮或通过通道菜单。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <simplesect lang='en'>
    <title lang="en">Using Selectionmasks</title>
    <para>
      Once the channel is initialized, selected (highlighted in blue),
      visible (eye-icon in the dialog), and displayed as you want
      (color and opacity attributes), you can start to work with all
      the paint tools.  The colors used are important. If you paint
      with some color other than white, grey, or black, the color Value
      (luminosity) will be used to define a gray (medium, light, or
      dark).  When your mask is painted, you can transform it to a
      selection by clicking on the <guilabel>Channel to
        selection</guilabel> button or from the context menu.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        You can work in selection masks not only with the paint tool
        but also with other tools. For instance, you can use the
        selection tools to fill areas uniformly with gradients or
        patterns.  By adding many selection masks in your list you can
        easily compose very complex selections. One can say that a
        selection mask is to a selection as a layer is to an image.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <caution>
      <para>
        As long as a selection mask is activated you are working in the
        mask and not in the image. To work in the image you have to
        deactivate all selection masks. Don't forget also to stop
        displaying masks in the image by removing the eye icon. Check
        also that all RGB and Alpha channels are activated and
        displayed in the image.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang='de'>
    <title lang="de">Auswahlmasken benutzen</title>
    <para>
      Sobald Sie eine Auswahl in einen Kanal gespeichert haben, können
      Sie diese Auswahl bearbeiten. Die Bearbeitung des Kanals erfolgt
      vorranging mit <link
        linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>Malwerkzeugen</link>. Die
      ausgewählten Farben spielen hier eine besondere Rolle.
    </para>
    <para>
      Benutzen Sie die Farbe Weiss um die erstellte Auswahl zu
      vergrössern und die Farbe Schwarz um die Auswahl zu verkleinern.
      Nur durch die Benutzung der beiden Farbarten, können erzeugen Sie
      eine Auswahl mit harten Kanten, d.h. das Ende der Auswahl wird
      durch die Schwarze Farbe bzw. der laufenden Ameisen
      gekennzeichnet.
    </para>
    <para>
      Möchten Sie die Auswahl langsam ausblenden, benutzen Sie Farben
      die sich zwischen Schwarz und Weiss befinden, also Grautöne. Je
      höher der Anteil von Weiss im Grau ist, desto durchsichtiger ist
      die Auswahl.
    </para>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Solang die Auswahlmaske aktiviert ist (gekennzeichnet durch das
        gesetzte Augensymbol des Kanals), haben die eingesetzten
        Werkzeuge nur auf die Auswahlmaske einen Effekt.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect lang='fr'>
    <para>
      Une fois le canal initialisé, activé (surligné en bleu), visible
      (l'icone en forme d'oeil dans le dialogue) et affiché à votre
      convenance (attributs de couleur et d'opacité) il devient
      possible de travailler dedans avec tous les outils de dessin
      classiques. Les couleurs utilisées sont évidemment importantes,
      si vous utilisez autre chose que du blanc, du noir ou du gris ce
      sera la valeur (luminosité) de la couleur qui sera utilisée pour
      définir un gris plus ou moins clair. Une fois votre masque
      dessiné vous pouvez le transformer en sélection depuis le bouton
      <guilabel>Canal vers sélection</guilabel> ou depuis le menu
      contextuel.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        Il est tout à fait possible de travailler avec d'autres
        outils que les outils de dessin dans les masques de sélection.
        Par exemple vous pouvez utiliser les outils de sélection pour
        remplir des zones uniformément, avec des motifs ou avec des
        dégradés.  En cumulant ainsi plusieurs masques de sélection
        dans votre liste vous pouvez arriver à composer des
        sélections vraiment complexes avec beaucoup de souplesse, on
        peut dire qu'un masque de sélection est à une sélection ce
        qu'un calque est à une image.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Tant qu'un masque de sélection est activé vous travaillez
        dans le masque et non pas dans l'image. Pour travailler à
        nouveau dans l'image vous devez impérativement désactiver
        tous les masques de sélection.  N'oubliez pas aussi de
        désactiver l'affichage des masques dans l'image en enlevant
        l'icone en forme d'oeil.  Vérifiez aussi que vos canaux RVB et
        Alpha sont bien actifs et affichés dans l'image.
      </para>
        </caution>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect lang='zh_CN'>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用选区蒙板</title>
        <para>
          一旦通道被初始化，选中(用蓝色高亮表示)可见(对话框中的眼睛图标)，让它如您所愿显示(颜色和不透明度属性)，然后您就能用任何涂画工具来使用它了。使用的颜色很重要，假如您用白，灰或黑以外的颜色涂画，颜色的亮度将被用来定义一个灰色(中等，明亮或阴暗)。当蒙板被涂画后，就可以通过点击通道菜单中<guilabel>通道到选区</guilabel>按钮将其转换为一个选区。
        </para>
        <tip>
	  <para>
	    您不光可以用涂画工具，而且可以用其它工具来在选区蒙板上进行处理。比如，可以用带渐变或图案的选择工具统一地填充区域。在列表中添加许多选区蒙板能很容易地生成非常复杂的选区。可以这么说，一个选区蒙板对一个选区就好比一个图层对一个图像。
	  </para>
        </tip>
        <caution>
	  <para>
	    当一个选区蒙板被激活后，您就对蒙板进行处理了，而不是对图像。如果要对图像处理就必须使所有选区蒙板不活动，另外不要忘记关闭眼睛图标使蒙板停止在图像中显示，然后还要检查所有的 RGB 和 Alpha 通道是否是活动和是否显示在图像上。
	  </para>
        </caution>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
