<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-23 j.h: no change for 2.8
  2008-12-13 j.h: updated to v2.6; added HTML-notation context menu (en;fr)
  2008-01-09 ude: added gimp-colorselector ids used by GIMP
    2007-11-03 j.h: added CSS keywords
  2007-08-25 jh: Revised en;fr for v2.4
  2006-03-29 made docbook compliant
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-color-dialog">
  <title>FG/BG Color Dialog</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Color Selector</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Color Selector</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <anchor id="gimp-colorselector-notebook"/>
  <para>
    The Color dialog lets you pick and manage colors. There are several
    different modes you can use to select colors. It also offers
    a color picker to select a color anywhere on your screen.
  </para>
  <para>
    This dialog works on either the foreground or the background color.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      This dialog is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can access it:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Colors</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog by clicking the
          <link linkend="tab-menus">tab menu button</link>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon> and selecting
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Colors</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-color-area">toolbox</link>:
          click on the current Foreground or Background color.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      In the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> menu, there is a list of
      <link linkend="gimp-dockable-menu">detached windows</link> which exists
      only if at least one dialog remains open. In this case, you can raise
      the <quote>FG/BG</quote> dialog from the main menu:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>FG/BG</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-colorselectors">
    <title>Using the <quote>FG/BG color</quote> dialog</title>
    <para>
      The dialog offers a number of different color selector modes at the top:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-gimp">
        <term>GIMP</term>
        <listitem>
  <figure>
    <title>GIMP Color Selector</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/color-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
          <para>
            With the GIMP Color Selector, you select a color by clicking on a
            one-dimensional strip located at the right edge, and then in a
            two-dimensional area located on the left. The one-dimensional
            strip can encode any of the color parameters H, S, V, R, G, or B,
            as determined by which of the adjoining buttons is pressed. The
            two-dimensional area then encodes the two complementary color
            parameters.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-cmyk">
        <term>CMYK</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>CMYK Color Selector</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/color-CMYK.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            You get to this selector by clicking on the CMYK icon. The CMYK
            view gives you the possibility to manage colors from the
            <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">CMYK</link> color model.
            If a CMYK profile is attached to the image, the profile will be
            used to determine the CMYK colors. See
            <link linkend="gimp-image-soft-proof-profile-assign">Soft-Proof Profile</link>
            for more information.
            Otherwise, a "naive" color conversion will be performed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-watercolor">
        <term>Watercolor</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Watercolor Color Selector</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <figure>
            <title>Watercolor Color Selector</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/dialogs/color-watercolor.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This selector is a little different than the other models.
            The principle consists in changing the
            current foreground color by clicking in the rectangular
            palette. If the current foreground color is for example
            white, then it turns reddish by clicking in the red
            color area. Repeated clicking strengthens the effect. With the
            slider, which is next to the color palette, you
            can set the color quantity per mouse click. The higher the
            sliding control is, the more color is taken up per click.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-triangle">
        <term>Wheel</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Wheel Color Selector</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <figure>
            <title>Wheel Color Selector</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/dialogs/color-triangle.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This selector uses the <xref linkend="glossary-hsv"/> color
            model. Click in the <emphasis>chromatic circle</emphasis> and drag
            the mouse pointer to select the Hue. Click-and-drag in the
            <emphasis>triangle</emphasis> to vary the Saturation
            (vertically) and Value (horizontally).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-palette">
        <term>Palette</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Palette Color Selector</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <figure>
            <title>Palette Color Selector</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/dialogs/color-palette.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This color selector brings up a list of the colors from the
            current palette in the
            <link linkend="gimp-palette-dialog">Palettes dialog</link>.
            You can set <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s foreground or background
            colors by clicking on colors in the colors display. You can also
            use the arrow keys to move within the list of colors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-scales">
        <term>Scales</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>Scales Color Selector</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/dialogs/color-scale.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This selector displays a global view of the R, G, B channels and
            either the H, S, V or L, c, h values, placed in sliders.
            The numbers can be represented as 0 to 255 or 0.0 to 100.0 ranges.
          </para>
          <para>
            Magenta areas on the sliders indicate colors that are out of gamut.
            This means that the value on the slider would mathematically define
            a color that does not exist in your chosen color profile. For more
            information, see <link linkend="glossary-gamut">Gamut</link>. If
            you move a slider to a value that is out of gamut, the color
            remains set to the last in-gamut color that you selected.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              You can set which color is used to mark out of gamut colors
              in the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-soft-proofing">Soft-Proofing
              Preferences</link>.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>
      At the bottom, further options and tools are available:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Foreground and background color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The symbol consisting of two arrows allows you to
            exchange the foreground and background color. At the bottom left of this
            icon, below the foreground color block, you find a switching
            surface with two small, one black and the other white, partially
            overlapping squares. If you click on these, the front and background
            color are reset to black and white respectively.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-picker">
        <term>Color picker</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Color Dialog color picker has a completely different behavior
            than the
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">color picker tool</link>.
            Instead of picking the colors from the active image, you're able
            to pick colors from the entire screen.
          </para>
          <para>
            The downside is that you get colors after they got processed
            by the full system color stack, in particular color
            management. It means that the resulting color values may end
            up different from ones returned by the
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">color picker tool</link>
            when picking over the canvas. It is up to you to make an
            informed choice of which color picker to use.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-colorselector-html">
        <term>HTML Notation</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>CSS Keywords</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            This is a text field with six characters.
            See <link linkend="glossary-html-notation">HTML notation</link>.
            You can also use the CSS keywords; enter the first letter of a
            color to get a list of colors with their keyword:
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>CSS keywords example</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/dialogs/css-keywords.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            Right-clicking in the HTML Notation text box opens a context
            menu that allows you to edit your notation, particularly to
            paste a complex notation you have copied elsewhere.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Last used colors</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Twelve buttons at the bottom show the last used colors. You may
            choose a color by clicking on one of these buttons or add the
            current foreground or background color to this history list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
