<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-07-01 j.h: create
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-dashboard-dialog">
  <title>Dashboard</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dashboard</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The Dashboard helps to monitor GIMP resource usage (Cache, Swap, CPU,
    Memory). This allows you to make more educated decisions about various
    configuration options, especially
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-system-resources">System Resources</link>.
    It is also used by developers.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>The Dashboard Dialog window</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dashboard-dialog.png"
format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      This dialog is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can access it:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Dashboard</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>;
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the Tab menu in any dockable dialog by clicking the
          <link linkend="tab-menus">tab menu button</link>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon> and selecting
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Dashboard</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Using the Dashboard</title>
    <para>
      The Dashboard consists of five groups that you can monitor:
      <guilabel>Cache</guilabel> usage, <guilabel>Swap</guilabel> usage,
      <guilabel>CPU</guilabel> usage, <guilabel>Memory</guilabel> usage, and
      <guilabel>Misc</guilabel> information. By default the
      Misc group is hidden and the CPU and Memory groups are collapsed.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each group has a separate <link linkend="tab-menus">Tab menu</link>
      where you can change settings related to that group.
    </para>
    <para>
      At the bottom of the Dashboard are two buttons, which will be explained
      in the Dashboard context menu, where these commands are also available.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dashboard context menu</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This context menu allows you to change what groups are visible,
            some other settings related to the Dashboard, as well as
            a few Dashboard related commands.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>The Dashboard context menu</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dashboard-context-menu.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-groups">
              <term>Groups submenu</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The Groups submenu allows you to change what groups are visible.
                  By default <guimenuitem>Cache</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Swap</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>CPU</guimenuitem>
                  and <guimenuitem>Memory</guimenuitem> are visible, and
                  <guimenuitem>Misc</guimenuitem> is hidden, but you can choose
                  to show or hide any of these here.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-update-interval">
              <term>Update Interval submenu</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The Update Interval submenu allows you to change how often the
                  information shown in the Dashboard is updated. The default is
                  0.25 seconds, but you can change this to a longer period up to
                  4 seconds.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-history-duration">
              <term>History Duration submenu</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The History Duration submenu allows you to change for what
                  period of time the information is shown. The default is 60
                  seconds, but you can choose from values between 15 and 240
                  seconds.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-log-record">
              <term>Start/Stop Recording…</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This is also available as a button at the bottom of the
                  Dashboard.
                  This allows you to start or stop recording a performance log.
                  In certain situations the developers may ask you to supply this
                  log if you are experiencing performance related issues. This
                  log can help them to figure out the problem.
                  When you start recording you will be asked to select a
                  location and filename where the log will be saved.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-log-add-marker">
              <term>Add Marker…</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you are recording a performance log, this enables you to
                  mark a certain event in the log. You will be asked to give a
                  name to this event. This can make it easier for developers to
                  find the problem area in your log, because logs can become
                  fairly large.
                  This is also available as a button at the bottom of the
                  Dashboard when you are recording a performance log.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-log-add-empty-marker">
              <term>Add Empty Marker…</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you are recording a performance log, this enables you to
                  mark a certain point in the log. An empty marker will be
                  added, meaning you won't be asked to give it a name. This can
                  make it easier for developers to find the problem area in your
                  log, because logs can become fairly large.
                  When you are recording you can also use the button at the
                  bottom of the Dashboard while pressing the
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap> key to add an empty marker.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-reset">
              <term>Reset</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Reset cumulative data removes the performance data and starts
                  from zero.
                  This is also available as a button at the bottom of the
                  Dashboard when you are not recording a performance log.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry id="gimp-dashboard-low-swap-space-warning">
              <term>Low Swap Space Warning…</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If this option is enabled, the Dashboard will be raised to the
                  top if your swap space is nearing the limit.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      We will now explain each group separately.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cache</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Cache shows what part of the tile cache, the size of which can be
            set in System Resources preferences, is currently being used.
            If your cache is often near the maximum, and you have enough
            available memory, you could consider increasing the cache size.
          </para>
          <para>
            By default this shows the currently occupied part of the Cache,
            and the maximum cache size as set in preferences. What is shown
            can be changed in the Cache tab menu by clicking on
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
            You can choose to show or hide
            <guilabel>Occupied</guilabel> size, <guilabel>Maximum</guilabel>
            size used since you started measuring, the cache
            <guilabel>Limit</guilabel>, the <guilabel>Compression</guilabel>
            ratio, and <guilabel>Hit/Miss</guilabel> ratio.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Swap</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Swap shows the current size of the on-disk tile swap, and what part
            of that is currently being used. It also shows the swap size limit.
            If your swap is often being used, and you have enough available
            memory, you could consider increasing the cache size.
          </para>
          <para>
            By default this shows the current Swap size and what part is
            occupied, as well as the Swap size limit.
            What is shown can be changed in the Swap tab menu by clicking on
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
            You can choose to show or hide the
            <guilabel>Occupied</guilabel> size, the current swap file
            <guilabel>Size</guilabel>, the swap file size
            <guilabel>Limit</guilabel>, the <guilabel>Queued</guilabel> size
            (the amount planned to be written to the swap file),
            <guilabel>Read</guilabel> is the total amount read from the swap
            file, <guilabel>Written</guilabel> is the total amount written to
            the swap file, and the <guilabel>Compression</guilabel> ratio of
            the data written to the swap file.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>CPU</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            CPU shows the current CPU usage.
          </para>
          <para>
            By default this shows the current CPU usage.
            What is shown can be changed in the CPU tab menu by clicking on
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
            You can choose to
            show or hide CPU <guilabel>Usage</guilabel>, and the total amount
            of time the CPU has been <guilabel>Active</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Memory</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Memory shows the current amount of memory used by GIMP, the
            amount of available (free) physical memory, and the total size of
            your physical memory.
          </para>
          <para>
            What is shown can be changed in the Memory tab menu by clicking on
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
            You can choose to show or hide
            the occupied tile <guilabel>Cache</guilabel>, the total size of
            the <guilabel>Tile</guilabel> memory, the amount of memory
            <guilabel>Used</guilabel>, the size of the
            <guilabel>Available</guilabel> physical memory, and the physical
            memory <guilabel>Size</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Misc</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Misc group is not shown by default, but has to be enabled in
            the Dashboard context menu first. It shows extra information
            mainly useful for developers.
          </para>
          <para>
            By default all settings are shown, but what is shown can be changed
            in the Misc tab menu by clicking on
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
            You can choose to show or
            hide total size of processed <guilabel>Mipmapped</guilabel> data,
            the number of <guilabel>Assigned</guilabel> worker threads,
            the number of <guilabel>Active</guilabel> worker threads, the
            number of <guilabel>Async</guilabel> (asynchronous) operations, the
            total size of <guilabel>Tile</guilabel> memory, the total size of
            <guilabel>Scratch</guilabel> memory, and the total size of
            <guilabel>TempBuf</guilabel> (temporary buffers).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
