<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-25 j.h: no change for 2.8
  2008-12-15 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-09-03 j.h : revised for v2.4. No change
  2006-04-29 lexa: cleaned up and made docbook compliant
  2006-03-01 added Activate Dialog by j.h
  2005-11-28 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<sect3 id="edit-template-dialog">
  <title>Edit Template</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Template</primary>
    <secondary>Edit</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Edit Template</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>The Edit Template dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-templates-edit.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
    The dialog allows you to set the specifications of the selected template.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can access this editor by clicking on the
    <guibutton>Edit Template</guibutton> button at the bottom of the dialog.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Options</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Name</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In this text box, you can modify the displayed template name.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Icon</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking on this icon, you open a list of icons. You can choose
          one of them to illustrate the selected template name.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Image size</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Here you set the width and height of the new image.  The
          default units are pixels, but you can switch to some other
          unit if you prefer, using the adjoining menu. If you do,
          note that the resulting pixel size will be determined by
          the X and Y resolution (which you can change in the
          Advanced Options), and by the setting of
          <quote>Dot for Dot</quote>, which you can change in the
          <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            Please keep in mind, that every Pixel of an image is stored
            in the memory. If you're creating large files with a high
            density of pixels, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will need some
            time for every function you're applying to the image.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Portrait/Landscape buttons</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          These buttons toggle between Portrait and Landscape mode.
          Concretely, their effect is to exchange the values for
          Width and Height.  If the X and Y resolutions are
          different (in Advanced Options), then these values are
          exchanged also. On the right, image size, image resolution and
          color space are displayed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Advanced Options</title>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>The <quote>Advanced Options</quote> dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-templates-edit-advanced.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
      These are options that will mainly be of interest to more advanced
      users.
    </para>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>X and Y resolution</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          These values come into play mainly in relation to
          printing:  they do not affect the size of the image in
          pixels, but they determine its size on paper when
          printed.  They can also affect the way the image is
          displayed on the monitor: if <quote>Dot for Dot</quote> is
          switched off
          in the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, then at 100% zoom,
          GIMP attempts to display the image on the monitor at the
          correct physical size, as calculated from the pixel
          dimensions and the resolution.  The display may not be
          accurate, however, unless the monitor has been calibrated.
          This can be done either when GIMP is installed, or from
          the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-display">Display tab</link> of
          the Preferences dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Colorspace</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can create the new image as either an RGB image or a grayscale
          image. You cannot create an indexed image directly in this way, but
          of course nothing prevents you from converting the image to indexed
          mode after it has been created.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Fill</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You have four choices for the solid color that will fill
          the new image's background layer:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Foreground color</guilabel>, as shown in the Main
              Toolbox.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Background color</guilabel>, as shown in the Main
              Toolbox.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>White</guilabel>, the more often used.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Transparent</guilabel>.  If this option is chosen,
              then the Background layer in the new image will be created
              with an alpha channel; otherwise not.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Comment</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can write a descriptive comment here.  The text will
          be attached to the image as a <quote>parasite</quote>, and will be
          saved along with the image by some file formats (but not
          all of them).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>
