<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="export-file-formats">
  <title>Export File Formats</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export File Formats</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    When exporting an image, most file formats have additional options that
    can be set. If that is the case, a new dialog opens after you have selected
    the filename and export file format. The following pages document the
    dialogs for export file formats in alphabetical order.
  </para>
  <para>
    Be aware that not all formats support all kinds of images. In particular
    certain formats may not be able to show transparency (like jpeg), while
    only a few formats support exporting an animation (like webp and gif).
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gimp-exporting-animations">
    <title>Exporting Animations</title>

    <para>
      Some file formats supported by <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allow you to
      export an animation, most notably
      <link linkend="file-webp-export">webp</link> and
      <link linkend="file-gif-export">gif</link>, but also
      <link linkend="file-mng-export">mng</link>, however this last format
      isn't supported very well by most applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is limited support in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> for creating
      animations. When exporting it is assumed that each layer in your image
      represents a frame in your animation. Exporting to animations usually
      doesn't support layer groups, so it's best not to use those if you
      want to make an animation.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can adjust the name of a layer, by adding some parameters in
      parenthesis, to let the animation export know how that layer needs to
      be animated and for how long it should be shown before going to the
      next frame. When both these things are set a name usually looks like this:
      <quote><literal>My layer name (delay in ms)(animation command)</literal></quote>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The delay sets the amount of time the frame will be visible, e.g.
      <literal>(200 ms)</literal> to set it to 200 milliseconds.
    </para>
    <para>
      The animation command specifies how the frame is combined with the
      previous one. You can only choose one animation command for each layer.
      The available commands are:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>replace</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <literal>(replace)</literal> command means that this layer (frame)
            will completely replace the previous one.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>combine</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <literal>(combine)</literal> command means that this layer (frame)
            will be combined with the previous one. Only the visible parts in
            this layer will replace that of the previous layer.
            Using <literal>(combine)</literal> can reduce the size of the animation
            and may improve playback speed for large size animations.
          </para>
          <para>
            You can use the
            <link linkend="plug-in-animationoptimize">optimize (for GIF)</link>
            command to change your <literal>(replace)</literal> layers to
            <literal>(combine)</literal>.
            This adjusts the layer to only contain what is different from the
            previous one and then sets it to <literal>(replace)</literal>.
            Don't hesitate to use this, even if you plan to export to
            a different format than GIF. This command was named at a time that
            there were not many other animation options than GIF, but can be
            used for any animation format that supports combining.
          </para>
          <para>
            Note that you can also do the reverse and
            <link linkend="plug-in-animationunoptimize">unoptimize</link> the
            animation, setting each layer to <literal>(replace)</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has a limited
      <link linkend="plug-in-animationplay">animation playback</link> ability
      that you can use to preview your animation.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
