<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="export-file-formats">
  <title>Export File Formats</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export File Formats</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    When exporting an image, most file formats have additional options that
    can be set. If that is the case, then a new dialog will open after you
    have selected the filename and export file format. This section will
    document the dialogs for all export file formats.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="file-gif-export">
    <title>Export Image as GIF</title>
    <anchor id="file-gif-load" xreflabel="GIF"/>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>GIF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>.gif</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Image as GIF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>GIF</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>The GIF Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-gif-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <warning>
      <para>
        The GIF file format does not support some basic image
        properties such as <emphasis>print resolution</emphasis>.
        If you care for these properties, use a different file
        format like PNG.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>GIF Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Interlace</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Checking interlace allows an image on a web page to be
                  progressively displayed as it is downloaded.
                  Progressive image display is useful with slow connection
                  speeds, because you can stop an image that is of no
                  interest; interlace is of less use today with our faster
                  connection speeds.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Save comment</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  GIF comments support only 7-bit ASCII characters.
                  If you use a character outside the 7-bit ASCII set,
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will export the image without
                  a comment, and then inform you that the comment was not
                  saved.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Animated GIF Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Animation</primary>
            <secondary>Animated GIF options</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>As animation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When this option is checked, the image will be
                  exported as an animation. Note that this option
                  will be disabled (and the animation options will
                  not be visible) if the image has only one layer.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Number of repeats</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  You can set how many times the animation will
                  repeat before it stops. This value is ignored if
                  <guilabel>Loop forever</guilabel> is checked.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Loop forever</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When this option is checked, the animation will
                  play repeatedly until you stop it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Delay between frames when unspecified</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  You can set the delay, in milliseconds, between frames
                  if it has not been set before. In this case, you can
                  modify every delay in the Layer Dialog. Note that some
                  operating systems and applications may override with a
                  lower frame rate due to computer speed, performance, or
                  other technical limitations.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Frame disposal when unspecified</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If this has not been set before, you can set how frames
                  will be superimposed. You can select among three options:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>I don't care</guilabel>:
                      you can use this option if all your layers are
                      opaque. Layers will overwrite what is beneath.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>Cumulative layers (combine)</guilabel>:
                      previous frames will not be deleted when a new one
                      is displayed.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>One frame per layer (replace)</guilabel>:
                      previous frames will be deleted before displaying a
                      new frame.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Use delay entered above for all frames</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The <guilabel>Delay between frames when unspecified</guilabel>
                  value will be used for all frames.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Use disposal entered above for all frames</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The <guilabel>Frame disposal when unspecified</guilabel>
                  value will be used for all frames.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="file-heif-export">
    <title>Export Image as HEIF/HEIC</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>HEIF/HEIC</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      HEIF stands for High Efficiency Image File Format. Also known as HEIC
      High Efficiency Image Coding.
    </para>
    <para>
      Twice as much information can be stored in a HEIF image as in a JPEG
      image of the same size, resulting in a better quality. As of
      September 2022, no browser supports HEIF natively.
    </para>
    <para>
      More information in <ulink
      url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Efficiency_Image_File_Format">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The HEIF/HEIC Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-heif-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>HEIF Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Lossless</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When checked, the image will be exported with lossless
                  compression. This will create a higher quality image at
                  the cost of a larger file size.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Quality</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If <guilabel>Lossless</guilabel> is not checked, this value
                  determines the quality of the image compression. 100 provides
                  the best quality image and lowest compression, while 0 provides
                  the highest compression and worst quality image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Pixel format</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Defines what pixel format the exported image should use for color
                  sub-sampling. There are three options:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                  <!-- Thanks to Daniel Novomeský for this information -->
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>YUV420</guilabel>:
                      Suitable for photographs with lossy compression. This format is
                      most compatible with other software that uses HEIF.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>YUV444</guilabel>:
                      When used with a high <guilabel>Quality</guilabel> setting, this
                      format exports a visually lossless image.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>RGB</guilabel>:
                      Useful when exporting images with true lossless quality.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Bit depth</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Determines if the pixel data should be stored using 8 bits, 10 bits,
                  or 12 bits per color channel.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Save color profile</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If checked, the color profile is embedded in the exported image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Save Exif</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If checked, the Exif metadata is embedded in the exported image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Save XMP</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If checked, the XMP metadata is embedded in the exported image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="file-jpeg-export">
    <title>Export Image as JPEG</title>
    <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" xreflabel="JPEG"/>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>JPEG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>.jpg</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>.jpeg</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Image as JPEG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>JPEG</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg. It is a
      very widely used format, because it compresses images very
      efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality. No other
      format comes close to achieving the same level of compression. It does
      not, however, support transparency or multiple layers.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The JPEG Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-jpeg-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering number
      of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this documentation.
      Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality parameter is probably the
      only one you will need to adjust.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Quality</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you save a file in JPEG format, a dialog is displayed
            that allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 0
            to 100. Values above 95 are generally not useful, though. The
            default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, but
            in many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
            lower without noticeably degrading the image. You can test the
            effect of different quality settings by checking
            <guilabel>Show Preview in image window</guilabel>
            in the JPEG dialog.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              Please note, that the numbers for the JPEG quality level have
              a different meaning in different applications.
              Saving with a quality level of 80 in GIMP is not
              necessarily comparable with saving with a quality level of
              80 in a different application.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
            Use quality settings from original image
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If a particular quality setting (or <quote>quantization
            table</quote>) was attached to the image when it was
            loaded, then this option allows you to use them instead of
            the standard ones.
          </para>
          <para>
            If you have only made a few changes to the image, then
            re-using the same quality setting will give you almost the
            same quality and file size as the original image. This
            will minimize the losses caused by the quantization step,
            compared to what would happen if you used different
            quality setting.
          </para>
          <para>
            If the quality setting found in the original file are not
            better than your default quality settings, then the option
            <quote>Use quality settings from original image</quote>
            will be available but not enabled. This ensures that you
            always get at least the minimum quality specified in your
            defaults. If you did not make major changes to the image
            and you want to save it using the same quality as the
            original, then you can do it by enabling this option.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show preview in image window</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Checking this option causes each change in quality (or any other
            JPEG parameter) to be shown in the image display. (This does not
            alter the image: the image reverts back to its original state
            when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Keep metadata</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the image you loaded has Exif, XMP, IPTC metadata, they are
            preserved, and you can keep them or not when exporting to JPEG.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save thumbnail, Save color profile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Many applications use the small thumbnail image as a quickly
            available small preview image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Comment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can edit the comment attached to the image you loaded or
            write a new one.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Advanced Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Some information about the advanced settings:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Optimize</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you enable this option, the optimization of entropy
                  encoding parameters will be used. The result is typically
                  a smaller file, but it takes more time to generate.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Smoothing</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  JPG compression creates artifacts. By using this option,
                  you can smooth the image when saving, reducing them. But
                  your image becomes somewhat blurred.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Use arithmetic coding</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Arithmetic encoding</emphasis> is a form of
                  entropy encoding (a lossless data compression scheme) that
                  can be used in exporting as JPEG. Images
                  using arithmetic encoding can be 5 - 10 % smaller. But older
                  software may have trouble opening these images.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Use restart markers</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The image file can include markers which allow the image
                  to be loaded as segments. If a connection is broken while
                  loading the image in a web page,
                  loading can resume from the next marker.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Interval (MCU rows)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  JPEG images are stored as a series of compressed square tiles
                  named MCU (Minimum Coding Unit). You can set the size of these
                  tiles (in pixels).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Progressive</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  With this option enabled, the image chunks are stored in
                  the file in an order that allows progressive image
                  refinement during a slow connection web download.
                  The progressive option for JPG has the same purpose as the
                  interlace option for GIF.
                  Unfortunately, the progressive option produces slightly
                  larger JPG files (than without the progressive option).
                </para>
                <note>
                  <para>
                    Beware that certain older TVs and photo frames (and maybe
                    other devices) may not be able to show jpeg images that
                    have been exported with the progressive setting enabled
                    (which is the default).
                  </para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Subsampling</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The human eye is not sensitive in the same way over
                  the entire color spectrum. The compression
                  can use this to treat slightly different colors
                  that the eye perceives as very close, as identical
                  colors. Three methods are available:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>1x1,1x1,1x1 (best quality)</guilabel>:
                      Commonly referred to as (4:4:4), this produces
                      the best quality,
                      preserving borders and contrasting colors, but
                      compression is less.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>2x1,1x1,1x1 (4:2:2)</guilabel>:
                      This is the standard subsampling, which usually
                      provides a good ratio between image quality and file
                      size. There are situations, however, in which using no
                      subsampling (4:4:4) provides a noticeable increase in
                      the image quality; for example, when the image
                      contains fine details such as text over a uniform
                      background, or images with almost-flat colors.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>1x2,1x1,1x1</guilabel>
                      This is similar to
                      (2x1,1x1,1x1), but the chroma sampling is in the
                      horizontal direction rather than the vertical
                      direction; as if someone rotated an image.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>2x2,1x1,1x1 (smallest file)</guilabel>:
                      Commonly referred to as (4:1:1), this produces
                      the smallest files. This suits images with weak
                      borders but tends to denature colors.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>DCT Method</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  DCT is <quote>discrete cosine transform</quote>,
                  and it is the first step in the JPEG algorithm going
                  from the spatial to the frequency domain. The choices are
                  <quote>float</quote>, <quote>integer</quote>
                  (the default), and <quote>fast integer</quote>.
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>float</guilabel>:
                      The float method is very slightly more accurate than
                      the integer method, but is much slower unless your
                      machine has very fast floating-point hardware. Also
                      note that the results of the floating-point method may
                      vary slightly across machines, while the integer
                      methods should give the same results everywhere.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>integer</guilabel>
                      (the default): This method is faster than
                      <quote>float</quote>, but not as accurate.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <guilabel>fast integer</guilabel>:
                      The fast integer method is much less accurate than
                      the other two.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="file-png-export">
    <title>Export Image as PNG</title>
    <anchor id="file-png-load" xreflabel="PNG"/>
    <anchor id="file-png-export-defaults" xreflabel="PNG"/>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Image as PNG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>PNG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>PNG</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Export Image as PNG</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-png-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Interlacing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Checking interlace allows an image on a web page to be
            progressively displayed as it is downloaded.
            Progressive image display is useful with slow connection
            speeds, because you can stop an image that is of no
            interest; interlace is of less use today with our faster
            connection speeds.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save background color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If your image has many transparency levels, the Internet
            browsers that recognize only two levels, will use the
            background color of your Toolbox instead.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save gamma</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Gamma correction is the ability to correct for
            differences in how computers interpret color values.
            This saves gamma information in the PNG that reflects
            the current Gamma factor for your display. Viewers on
            other computers can then compensate to ensure that the image
            is not too dark or too bright.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save layer offset</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            PNG supports an offset value called the
            <quote>oFFs chunk</quote>, which provides position data.
            Unfortunately, PNG offset support in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            is broken, or at least is not compatible with other
            applications,
            and has been for a long time. Do not enable offsets,
            let <acronym>GIMP</acronym> flatten the layers before
            saving, and you will have no problems.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Resolution</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Save the image resolution, in ppi (pixels per inch).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save creation time</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Date the file was saved.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save comment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can read this comment in the
            <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is checked, the color values are saved even if
            the pixels are completely transparent. But this is possible only
            with a single layer, not with a merged composition. When a
            multi-layer image gets exported to a single-layer file format,
            there is no way <acronym>GIMP</acronym> could preserve the color
            values in the transparent pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pixelformat</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By default your PNG image is exported in a pixelformat that
            resembles the settings of your image in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            This is usually what you want, but when you need a specific
            output format you can change this here to 8 or 16 bits per channel
            RGB or Grayscale, with or without alpha channel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compression level</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Since compression is not lossy, the only reason to use a
            compression level less than 9, is if it takes too long to
            compress a file on a slow computer.
            Nothing to fear from
            decompression: it is as quick whatever the compression level.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Keep metadata</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the image you loaded has Exif, XMP, IPTC metadata, they are
            preserved, and you can keep them or not when exporting to PNG.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Defaults</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Click to save the current settings. Latter, you can use
            <guibutton>Load Defaults</guibutton> to load the saved
            settings.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <note>
      <para>
        The PNG format supports indexed images. Using fewer colors,
        therefore, results in a smaller file; this is especially useful
        for creating web images;
        see <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Computers work on 8 bits blocks named <quote>Byte</quote>.
        A byte allows 256 colors. Reducing the number of colors below 256
        is not useful: a byte will be used anyway and the file size will not
        be less. More, this <quote>PNG8</quote>
        format, like GIF, uses only one bit for transparency; only two
        transparency levels are possible, transparent or opaque.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="file-tiff-export">
    <title>Export Image as TIFF</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Image as TIFF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>TIFF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>TIFF</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>The TIFF Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-tiff-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compression</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option allows you to specify the algorithm used to
            compress the image.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>None</guilabel>: is fast, and lossless, but the
                resulting file can be very large.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>LZW</guilabel>: The image is compressed
                using the <quote>Lempel-Ziv-Welch</quote> algorithm, a
                lossless compression technique. This is efficient and fast.
                More information at
                <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-lzw"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Pack Bits</guilabel>: is a fast, simple
                compression scheme for run-length encoding of data. Apple
                introduced the PackBits format with the release of
                MacPaint on the Macintosh computer. A PackBits data
                stream consists of packets of one byte of header followed
                by data. (Source:
                <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-packbits"/>)
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Deflate</guilabel>: is a lossless data
                compression algorithm that uses a combination of the LZ77
                algorithm and Huffman coding. It is also used in Zip and
                Gzip files and PNG images. Source:
                <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-deflate"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>JPEG</guilabel>: is a very good compression
                algorithm but lossy. This is the same compression as used in
                JPEG images. Since it is lossy, you should not use this when
                image quality is important. This compression can not be
                used when your image is in indexed mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>CCITT Group 3 fax</guilabel> and
                <guilabel>CCITT Group 4 fax</guilabel> are black and white
                formats developed to transfer images by FAX.
              </para>
              <note>
                <para>
                  These two compression modes can only be selected, if the
                  image is in indexed mode and reduced to two colors. Use
                  <menuchoice>
                      <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                      <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu>
                      <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice>
                  to convert the image to indexed mode. Make sure that
                  <quote>Use black and white (1-bit) palette</quote> is
                  checked.
                </para>
              </note>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save layers</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Since GIMP-2.10.12, you can save layers when exporting to TIFF.
            Each layer will be a separate page in the TIFF image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Crop layers</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When <guilabel>Save layers</guilabel> is checked, this option,
            which is enabled by default, will resize all layers to the size
            of the image. TIFF images can not have negative offsets. This
            option enables you to import the TIFF again without having to
            change the position of layers that had a different size as the
            image in the original.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this is enabled the color values are saved even if the pixels
            are completely transparent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Metadata (edit)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can click the <quote>(edit)</quote> link to open the metadata
            editor to change or add any metadata that you want to be
            included in the image. Note: you will also still need to
            enable the relevant metadata saving options listed below.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Exif data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled existing EXIF metadata will be saved
            in the exported TIFF image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save IPTC data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled existing IPTC metadata will be saved
            in the exported TIFF image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save XMP data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled existing XMP metadata will be saved
            in the exported TIFF image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save color profile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled the color profile will be saved in
            the exported TIFF image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save thumbnail</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled a thumbnail will be saved as the
            second page in the exported TIFF image. This will also cause
            certain EXIF tags to be saved even if you have disabled saving
            EXIF metadata.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save GeoTIFF data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled GeoTIFF metadata that was present in
            the original image will be saved in the exported TIFF image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save comment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Here you can enable saving a comment that is associated with the
            image. The comment can be entered in the text box below this
            option.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="file-webp-export">
    <title>Export Image as WebP</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Image as WebP</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>WebP</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>WebP</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>The WebP Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-webp-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source Type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This selects the type of image you are trying to export.
            Presumably this will help in deciding the best way to compress
            the image.
          </para>
          <para>
            Choices are: <guilabel>Default</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Picture</guilabel> for digital pictures, like portraits
            or inside shots, <guilabel>Photo</guilabel> for outdoor
            photography with natural lighting, <guilabel>Drawing</guilabel>
            for hand or line drawing, with high-contrast details,
            <guilabel>Icon</guilabel> for small-sized colorful images, and
            <guilabel>Text</guilabel> for images containing mostly text.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Lossless</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, the image will be saved in a way that keeps the
            original quality. This disables the
            <guilabel>Image quality</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>Alpha quality</guilabel> settings.
            When unchecked, the image will be saved based on the quality
            settings below, which may cause some loss of quality, but at a
            better compression ratio. This is the default.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image quality, Alpha quality</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These settings determine at what quality the image will be saved.
            A higher image quality usually means a larger filesize. When
            filesize is important you can check if a lower quality is still
            good enough for your purposes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use Sharp YUV</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, a sharper and more accurate RGB to YUV conversion
            method is used to export the image. This can better preserve fine
            details like thin lines in the final image. Setting this option
            can increase the export time for an image, and it is only
            available when <guilabel>Lossless</guilabel> is not checked.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Exif data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled existing EXIF metadata will be saved
            in the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save IPTC data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled existing IPTC metadata will be saved
            in the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save XMP data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled existing XMP metadata will be saved
            in the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save color profile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled the color profile will be saved in
            the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save thumbnail</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is enabled a thumbnail will be saved in the
            exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="file-mng-export">
    <title>Export Image as MNG</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Image as MNG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>MNG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>MNG</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>Export MNG File Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-mng-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      MNG is acronym for <quote>Multiple-Image Network Graphics</quote>.
    </para>
    <para>
      No common web browsers recognize the MNG animation format. See
      <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple-image_Network_Graphics"/>.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
