<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-tiff-export">
  <title>Export Image as TIFF</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as TIFF</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>TIFF</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>TIFF</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>The TIFF Export dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/export-tiff-dialog.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Compression</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option allows you to specify the algorithm used to
          compress the image.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>None</guilabel>: is fast, and lossless, but the
              resulting file can be very large.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>LZW</guilabel>: The image is compressed
              using the <quote>Lempel-Ziv-Welch</quote> algorithm, a
              lossless compression technique. This is efficient and fast.
              More information at
              <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-lzw"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Pack Bits</guilabel>: is a fast, simple
              compression scheme for run-length encoding of data. Apple
              introduced the PackBits format with the release of
              MacPaint on the Macintosh computer. A PackBits data
              stream consists of packets of one byte of header followed
              by data. (Source:
              <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-packbits"/>)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Deflate</guilabel>: is a lossless data
              compression algorithm that uses a combination of the LZ77
              algorithm and Huffman coding. It is also used in Zip and
              Gzip files and PNG images. Source:
              <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-deflate"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>JPEG</guilabel>: is a very good compression
              algorithm but lossy. This is the same compression as used in
              JPEG images. Since it is lossy, you should not use this when
              image quality is important. This compression can not be
              used when your image is in indexed mode.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>CCITT Group 3 fax</guilabel> and
              <guilabel>CCITT Group 4 fax</guilabel> are black and white
              formats developed to transfer images by FAX.
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                These two compression modes can only be selected, if the
                image is in indexed mode and reduced to two colors. Use
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                to convert the image to indexed mode. Make sure that
                <quote>Use black and white (1-bit) palette</quote> is
                checked.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save layers</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can save layers when exporting to TIFF.
          Each layer will be a separate page in the TIFF image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Crop layers</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When <guilabel>Save layers</guilabel> is checked, this option,
          which is enabled by default, will resize all layers to the size
          of the image. TIFF images can not have negative offsets. This
          option enables you to import the TIFF again without having to
          change the position of layers that had a different size as the
          image in the original.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this is enabled the color values are saved even if the pixels
          are completely transparent.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Export as CMYK</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Whether to export using a CMYK
          <link linkend="gimp-concepts-color-management">Color Profile</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Metadata (edit)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can click the <quote>(edit)</quote> link to open the metadata
          editor to change or add any metadata that you want to be
          included in the image. Note: you will also still need to
          enable the relevant metadata saving options listed below.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save Exif data</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is enabled existing EXIF metadata will be saved
          in the exported TIFF image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save IPTC data</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is enabled existing IPTC metadata will be saved
          in the exported TIFF image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save XMP data</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is enabled existing XMP metadata will be saved
          in the exported TIFF image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save color profile</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is enabled the color profile will be saved in
          the exported TIFF image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save thumbnail</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is enabled a thumbnail will be saved as the
          second page in the exported TIFF image. This will also cause
          certain EXIF tags to be saved even if you have disabled saving
          EXIF metadata.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save GeoTIFF data</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is enabled GeoTIFF metadata that was present in
          the original image will be saved in the exported TIFF image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save comment</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Here you can enable saving a comment that is associated with the
          image. The comment can be entered in the text box below this
          option.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
