<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-pdf-export">
  <title>Export Image as PDF</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as PDF</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>PDF</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The PDF Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-pdf-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You can export your image in PDF format when you choose the
      <quote>.pdf</quote> extension, or explicitly choose <quote>Portable
      Document Format</quote> as file type in the export dialog.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Layers as pages</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, creates a page for each layer in your image, starting
            from the bottom layer. This setting is disabled when you only have
            one layer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reverse order</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, the pages are created in reverse order, starting
            from the top.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Root layers only</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, only the layers not inside a group will be used to
            create pages. Groups at the root level will be included by merging
            the layers inside them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Apply layer masks</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, applies the layer mask before saving. This does not
            change the PDF output, only the internal structure of the PDF.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Convert bitmaps to vector graphics where possible</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, vector graphics will be used instead of bitmaps,
            where possible.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Omit hidden layers and layers with zero opacity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, layers that have visibility turned off, or where the
            opacity of the layer is set to zero, will be ignored when creating
            the page or pages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fill transparent areas with background color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, if there are transparent areas, it will
            replace those with the background color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Convert text layers to image</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, text layers will be converted to raster graphics
            instead of including it as actual text.
            This can be useful if the font used for the text cannot be found
            by the PDF exporter and thus not included in the PDF. If the font
            is not included in your PDF, there is no guarantee that the text
            will look the same to someone else.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
