<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-jpegxl-export">
  <title>Export Image as JPEG XL</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>JPEG XL</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>.jxl</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as JPEG XL</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>JPEG XL</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPEG_XL">JPEG XL</ulink>
      is an image format that supports both lossy and lossless compression.
      The lossy compression is similar to that of JPEG, but significantly
      improved. Besides that there is a <quote>modular</quote> mode, that can
      be used for lossless compression similar to PNG, and also as an
      alternate lossy compression mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can export your image in this format when you choose the
      <quote>.jxl</quote> extension, or explicitly choose <quote>JPEG XL</quote>
      as file type in the export dialog.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>The JPEG XL Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-jpegxl-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Lossless</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, the image will be exported with lossless
            compression. This will create a higher quality image at
            the cost of a larger file size.
          </para>
          <para>
            When unchecked, the image will use a lossy compression technique
            that can reduce the file size more.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compression/maxError</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When <guilabel>Lossless</guilabel> is unchecked, this setting
            influences the amount of compression. Lower values give higher
            quality. At the minimum value of 1.0 it is visually almost
            the same as lossless.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Effort/Speed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This setting determines how much effort the encoder will put into
            reaching the desired quality, influenced by the
            <guilabel>Compression/maxError</guilabel> parameter.
          </para>
          <para>
            A higher effort may create more accurate results, but sometimes
            higher file size in lossy compression mode. A higher effort also
            consumes more memory too. Usually there is no reason to change
            the default value (<guilabel>squirrel</guilabel>).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Bit depth</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Determines if the pixel data should be stored using 8 bits or
            16 bits per color channel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export as CMYK</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you have a CMYK profile assigned to your image as soft-proofing
            profiles, this setting can be checked to have the image exported
            using the CMYK profile.
            If this setting is disabled, you don't have a soft-proofing profile
            set for this image yet. See assigning a
            <link linkend="gimp-image-soft-proof-profile-assign">Soft-Proof
            Profile</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The name of the CMYK profile that is assigned to this image will
            be shown below this setting.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Exif</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If checked, the Exif metadata is embedded in the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save XMP</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If checked, the XMP metadata is embedded in the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
