<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-png-export">
  <title>Export Image as PNG</title>
  <anchor id="file-png-load" xreflabel="PNG"/>
  <anchor id="file-png-export-defaults" xreflabel="PNG"/>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as PNG</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>PNG</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>PNG</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>The PNG Export dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/export-png-dialog.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Pixel format</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By default your PNG image is exported in a pixelformat that
          resembles the settings of your image in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          This is usually what you want, but when you need a specific
          output format you can change this here to 8 or 16 bits per channel
          RGB or Grayscale, with or without alpha channel.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Compression level</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Since compression is not lossy, the only reason to use a
          compression level less than 9, is if it takes too long to
          compress a file on a slow computer.
          Nothing to fear from
          decompression: it is as quick whatever the compression level.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Interlacing</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Checking interlace allows an image on a web page to be
          progressively displayed as it is downloaded.
          Progressive image display is useful with slow connection
          speeds, because you can stop an image that is of no
          interest; interlace is of less use today with our faster
          connection speeds.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When this option is checked, the color values are saved even if
          the pixels are completely transparent. But this is possible only
          with a single layer, not with a merged composition. When a
          multi-layer image gets exported to a single-layer file format,
          there is no way <acronym>GIMP</acronym> could preserve the color
          values in the transparent pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Metadata (edit)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can click the <quote>(edit)</quote> link to open the metadata
          editor to change or add any metadata that you want to be
          included in the image. Note: you will also still need to
          enable the relevant metadata saving options listed below.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save background color</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If your image has many transparency levels, the Internet
          browsers that recognize only two levels, will use the
          background color of your Toolbox instead.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save layer offset</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          PNG supports an offset value called the
          <quote>oFFs chunk</quote>, which provides position data.
          Unfortunately, PNG offset support in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          is broken, or at least is not compatible with other
          applications,
          and has been for a long time. Do not enable offsets,
          let <acronym>GIMP</acronym> flatten the layers before
          saving, and you will have no problems.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save resolution</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Save the image resolution, in ppi (pixels per inch).</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save creation time</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Date the file was saved.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save comment</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can read this comment in the
          <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Other Metadata</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If the image you loaded has Exif, XMP, IPTC metadata, select which
          metadata you want to preserve keep when exporting.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can also save the color profile, a custom comment to be shown
          in the <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>,
          and include a small preview thumbnail of the image when exporting.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Save Settings</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Click to save the current settings. Later, you can use
          <guibutton>Load Saved Settings</guibutton> to load the saved
          settings.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <note>
    <para>
      The PNG format supports indexed images. Using fewer colors,
      therefore, results in a smaller file; this is especially useful
      for creating web images;
      see <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Computers work on 8 bits blocks named <quote>Byte</quote>.
      A byte allows 256 colors. Reducing the number of colors below 256
      is not useful: a byte will be used anyway and the file size will not
      be less. More, this <quote>PNG8</quote>
      format, like GIF, uses only one bit for transparency; only two
      transparency levels are possible, transparent or opaque.
    </para>
  </note>
</sect2>
