<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-dds-export">
  <title>Export Image as DDS</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as DDS</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>dds</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <figure>
      <title>The DDS Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-dds-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DirectDraw_Surface">DDS</ulink>
      file format is often used in games for storing textures and environment
      maps. It supports both compressed and uncompressed textures.
    </para>
    <para>
      In most cases game engines require the texture dimensions to be a power
      of two, but width and height do not need to be the same. Common values
      are 64, 128, 256, 512, etc.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compression</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The type of compression to use. When set to
            <guilabel>None</guilabel>, the non-compressed format can be
            selected from <guilabel>Format</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Usually games only support some of the compressed and non-compressed
            formats. Check the game documentation which modes they support.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>None</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The image data is stored uncompressed. The actual format
                  is determined from the <guilabel>Format</guilabel> setting.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BC1 / DXT1</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Stores 5 bits of red, 6 bits of green and 5 bits of blue
                  per color. If there is an alpha channel, only 1 bit of
                  alpha (either full transparent or full opaque) is stored,
                  taking away 1 bit of green.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This format creates the smallest size files. It doesn't
                  work well on images that have sudden changes in color,
                  like pixel art.
                  In general not recommended when you have an alpha channel.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BC2 / DXT3</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Stores colors the same as DXT1, except it also stores full
                  alpha channels. This format is rarely used.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BC3 / DXT5</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Stores colors the same as DXT1, but supports full alpha
                  channels, which it stores pre-multiplied.
                </para>
                <para>
                  In general preferrable over DXT3 and commonly used where
                  alpha channels are important.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BC3nm / DXT5nm</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A variant of DXT5 used for storing normal maps.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BC4 / ATI1 (3Dc+)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This is used for storing one color channel only. Only the
                  red channel in a color image will be stored. The other
                  channels will be ignored as well as the alpha channel.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BC5 / ATI2 (3Dc)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This is used for storing two color channels. Only the red
                  and green channels in a color image will be stored. The
                  blue channel will be ignored as well as the alpha channel.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RXGB (DXT5)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A variant of DXT5. It is rarely used and requires explicit
                  support by the game that uses it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alpha Exponent (DXT5)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A variant of DXT5 that has a highly compressed alpha channel.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>YCoCg (DXT5)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A special variant of DXT5 that converts the RGB color
                  channels to YCoCg, which allows high-quality compression
                  of images. This requires explicit support by the game
                  that uses it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>YCoCg scaled (DXT5)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Same as above, but improves pixel quality at the cost of
                  longer processing time. This requires explicit support by the
                  game that uses it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use perceptual error metric</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This setting is only enabled when compression is not
            <guilabel>None</guilabel>.
            Enabling this setting may enhance visual quality in certain cases.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Format</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This setting determines the color format for non-compressed
            textures. There exist a wide range of formats, but not all of them
            are equally well supported by games and image viewers.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Chooses the best fitting format based on the type of
                  image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGB8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 8 bits per channel for red, green and
                  blue.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGBA8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 8 bits per channel for red, green, blue
                  and alpha.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BGR8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 8 bits per channel in reverse order for
                  blue, green and red.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>ABGR8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 8 bits per channel in reverse order with
                  the alpha channel first, then blue, green and red.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>R5G6B5</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 5 bits of red, 6 bits of green and 5 bits
                  of blue.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGBA4</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 4 bits of red, green, blue and alpha.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGB5A1</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 5 bits of red, green and blue, with
                  one bit of alpha.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGB10A2</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores 10 bits of red, green and blue, with
                  two bits of alpha.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>R3G3B2</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores three bits of red and green and two bits
                  of blue.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>A8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores a single component of 8 bits. This is
                  taken from the alpha channel.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>L8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores a single component of 8 bits. This is
                  taken from the red or grayscale channel. This is often used
                  to enhance luminance.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>L8A8</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This format stores two components of 8 bits. This is
                  taken from the red or grayscale and alpha channels.
                  This is often used to enhance luminance.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>AEXP</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This stands for <quote>Alpha Exponent</quote> and uses the
                  same algorithm as the
                  <guilabel>Alpha Exponent (DXT5)</guilabel> compression.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This is rarely used. Check first if it is supported and
                  required by your game engine.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>YCOCG</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This uses the same algorithm as the
                  <guilabel>YCoCg (DXT5)</guilabel> compression.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This is rarely used. Check first if it is supported and
                  required by your game engine.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This determines how your image will be saved.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Selected layer</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Only the currently selected layer will be exported.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>All visible layers</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  All visible layers will be merged and then exported.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>As cube map</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Your selected layer will be exported as a cube map. A cube
                  map is a special layout of related textures, where each
                  layer represents one side of a cube.
                </para>
                <para>
                  A Cube Map requires six layers that are all the same size,
                  with or without transparency. Each layer must have one of the
                  correct identifiers at the end of the layer name.
                </para>
                <para>
                  These identifiers are <quote>Front</quote>, <quote>Back</quote>,
                  <quote>Left</quote>, <quote>Right</quote>, <quote>Top</quote>,
                  <quote>Bottom</quote>.
                  For example your layers could be named: <quote>woodland_front</quote>,
                  <quote>woodland_back</quote>, etc.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This setting is only enabled when the above conditions are
                  met.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>As volume map</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Your selected layer will be exported as a volume map. A volume
                  map is similar to a cube map, but the textures are not
                  expected to be part of a cube, so no fixed number of layers
                  are required.
                </para>
                <para>
                  A Volume Maps also requires all layers to have the same size,
                  with or without transparency. However, you are not limited to
                  the number of layers you want to use and no special naming of
                  layers is required.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This setting is only enabled when the above conditions are
                  met.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>As texture array</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Your image will be exported as a texture array. Only layers
                  that have the same size as the image will be exported.
                  This stores a collection of textures in one image.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This setting is only enabled when there are at least two
                  layers.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Flip image vertically on export</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Some game engines require the image to be turned upside down.
            Enabling this setting will do that for you.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mipmaps </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Mipmaps are reduced size versions of the same image where each
            mipmap is half the width and height of the previous one. Often
            used in game engines to improve loading in scenes where the object
            is located far away.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>No mipmaps</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  No mipmaps are added to the exported image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Generate mipmaps</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  New mipmaps are created and added to the exported image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Use existing mipmaps</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Already available mipmaps in your image will be reused and
                  added to the exported image. This will only be enabled if
                  the correct number of mipmaps using the expected sizes are
                  available.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Set transparent color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, this uses the below specified indexed color for
            setting transparency in the exported image. This setting is only
            enabled when your image is in indexed mode.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Transparent index</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When the previous setting is checked and enabled, this lets you
            specify which palette index should be used for transparency in
            the exported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mipmap Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The following options are only enabled when you are adding mipmaps
            to your image.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Filter</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This setting determines which filter will be used for
                  interpolation when downsizing your image to create a mipmap.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Default</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        No filtering is applied to create the mipmap. This can
                        cause visual anomalies such as excessively sharp edges
                        and stair-stepping artifacts.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Nearest</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This is a bilinear filter, may enable better
                        switching between mipmaps.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Box</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This is a polyphase box filter. Outside of the
                        <guilabel>Lanczos</guilabel> and
                        <guilabel>Kaiser</guilabel> filters, it’s a good choice
                        for most cases and also much faster than other filters.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Triangle</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This uses a triangle filter. The kernel has a larger
                        width and thus produces blurrier results than the
                        <guilabel>Box</guilabel> filter.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Quadratic</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This is a gaussian type filter.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>B-Spline</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This is a trilinear filter.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Mitchell</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This filter is used primarily to reduce loss of detail
                        while upsampling.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Catmull-Rom</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Lanczos</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This is similar to the <guilabel>Kaiser</guilabel>
                        filter. The results are usually indistinguishable
                        between the two. Lanczos may handle ringing and
                        artifacts better.
                        This filter can be further tweaked using the
                        <guilabel>Wrap mode</guilabel> setting.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Kaiser</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This filter is generally considered the best choice for
                        downsampling, but in order to obtain best results it is
                        advisable to experiment with the
                        <guilabel>Wrap mode</guilabel> setting. Otherwise the
                        resulting images could suffer from fringing artifacts
                        or the result may not be as sharp as desired.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Wrap mode</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When evaluating the color of texels that are near the border,
                  most of the filters usually sample outside of the texture.
                  This setting determines how these samples are handled.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Default</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This generally looks good enough. Often better results
                        can be achieved by explicitly specifying one of the next
                        modes.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Mirror</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        Mirroring is used for many other image processing
                        operations, like normal map generation, and is
                        generally considered the best option. It takes the
                        data from the other side of the image.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Repeat</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This takes the data outside the edges from the value
                        just inside it.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Clamp</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This clamps the data outside the edges to the values
                        at the edges.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Apply gamma correction</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When checked, uses gamma correction for mipmap filtering.
                  This adjusts the reflectiveness of an object while also
                  making the entire image lighter or darker, depending
                  on the value used below.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Use sRGB colorspace for gamma correction</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When checked, uses the sRGB color space for gamma correction
                  of mipmaps.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Gamma</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  You can set the desired <guilabel>Gamma</guilabel> value to
                  be used for gamma correction here.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Preserve alpha test coverage</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When checked, this preserves alpha test coverage for alpha
                  channel maps, based on a threshold set below.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alpha test threshold</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The threshold value to be used for preserving test coverage
                  of alpha channels.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
