<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-jpeg-export">
  <title>Export Image as JPEG</title>
  <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" xreflabel="JPEG"/>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>JPEG</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>.jpg</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>.jpeg</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as JPEG</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>JPEG</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg. It is a
    very widely used format, because it compresses images very
    efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality. No other
    format comes close to achieving the same level of compression. It does
    not, however, support transparency or multiple layers.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>The JPEG Export dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/export-jpeg-dialog.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering number
    of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this documentation.
    Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality parameter is probably the
    only one you will need to adjust.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Quality</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When you save a file in JPEG format, a dialog is displayed
          that allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 0
          to 100. Values above 95 are generally not useful, though. The
          default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, but
          in many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
          lower without noticeably degrading the image. You can test the
          effect of different quality settings by checking
          <guilabel>Show Preview in image window</guilabel>
          in the JPEG dialog.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            Please note, that the numbers for the JPEG quality level have
            a different meaning in different applications.
            Saving with a quality level of 80 in GIMP is not
            necessarily comparable with saving with a quality level of
            80 in a different application.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        Use quality settings from original image
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a particular quality setting (or <quote>quantization
          table</quote>) was attached to the image when it was
          loaded, then this option allows you to use them instead of
          the standard ones.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you have only made a few changes to the image, then
          re-using the same quality setting will give you almost the
          same quality and file size as the original image. This
          will minimize the losses caused by the quantization step,
          compared to what would happen if you used different
          quality setting.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the quality setting found in the original file are not
          better than your default quality settings, then the option
          <quote>Use quality settings from original image</quote>
          will be available but not enabled. This ensures that you
          always get at least the minimum quality specified in your
          defaults. If you did not make major changes to the image
          and you want to save it using the same quality as the
          original, then you can do it by enabling this option.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Show preview in image window</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Checking this option causes each change in quality (or any other
          JPEG parameter) to be shown in the image display. (This does not
          alter the image: the image reverts back to its original state
          when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Advanced Options</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Some information about the advanced settings:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Smoothing</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                JPG compression creates artifacts. By using this option,
                you can smooth the image when saving, reducing them. But
                your image becomes somewhat blurred.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Progressive</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                With this option enabled, the image chunks are stored in
                the file in an order that allows progressive image
                refinement during a slow connection web download.
                The progressive option for JPG has the same purpose as the
                interlace option for GIF.
                Unfortunately, the progressive option produces slightly
                larger JPG files (than without the progressive option).
              </para>
              <note>
                <para>
                  Beware that certain older TVs and photo frames (and maybe
                  other devices) may not be able to show jpeg images that
                  have been exported with the progressive setting enabled
                  (which is the default).
                </para>
              </note>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Export as CMYK</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Whether to export using a CMYK
                <link linkend="gimp-concepts-color-management">Color Profile</link>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Use arithmetic coding</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Arithmetic encoding</emphasis> is a form of
                entropy encoding (a lossless data compression scheme) that
                can be used in exporting as JPEG. Images
                using arithmetic encoding can be 5 - 10 % smaller. But older
                software may have trouble opening these images.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Optimize</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you enable this option, the optimization of entropy
                encoding parameters will be used. The result is typically
                a smaller file, but it takes more time to generate.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Use restart markers</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The image file can include markers which allow the image
                to be loaded as segments. If a connection is broken while
                loading the image in a web page,
                loading can resume from the next marker.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Interval (MCU rows)</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                JPEG images are stored as a series of compressed square tiles
                named MCU (Minimum Coding Unit). You can set the size of these
                tiles (in pixels).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Subsampling</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The human eye is not sensitive in the same way over
                the entire color spectrum. The compression
                can use this to treat slightly different colors
                that the eye perceives as very close, as identical
                colors. Three methods are available:
              </para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>1x1,1x1,1x1 (best quality)</guilabel>:
                    Commonly referred to as (4:4:4), this produces
                    the best quality,
                    preserving borders and contrasting colors, but
                    compression is less.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>2x1,1x1,1x1 (4:2:2)</guilabel>:
                    This is the standard subsampling, which usually
                    provides a good ratio between image quality and file
                    size. There are situations, however, in which using no
                    subsampling (4:4:4) provides a noticeable increase in
                    the image quality; for example, when the image
                    contains fine details such as text over a uniform
                    background, or images with almost-flat colors.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>1x2,1x1,1x1</guilabel>
                    This is similar to
                    (2x1,1x1,1x1), but the chroma sampling is in the
                    horizontal direction rather than the vertical
                    direction; as if someone rotated an image.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>2x2,1x1,1x1 (smallest file)</guilabel>:
                    Commonly referred to as (4:1:1), this produces
                    the smallest files. This suits images with weak
                    borders but tends to denature colors.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>DCT Method</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                DCT is <quote>discrete cosine transform</quote>,
                and it is the first step in the JPEG algorithm going
                from the spatial to the frequency domain. The choices are
                <quote>float</quote>, <quote>integer</quote>
                (the default), and <quote>fast integer</quote>.
              </para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>float</guilabel>:
                    The float method is very slightly more accurate than
                    the integer method, but is much slower unless your
                    machine has very fast floating-point hardware. Also
                    note that the results of the floating-point method may
                    vary slightly across machines, while the integer
                    methods should give the same results everywhere.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>integer</guilabel>
                    (the default): This method is faster than
                    <quote>float</quote>, but not as accurate.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>fast integer</guilabel>:
                    The fast integer method is much less accurate than
                    the other two.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Metadata (edit)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can click the <quote>(edit)</quote> link to open the metadata
          editor to change or add any metadata that you want to be
          included in the image. Note: you will also still need to
          enable the relevant metadata saving options listed below.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Metadata</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If the image you loaded has Exif, XMP, IPTC metadata, select which
          metadata you want to preserve keep when exporting.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can also save the color profile, a custom comment to be shown
          in the <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>,
          and include a small preview thumbnail of the image when exporting.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
