<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="file-xbm-export">
  <title>Export Image as X BitMap</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Export Image as X BitMap</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Formats</primary>
    <secondary>xbm</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <figure>
      <title>The XBM Export dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/export-xbm-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_BitMap">X BitMap</ulink>
      (XBM), is a plain text image format that was mainly used for cursors
      and icon bitmaps in the X GUI. This format was superseded by
      <link linkend="file-xpm-export">X PixMap</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      This format only supports exporting as black and white monochrome
      images. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> only supports exporting to this from
      8-bits per channel images.
    </para>
    <para>
      Due to being stored in the form of C source files, this format can
      take up more space than other binary formats.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>X10 format bitmap</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, the image will use short integers instead of bytes
            to write the data.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Identifier prefix</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The prefix used to write the data. This is mainly useful if you
            intend to read this file from C source code.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Write comment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, a comment will be added to the output file. Not all
            image viewers are able to correctly show this image if a comment
            is present.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Comment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When the above setting is enabled, you can enter your comment here.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Write hot spot values</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, hot spot values will be added. These are used in
            icon files to set the location of the icon hot spot.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hot spot X</term>
        <term>Hot spot Y</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These values set the X and Y coordinate of the hot spot of the
            mouse cursor.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Write extra mask file</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, a separate mask file will be created. The mask file
            contains the alpha channel for the XBM image.
            This setting is only enabled when your image has an alpha channel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mask file extensions</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This allows you to set the suffix that will be added to the name
            of your image. The name with suffix will be used to write the
            mask file.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
