<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-font-dialog' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Fonts dialog</title>
  <title lang="cs">Dialog Písma</title>
  <title lang="fr">Dialogue des polices</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">字体对话框</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Fonts</secondary>
    <primary lang="cs">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Písma</secondary>
    <primary lang="fr">Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Polices</secondary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">字体</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en;cs;zh_CN'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-fonts.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-fonts.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para lang='en'>
	  The Fonts dialog
	</para>
        <para lang='cs'>
         Dialog Písma
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Le dialogue des polices
        </para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  字体对话框
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Fonts dialog is used for selecting fonts for the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-text'>Text tool</link>.  It also allows you to refresh
    the list of available fonts, if you add new ones to your system
    while GIMP is running.
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Dialog Písma se používá pro výběr vhodného řezu písma (fontu) pro
    nástroj (FIXLINK)Text. Umožňuje rovněž
    obnovit seznam dostupných písem v případě, že nějaká do vašeho systému
    přidáte během práce s Gimpem.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Le dialogue des polices est utilisé pour sélectionner les polices
    pour l'outil <link linkend='gimp-tool-text'>Texte</link>.
    Il vous permet aussi de rafraîchir la liste des polices
    disponibles si vous en installez des nouvelles durant l'utilisation
    de Gimp.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    字体对话框是<link linkend='gimp-tool-text'>文字工具</link>在其中选取字体。在 GIMP 运行同时为系统添加了新的字体，也可以用该对话框来刷新可用字体的列表。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Fonts dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Dialog Písma je dokovatelný; viz část
    <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dokování dialogů</link>.
    Dialog Písma lze vyvolat několika způsoby:
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Le dialogue des polices est un dialogue rattachable, voyez la
    section <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogues attachables</link>
    pour plus de détails. Il peut être lancer de plusieurs façons :
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    字体对话框是可停靠对话框；关于如何使用它，请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>这节。有多种方式开启它：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>
      <para>
        Z nabídky Panelu nástrojů:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogy</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Písma</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='fr'>
      <para>    
        Depuis le menu de la boîte à outils :
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogues</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>olices</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>字体</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='fr'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>
      <para>
        Z nabídky obrázku:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogy</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Písma</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        Depuis le menu d'image :
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogues</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>olices</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>字体</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>onts</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>
      <para>
        Z nabídky odrážek jakéhokoliv dokovatelného dialogu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Přidat odrážku</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Písma</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='fr'>      
      <para>    
        Depuis le menu d'onglet d'un autre dialogue
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Ajouter un onglet</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>olices</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从任何可停靠对话框：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>添加菜单</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>字体</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tool Options for the Text tool.  If you click on the
      "Font" button, a Font-selector pops up.  In the lower right
      corner is a button that, if pressed, brings up the Fonts
      dialog. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>
      <para>
        Z dialogu Volby nástroje Text. Kliknete-li na tlačítko pro výběr
        písma, zobrazí se volič písem, v jehož pravém dolním rohu je tlačítko.
        Jeho stisknutím otevřete dialog Písma.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='fr'>      
      <para>    
        Depuis les options de l'outil Texte. Si vous cliquez sur le
        bouton Police un menu de sélection des polices apparaît. En
        bas à droite vous retrouvez un bouton qui va ouvrir le
        dialogue des polices.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        在文字工具的工具选修中，点击“字体”按钮，将弹出一个字体选择器，然后按下它右下角按钮就会出现字体对话框。
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>
    <title lang="cs">Režim mřížky a seznamu</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">阵列/列表模式</title>
    <title lang="fr">Modes grille et liste</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang='en;cs;zh_CN'>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-fonts-grid.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang='fr'>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-fonts-grid.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    The Fonts dialog (Grid View)
	  </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            Dialog Písma (režim mřížky)
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            Le dialogue des polices (mode grille)
          </para>
	  <para lang="zh_CN">
	    字体对话框(以阵列方式查看)
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu for the Fonts dialog, you can choose between
      <guimenuitem>View as Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as
      List</guimenuitem>.   In Grid mode, the fonts are laid out in a
      rectangular array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically,
      with each row showing an example of the appearance of the font
      ("Aa"), followed by the name of the font.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      V nabídce odrážky dialogu Písma můžete vybrat mezi zobrazením v režimu
      mřížky (<guimenuitem>Zobrazit jako mřížku</guimenuitem>) či seznamu
      (<guimenuitem>Zobrazit jako seznam</guimenuitem>). V režimu mřížky jsou
      písma zobrazena v pravidelné čtvercové síti, v režimu seznamu tvoří
      vertikálně seřazený seznam obѕahující ukázku písma
      <guilabel>Aa</guilabel> a jeho jméno.
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Dans le menu d'onglet du dialogue des polices vous pouvez
      choisir entre les modes 
      <guimenuitem>Voir comme une liste</guimenuitem> et
      <guimenuitem>Voir comme une grille</guimenuitem>.
      Dans le mode grille les polices sont disposées de façon
      rectangulaire. Dans le mode liste elles sont alignés
      verticalement avec chaque rangée montrant un (Aa) aperçu
      de rendu suivi du nom de la police.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您可以在字体对话框的页签菜单中选择是<guimenuitem>以阵列方式查看</guimenuitem>还是<guimenuitem>以列表方式查看</guimenuitem>。阵列模式中，字体以矩形阵列排列，而列表模式中，它们垂直线性排列，每一行则是字体显示的一个例子(“Aa”)，其后是该字体的名字。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Fonts dialog</title>
    <title lang="cs">Použití dialogu Písma</title>
    <title lang="fr">Utiliser le dialogue des polices</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用字体对话框</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a font by clicking
      on it:  this font will then be used by the Text tool.  If
      instead of clicking and releasing, you hold down the 
      left mouse button with the pointer positioned over the font
      example ("Aa"), a window showing a larger text example will
      pop up ("Pack my box with five dozen liquor jugs.").
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Základním úkonem, ke kterému dialog slouží, je výběr požadovaného
      písma ze seznamu kliknutím. Vybraný font bude používán nástrojem
      Text. Pokud kliknete na ukázku písma (<guilabel>Aa</guilabel>) a
      tlačítko myši neuvolníte, ale ponecháte chvíli stisknuté, objeví
      se větší ukázka daného písma („Příliš žluťoučký kůň úpěl ďábelské
      ódy“).
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      La chose la plus simple que vous pouvez faire est de
      sélectionner une police en cliquant dessus, elle sera ensuite
      utilisée par l'outil Texte. Si vous cliquez sur le texte
      Aa d'aperçu avec le bouton gauche de la souris, un texte
      plus complet sera affiché pour vous faire une meilleure
      idée du rendu de la police.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      最基本的操作就是在字体对话框中点击并选取一个字体：字体工具会使用该字体。假如不是点击再松开，而是按住左键并将光标置于一个字体例子(“Aa”)上，则会弹出一个显示更大字体例子的窗口。
    </para>

    <anchor id='gimp-font-refresh' />

    <para lang='en'>
      Pressing the button at the bottom of the dialog causes the
      system font list to be rescanned.  This may be useful if you add
      new fonts while GIMP is running, and want to make them
      accessible for the Text tool.  You can also cause the font list
      to be rescanned by right-clicking in the font display, and
      selecting "Rescan Font List" from the menu that pops up (it is
      actually the only option in the menu).
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Stisknutí tlačítka ve spodní části dialogu obnoví seznam písem.
      To je užitečné v případě, že přidáte do svého systému písma během práce
      s Gimpem, a chcete je ihned použít. Obnovení seznamu písem můžete
      dosáhnout také kliknutím pravým tlačítkem myši v seznamu písem a
      výběrem <guimenuitem>Znovu načíst seznam písem</guimenuitem> (je
      to jediná položka v nabídce).
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      En pressant le bouton en bas du dialogue la liste des polices
      du système sera rescannée. Vous pouvez aussi le faire en
      cliquant droit pour appeler le menu contextuel et en sélectionnant
      l'entrée Recharger la liste des polices.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      点击对话框底部的按钮将重新扫描系统字体列表。在 GIMP 运行同时为系统添加了新的字体并想在文字工具中使用它们时非常有用。也可以在字体列表中点击右键，并从弹出菜单中选择“重新扫描字体列表”(实际上它是该菜单中唯一的选项)。
    </para>

    <note lang='en'>
      <para>
        You can change the size of the font previews in the dialog using
        the "Preview Size" submenu of the dialog's Tab menu.
      </para>
    </note>
    <note lang='cs'>
      <para>
        velikost náhledů písem můžete změnit pomocí podnabídky
        <guisubmenu>Velikost náhledu</guisubmenu> v nabídce odrážky
        dialogu Písma.
      </para>
    </note>
    <note lang='fr'>
      <para>
        Vous pouvez changer la taille d'aperçu des polices en utilisant
        le sous-menu Taille de l'aperçu dans le menu d'onglet. 
      </para>
    </note>
    <note lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        您可以通过在对话框的页签菜单中使用“预览大小”子菜单改变字体预览的大小。
      </para>
    </note>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
