<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-gradient-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Gradients dialog</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Gradients dialog
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Gradients dialog is used to select a gradient -- a set of
    colors arranged in a linear scale -- for use with the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Blend tool</link> and numerous other
    operations.  It also gives you access to several functions for
    manipulating gradients.  You can select a gradient by clicking on
    it in the list:  it will then be shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  A few dozen nice
    gradients come pre-installed with GIMP.  You can create more using
    the Gradient Editor.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Gradients dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Create New Dock</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brushes, Patterns, and Gradients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        This gives you a dock containing three dialogs, with the
        Gradients dialog one of them.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox, by clicking on the current gradient in the
        Brush/Pattern/Gradient area.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Gradients dialog</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic, and most commonly used, operation with the
      dialog is simply to click on one of the gradients in the
      scrollable list, in order to make it GIMP's current gradient,
      which will then be used by any operation that involves a
      gradient.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      If you <emphasis>double-click</emphasis> on a gradient, you will
      be able to edit its name.  Note, however, that you are only
      allowed to change the names of gradients that you have created
      yourself, not the ones that come pre-installed with GIMP.  If
      you try to rename a pre-installed gradient, you will be able to
      edit the name, but as soon as you hit return or click somewhere
      else, the name will revert to its original value.  It is a
      general rule that you cannot alter the resources that GIMP
      pre-installs for you: brushes, patterns, gradients, etc; only
      ones that you create yourself.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The buttons at the bottom of the dialog allow you to operate on
      gradients in several ways:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="">Edit Gradient</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This activates the Gradient Editor, described below.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">New Gradient</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This creates a new gradient, initialized as a simple
            grayscale, and activates the Gradient Editor so that you
            can alter it.  Gradients that you create are automatically
            saved in the <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your
            personal GIMP directory, from which they are automatically
            loaded when GIMP starts.  (You can change this folder, or
            add new ones, using the Preferences dialog.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Duplicate Gradient</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This creates a copy of the currently selected gradient.
            You will be able to edit the copy even if you cannot edit
            the original.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Delete Gradient</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This removes all traces of the gradient, if you have
            permission to do so.  It asks for confirmation before
            doing anything.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Refresh Gradients</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            If you add gradients to your personal
            <filename>gradients</filename> folder by some means
            other than this dialog, this button
            causes the list to be reloaded, so that the new entries
            will be available.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <para lang='en'>
      The functions performed by these buttons can also be accessed
      from the dialog pop-up menu, activated by right-clicking
      anywhere in the gradient list.  The menu also gives you one
      additional function:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Save as POV-Ray...</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            This allows you to save the gradient in the format used by
            the <application>POV-Ray</application> 3D ray-tracing
            program. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <sect2 id='dialogs-gradient-editor' >
    <title lang="en">Gradient Editor</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Gradient Editor dialog
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang="en">
      The Gradient Editor allows you to edit the colors in a
      gradient.  It can only be used on gradients you have created
      yourself, not on the gradients that come pre-installed with
      GIMP.  This is a sophisticated tool that may take a bit of
      effort to understand.  The concept behind it is that a gradient
      can be decomposed into a series of adjoining
      <emphasis>segments</emphasis>, with each segment consisting of a
      smooth transition from the color on the left edge to the color
      on the right edge.  The Gradient Editor allows you to pack
      together any number of segments, with any colors you want for the
      left and right edges of each segment, and with several options for
      the shape of the transition from left to right. 
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>Layout</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Name</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            At the top of the dialog you see the name of the
            gradient.  You can edit this if you want to.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Gradient Display</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the name, you see the current result of your work.
            If "Instant update" is checked, the display is updated any
            time you take an action that changes the gradient.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Range Selection/Control Sliders</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the gradient display, you see a set of black and
            white triangles lined up in row.  A
            <emphasis>segment</emphasis> is the space between two
            consecutive <emphasis>black</emphasis> triangles.  Inside
            each segment is a white triangle, which is used to "warp"
            the colors in the range, in the same way that the middle
            slider in the Levels tool warps the colors there.  You can
            select a segment by clicking between the two black triangles
            that define it.  You can select a range of segments
            by shift-clicking on them.  The selected range always
            consists of a set of <emphasis>consecutive</emphasis>
            segments, so if you skip over any when shift-clicking, they
            will be included automatically.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Scroolbar</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the sliders is a scrollbar.  This comes into play if
            you zoom in using the buttons at the bottom.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Feedback Area</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the sliders is an area that initially is blank, but
            depending on your actions, helpful hints or feedback
            messages may appear here.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Buttons</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            At the bottom of the dialog appear five buttons:
          </para>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Save</title>
            Clicking this button causes the gradient, in its current
            state, to be saved in your personal
            <filename>gradients</filename> folder, so that it will
            automatically be loaded the next time you start GIMP.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Revert</title>
            Clicking this button undoes all of your editing.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Zoom Out</title>
            Clicking this button shrinks the gradient display
            horizontally. 
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Zoom In</title>
            Clicking this button expands the gradient display
            horizontally.  You can then use the scrollbar to pan the
            display left or right.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Zoom All</title>
            Clicking this button resizes the display horizontally so
            that it fits precisely into the window.
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Gradient Editor Menu</title>
      
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject lang="en">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-menu.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang='en'>
            The Gradient Editor menu
          </para>
        </caption>
      </informalfigure>

      <para lang='en'>
        You can access the Gradient Editor menu either by
        right-clicking on the gradient display, or by choosing the top
        item in the dialog's tab menu.  The menu allows you to set the
        left and right edge colors for each segment, and control the
        transition from one color to the other.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <title lang='en'>Options</title>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Left [Right] Endpoint's Color</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              These options allow you to choose a color for the
              respective endpoint using a Color Editor.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Load Left [Right] Color From</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-colorfrom.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  The "Load Color From" submenu
                </para>
              </caption>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>
              These options give you a number of alternative ways of
              assigning colors to the endpoints.  From the submenu you
              can choose (assuming we're dealing with the left
              endpoint): 
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Left Neighbor's Right Endpoint</title>
                  This choice will cause the color of the right
                  endpoint of the segment neighboring on the left to be
                  assigned to the left endpoint of the selected range.
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Right Endpoint</title>
                  This choice will cause the color of the right
                  endpoint of the selected range to be assigned to the
                  left endpoint.
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>FG/BG color</title>
                  These choice cause GIMP's current foreground or
                  background color, as shown in the Toolbox, to be
                  assigned to the endpoint.
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>RGBA slots</title>
                  At the bottom of the menu are 10 "memory slots".
                  You can assign colors to them using the "Save" menu
                  option described below.  If you choose one of the
                  slots, the color in it will be assigned to the
                  endpoint. 
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Save Left [Right] Color To</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              These options cause the color of the endpoint in
              question to be assigned to the "memory slot" selected
              from the submenu.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Blending Function for Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-blend.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  The Blending Function submenu
                </para>
              </caption>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>
              This option determines the course of the transition from
              one endpoint of the range to the other, by fitting the
              specified type of function to the endpoints and midpoint
              of the range.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Coloring Type for Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-color.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  The Coloring Type submenu
                </para>
              </caption>
            </informalfigure>
             <para>
              This option gives you additional control of the type of
              transition from one endpoint to the other:  as a line
              either in RGB space or in HSV space.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Flip Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option does a right-to-left flip of the selected
              range, flipping all colors and endpoint locations.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Replicate Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option splits the selected range into two parts,
              each of which is a perfect compressed copy of the
              original range.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Split Segments at Midpoints</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option splits each segment in the selected range in into
              two segments, splitting at the location of the white
              triangle. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Split Segments Uniformly</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option is similar to the previous one, but it
              splits each segment halfway between the endpoints,
              instead of at the white triangle.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Delete Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option deletes all segments in the selected range,
              replacing them with a single black triangle at the
              center, and enlarging the segments on both sides to fill
              the void.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Re-center Midpoints in Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option moves the white triangle for each segment in
              the selected range to a point halfway between the
              neighboring black triangles.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Re-distribute Handles in Selection</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option causes the black and white triangles in
              the selected range to be shifted so that the distances
              from one to the next are all equal.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Blend Endpoints' Colors</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option is only available if more than one segment
              is selected.  It causes the colors at interior endpoints
              in the range to be averaged, so that the transition
              from each segment to the next is smooth.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Blend Endpoints' Opacity</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option does the same thing as the previous option,
              but with opacity instead of color.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

      <caution lang='en'>
        There is no "undo" available within the Gradient Editor, so be
        careful! 
      </caution>

    </simplesect>


  </sect2>

</sect1>
