<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-gradient-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Gradients dialog</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">渐变对话框</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para>
	  The Gradients dialog
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para>
	  渐变对话框
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Gradients dialog is used to select a gradient -- a set of
    colors arranged in a linear scale -- for use with the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Blend tool</link> and numerous other
    operations.  It also gives you access to several functions for
    manipulating gradients.  You can select a gradient by clicking on
    it in the list:  it will then be shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  A few dozen nice
    gradients come pre-installed with GIMP.  You can create more using
    the <link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>Gradient Editor</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    渐变对话框用作选取一个渐变--一系列线性排列的颜色--在<link linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>渐变工具</link>和为数众多的其它操作中使用，它也提供许多处理渐变的功能。通过在列表中点击一个渐变来选中它：然后它会在工具箱的 画笔/图案/渐变 区域显示。GIMP 自带了许多好的渐变，不过您也可以用<link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>渐变编辑器</link>
来创建更多。
   </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    The Gradients dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    渐变对话框是一个可停靠对话框；请看<link linkend='gimp-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>。有多种方式来开启它：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
         在工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>渐变</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Create New Dock</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brushes, Patterns, and Gradients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        This gives you a dock containing three dialogs, with the
        Gradients dialog one of them.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
         在工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>创建新停靠栏</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>画笔，图案和渐变</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox, by clicking on the current gradient in the
        Brush/Pattern/Gradient area.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        在工具箱中，点击 画笔/图案/渐变 区域的当前画笔。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从一个图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>渐变</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        在任何可停靠对话框中的页签菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>添加页签</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>渐变</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">阵列/列表模式</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the gradients are laid out in a rectangular
      array.  They look quite dazzling when viewed this way, but it is
      not very easy to pick the one you want, because of visual
      interference from the neighboring ones.  In List mode, the
      more usable default, the gradients are lined up vertically, with
      each row showing the tool name, tool icon, and an "eye" icon if
      the tool is currently visible in the Toolbox.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在页签菜单中，您能在<guimenuitem>以阵列方式查看</guimenuitem>和<guimenuitem>以列表方式查看</guimenuitem>之间选择。在阵列模式中，渐变以矩形列阵排列，这样看上去比较耀眼，不过由于相互间的视觉干扰，并不容易选中您想要的那个渐变。在列表模式中，是更为可用的默认值，渐变垂直排列，每一行则显示渐变缩略图和它的名字。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Gradients dialog</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用渐变对话框</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic, and most commonly used, operation with the
      dialog is simply to click on one of the gradients in the
      scrollable list, in order to make it GIMP's current gradient,
      which will then be used by any operation that involves a
      gradient.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      对该对话框最基本，常见的使用是，简单地点击在列表中地一个渐变使它成为 GIMP 当前渐变，这样就可以应用在其后与渐变有关的操作中。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      If you <emphasis>double-click</emphasis> on a gradient, you will
      be able to edit its name.  Note, however, that you are only
      allowed to change the names of gradients that you have created
      yourself, not the ones that come pre-installed with GIMP.  If
      you try to rename a pre-installed gradient, you will be able to
      edit the name, but as soon as you hit return or click somewhere
      else, the name will revert to its original value.  It is a
      general rule that you cannot alter the resources that GIMP
      pre-installs for you: brushes, patterns, gradients, etc; only
      ones that you create yourself.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <emphasis>双击</emphasis>一个渐变可以编辑它的名字，不过这种方法只允许改变您自己创建的渐变的名字，而不是 GIMP 自带的渐变。您能编辑其名字，不过当您敲入回车或点击其它位置时，其名字会变回到原来的名字。不能更改 GIMP 自带的资源是一个基本原则：画笔，图案，渐变等；只能改变您自建的。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The buttons at the bottom of the dialog allow you to operate on
      gradients in several ways:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      对话框底部的按钮让您有多种方式操作渐变：
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Edit Gradient</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">编辑渐变</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This button activates the <link
            linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>Gradient
            Editor</link>. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            该按钮开启<link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>渐变编辑器</link>
          </para>
        </listitem> 
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-gradient-new' />
        <term lang="en">New Gradient</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">新建渐变</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This creates a new gradient, initialized as a simple
            grayscale, and activates the Gradient Editor so that you
            can alter it.  Gradients that you create are automatically
            saved in the <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your
            personal GIMP directory, from which they are automatically
            loaded when GIMP starts.  (You can change this folder, or
            add new ones, using the Preferences dialog.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
             它新建一个渐变，初始化为一个简单灰度，并打开渐变对话框让您能修改它。创建的渐变将自动保存在您的个人 GIMP 目录下的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹，GIMP 启动时就能自动加载。(使用首选项对话框能更改该文件夹或添加新的。)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-gradient-duplicate' />
        <term lang="en">Duplicate Gradient</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">复制渐变</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This creates a copy of the currently selected gradient.
            You will be able to edit the copy even if you cannot edit
            the original.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            它创建当前选取渐变的一个拷贝。如果无法编辑源渐变，就可以编辑该拷贝。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-gradient-delete' />
        <term lang="en">Delete Gradient</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">删除渐变</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            This removes all traces of the gradient, if you have
            permission to do so.  It asks for confirmation before
            doing anything.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            它从对话框和保存文件的文件夹中将渐变删除，当然您要有相应的权限。在执行任何动作之前，它会要您确认。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-gradient-refresh' />
        <term lang="en">Refresh Gradients</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">刷新渐变</term>
        <listitem lang="en" >
          <para>
            If you add gradients to your personal
            <filename>gradients</filename> folder by some means
            other than this dialog, this button
            causes the list to be reloaded, so that the new entries
            will be available.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            该按钮使列表被重新加载，这样您在个人 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹或任何渐变搜索路径添加的画笔，就会立即在对话框中可用。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <para lang='en'>
      The functions performed by these buttons can also be accessed
      from the dialog pop-up menu, activated by right-clicking
      anywhere in the gradient list.  The menu also gives you one
      additional function:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这些按钮所提供的功能也可以通过用右键点击渐变列表中任何地方所开启的弹出菜单中获得。该菜单还提供另外一个功能：
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-gradient-save-as-pov' />
        <term lang="en">Save as POV-Ray...</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">保存为 POV-Ray...</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            This allows you to save the gradient in the format used by
            the <application>POV-Ray</application> 3D ray-tracing
            program. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            它可以将渐变保存为能在 3D 光线追踪程序 <application>POV-Ray</application> 中使用的格式。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <sect2 id='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog' >
    <title lang="en">Gradient Editor</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">渐变编辑器</title>
    <anchor id='gimp-gradient-edit' />

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The Gradient Editor dialog
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para>
	    渐变编辑器对话框
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang="en">
      The Gradient Editor allows you to edit the colors in a
      gradient.  It can only be used on gradients you have created
      yourself, not on the gradients that come pre-installed with
      GIMP.  This is a sophisticated tool that may take a bit of
      effort to understand.  The concept behind it is that a gradient
      can be decomposed into a series of adjoining
      <emphasis>segments</emphasis>, with each segment consisting of a
      smooth transition from the color on the left edge to the color
      on the right edge.  The Gradient Editor allows you to pack
      together any number of segments, with any colors you want for the
      left and right edges of each segment, and with several options for
      the shape of the transition from left to right. 
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      渐变编辑器允许您编辑一个渐变中的颜色。它只能用在您自己创建的渐变上，对 GIMP 自带的无效。该工具非常复杂，需要一点时间来了解。它的基本概念就是一个渐变可以分解为一系列相邻的<emphasis>片段</emphasis>，每个片段由从左边界颜色到右边界颜色间的平滑过渡构成。而渐变编辑器让您组合任何数量的片段，对每个片段使用任何左边界和右边界颜色，以及设定许多有关从左到右的过渡形状的选项。
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>Layout</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">布局</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Name</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">名字</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            At the top of the dialog you see the name of the
            gradient.  You can edit this if you want to.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            对话框最上面可以看到是渐变的名字。如果您想，可以编辑它。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Gradient Display</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">渐变显示</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the name, you see the current result of your work.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            名字下面您看到的是您作品的当前结果。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Range Selection/Control Sliders</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">范围选择/控制滑动器</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the gradient display, you see a set of black and
            white triangles lined up in row.  A
            <emphasis>segment</emphasis> is the space between two
            consecutive <emphasis>black</emphasis> triangles.  Inside
            each segment is a white triangle, which is used to "warp"
            the colors in the segment, in the same way that the middle
            slider in the Levels tool warps the colors there.  You can
            select a segment by clicking between the two black triangles
            that define it.  You can select a range of segments
            by shift-clicking on them.  The selected range always
            consists of a set of <emphasis>consecutive</emphasis>
            segments, so if you skip over any when shift-clicking, they
            will be included automatically.
            If "Instant update" is checked, the display is updated
            immediately after any slider movement; if it is unchecked,
            updates only occur when you release the mouse button.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
             渐变显示下面是一系列排成一排的黑色和白色三角。而<emphasis>片段</emphasis>就是相邻的两个<emphasis>黑色</emphasis>三角之间的空间。在每个片段中都有一个白色三角，它用来在片段中“偏离”颜色，和色阶工具的中间滑动器偏离颜色的方式一样。点击两个黑色三角间来选取那个片段，按住 Shift 点击则选中一定范围的片段。选中范围总是右一系列<emphasis>相邻</emphasis>的片段组成，所以如果用 Shift 并点击时跳过了一些，它们会自动包括进去。如果勾选了“立即更新”，显示会在任何滑动器移动后立即显示出来；当没有勾选时，就只会在放开鼠标键是才各更新。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Scrollbar</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">滚动条</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the sliders is a scrollbar.  This only comes into play if
            you zoom in using the buttons at the bottom.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            滑动器下面是滚动条。它只有在使用底部的缩放按钮后才起作用。
          </para>
        </listitem> 
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Feedback Area</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">反馈区域</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            Below the sliders is an area that initially is blank, but
            depending on your actions, helpful hints or feedback
            messages may appear here.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            滚动条下面是初始化为黑色的一个区域，但它根据您的操作，可能显示帮助提示或反馈信息。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Buttons</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">按键</term>

        <listitem>

          <para lang='en'>
            At the bottom of the dialog appear five buttons:
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            对话框底部有五个按钮：
          </para>

          <formalpara lang='en'>
            <title>Save</title>
            Clicking this button causes the gradient, in its current
            state, to be saved in your personal
            <filename>gradients</filename> folder, so that it will
            automatically be loaded the next time you start GIMP.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>保存</title>
            点击该按钮将保存当前状态的渐变到您的个人 <filename>gradients</filename> 目录中，这样下次启动 GIMP 时就会自动被加载。
          </formalpara>

          <formalpara lang='en'>
            <title>Revert</title>
            Clicking this button undoes all of your editing.
            (However, at the time this is being written, this
            function is not yet implemented.)
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>恢复</title>
            点击该按键将撤消您的所有编辑。
          </formalpara>

          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-zoom-out' />
          <formalpara lang='en'>
            <title>Zoom Out</title>
            Clicking this button shrinks the gradient display
            horizontally. 
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>缩小</title>
            点击该按钮将水平减小渐变显示。
          </formalpara>

          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-zoom-in' />
          <formalpara lang='en'>
            <title>Zoom In</title>
            Clicking this button expands the gradient display
            horizontally.  You can then use the scrollbar to pan the
            display left or right.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>放大</title>
            点击该按钮将水平扩大渐变显示。然后可以用滚动条左右移动显示。
          </formalpara>

          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-zoom-all' />
          <formalpara lang='en'>
            <title>Zoom All</title>
            Clicking this button resizes the display horizontally so
            that it fits precisely into the window.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>完整镜头</title>
            点击该按钮将水平缩放显示使它与窗口大小刚刚合适。
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Gradient Editor Menu</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">渐变编辑器菜单</title>
      
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject lang="en">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-menu.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
          </imageobject>

	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Gradient Editor menu
	    </para>
	  </caption>
        </mediaobject>

        <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-menu.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
          </imageobject>

	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      渐变编辑器菜单
	    </para>
	  </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

      <para lang='en'>
        You can access the Gradient Editor menu either by
        right-clicking on the gradient display, or by choosing the top
        item in the dialog's tab menu.  The menu allows you to set the
        left and right edge colors for each segment, and control the
        transition from one color to the other.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        可以通过在右键单击渐变显示或在对话框页签菜单中选择最上面项来得到渐变编辑器菜单。用该菜单可以设置每个片段的左右边界的颜色，和控制从一种颜色到另一种颜色的过渡。
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <title lang='en'>Options</title>
        <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-left-color' />
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-right-color' />
          <term lang='en'>Left [Right] Endpoint's Color</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">左[右]端点颜色</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              These options allow you to choose a color for the
              respective endpoint using a Color Editor.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项可以让您用一颜色编辑器给相应端点选择一种颜色。
            </para>
          </listitem>
              
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-left-load' />
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-right-load' />
          <term lang='en'>Load Left [Right] Color From</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">左[右]端颜色加载自</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-colorfrom.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>

		<caption>
		  <para>
		    The "Load Color From" submenu
		  </para>
		</caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>

            <para>
              These options give you a number of alternative ways of
              assigning colors to the endpoints.  From the submenu you
              can choose (assuming we're dealing with the left
              endpoint): 
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Left Neighbor's Right Endpoint</title>
                  This choice will cause the color of the right
                  endpoint of the segment neighboring on the left to be
                  assigned to the left endpoint of the selected range.
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Right Endpoint</title>
                  This choice will cause the color of the right
                  endpoint of the selected range to be assigned to the
                  left endpoint.
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>FG/BG color</title>
                  These choice cause GIMP's current foreground or
                  background color, as shown in the Toolbox, to be
                  assigned to the endpoint.
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>RGBA slots</title>
                  At the bottom of the menu are 10 "memory slots".
                  You can assign colors to them using the "Save" menu
                  option described below.  If you choose one of the
                  slots, the color in it will be assigned to the
                  endpoint. 
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-colorfrom.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>

		<caption>
		  <para>
		    “加载颜色自” 子菜单
		  </para>
		</caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>
              这些选项提供您给端点指定颜色的若干不同的方法。在子菜单中您可以选择(假设对左端点)：
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>左邻的右端点</title>
                  该选项将选中范围左边相邻片段的右端点的颜色赋予选中范围的左端点。
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>右端点</title>
                  该选项将选中范围右端点的颜色赋予左端点。
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>前景/背景色</title>
                  该选项将显示在工具箱中的前景和后景色赋予左端点。
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>RGBA 槽</title>
                  在菜单底部是 10 个“记忆槽”。用下面要介绍的“保存”菜单能给它们赋予颜色，当选择其中一个槽时，其中的颜色将赋予端点。
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-left-save' />
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-right-save' />
          <term lang='en'>Save Left [Right] Color To</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">保存左[右]端颜色到</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              These options cause the color of the endpoint in
              question to be assigned to the "memory slot" selected
              from the submenu.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项使上面提到的端点的颜色赋予到从子菜单选中的“记忆槽”中。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-blending' />
          <term lang='en'>Blending Function for Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">选区的混合函数</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-blend.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>

		<caption>
		  <para>
		    The Blending Function submenu
		  </para>
		</caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>
              This option determines the course of the transition from
              one endpoint of the range to the other, by fitting the
              specified type of function to the endpoints and midpoint
              of the range.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-blend.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>

		<caption>
		  <para>
		    混合函数子菜单
		  </para>
		</caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>
              该选项通过对一个范围的端点和中点使用特定类型函数，决定从一个端点到另一个端点过渡的方向。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-coloring' />
          <term lang='en'>Coloring Type for Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">选区的着色类型</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-color.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>

		<caption>
		  <para>
		    The Coloring Type submenu
		  </para>
		</caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
             <para>
              This option gives you additional control of the type of
              transition from one endpoint to the other:  as a line
              either in RGB space or in HSV space.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN" >
            <informalfigure>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-gradient-editor-color.png'
                    format="PNG"/> 
                </imageobject>

		<caption>
		  <para>
		    着色类型子菜单
		  </para>
		</caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
             <para>
              该选项对从一个端点到另一个端点过渡做另外的控制：其中的线条是使用 RGB 空间还是 HSV 空间。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-flip' />
          <term lang='en'>Flip Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">翻转选区</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option does a right-to-left flip of the selected
              range, flipping all colors and endpoint locations.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项对选中范围做一个从右到左的翻转，其中所有颜色和端点位置都背翻转。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-replicate' />
          <term lang='en'>Replicate Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">复制选区</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option splits the selected range into two parts,
              each of which is a perfect compressed copy of the
              original range.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项将选中范围分成两部分，每部分都是一个背压缩的源范围的完整拷贝。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-split-midpoint' />
          <term lang='en'>Split Segments at Midpoints</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">从中点处分割段</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option splits each segment in the selected range in into
              two segments, splitting at the location of the white
              triangle. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项将选中范围中的每个片段从白色三角处分成两个片段。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-split-uniform' />
          <term lang='en'>Split Segments Uniformly</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">等分切割段</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option is similar to the previous one, but it
              splits each segment halfway between the endpoints,
              instead of at the white triangle.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项和前一个相同，只不过不是在白色三角处，而是在左右端点的中点分割。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-delete' />
          <term lang='en'>Delete Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">删除选中区域</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option deletes all segments in the selected range,
              replacing them with a single black triangle at the
              center, and enlarging the segments on both sides to fill
              the void.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项删除选中范围中所有片段，中间只有一个白色三角，并拉伸片段的两端使其适合大小。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-recenter' />
          <term lang='en'>Re-center Midpoints in Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">重置选中区域的中点</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option moves the white triangle for each segment in
              the selected range to a point halfway between the
              neighboring black triangles.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项移动选中范围中每个片段的白色三角到相邻的黑色三角间的中点。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-redistribute' />
          <term lang='en'>Re-distribute Handles in Selection</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">重置选中区域的支点</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option causes the black and white triangles in
              the selected range to be shifted so that the distances
              from one to the next are all equal.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
               该选项移动选中范围中白色和黑色三角的位置，使一个三角到下一个的距离的距离都相同。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-blend-color' />
          <term lang='en'>Blend Endpoints' Colors</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">混合端点的颜色</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option is only available if more than one segment
              is selected.  It causes the colors at interior endpoints
              in the range to be averaged, so that the transition
              from each segment to the next is smooth.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选择只有当选中多个片段时才能使用。它平均化选中范围内部端点的颜色，这样从一个片段到下一个的过渡就比较平滑。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <anchor id='gimp-gradient-editor-blend-opacity' />
          <term lang='en'>Blend Endpoints' Opacity</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">混合端点的不透明度</term>
          <listitem lang="en" >
            <para>
              This option does the same thing as the previous option,
              but with opacity instead of color.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem lang="zh_CN">
            <para>
              该选项和上面选项基本一样，只是对不透明度而不是颜色。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

      <caution lang='en'>
        There is no "undo" available within the Gradient Editor, so be
        careful! 
      </caution>
      <caution lang="zh_CN">
        对渐变编辑器而言，不能“撤消”，所以请小心！
      </caution>

    </simplesect>


  </sect2>

</sect1>
