<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-12-15 j.h: updated en;fr to v2.6
  2008-02-22 j.h: added description for the four first gradients en;fr.
  2008-01-18 ude: added v2.4. gradient menu options and screenshot
  2007-09-30 j.h : revised en ;fr for v2.4. no change
  2006-08-30 ciampix: added italian translation
  2006-04-29 lexa: made file docbook compliant
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-gradient-dialog">
  <!--<sect2info role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-12-15</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>-->
  <title>
    <phrase>Gradients Dialog</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Gradient Dialog</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Gradient</primary>
    <secondary>Dialog</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase>
        The screenshot illustrates the Gradients dialog
      </phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/gradient-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Gradients dialog offers a gradient palette which is used to select
    a gradient -- a set of colors arranged in a linear scale -- for use
    with the <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">Blend tool</link> and numerous
    other operations. It also gives you access to several functions for
    manipulating gradients.  You can select a gradient by clicking on it in
    the list: it will then be shown in the Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of
    the Toolbox.  A few dozen nice gradients come pre-installed with GIMP.
    You can create more using the <link linkend="gimp-gradient-editor-dialog">Gradient Editor</link>.  General
    information about gradients and how they are used in GIMP can be found
    in the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-gradients">Gradients</link>
    section.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The first four gradients are particular: they reproduce the gradient
      between Foreground and background colors of toolbox in different ways.
    </para>
    <listitem>
      <para><guilabel>FG to BG (RGB)</guilabel>: default gradient, between the
        Foreground and the background colors of the Toolbox, in the RGB mode.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><guilabel>FG to BG (HSV clock-wise/counter-clockwise Hue)</guilabel>:
        all hues in the color circle between the Foreground and the
        background color, clockwise or counter-clockwise.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><guilabel>FG to Transparent</guilabel>: only uses one color (the
        Foreground color) from complete opacity to complete transparency.
        This gradient is very useful when you work with softly blended
        collages or fog effects.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <sect3 id="gimp-gradient-dialog-activate">
    <title>
      <phrase>Activate Dialog</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      The Gradients dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
      manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the Toolbox, by clicking on the current gradient in the
          Brush/Pattern/Gradient area.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From an image menu:
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Windows</guimenu><guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Gradients</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu><guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>radients</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the image by using the <keycap>Ctrl+G</keycap> shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="gimp-gradient-dialog-using">
    <title>
      <phrase>Using the Gradients dialog</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      The most basic, and most commonly used, operation with the dialog is
      simply to click on one of the gradients in the scrollable list, in order
      to make it GIMP's current gradient, which will then be used by any
      operation that involves a gradient.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you <emphasis>double-click</emphasis>
      on a gradient, you open the Gradient Editor where you will be able to
      edit its name. Note, however, that you are only allowed to change the
      names of gradients that you have created yourself, not the ones that
      come pre-installed with GIMP. If you try to rename a pre-installed
      gradient, you will be able to edit the name, but as soon as you hit
      return or click somewhere else, the name will revert to its original
      value. It is a general rule that you cannot alter the resources that
      GIMP pre-installs for you: brushes, patterns, gradients, etc; only ones
      that you create yourself.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Grid/List modes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
            Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
            In Grid mode, the gradients are laid out in a rectangular
            array.  They look quite dazzling when viewed this way, but it is
            not very easy to pick the one you want, because of visual
            interference from the neighboring ones.  In List mode, the
            more usable default, the gradients are lined up vertically, with
            each row showing its name.
          </para>
          <para>
            In the Tab menu, the option <guilabel>Preview Size</guilabel>
            allows you to adapt the size of gradient previews to your
            liking.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The buttons at the bottom of the dialog allow you to operate on
      gradients in several ways:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edit Gradient</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This button activates the
            <link linkend="gimp-gradient-editor-dialog">Gradient Editor</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>New Gradient</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-gradient-new"/>
          <para>
            This creates a new gradient, initialized as a simple grayscale,
            and activates the Gradient Editor so that you can alter it.
            Gradients that you create are automatically saved in the
            <filename>gradients</filename>
            folder of your personal GIMP directory, from which they are
            automatically loaded when GIMP starts. (You can change this
            folder, or add new ones, using the Preferences dialog.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Duplicate Gradient</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-gradient-duplicate"/>
          <para>
            This creates a copy of the currently selected gradient. You will
            be able to edit the copy even if you cannot edit the original.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Delete Gradient</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-gradient-delete"/>
          <para>
            This removes all traces of the gradient, if you have permission to
            do so. It asks for confirmation before doing anything.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Refresh Gradients</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-gradient-refresh"/>
          <para>
            If you add gradients to your personal
            <filename>gradients</filename>
            folder by some means other than this dialog, this button causes
            the list to be reloaded, so that the new entries will be
            available.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The functions performed by these buttons can also be accessed from the
      dialog pop-up menu, activated by right-clicking anywhere in the
      gradient list, or via <guisubmenu>Gradient Menu</guisubmenu> in the
      Tab menu:
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>The Gradients Menu</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/gradient-menu.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The gradient menu also gives you some additional functions:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-gradient-save-as-pov">
        <term>Save as POV-Ray...</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This allows you to save the gradient in the format used by
            the <application>POV-Ray</application> 3D ray-tracing
            program.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-gradient-copy-location">
        <term>
          <phrase>Copy Gradient Location</phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command allows you to copy the gradient file location to
            the clipboard. You can then use it in a text editor.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="script-fu-gradient-example">
        <term>
          <phrase>Custom Gradient...</phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command creates a sample image filled with the selected
            gradient. You can select width and height of the image as well as
            the gradient direction in the dialog window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
  <xi:include href="gradient-editor-dialog.xml"/>
</sect2>
