<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-histogram-dialog' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Histogram dialog</title>
  <title lang="fr">Dialogue Histogramme</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">柱状图对话框</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Dialogue</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Histogram</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Histogramme</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">柱状图</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang='en'>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-basic.png'
        format="PNG"/>  
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The Histogram dialog
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang='fr'>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-histogram-basic.png'
        format="PNG"/>  
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  Le dialogue Histogramme
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-basic.png'
        format="PNG"/>  
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  柱状图对话框
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  
  <para lang="en">
    The Histogram dialog shows you information about the statistical
    distribution of color values in the image that is currently
    active.  This information is often useful when you are trying to
    <emphasis>color balance</emphasis> an image.  However, the
    Histogram dialog is purely informational:  nothing you do with it
    will cause any change to the image.  If you want to perform a
    histogram-based color correction, use the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-levels'>Levels</link> tool.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La fenêtre de dialogue Histogramme vous fournit des renseignements 
    sur la distribution statistique des valeurs de couleurs dans 
    l'image active. Cette information est souvent utile quand vous 
    cherchez à équilibrer les couleurs d'une image. Mais elle ne fait 
    que vous renseigner, sans vous donner la possibilité de modifier 
    les couleurs. Pour cela, utilisez l'outil <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-levels'>Niveaux</link>
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    柱状图对话框显示当前活动图像的色彩值的统计分布信息，该信息在当您要对一个图像进行<emphasis>色彩平衡</emphasis>时通常很有用。不过，柱状图对话框只是提供信息的：使用它不能对图像有任何改变。如果要对一个图像进行基于柱状图的色彩修正，请使用<link linkend='gimp-tool-levels'>色阶</link>工具。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    This is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in two ways:
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Le Dialogue Histogramme est un dialogue attachable; voyez la 
    section <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogues et attachements</link>
    pour plus d'informations. Il peut être appelé de différentes 
    façons:
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    这是一个可停靠对话框；请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>。有两种方法开启它：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>   
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Histogram</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>

      <para lang='fr'>   
        A partir du menu de la Boîte à outils:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogues</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Histogramme</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        从工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>柱状图</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>   
        From the image menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Histogram</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>

      <para lang='fr'>   
        A partir du menu de l'image:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Dialogues</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Histogramme</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">   
        从图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>柱状图</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>About Histograms</title>
    <title lang='fr'>A propos d'histogrammes</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">关于柱状图</title>
    
    <para lang='en'>
      In GIMP, each layer of an image can be decomposed into one or
      more color channels:  for an RGB image, into R, G, and B
      channels; for a grayscale image, into a single Value channel.
      Layers that support transparency have an additional channel, the
      alpha channel.  Each channel supports a range of intensity
      levels from 0 to 255 (integer valued).  Thus, a black pixel is
      encoded by 0 on all color channels; a white pixel by 255 on all
      color channels.  A transparent pixel is encoded by 0 on the
      alpha channel; an opaque pixel by 255.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Dans Gimp, chaque calque d'une image peut être décomposé en un 
      ou plusieurs canaux: pour une image RVB, il s'agit des canaux 
      Rouge, Vert et Bleu; pour une image en nuances de gris, il n'y a 
      qu'un seul canal de Valeur. Les calques utilisant la 
      transparence disposent d'un canal supplémentaire: le canal Alpha.
      Chaque canal possède un intervalle de niveaux d'intensité de 0 à 
      255 (valeurs entières). Ainsi, un pixel noir est codé 0 dans 
      tous les canaux de couleur; un pixel blanc est codé 255 dans tous 
      les canaux de couleur. Un pixel transparent est codé 0 dans le 
      canal Alpha et un pixel opaque 255.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      GIMP 中，一个图像的每个图层都可以分解成一个或多个颜色通道：对 RGB 图像而言，是红色，绿色和蓝色通道；对于灰度图像而言，则是单独的一个亮度通道。支持透明的图层会有一个附加通道-- alpha 通道。每个通道其强度值取值为 0 到 255 (整数值)，因此，一个黑色像素在所有颜色通道其值为 0，而一个白色像素其值为 255。一个透明像素在 alpha 通道取值为 0，反之，一个不透明像素为 255。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      For RGB images, it is convenient to define a Value "pseudochannel".
      This is not a real color channel:  it does not reflect
      any information stored directly in the image.  Instead, the
      Value at a pixel is given by the equation 
      <code>
        V = (R + G + B)/3
      </code>,
      rounded to the nearest integer.  Essentially, the Value is what
      you would get at that pixel if you converted the image to
      Grayscale mode.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour les images RVB, il est pratique de définir une Valeur 
      «pseudocanal». Ce n'est pas un vrai canal: il ne reflète aucune 
      information de l'image. La Valeur d'un pixel est donnée par la 
      formule  
      <code>
        V = (R + V + B)/3
      </code>,
      arrondie à l'entier le plus proche. En gros, la Valeur est celle 
      que vous donneriez à ce pixel si l'image était convertie en 
      niveaux de gris.

    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      对于 RGB 图像，为方便起见，我们定义了“亮度”这个“伪通道”，它不是一个真正的颜色通道：并不反映直接保存在图像上的任何信息，相反，一个像素的亮度可以表示成
      <code>
        亮度 = (红 + 绿 + 蓝)/3
      </code>，
      并四舍五入为整数。一般来说，在某点像素的“亮度”就是当把图像转换为灰度模式时那点的亮度值。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      For more information on channels, please consult the <link
      linkend='gimp-concepts-images'>Working with Images</link> section.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour de plus amples renseignements sur les canaux, voyez <link
      linkend='gimp-concepts-images'>Travailler sur les images</link>
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      关于通道的更多信息，请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-images'>了解图像</link>这章。
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>Using the Histogram dialog</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Utilisation du dialogue Histogramme</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">使用柱状图对话框</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Channel</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Canal</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">通道</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-menu.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>

	      <caption>
		<para>
		  Channel options for an RGB layer with alpha channel.
		</para>
	      </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            This allows you to select which channel to use.  The
            possibilities depend on the layer type of the active
            layer.  Here are the entries you might see, and what they
            mean: 
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Value</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  For RGB and Grayscale images, this shows the
                  distribution of brightness values 
                  across the layer.  For a grayscale image, these are
                  read directly from the image data.  For an RGB
                  image, they are taken from the Value pseudochannel.  
                </para>
                <para>
                  For an indexed image, the "Value" channel actually
                  shows the distribution of frequencies for each
                  colormap index:  thus, it is a "pseudocolor"
                  histogram rather than a true color histogram.  
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Red, Green, Blue</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  These only appear for layers from RGB images.  They
                  show the distribution of intensity levels for the
                  Red, Green, or Blue channels respectively.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alpha</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This shows the distribution of opacity levels.  If
                  the layer is completely opaque or completely
                  transparent, the histogram will consist of a single
                  bar on the left or right edge.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGB</term>
              <listitem>
                <informalfigure>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata
                        fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-rgb.png'
                        format="PNG"/>  
		    </imageobject>

		    <caption>
		      <para>
			Combined histograms of R, G, and B channels.
		      </para>
		    </caption>
		  </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>

                <para>
                  This entry, only available for RGB layers, shows the
                  R, G, and B histograms superimposed, so that you can
                  see all of the color distribution information in a
                  single view.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
           </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang='fr'>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-histogram-menu.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Options des canaux pour un calque RVB avec canal Alpha.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            Vous permet de choisir le canal à utiliser. Les 
            possibilités dépendent du type du calque actif. Voici 
            les entrées que vous verrez et ce qu'elles signifient:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Valeur</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Pour les images RVB et en niveaux de gris, la Valeur 
                  indique la distribution des luminosités dans le 
                  calque. Pour les images en niveaux de gris, elle est 
                  tirée directement des données de l'image. Pour les 
                  images RVB, elle est tirée du pseudocanal Valeur.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Pour les images indexées, le canal «Valeur» donne en 
                  fait la distribution des fréquences de chaque index 
                  de la carte des couleurs: on a donc un 
                  histogramme en «pseudocouleurs» plutôt qu'un 
                  véritable histogramme des couleurs.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Rouge, Vert, Bleu</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Ces mentions n'apparaissent que pour les calques des 
                  images RVB. Elles donnent la distribution des 
                  niveaux d'intensité pour chacun des canaux Rouge, 
                  Vert et Bleu.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alpha</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Donne la distribution des niveaux d'opacité. Si le 
                  calque est complètement opaque ou complètement 
                  transparent, l'histogramme consistera en une simple 
                  barre verticale à gauche ou à droite.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RVB</term>
              <listitem>
                <informalfigure>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata
                        fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-histogram-rgb.png'
                        format="PNG"/>  
            		    </imageobject>

            		    <caption>
            		      <para>
                        Histogrammes combinés des canaux R, V, B.
            		      </para>
            		    </caption>
            		  </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>

                <para>
                  Cette entrée, disponible seulement pour les calques 
                  RVB, donne les histogrammes R, V, B superposés, de 
                  telle sorte que vous voyez d'un seul coup d'œil 
                  l'ensemble de la distribution des couleurs.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
           </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-menu.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>

	      <caption>
		<para>
		  一个带 Alpha 通道的图层的通道选项。
		</para>
	      </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            通过它可以选择将使用的通道，其可选范围有当前图层的图层类型决定。下面是您可能遇到的选择及其所表示的意思：
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>亮度</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  对于 RGB 和 灰度图像，它表示图层上不同明亮度的分布情况。如果是个灰度图像，将直接从图像数据中读取，而如果是个 RGB 图像，就从“亮度”这个伪通道中获取。
                </para>
                <para>
                  对于索引图像，其“亮度”通道实际上是表示每个颜色表索引的频率分布情况：因此，它是一个“伪色彩”柱状图。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>红色, 绿色, 蓝色</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  它们只在 RGB 图像中的图层出现，分别显示红色，绿色和蓝色通道不同强度的分布。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alpha</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  它表示不透明程度的分布情况。假如图层是完全不透明或透明，其将在柱状图上显示为一个在左边界或右边界处的竖条。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGB</term>
              <listitem>
                <informalfigure>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata
                        fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-rgb.png'
                        format="PNG"/>  
		    </imageobject>

                    <caption>
		      <para>
			将红色，绿色和蓝色通道结合。
		      </para>
		    </caption>
		  </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>

                <para>
                  它只出现在 RGB 图层中，它将红色，绿色和蓝色柱状图重叠在一起，这样可以在同时看到所有的颜色分布情况。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
           </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Linear/Logarithmic buttons</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Les boutons Linéaire/Logarithmique</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">线性/对数按钮</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-log.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>

	      <caption>
		<para lang='en'>
		  The histogram shown at the top, changed to logarithmic
		  mode. 
		</para>
	      </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            These buttons determine whether the histogram will be
            displayed using a linear or logarithmic Y axis.  For
            images taken from photographs, the linear mode is most
            commonly useful.  For images that contain substantial
            areas of constant color, though, a linear histogram will
            often be dominated by a single bar, and a logarthmic
            histogram will often be more useful.  
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang='fr'>
          <para>
            Ces boutons déterminent si l'histogramme sera affiché avec 
            un axe y linéaire ou logarithmique. En ce qui concerne les 
            photographies, le mode linéaire est le plus utile. Pour 
            les images qui possèdent de larges aplats de couleur 
            uniforme , l'histogramme linéaire rique de se réduire à 
            quelques barres verticales, et le mode logarithmique sera 
            plus approprié.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-log.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>
	      <caption>
		<para>
		  上面的柱状图用对数模式显示。
		</para>
	      </caption>

            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            这些按钮决定柱状图是用一个线性的还是一个对数的 Y 轴显示。对于基于照片的图像，线性模式更有用，而对于那些包含大量连续颜色区域的图像，线性柱状图常常都是些单个的竖条，这时对数柱状图就更为有用。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Range Setting</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Fixer un intervalle</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">强度范围</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-range.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>

      	      <caption>
            		<para>
                  Dialog aspect after range fixing.
            		</para>
      	      </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            You can restrict the analysis, for the statistics shown at
            the bottom of the dialog, to a limited range of values if
            you wish.  You can set the range in one of three ways:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Click and drag the pointer across the histogram
                display area, from the lowest level to the highest
                level of the range you want.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Click and drag the black or white triangles on the
                slider below the histogram.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Use the spinbutton entries below the slider (left
                entry: bottom of range; right entry: top of range).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang='fr'>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-histogram-range.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>

      	      <caption>
            		<para>
                  Aspect du dialogue après avoir fixé un intervalle.
            		</para>
      	      </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            Vous pouvez réduire l'analyse à un intervalle limité de 
            valeurs, et ce, de trois façons:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cliquer-glisser le pointeur sur l'aire d'affichage de 
                l'histogramme, du niveau le plus bas au niveau le 
                plus haut souhaités. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cliquer-glisser les triangles noir ou blanc du 
                curseur situé sous l'histogramme.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Utiliser les boutons molette sous le curseur (entrée 
                gauche pour le niveau bas, entrée droite pour le 
                niveau haut).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-range.png'
                  format="PNG"/>  
              </imageobject>

	      <caption>
		<para>
		  在设定一个范围后的显示。
		</para>
	      </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para>
            通过它您可以缩小分析范围，对话框底部是统计数字。有三种方法来设定范围：
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                在柱状图显示区域您所要范围的左边界处点击左键，并拖动到所要范围的右边界处。
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                点击柱状图下面滑条上的黑色或白色三角并拖动它们。
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                用滑条下的上下箭头(左边的：范围的左边界；右边的：范围的右边界)。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Statistics</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Statistiques</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">统计数字</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            At the bottom of the dialog are shown some basic
            statistics describing the distribution of channel values,
            restricted to the selected range.  These are the mean,
            standard deviation, and median of the selected histogram
            portion; the number of pixels in the image; the number
            whose values fall within the selected range; and the
            percentage whose values fall within the selected range.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang='fr'>
          <para>
            En bas de la fenêtre, on trouve quelques indications 
            statistiques sur la distribution des valeurs des canaux 
            limitées à l'intervalle choisi. Ce sont la moyenne, la 
            déviation standard et la médiane de la portion 
            d'histogramme sélectionnée; le nombre de valeurs à 
            l'intérieur de l'intervalle; et le pourcentage de valeurs 
            situé dans l'intervalle.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            对话框下面显示的是在选定范围内通道值分布情况的一些基本统计数字。其中包括选中柱状图范围的平均值，标准偏差和中值，以及选中范围在整个柱状图中所占的百分比。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
    
   </variablelist>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
