<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-12-13 j.h:updated en;fr to v2.6
  2007-12-04 ude: updated 'de'
  2007-10-05 KoSt: updated 'no'
  2007-09-07 j.h: detailed statistics, added Layer name
  2006-03-11 lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant
  2005-11-29 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-histogram-dialog">
  <sect2info>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-12-13</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  <title>
    <phrase>Histogram dialog</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Histogram</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Histogram</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase>The Histogram dialog</phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-basic.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Histogram dialog shows you information about the statistical
    distribution of color values in the active layer or selection. This
    information is often useful when you are trying to
    <emphasis>color balance</emphasis>
    an image. However, the Histogram dialog is purely informational: nothing
    you do with it will cause any change to the image. If you want to perform
    a histogram-based color correction, use the
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels</link> tool.
  </para>
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase>Dialog call</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      This is a dockable dialog; see the section on
      <link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">Dialogs and Docking</link>
      for help on manipulating it. It can be activated in two ways:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the image menu:
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Windows</guimenu><guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Histogram</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the image menu:
          <menuchoice><guimenu>Colors</guimenu><guisubmenu>Info</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Histogram</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase>About Histograms</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      In GIMP, each layer of an image can be decomposed into one or more color
      channels: for an RGB image, into R, G, and B channels; for a grayscale
      image, into a single Value channel. Layers that support transparency
      have an additional channel, the alpha channel. Each channel supports a
      range of intensity levels from 0 to 255 (integer valued). Thus, a black
      pixel is encoded by 0 on all color channels; a white pixel by 255 on all
      color channels. A transparent pixel is encoded by 0 on the alpha
      channel; an opaque pixel by 255.
    </para>
    <para>
      For RGB images, it is convenient to define a Value "pseudochannel". This
      is not a real color channel: it does not reflect any information stored
      directly in the image. Instead, the Value at a pixel is given by the
      equation <code>V = max(R,G,B)</code>.
      Essentially, the Value is what you would get at that pixel if you
      converted the image to Grayscale mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      For more information on channels, please consult the
      <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-image-types"/>.
    </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase>Using the Histogram dialog</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      The active layer name is shown at the top of the dialog.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Channel</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase>
                Channel options for an RGB layer with alpha channel.
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-menu.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This allows you to select which channel to use. The possibilities
            depend on the layer type of the active layer. Here are the entries
            you might see, and what they mean:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Value</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  For RGB and Grayscale images, this shows the distribution of
                  brightness values across the layer. For a grayscale image,
                  these are read directly from the image data. For an RGB
                  image, they are taken from the Value pseudochannel.
                </para>
                <para>
                  For an indexed image, the "Value" channel actually shows the
                  distribution of frequencies for each colormap index: thus,
                  it is a "pseudocolor" histogram rather than a true color
                  histogram.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Red, Green, Blue</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  These only appear for layers from RGB images. They show the
                  distribution of intensity levels for the Red, Green, or Blue
                  channels respectively.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alpha</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This shows the distribution of opacity levels. If the layer
                  is completely opaque or completely transparent, the
                  histogram will consist of a single bar on the left or right
                  edge.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>RGB</term>
              <listitem>
                <figure>
                  <title>
                    <phrase>
                      Combined histograms of R, G, and B channels.
                    </phrase>
                  </title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-rgb.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>
                  This entry, only available for RGB layers, shows the R, G,
                  and B histograms superimposed, so that you can see all of
                  the color distribution information in a single view.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Linear/Logarithmic buttons</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase>
                The histogram shown at the top, changed to logarithmic mode.
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-log.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            These buttons determine whether the histogram will be displayed
            using a linear or logarithmic Y axis. For images taken from
            photographs, the linear mode is most commonly useful. For images
            that contain substantial areas of constant color, though, a linear
            histogram will often be dominated by a single bar, and a
            logarithmic histogram will often be more useful.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Range Setting</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase>Dialog aspect after range fixing.</phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/dialogs-histogram-range.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            You can restrict the analysis, for the statistics shown at the
            bottom of the dialog, to a limited range of values if you wish.
            You can set the range in one of three ways:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Click and drag the pointer across the histogram display area,
                from the lowest level to the highest level of the range you
                want.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Click and drag the black or white triangles on the slider
                below the histogram.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Use the spinbutton entries below the slider (left entry:
                bottom of range; right entry: top of range).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Statistics</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            At the bottom of the dialog some basic statistics are shown
            describing the distribution of channel values, restricted to the
            selected range:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Mean</guilabel> : the mean value of the interval
                 in the selected channel.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Std Dev</guilabel> : Standard deviation. Gives an
                 idea about how homogeneous the distribution of values in the
                 interval is.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Median</guilabel> : For example, the value of the
                 fiftieth peak in a 100 peaks interval.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Pixels</guilabel> : The number of pixels in the
                 active layer or selection.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Count</guilabel> : The number of pixels in a peak
                 (when you click on the histogram) or in the interval.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Percentile</guilabel> : The ratio between the
                 number of pixels in the interval and the total number of
                 pixels in the active layer or selection.
               </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
