<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: 
  2006-03-12 lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant
  2005-11-29 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->    
<sect2 id="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-29</date>
        <authorinitials>scb</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-12</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Colormap dialog</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Dialog Mapa barev</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Der Dialog <quote>Farbtabelle</quote></phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Dialogue Palette des couleurs indexées</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Finestra mappa colori</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Цветовая карта</phrase> 
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">颜色表对话框</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialog</primary>
    <secondary>Colormap</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Dialog</primary>
    <secondary>Mapa barev</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Palette indexée</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestre</primary>
    <secondary>Mappa colori</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Диалог</primary>
    <secondary>Цветовая карта</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>颜色表</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Colormap</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Mapa barev</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Palette indexée</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Mappa colori</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Цветовая карта</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>颜色表</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">The Colormap dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Dialog Mapa barev</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Ansicht des Dialoges <quote>Farbtabelle</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Le dialogue Palette de couleurs indexées</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">La finestra mappa colori</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Диалог "Цветовая карта"</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">颜色表对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-indexed-palette.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-indexed-palette.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-indexed-palette.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/it/dialogs-indexed-palette.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/ru/dialogs-indexed-palette.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-indexed-palette.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Colormap (Indexed Palette is a better name) dialog allows you to 
    edit the colormap of an indexed image.  (If the mode of the active image 
    is RGB or Grayscale instead of Indexed, the dialog is empty and 
    unusable.)
    This is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in two ways:
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Dialog Mapa barev umožňuje upravovat paletu barev obrázku v režimu
    indexovaných barev. (Pokud je obrázek v režimu RGB nebo stupně šedi, je
    tento dialog nepoužitelný.) Tento dialog je dokovatelný; viz
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">Dokování dialogů</link>.
    Lze ho vyvolat několika způsoby:
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Der Dialog <quote>Farbtabelle</quote> ermöglicht es Ihnen die Farbtabellen
    von Bildern im Farbmodus <quote>indiziert</quote> zu bearbeiten. Falls
    sich das aktive Bild in einem anderen Farbmodus befindet, ist dieser
    Dialog deaktiviert und nutzlos. Der Dialog kann auf verschiedene Arten
    aufgerufen werden:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le dialogue Palette de couleurs indexées vous permet d'afficher et de
    modifier la palette des couleurs d'une image indexée (image que vous
    venez de transformer en image indexée ou que vous avez enregistrée
    dans un format acceptant le mode indexé). Si le mode
    d'image n'est pas indexé (RVB simple ou Niveaux de gris), cette fenêtre
    de dialogue est vide et inutilisable. C'est un dialogue attachable: voir
    la section <link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">Dialogues, fenêtres et
    onglets</link>. On y accède de deux façons:
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    La finestra mappa colori permette di modificare la mappa dei colori di
    un'immagine indicizzata. (Se la modalità dell'immagine attiva è RGB o
    scala di grigi questa finestra è vuota ed inutilizzabile.) Questa è una
    finestra agganciabile: vedi la sezione sulle
    <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/ -->
    finestre agganciabili<!-- /link -->
    per aiuto su come manovrarle. Essa può essere attivata in due modi:
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Цветовая карта предоставляет возможность редактировать набор цветов 
    индексированного изображения. (Если изображение в режиме RGB или 
    "градации серого", цветовая карта ничего не отображает.) Этот диалог 
    можно прикрепить на панель. Более подробно об этом написано в разделе 
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">Диалоги и закладки</link>. 
    Цветовую карту можно открыть двумя способами: 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    通过索引对话框可以编辑索引图像的颜色表。(当活动图像模式为 RGB 或灰度时，该对话框是空的并且不可用。)它是一个可停靠的对话框；请看<link linkend="gimp-concepts-docks">对话框和停靠栏</link>。有两种方法开启它：
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Dialog call</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Vyvolání dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Dialogaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Lancement du dialogue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Visualizzazione della finestra</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Вызов диалога</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">   
          From the Toolbox menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Colormap</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">   
          Z nabídky Panelu nástrojů:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dialogy</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mapa barev</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">   
          Im Menü des Werkzeugfensters über das Kommando:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>D</accel>ialoge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Farb<accel>t</accel>abelle</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">   
          A partir du menu de la Boîte à outils:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dialogues</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Palette de couleurs</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="it">   
          Dal menu della barra degli strumenti:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Finestre</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mappa colori</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">   
          Из меню панели инструментов:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Файл</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Диалоги</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Цветовая карта</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">   
          从工具箱菜单中：
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>颜色表</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
  
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">   
          From the image menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Colormap</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Z nabídky obrázku:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Dialogy</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mapa barev</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">   
          Im Menü des Bildfensters über das Kommando:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>D</accel>ialoge</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Farb<accel>t</accel>abelle</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">   
          A partir du menu de l'image:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Dialogues</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Palette de couleurs</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="it">   
          Dal menu immagine:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Finestre</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Mappa colori</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">   
          Из меню изображения:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Диалоги</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Цветовая карта</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">   
          从图像菜单中：
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>颜色表</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Colormaps and Indexed Images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Mapy barev a indexované obrázky</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Farbtabellen und Bilder im Modus <quote>indiziert</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Palette de couleurs et images indexées</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">La mappa colori e le immagini indicizzate</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Цветовая карта и индексированные изображения</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">颜色表和索引图像</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      In an Indexed image, colors are assigned to pixels by an indirect
      method, using a lookup table called a <emphasis>colormap</emphasis>.
      In GIMP, the maximum number of entries in a colormap is 256. For a
      maximum-sized colormap, each index from 0 to 255 is assigned an
      arbitrary RGB color. There are no rules restricting the colors that can
      be assigned to an index or the order they appear in: any index can be
      assigned any color.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      V indexovaném obrázku jsou barvy jednotlivým pixelům přiřazovány
      nepřímo, pomocí převodní tabulky zvané <emphasis>mapa barev</emphasis>.
      V Gimpu může mít barevná mapa maximálně 256 barev. Maximálně využitá
      barevná mapa přiřazuje všem indexům v rozsahu 0-255 nějakou, libovolnou,
      barvu. Neexistuje žádné pravidlo, které by použité barvy nebo jejich
      pořadí nějak omezovalo; každý index může mít přiřazenu libovolnou barvu.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn sich ein Bild im Farbmodus <quote>indiziert</quote> befindet,
      wird die Farbe den Pixeln indirekt zugewiesen. Dies bedeutet, dass die
      Pixel statt einer Farbe, einen Eintrag in einer
      <emphasis>Farbtabelle</emphasis> zugewiesen bekommen. In der Farbtabelle
      wird dann für die einzelnen Einträge die Farbe selbst zugewiesen. In
      GIMP können Farbtabellen maximal 256 Einträge haben. Dabei kann jedem
      Eintrag eine beliebige Farbe zugeordnet werden.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans une image indexée, les couleurs sont assignées aux pixels de façon
      indirecte, à travers une table de référence appelée
      <emphasis>Carte de couleurs</emphasis>.
      Dans Gimp, le maximum d'entrées dans une carte de couleurs est de 256:
      à chaque indice de 0 à 255 est ainsi affectée une couleur particulière.
      Il n'y a aucune règle restreignant les couleurs pouvant être affectées à
      un indice ou l'ordre dans lequel elles apparaissent: n'importe quelle
      couleur peut-être affectée à n'importe quel indice.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      In un'immagine indicizzata i colori vengono assegnati ai pixel con un
      metodo indiretto, usando una tabella di riferimento chiamata
      <emphasis>mappa colori</emphasis>.
      In GIMP il numero massimo di elementi in una mappa colori è di 256. In
      una mappa colori della massima estensione, ad ogni indice da 0 a 255
      viene assegnato un colore RGB a scelta. Non vi sono regole che limitino
      i colori assegnabili ad un indice o che definiscano l'ordine in cui
      appaiono: ad ogni indice può essere assegnato qualsiasi colore.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В индексированных изображениях цвета ассоциируются с пикселами 
      согласно <emphasis>цветовой карте</emphasis>.  Максимальное 
      количество цветов в цветовой карте GIMP - 256. Каждому цвету 
      присваивается индекс от 0 до 255. Никаких правил для присвоения 
      индекса определенному цвету нет, любой индекс может быть 
      присвоен любому цвету.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在索引图像中，颜色通过间接地方式指定给像素，即从 <emphasis>颜色表</emphasis>
      中进行查找。GIMP 中，颜色表最多只能有 256 个项，其中从 0 到 255 的每个索引都被指定为任意的一种 RGB
      颜色。对于每个索引的颜色或它们的顺序都没有约束：任何索引可以被指定为任何颜色。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      In an Indexed image, instead of being assigned a color directly (as
      happens in RGB and Grayscale images), each pixel is assigned an index.
      To determine the color that should be shown for that pixel, GIMP looks
      up the index in the image's colormap. Each indexed image has its own
      private colormap.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Obrázek v režimu indexovaných barev nemá barvy přiřazované přímo (jako v
      případě režimů RGB či stupně šedi), ale jednotlivým pixelům jsou
      přiřazovány indexy. Jakou barvu má Gimp pixelům přiřadit, zjistí v mapě
      barev. Každý indexovaný obrázek má svou vlastní mapu barev.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans une image indexée, au lieu de recevoir directement une couleur
      (comme dans les images RVB ou en niveaux de gris), chaque pixel reçoit
      un indice correspondant dans la Carte des couleurs.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      In un'immagine indicizzata ad ogni pixel viene assegnato un indice,
      anzichè assegnargli direttamente un colore (come avviene nelle immagini
      RGB ed in scala di grigio), Per determinare il colore che dev'essere
      visualizzato per quel pixel, GIMP cerca l'indice corrispondente nella
      mappa colori. Ogni immagine indicizzata ha una sua specifica mappa
      colori.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В отличие от изображения RGB, где пикселы ассоциируются 
      непосредственно с цветом, в индексированном изображении пикселы 
      ассоциируются  с индексом. Чтобы определить, какого цвета должен 
      быть пиксел, GIMP использует цветовую карту. Каждое индексированное 
      изображение имеет свою, уникакльную карту.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在索引图像中，每个像素不是直接被赋予一种颜色(RGB 和
      灰度图像则是这样)，而是给它们指定一个颜色表，通过它来决定该像素该显示为哪种颜色。GIMP
      在图像的颜色表中查找索引，每个索引图像都有自己的颜色表。
    </para>

    <para lang="en"> <!-- changed dithering to quantization, bug #356354 -->
      It is important to realize that the colors in the colormap are the
      <emphasis>only colors available</emphasis>
      for an indexed image (that is, unless you add new colors to the
      colormap). This has a major effect on many GIMP operations: for example,
      in a pattern fill, GIMP will usually not be able to find exactly the
      right colors in the colormap, so it will approximate them by
      using the nearest color available.
      <footnote>
        <para>
          This is sometimes referred to as
          <link linkend="glossary-quantization">Quantization</link>, which
          is described in the Glossary.
        </para>
      </footnote>
      If the colormap is too limited or poorly chosen, this can easily
      produce very poor image quality.
    </para>
    <para lang="de"> <!-- FIXME: quantization, not dithering -->
      Es ist wichtig zu beachten, dass die Farben in der Farbtabelle eines
      Bildes im Farbmodus <quote>indiziert</quote> dien einzigen Farben sind,
      die in diesem Bild zur Verfügung stehen. Dies gilt natürlich auch für
      Aktionen wie das Füllen von Bereichen eines solchen Bildes mit einem
      Muster. Dabei wird GIMP vermutlich nicht alle Farben des Musters in
      der Farbtabelle des Bildes finden. In einem solchen Fall werden die
      nicht verfügbaren Farben angenähert. Die dabei verwendeten Algorithmen
      werden im Glossar als <xref linkend="glossary-dithering" /> beschrieben.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs"> <!-- FIXME: quantization, not dithering -->
      Je důležité si uvědomit, že barvy obsažené v mapě barev jsou
      <emphasis>jediné dostupné barvy</emphasis>
      pro daný indexovaný obrázek (pokud do mapy nepřidáte další barvy). To má
      zásadní vliv na funkci Gimpu: například při tvorbě přechodu Gimp nebude
      mít k dispozici požadované barvy a proto je nahradí
      <!--FIXME cs <link linkend="glossary-dithering">-->Rozptylem<!--</link>-->.
      Pokud je mapa barev příliš malá nebo nevhodně sestavená, může být
      výsledná kvalita obrázku velmi špatná.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr"> <!-- FIXME: quantization, not dithering -->
      Il est important de réaliser que, pour une images indexée, les couleurs
      disponibles sont celles de la Carte des couleurs et aucune autre
      (jusqu'à ce que vous en ajoutiez). Cela a un effet majeur sur de
      nombreuses opérations de Gimp: par exemple, lors du remplissage par un
      motif, il risque de ne pas trouver toutes les couleurs nécessaires et
      créera une couleur approchée par
      <link linkend="glossary-dithering-fr">Tramage</link>.
      Si la carte des couleurs est pauvre en couleurs, le résultat sera de
      piètre qualité.
    </para>
    <para lang="it"> <!-- FIXME: quantization, not dithering -->
      E' importante capire che i colori presenti nella mappa colori sono i
      <emphasis>soli colori disponibili</emphasis>
      in un'immagine indicizzata (a meno che non ne vengano aggiunti di nuovi
      nella mappa colori). Questo ha un effetto rilevante su molte operazioni
      di GIMP: ad esempio, nel riempimento con un motivo, solitamente GIMP non
      sarà in grado di trovare esattamente i colori giusti nella mappa colori,
      perciò dovrà approssimarli con il metodo del
      <link linkend="glossary-dithering">Dithering</link>.
      Se la mappa colori è troppo limitata o con delle scelte scarse, questo
      può facilmente portare a delle immagine qualitativamente molto povere.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Обратите внимание на то, что в индексированном изображении могут 
      использоваться <emphasis>только те цвета</emphasis>, которые есть 
      в цветовой карте. Это сказывается на результатах большинства 
      операций GIMP. Например, при заливке индексированного изображения 
      шаблоном, GIMP в большинстве случаев не сможет подобрать корректные 
      цвета из тех, которые есть в цветовой карте и воспользуется наиболее 
      близкими цветами. Таким образом, если в цветовой карте мало цветов 
      или среди них нет тех, которые используются в шаблоне, то в 
      результате получится изображение очень плохого качества.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      需要注意的是，一个索引图像颜色表中的颜色是它<emphasis>唯一可使用</emphasis>的颜色(除非您在颜色表中添加新颜色)，这对很多 GIMP 操作都有影响：比如在进行一个图像填充时，GIMP 就常常在颜色表中无法找到正确的颜色，因此只能通过“抖动”来估计。当颜色表中颜色很有限或选得很差时，很容易产生很差的图像质量。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      The Colormap dialog allows you to alter the colormap for an image,
      either by creating new entries, or by changing the colors for the
      existing entries. If you change the color associated with a given index,
      you will see the changes reflected throughout the image, as a color
      shift for all pixels that are assigned that index. The entries are
      numbered with 0 in the upper left corner, 1 to its right, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Dialog Mapa barev umožňuje upravovat mapu barev obrázku přiřazováním
      nových barev do mapy nebo změnou existujících barev. Pokud již
      existující barvu přiřazenou určitému indexu změníte, změní se barva
      všech pixelů v obrázku s daným indexem. Barvy jsou číslované od nuly v
      levém horním rohu po řádcích.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der Dialog erlaubt es Ihnen die Farbtabelle des Bildes zur bearbeiten.
      Dabei können Sie nicht nur die Farbe der Einträge ändern, sondern auch
      Einträge entfernen und neue Einträge hinzufügen. Die Änderungen werden
      sofort im Bild sichtbar. Wenn Sie einen Eintrag der Farbtabelle
      entfernen, so werden alle nachfolgenden Einträge der Tabelle nach oben
      rutschen. Dadurch ändert sich auch die Nummer des Eintrages in der
      Farbtabelle und damit auch die Farben im Bild.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le dialogue Palette de couleurs vous permet de modifier la Carte des
      couleurs d'une image, en changeant les couleurs existantes ou en
      ajoutant de nouvelles. Si vous changez la couleur d'un indice donné,
      vous verrez se modifier tous les pixels correspondant à cet indice dans
      l'image. Les indices sont numérotés avec le 0 dans le coin en haut à
      gauche, le 1 à sa droite...etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      La finestra della mappa colori permette di modificare la mappa colori di
      un'immagine, sia inserendo nuovi elementi, sia modificando i colori
      degli elementi esistenti. Modificando il colore associato ad un dato
      indice, si vedrà che il cambiamento si rifletterà attraverso l'intera
      immagine, infatti il colore verrà applicato a tutti i pixel ai quali è
      assegnato quell'indice. Gli elementi sono numerati a partire dallo 0
      nell'angolo in alto a sinistra, 1 alla sua destra, ecc.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      С помощью диалога цветовой карты можно как добавлять новые цвета, 
      так и редактировать уже существующие. Если вы изменяете существующий 
      цвет, то будьте готовы к тому, что это моментально скажется на 
      изображении - цвет всех пикселов, ассоциирующиеся с этим индексом, 
      будет изменен.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      通过颜色表对话框可以在图像的颜色表中添加颜色项，或改变现有颜色项。当改变一个给定索引的颜色时，您就能看到它对图像产生的影响，即被指定为该索引的所有像素其颜色都将改变。值为 0 的项在最左上角，1 则在它右边，依此类推。
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Using the Colormap dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Použití dialogu Mapa barev</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Aufbau und Benutzung des Dialoges <quote>Farbtabelle</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Utilisation du dialogue Palette de couleurs</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Utilizzo della finestra della mappa colori</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Использование цветовой карты</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用颜色表对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      Here are the operations you can perform using this dialog:
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">Dialog Mapa barev umožňuje následující operace:</para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die folgenden Kommandos können Sie im Dialog ausführen:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Voici les opérations que vous pouvez réaliser avec ce dialogue:
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Queste sono le operazioni che si possono eseguire da questa finestra:
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Ниже приведен список функций, которые можно выполнить с помощью 
      этого диалога:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">用该对话框可以进行下列操作：</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Click on a color entry</term>
        <term lang="cs">Kliknutí na barevnou položku</term>
        <term lang="de">
          <mousebutton>Mausklick</mousebutton>
          auf einen Eintrag der Farbtabelle
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">Clic sur une case de couleur</term>
        <term lang="it">Clic su di un colore</term>
        <term lang="ru">Щелчок на цвете палитры</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">点击一个颜色项</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This sets GIMP's foreground color to the color you click on, as
            shown in the Toolbox color area. As a result, this color will be
            used for the next painting operation you do.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Barvu, na kterou kliknete, nastaví Gimp jako barvu popředí
            (zobrazenou například v panelu nástrojů).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Damit setzen Sie die Farbe des Eintrages der Farbtabelle als
            aktuelle Vordergrundfarbe in GIMP. Diese Farbe wird also für alle
            nachfolgenden Anwendungen eines Malwerkzeuges verwendet.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le fait de cliquer sur une case de couleur place cette couleur en
            couleur de Premier-plan dans la Boîte à outils.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo imposta il colore di primo piano di GIMP al colore sul
            quale si è fatto clic, come si vede dalla visualizzazione
            nell'area dei colori attivi nella barra degli strumenti. Di
            conseguenza, questo colore sarà utilizzato per le prossime
            operazioni di disegno che verrano eseguite.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Цвет переднего плана станет равным тому цвету, на который вы 
            нажали. В результате выбранный цвет будет использоваться 
            всеми операциями, использующими цвет переднего плана.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">它将把您点击的颜色设为 GIMP 的前景色，这样可以在下次绘画操作中使用。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Ctrl-click on a color entry</term>
        <term lang="cs">Kliknutí na barevnou položku s modifikační klávesou Ctrl</term>
        <term lang="de">
          <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap>
            <mousebutton>Mausklick</mousebutton>
          </keycombo> auf einen Eintrag der Farbtabelle
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">Ctrl-clic sur une case de couleur</term>
        <term lang="it">Ctrl-clic su di un colore</term>
        <term lang="ru">Ctrl+Щелчок на цвете палитры</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">Ctrl-点击一个颜色项</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en;cs"><!-- FIXME: cs -->
            This sets GIMP's background color to the color you Ctrl-click on,
            as shown in the Toolbox color area.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Hierbei setzen Sie die aktuelle Hintergrundfarbe in GIMP auf die
            Farbe der Tabellenzelle, welche Sie angeklickt haben.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le Ctrl-clic sur une case de couleur place cette couleur en
            couleur d'Arrière-plan dans la Boîte à outils.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo imposta il colore di sfondo di GIMP al colore sul quale si
            è fatto Ctrl-clic, come si vede dalla visualizzazione nell'area
            dei colori attivi nella barra degli strumenti.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Цвет фона станет равным тому, на который вы нажали.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
          它将把您点击的颜色设为 GIMP 的背景色。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Double-click on a color entry</term>
        <term lang="cs">Dvojité poklepání na barevnou položku</term>
        <term lang="de">
          <mousebutton>Doppelklick</mousebutton>
          auf einen Eintrag in der Farbtabelle
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">Double-clic sur une case de couleur</term>
        <term lang="it">Doppio-clic su di un colore</term>
        <term lang="ru">Двойной щелчок на цвете</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">双击一个颜色项</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This sets GIMP's foreground color to the color you click on, and
            also brings up a Color Editor that allows you to change that
            colormap entry to a new color.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Nastaví barvu popředí na hodnotu barvy, na kterou jste poklepali,
            ale zároveň otevře dialog pro změnu této položky v mapě barev.
            <!--  FIXME: cs -->
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Hiermit können Sie den GIMP Farbwähler öffnen, um die Farbe des
            Eintrages zu ändern. Gleichzeitig wird der Eintrag auch zur
            aktuellen Vordergrundfarbe von GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cela place la couleur en Premier-plan, mais aussi ouvre un Éditeur
            de couleurs qui vous permet de modifier cette couleur dans la
            Carte des couleurs.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo imposta il colore di primo piano di GIMP al colore sul
            quale si è fatto clic, e fa inoltre apparire una finestra di
            modifica del colore che permette di cambiare l'elemento della
            mappa colori impostandolo ad un nuovo colore.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            它将把您点击的颜色设为 GIMP 的前景色，同时打开一个颜色编辑器，在其中可以改变该颜色表项为一个新颜色。
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Цвет переднего плана становится равным цвету палитры, на 
            который вы нажали. Кроме того, открывается окно выбора цвета, 
            в котором можно изменить цвет палитры.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Color index</term>
        <term lang="cs">Index barvy</term>
        <term lang="de">Farbindex</term>
        <term lang="fr">Indice de couleur</term>
        <term lang="it">Indice colore</term>
        <term lang="ru">Номер цвета</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">颜色索引</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can select a different colormap entry by typing its index
            here, or clicking the spinbutton to the right.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Zápisem čísla do této kolonky zvolíte daný index.
            <!-- FIXME: cs -->
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesem Eingabefeld können Sie einen anderen Farbeintrag durch
            Eingabe der Nummer des Eintrages auswählen. Ausserdem wird in
            diesem Feld die Nummer des jeweils aktuellen Eintrages der
            Farbtabelle angezeigt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous pouvez entrer là l'indice d'une couleur soit en la tapant
            soit en utilisant les boutons molette.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            E' possibile selezionare un elemento della mappa colori digitando
            qui il suo indice, oppure facendo clic sulle freccette a destra.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Цвета можно выбирать, указывая их индекс в этом поле ввода.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">您可以通过在其中输入索引值或点击右边的上下箭头来选取一个不同的颜色表项。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Hex triplet</term>
        <term lang="cs">Notace HTML</term>
        <term lang="de">HTML-Notation</term>
        <term lang="fr">Notation HTML</term>
        <term lang="it">Notazione esadecimale</term>
        <term lang="ru">Нотация HTML</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">十六进制值</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This area shows a hex-code representation (such as is used in
            HTML) for the color assigned to the currently selected colormap
            entry. You can edit the color here, instead of using a Color
            Editor, if you want to. See
            <link linkend="glossary-hextriplet">HexTriplet</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Hexadecimální reprezentace barvy (tak, jak se používá v HTML)
            přiřazené právě zvolené položce barevné mapy. Pomocí ní můžete
            barvu upravit bez použití editoru barev. Viz FIXME
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In diesem Eingabefeld wird Ihnen die Farbe des aktuellen Eintrages
            der Farbtabelle als sogenanntes
            <link linkend="glossary-hextriplet">HexTriplet</link>
            angezeigt. Dabei die Intensität jeder der Grundfarben Rot, Grün
            und Blau als Hexadezimalzahl angezeigt. Diese Art eine Farbe durch
            sechs Zeichen zu beschreiben ist bei der Erstellung von Webseiten
            üblich. Sie können die Farbe auch durch Eingabe eines anderen
            Farbcodes verändern.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette aire donne le code hexadécimal de la couleur. Vous 
            pouvez entrer un triplet hexa pour obtenir une couleur. Voir 
            <link linkend="glossary-hextriplet">HexTriplet</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questa casella visualizza una rappresentazione in codice
            esadecimale (così come utilizzato in HTML) del colore assegnato
            all'elemento della mappa colori selezionato in quel momento.
            Volendo è possibile modificare il colore da qui, invece che
            utilizzare la finestra di modifica del colore. Vedi
            <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="glossary-hextriplet"-->
            Tripletta esadecimale<!-- /link -->
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            В этом поле ввода указывается шестнадцатеричный код цвета, 
            который используется в HTML. Выбранный цвет можно 
            редактировать не только при помощи окна выбора цвета, но и 
            используя это поле ввода. Более подробно о шестнадцатеричном 
            обозначении цвета написано в разделе
            <!--link linkend="glossary-hextriplet"-->
              Шестнадцатеричный триплет
            <!--/link-->
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该区域显示当前选取颜色表项的十六进制代码(如 HTML 中所使用的)。如果您愿意，可以在这里编辑颜色，而不用使用颜色编辑器。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Edit color</term>
        <term lang="cs">Upravit barvu</term>
        <term lang="de"><quote>Farbe bearbeiten</quote> Schaltfläche</term>
        <term lang="fr">Édition</term>
        <term lang="it">Modifica colore</term>
        <term lang="ru">Редактировать цвет</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">编辑颜色</term>

        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-indexed-palette-edit" />
          <para lang="en">
            This button (in the lower left corner of the dialog) brings up a
            Color Editor that allows you to change the color for the currently
            selected colormap entry. The effect is similar to double-clicking
            on the entry, except that it does not set GIMP's foreground color.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Toto tlačítko (v levém dolním rohu dialogu) otevře editor barev,
            ve kterém můžete změnit barvu přiřazenou právě zvolené položce
            mapy barev. Funkce je podobná jako když dvojitě poklepáte na
            barevnou položku, ale barva se nenastaví jako barva popředí.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Schaltfläche können Sie den Farbwähler Dialog öffnen,
            um die Farbe des aktuellen Eintrages der Farbtabelle zu
            bearbeiten.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce bouton (en bas à gauche de la fenêtre) fait venir un Éditeur de
            couleur qui vous permet de modifier la couleur de la case
            sélectionnée dans la Carte de couleurs. C'est la même chose qu'en
            double-cliquant sur la case, sauf que la couleur de Premier-plan
            n'est pas mise à jour.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo pulsante (nell'angolo in basso a sinistra della finestra)
            fa apparire una finestra di modifica del colore che permette di
            cambiare il colore dell'elemento selezionato in quel momento nella
            mappa colori. L'effetto è simile a quello di fare un doppio clic
            sull'elemento, ad eccezione del fatto che non viene impostato il
            colore di primo piano attivo in GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При нажатии на эту кнопку, расположенную в нижней части 
            диалога, появляется окно выбора цвета. Таким образом, она 
            выполняет ту же функцию, что и двойной щелчок по цвету.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该按钮(在对话框的左下角)可以弹出一个颜色编辑器，让您改变当前选取的颜色表项的颜色。其效果和双击一个项几乎相同，除了不设定 GIMP
            的前景色。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Add color</term>
        <term lang="cs">Přidat barvu</term>
        <term lang="de"><quote>Farbe hinzufügen</quote> Schaltfläche</term>
        <term lang="fr">Ajouter</term>
        <term lang="it">Aggiungi colore</term>
        <term lang="ru">Добавить цвет</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">添加颜色</term>

        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-indexed-palette-add" />
          <para lang="en">
            This button (in the lower right corner of the dialog) allows you
            to add new colors to the colormap. If you click on the button, the
            current foreground color, as shown in the Toolbox, will be tacked
            on to the end of the colormap. If instead you hold down
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and click, the background color from the
            Toolbox will be added. (If the colormap contains 256 entries, it
            is full, and trying to add more will have no effect.)
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tímto tlačítkem (v pravém dolním rohu dialogu) přidáte do mapy
            barev novou barvu. Pokud na tlačítko kliknete bez použití
            modifikační klávesy, přidá se, na poslední místo, barva popředí.
            Pokud použijete modifikační klávesu <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>,
            přidá se barva pozadí. (Pokud má mapa 256 položek, nelze další
            položky přidávat).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Schaltfläche können Sie neue Einträge zur Farbtabelle
            hinzufügen. Wenn Sie dieses Kommando ausführen, wird die aktuelle
            Vordergrundfarbe in GIMP als neuer Eintrag an die vorhandene
            Farbtabelle angefügt. Um statt der Vorder- die aktuelle
            Hintergrundfarbe zu verwenden, halten Sie wie üblich die
            <keycap>Strg</keycap>
            Taste während des klickens auf die Schaltfläche gedrückt. Bitte
            beachten Sie, dass eine Farbtabelle in GIMP maximal 256 Einträge
            umfassen kann. Sofern die Tabelle bereits die maximale Anzahl an
            Einträgen enthält, wird die Schaltfläche inaktiviert (ausgegraut).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce bouton (en bas à droite de la fenêtre) vous permet d'ajouter de
            nouvelles couleurs à la Carte des couleurs. En cliquant dessus, la
            couleur de Premier-plan de la Boîte à outils vient se placer en
            fin de Carte. Avec Ctrl-clic, ce sera la couleur d'Arrière-plan
            (Notez que vous ne pouvez pas dépasser 256 couleurs).
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo pulsante (nell'angolo in basso a destra della finestra)
            permette di aggiungere nuovi colori alla mappa colori. Facendo
            clic su questo pulsante il colore di primo piano attivo,
            visualizzato nella barra degli strumenti, viene accodato alla fine
            della mappa colori. Se invece si tiene premuto il tasto
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            mentre si fa clic, allora verrà aggiunto il colore di sfondo.
            (Quando la mappa colori contiene 256 elementi, è piena, ed il
            tentativo di aggiungerne di nuovi non avrà effetto.)
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Эта кнопка расположена в правом нижнем углу диалога. При 
            нажатии на нее в палитру добавляется еще одни цвет, равный 
            цвету переднего плана. Если нажать на кнопку, удерживая 
            клавишу <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, то в цветовую карту будет 
            добавлен цвет фона. Обратите внимание на то, что в 
            индексированной палитре может быть только 256 цветов. Если 
            все они уже присутствую, то пытаться добавить что-либо в 
            палитру бесполезно.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该按钮(在对话框右下角)让您在颜色表中添加一种新颜色。点击该按钮时，显示在工具箱的当前前景色将添加在颜色表的尾部。而
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-点击按钮时，将添加背景色。(如果颜色表已经有 256 个项，表示它已经满了，就无法再添加了。)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>

    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        If you make a mistake, you can undo it by focusing the pointer in
        the image whose colormap you have changed, and then pressing
        <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> or choosing
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> 
        in the image menu.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pokud uděláte chybu, můžete ji vrátit klávesovou zkratkou
        <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> nebo příkazem
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Editovat</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Zpět</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> z nabídky obrázku.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Falls Ihnen bei der Änderung ein Fehler unterläuft, können Sie diesen
        Rückgängig machen, indem Sie das Bildfenster des Bildes aktivieren
        für dass Sie versehentlich die Farbtabelle verändert haben und dann
        das Kommando
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Bearbeite<accel>n</accel></guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>ückgängig</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> aufrufen. Alternativ können Sie auch das Tastenkürzel
        <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>
        verwenden.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Si vous faites une erreur, vous pouver l'annuler en plaçant le 
        focus sur l'image dont vous avez changé la palette et en tapant 
        <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> ou en choisissant
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Édition</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Annuler</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> 
        dans le menu de l'image.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Se si è commesso un errore, è possibile annullarlo attivando la 
        finestra dell'immagine della quale si è modificato la mappa colori e 
        premendo i tasti <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> oppure scegliendo 
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Modifica</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Annulla</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> 
        dal menu immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru"> 
        Действия, произведенные с цветовой картой, можно отменить. 
        Для этого поместите курсор в окно того изображения, чью 
        карту вы редактируете, и нажмите
        <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> или воспользуйтесь пунктом меню 
        изображения
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Правка</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Отменить</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当操作错误时，可以撤消它：将光标放在在颜色表被改变的图像中，然后按下 <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> 或在图像菜单中选取
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>编辑</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>撤消</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
    </tip>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        This dialog provides the most commonly used methods for altering the
        colormap for an indexed image. The color tools, such as
        Brightness/Contrast, Hue/Saturation, etc, do not operate on indexed
        images. There are a few plug-ins that do so, including the
        "Normalize", "Color Enhance", and "Stretch Contrast" operations, and
        it is possible to create others as well.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Tento dialog ale není jedinou možnou cestou ke změně barevné mapy
        indexovaného obrázku. Nástroje pro úpravu barev jako Jas/Kontrast
        apod. též mění barvy v mapě barev.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Bitte beachten Sie, dass Sie mit diesem Dialog die wichtigsten
        Möglichkeiten zur Veränderung von Farben in Bildern im Farbmodus
        <quote>indiziert</quote> kennen gelernt haben. Die für Bilder im
        Farbmodus RGB üblichen Werkzeuge zur Kontrast- und Farbkorrektur
        können in diesem Fall genauso wenig verwendet werden wie verschiedene
        Filter.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Ce dialogue n'est pas la seule façon de modifier la carte des couleurs
        d'une image indexée. Les outils de couleur, comme
        Luminosité/Contraste, Teinte/Saturation le permettent aussi.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        La finestra mette a disposizione le funzioni più comunemente usate per
        alterare la mappa colori di un'immagine indicizzata. Gli strumenti di
        colore, come Luminosità/Contrasto, Tonalità/Saturazione, ecc., non
        operano sulle immagini indicizzate. Ci sono alcuni plug-in che si
        comportano allo stesso modo, tra i quali le operazioni "Normalizza",
        "Accentua Colore", ed "Aggiustamento Contrasto", è inoltre possibile
        crearne di nuovi.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Этот диалог не является единственным способом редактирования 
        цветовой карты индексированного изображения. Такие инструменты, 
        как Яркость-Контрастность, Тон-Насыщенность и т.п., так же 
        влияют на цветовую карту.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该对话框不是改变一个索引图像颜色变的唯一方法，也可以通过颜色工具，如亮度/对比度，色调/饱和度等
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
