<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-26 j.h: no change for v2.8
  2007-08-12 j.h: updated to v2.4 ; colormap submenu and a note added en;fr
  2006-03-12 made docbook compliant
  2005-11-29 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">
  <title>Colormap Dialog</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Colormap</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Colormap</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>An indexed image with 6 colors and its Colormap dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/examples/cosmos-6.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/colormap-dialog.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Colormap (Indexed Palette is a better name) dialog allows you to edit
    the colormap of an indexed image. (If the mode of the active image is RGB
    or Grayscale instead of Indexed, the dialog is empty and unusable.)
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog-activate">
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      This dialog is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can access it:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Colormap</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>;
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the Tab menu in any dockable dialog by clicking the
          <link linkend="tab-menus">tab menu button</link>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon> and selecting
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Colormap</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      In the <guimenu>Windows</guimenu> menu, there is a list of
      <link linkend="gimp-dockable-menu">detached windows</link> which exists
      only if at least one dialog remains open. In this case, you can raise
      the <quote>Colormap</quote> dialog from the main menu:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Colormap</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog-colormaps">
    <title>Colormaps and Indexed Images</title>
    <para>
      In an Indexed image, instead of being assigned a color directly (as
      happens in RGB and Grayscale images), colors are assigned to pixels by
      an indirect method, using a look-up table called a
      <emphasis>colormap</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      To determine the color that should be shown for that pixel, GIMP looks
      up the index in the image's colormap. Each indexed image has its own
      private colormap. In GIMP, the maximum number of entries in a colormap
      is 256. For a maximum-sized colormap, each index from 0 to 255 is
      assigned an arbitrary RGB color. There are no rules restricting the
      colors that can be assigned to an index or the order they appear in: any
      index can be assigned any color.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is important to realize that the colors in the colormap are the
      <emphasis>only colors available</emphasis> for an indexed image (that
      is, unless you add new colors to the colormap). This has a major effect
      on many GIMP operations: for example, in a pattern fill, GIMP will
      usually not be able to find exactly the right colors in the colormap, so
      it will approximate them by using the nearest color available. This is
      sometimes referred to as
      <link linkend="glossary-quantization">Quantization</link>.
      If the colormap is too limited or poorly chosen, this can easily produce
      very poor image quality.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Colormap dialog allows you to alter the colormap for an image,
      either by creating new entries, or by changing the colors for the
      existing entries. If you change the color associated with a given index,
      you will see the changes reflected throughout the image, as a color
      shift for all pixels that are assigned that index. The entries are
      numbered with 0 in the upper left corner, 1 to its right, etc.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog-using">
    <title>Using the Colormap dialog</title>
    <para>
      Here are the operations you can perform using this dialog:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Click on a color entry</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This sets GIMP's foreground color to the color you click on, as
            shown in the Toolbox color area. As a result, this color will be
            used for the next painting operation you do.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-click on a color entry</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This sets <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s background color to the
            color you <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-click on,
            as shown in the Toolbox color area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Double-click on a color entry</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This sets GIMP's foreground color to the color you click on, and
            also brings up a Color Editor that allows you to change that
            colormap entry to a new color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Color index</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can select a different colormap entry by typing its index
            here, or clicking the spinbutton to the right.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>HTML notation</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This area shows a hex-code representation (such as is used in
            HTML) for the color assigned to the currently selected colormap
            entry. You can edit the color here, instead of using a Color
            Editor, if you want to. See
            <link linkend="glossary-html-notation">HTML notation</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Buttons</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The button bar at the bottom offers the following functionality:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gtk-edit.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Edit color</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <anchor id="gimp-indexed-palette-edit"/>
                <para>
                  This button (in the lower left corner of the dialog) brings up a
                  Color Editor that allows you to change the color for the currently
                  selected colormap entry. The effect is similar to double-clicking
                  on the entry, except that it does not set GIMP's foreground color.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/edit-delete.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Delete color</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <anchor id="gimp-indexed-palette-delete"/>
                <para>
                  This button (in the lower left corner of the dialog) allows you to
                  delete a color which is not used in the image from the colormap.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/list-add.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase condition="tag-is-required">Add color</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <anchor id="gimp-indexed-palette-add"/>
                <para>
                  This button (at the bottom of the dialog) allows you to add new
                  colors to the colormap. If you click on the button, the current
                  foreground color, as shown in the Toolbox, will be added to the end
                  of the colormap. If instead you hold down <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and
                  click, the background color from the Toolbox will be added.
                </para>
                <note>
                  <para>
                    The colormap can not contain more than 256 entries. If it already
                    has 256 entries, trying to add a color will have no effect.
                  </para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
                <guiicon>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                <phrase>Select all pixels with this color</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This button allows you to select all pixels with this color.
                  To add to the selection, use <keycap>Shift</keycap> buttonclick,
                  to subtract use <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> buttonclick, and to
                  intersect with the current selection use
                  <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
                  buttonclick.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <tip>
      <para>
        If you make a mistake, you can undo it by focusing the pointer in
        the image whose colormap you have changed, and then pressing
        <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo> or
        choosing
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        in the main menu.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <note>
      <para>
        If you paint an indexed image with a color which is not in the
        Colormap, GIMP will use the most similar color of the Colormap.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog-submenu">
    <title>The Colormap context menu</title>
    <para>
      Right-clicking on a color in the Colormap selects this color and opens
      a context menu with the following options:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edit color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command opens a color selector which allows you to modify
            the color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Add Color from FG</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command is enabled only if the indexed palette contains less
            than 256 colors. The background color of the Toolbox is appended
            to the color map.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Add Color from BG</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command is enabled only if the indexed palette contains less
            than 256 colors. The background color of the Toolbox is appended
            to the color list.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-indexed-palette-selection-replace">
        <term>Select this Color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This selects all pixels in the image which have the chosen
            palette index.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-indexed-palette-selection-add">
        <term>Add to Selection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Adds all pixels in the image which have the chosen palette index
            to the selection.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-indexed-palette-selection-subtract">
        <term>Subtract from Selection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Subtracts all pixels in the image which have the chosen palette index
            from the selection.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-indexed-palette-selection-intersect">
        <term>Intersect with Selection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Intersect all pixels in the image with the chosen palette index
            with the current selection.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rearrange Colormap</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rearrange Colormap: This command is described in
            <xref linkend="plug-in-colormap-remap"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
