<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-indexed-palette-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Indexed Palette dialog</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Indexed Palette</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en">
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-indexed-palette.png'
        format="PNG"/>  
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Indexed Palette dialog
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>
  

  <para lang="en">
    The Indexed Palette dialog allows you to edit the colormap of an
    indexed image.  (If the mode of the active image is RGB or
    Grayscale instead of Indexed, the dialog is empty and unusable.)
    This is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in two ways:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>   
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Indexed Palette</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>   
        From the image menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Indexed Palette</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Colormaps and Indexed Images</title>
    
    <para lang='en'>
      In an Indexed image, colors are assigned to pixels by an
      indirect method, using a lookup table called a
      <emphasis>colormap</emphasis>.  In GIMP, the maximum number of
      entries in a colormap is 256.  For a maximum-sized colormap,
      each index from 0 to 255 is assigned an arbitrary RGB color.
      There are no rules restricting the colors that can be assigned
      to an index or the order they appear in:  any index can be
      assigned any color.  
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      In an Indexed image, instead of being assigned a color directly
      (as happens in RGB and Grayscale images), each pixel is assigned
      an index.  To determine the color that should be shown for that
      pixel, GIMP looks up the index in the image's colormap.  Each
      indexed image has its own private colormap.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      It is important to realize that the colors in the colormap are
      the <emphasis>only colors available</emphasis> for an indexed
      image (that is, unless you add new colors to the colormap).
      This has a major effect on many gimp operations:  for example,
      in a pattern fill, GIMP will usually not be
      able to find exactly the right colors in the colormap, so it
      will approximate them by "dithering".  If the colormap is too
      limited or poorly chosen, this can easily produce very poor
      image quality.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      The Indexed Palette dialog allows you to alter the colormap for an
      image, either by creating new entries, or by changing the colors
      for the existing entries.  If you change the color associated
      with a given index, you will see the changes reflected
      throughout the image, as a color shift for all pixels that are
      assigned that index.  The entries are numbered with 0 in the
      upper left corner, 1 to its right, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      Here are the operations you can perform using this dialog:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>Using the Indexed Palette dialog</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Click on a color entry</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            This sets GIMP's foreground color to the color you click
            on, as shown in the Toolbox color area.  As a result, this
            color will be used for the next painting operation you do.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Ctrl-click on a color entry</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            This sets GIMP's background color to the color you click
            on, as shown in the Toolbox color area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Double-click on a color entry</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            This sets GIMP's foreground color to the color you click
            on, and also brings up a Color Editor that allows you to
            change that colormap entry to a new color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Color index</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            You can select a different colormap entry by typing its
            index here, or clicking the spinbutton to the right.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Hex triplet</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            This area shows a hex-code representation (such as is used
            in HTML) for the color assigned to the currently selected
            colormap entry.  You can edit the color here, instead of
            using a Color Editor, if you want to.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-indexed-palette-edit' />
        <term lang='en'>Edit color</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            This button (in the lower left corner of the dialog)
            brings up a Color Editor that allows you to change the
            color for the currently selected colormap entry.  The
            effect is similar to double-clicking on the entry, except
            that it does not set GIMP's foreground color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <anchor id='gimp-indexed-palette-add' />
        <term lang='en'>Add color</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            This button (in the lower right corner of the dialog)
            allows you to add new colors to the colormap.  If you
            click on the button, the current foreground color, as
            shown in the Toolbox, will be tacked on to the end of the
            colormap.  If instead you hold down <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            and click, the background color from the Toolbox will be
            added.  (If the colormap contains 256 entries, it is full,
            and trying to add more will have no effect.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    
   </variablelist>

    <tip lang='en'>    
      If you make a mistake, you can undo it by focusing the pointer in
      the image whose colormap you have changed, and then pressing
      <keycap>Ctrl-Z</keycap> or choosing
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> 
      in the image menu.
    </tip>

    <note lang='en'> 
      This dialog is not the only way of altering the colormap for an
      indexed image.  The color tools, such as Brightness/Contrast,
      Hue/Saturation, etc, also change the colors in the colormap.
    </note>
   
  </simplesect>

</sect1>
