<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-26 j.h: no change for v2.8
  2007-09-30 j.h : updated en ; fr to v2.4. Channel option added
  2007-06-15 j.h : some improvement in Add Layer Mask explanations
  2006-03-09 lexa: reviewed and made docbook compliant
-->
<sect3 id="gimp-layer-mask">
  <title>Layer masks</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer mask</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Masks</primary>
    <secondary>Layer mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title><quote>Add mask</quote> dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/layer-mask-add.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Overview</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A transparency mask can be added to each layer, which defines what
          parts of the layer are transparent or opaque. We call this a layer
          mask. A layer mask has the same size and same number of pixels as
          the layer to which it is attached. Every pixel of the mask can then
          be coupled with a pixel at the same location in the layer. The mask
          is a set of pixels in grayscale. The pixels with a value 0 are black
          and give a full transparency to the coupled pixel in the layer.
          The pixels with the maximum value (either 1.0 or 255) are white and
          give full opacity to the coupled pixel in the layer.
        </para>
        <para>
          To create a layer mask start with a right click on the layer to call
          the context menu and select <guimenuitem>Add Layer Masks…</guimenuitem>
          in the menu. A dialog appears where you can initialize the content of
          the mask:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>White (full opacity)</guilabel>:
              the mask is white
              in the Layers dialog. So, all pixels of the layer are visible
              in the image window since painting the mask with white makes
              layer pixels fully visible. You will paint with black to make
              layer pixels transparent.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Black (full transparency)</guilabel>: the mask is
              black in the Layers dialog. So, the layer is fully transparent
              since painting the mask with black makes layer pixels
              transparent. Painting with white will remove the mask and make
              layer pixels visible.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Layer's alpha channel</guilabel>: the mask is
              initialized according to the contents of the layer's alpha
              channel.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Transfer layer's alpha channel</guilabel>:
              Does the same thing as the previous option, except that it
              also resets the layer's alpha channel to full opacity.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Selection</guilabel>: the mask is initialized
              according to pixel values found in the current selection.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Grayscale copy of layer</guilabel>: the mask
              is initialized according to a grayscale representation of the
              pixel values of the layer.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Channel</guilabel>: The layer mask is initialized
              with a selection mask you have created before, stored in the
              Channels dialog.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Invert mask</guilabel>: This checkbox allows you to
              invert: black turns to white and white turns to black.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          When the mask is created, it appears as a thumbnail next to that of
          the layer itself. You can select the layer or the mask for editing by
          clicking on their respective thumbnails. The active item has a white
          border (which may not be clearly visible when you have a white mask).
        </para>
        <para>
          When working with masks, it is a good idea to keep the Layers Dialog
          prominently visible, because you can't see, by looking at the canvas,
          whether the layer or the mask is active.
        </para>
        <para>
          Pressing <keycap>Alt</keycap> (or
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> and
          clicking on the layer mask thumbnail) is equivalent to the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask-show">Show Layer Mask</link>
          command: the layer mask border turns to green. If you press
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> the border is red and the result is
          equivalent to the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask-disable">Disable Layer Mask</link>
          command. To return to normal view repeat the last operation. These
          options are for greater convenience in your work.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layer Mask example</term>
      <listitem>
        <figure>
          <title>A layer with layer mask</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="images/dialogs/examples/layer-mask-1-example.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Original image.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="images/dialogs/examples/layer-mask-1-dialog.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                This image has a background layer with a flower and another
                blue layer, fully opaque. A white layer mask has been added to
                the blue layer. The blue layer remains
                visible because a white mask makes layer pixels visible.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Painting the layer mask</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="images/dialogs/examples/layer-mask-2-example.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Foreground color set to black; Resulting image.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="images/dialogs/examples/layer-mask-2-dialog.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                The layer mask is active. Painting with black makes the layer
                transparent: the underlying layer becomes visible.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>
