<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-new-layer-dialog' lang="en">
  <title lang="en">New Layer Dialog</title>
  
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">New Layer Dialog</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-layer.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para>
	    New Layer dialog
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      This dialog comes up when you create a new layer within an
      image.  It is activated by choosing  
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>New Layer</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      from the image menu.  The new layer is always given an alpha
      channel, and filled with a solid
      color, for which you have four choices.  The Mode for the new
      layer is set to "Normal", the opacity is set to 100
      (completely opaque), and "Keep Transparency" is set to
      "off". By default the new layer is given
      the same size as the image, but you can change this.  You
      cannot alter the position of the layer within the image using
      this dialog: it can only be moved after it has been created.
      (See the <link linkend='gimp-layers'>Layers</link> section for
      help with layers and how to use them them.) 
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <variablelist>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Layer Name</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            Here you assign the layer a name.  This does not have any
            functional significance:  it is simply a convenience to
            help you remember the role you intended the layer to play
            when you created it.  By default, the name "New Layer" is
            used.  If a layer with this name (or whatever name you
            choose) already exists, after you hit the "OK" button, a
            number will be appended to the name in order to make it
            unique, i. e., "New Layer#1".
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Width and Height</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            Here you set the dimensions of the new layer.  When the
            dialog appears, the values are initialized to the
            dimensions of the image.  You can change them, and if you
            want to use units other than pixels, you can get them
            using the Units menu to the right.  You can't set the
            position of the layer within the image here, but you can
            always move it after it has been created.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Layer Fill Type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            Here you have four options for the solid color that will
            fill the layer:  the foreground or background colors as
            shown in the Main Toolbox; white; or transparent. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

</sect1>

 
