<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-new-image-dialog'>

  <title lang="en">New Image Dialog</title>
  
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">New Image Dialog</primary>
  </indexterm>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-image.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          New Image dialog (basic form)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    <para lang='en'>
      This dialog comes up when you create a new image from scratch,
      as opposed to opening an image from a file, or duplicating an
      existing image.  It is activated by choosing
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>New Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      from either an image menu or the main Toolbox menu.  Nearly all
      of the default values can be customized in the <!--link
      linkend='gimp-prefs-new-image'-->New Image Preferences tab.
      The new image is created with a single layer, sized to the image
      dimensions, filled with a solid color. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Basic Options</title>
    <variablelist>
    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Template</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en">
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-image-templates.png'
                format='PNG'/> 
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang='en'>
                Template menu (default)
              </para>
            </caption>
          </informalfigure>
          <para lang='en'>
            Instead of filling in all the numbers by hand, you can
            choose the dimensions of the image from a menu of
            templates, representing shapes that are more or less
            commonly useful.  If there is an image shape that you use
            often, and it does not appear in the list, you can create
            a new template using the <!--link
            linkend='gimp-templates-dialog'-->Templates dialog. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Image Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            Here you set the width and height of the new image.  The
            default units are pixels, but you can switch to some other
            unit if you prefer, using the adjoining menu. If you do,
            note that the resulting pixel size will be determined by
            the X and Y resolution (which you can change in the
            Advanced Options), and by the setting of "Dot for Dot",
            which you can change in the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.  
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Portrait/Landscape buttons</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            These buttons toggle between Portrait and Landscape mode.
            Concretely, their effect is to exchange the values for
            Width and Height.  If the X and Y resolutions are
            different (in Advanced Options), then these values are
            exchanged also.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Advanced Options</title>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-image-advanced.png'
          format='PNG'/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          New Image dialog (Advanced Options)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    <para lang='en'>
      These are options that will mainly be of interest to more
      advanced users.  (Gimp 2.0 does not distinguish between Basic
      and Advanced Options; all of the options are visible at the same
      level.) 
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>X and Y resolution</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            These values come into play mainly in relation to
            printing:  they do not affect the size of the image in
            pixels, but they determine its size on paper when
            printed.  They can also affect the way the image is
            displayed on the monitor: if "Dot for Dot" is switched off
            in the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, then at 100$ zoom,
            Gimp attempts to display the image on the monitor at the
            correct physical size, as calculated from the pixel
            dimensions and the resolution.  The display may not be
            accurate, however, unless the monitor has been calibrated.
            This can be done either when Gimp is installed, or from
            the <!--link linkend='prefs-display'-->Display tab of
            the Preferences dialog. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Colorspace</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-image-colorspace.png'
                format='PNG'/> 
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang='en'>
                Colorspace menu
              </para>
            </caption>
          </informalfigure>
          <para lang='en'>
            You can create the new image as either an RGB image or a
            grayscale image.  You cannot create an indexed image
            directly in this way, but of course nothing prevents you
            from converting the image to indexed mode after it has
            been created.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Fill</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-new-image-fill.png'
                format='PNG'/> 
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang='en'>
                Fill menu
              </para>
            </caption>
          </informalfigure>
          <para lang='en'>
            You have four choices for the solid color that will fill
            the new image's background layer:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>
                The Foreground color as shown in the Main Toolbox.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>
                The Background color as shown in the Main Toolbox.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>
                White
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>
                Transparent.  If this option is chosen, then the
                Background layer in the new image will be created with
                an alpha channel; otherwise not.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Comment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            You can write a descriptive comment here.  The text will
            be attached to the image as a "parasite", and will be
            saved along with the image by some file formats (but not
            all of them).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

</sect1>

 
