<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="gimp-open-dialog">
  <title>Open Image</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Open image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Open image</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Import image</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Open Image</guimenuitem> dialog lets you select an image to
    be loaded from your hard-drive or an external device.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access the <guimenuitem>Open Image</guimenuitem> dialog
          from the menu through:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Open…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can also open this dialog by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>File browsing</title>

    <figure>
      <!-- file-open.xcf.gz in src/images/dialogs-->
      <title>The Open Image Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/open-image-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      This file selection dialog should look familiar when you have worked with
      files before. Note that depending on your Operating System there may be
      some differences in the way this dialog looks. We will explain the
      details of this dialog based on the numbers in the red circles.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><!--1-->
        <para>
          This area gives you access to your main folders and your storage
          devices. The first time you open this dialog after starting GIMP,
          <guilabel>Recent</guilabel> will be selected here. This is a special
          folder that shows the images (see 3) that you have recently opened in
          GIMP.
        </para>
        <para>
          Besides the <guilabel>Recent</guilabel> folder, you can find here
          your <guilabel>Home</guilabel> folder, folders to you documents,
          pictures and other special locations, as well as your hard drives,
          external drives and network shares. Left clicking on one of these
          folders will select that one as the current folder and update the
          list of images in the image list area (3).
        </para>
        <para>
          By right-clicking on a folder in this list, a context menu will
          open. Not all commands will always be available, or enabled.
          The same context menu is also shown in the bookmark folders list,
          see (5).
        </para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/folder-context-menu.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>The folder and bookmark list context menu</caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Open</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This opens the contents of the selected folder in the image
                list window (3).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add Bookmark</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This allows you to add the selected folder as a bookmark.
                Bookmarks are shown in the area marked (5).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This allows you to remove a bookmark. It is disabled for
                other folders and devices.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Rename…</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This allows you to rename a bookmark or certain special folders.
                Note that it only renames the bookmark or special folder as
                shown inside the file dialog, not the actual folder it points
                to.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--2-->
        <para>
          By default, this shows the path to the current folder. You can
          navigate to one of the parent folders by clicking on the desired part.
        </para>
        <para>
          Alternatively, you can enter the name of an image. As soon as you
          start typing, the list of files (3) changes to show only the one
          containing the letter combination you entered.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you need to navigate to another location not available by clicking,
          you can open a text field where you can type or paste the desired
          location. To access this use
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>, then
          after you have entered the location, press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            You can use this location entry field to show the contents of a
            different folder, by entering the location of a folder; or open a
            specific image by entering the complete path to the image.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--3-->
        <para>
          The contents of the selected folder is displayed here. Change your
          current folder by double left clicking on a folder in this
          panel. Select a file with a single left click. You can then open
          the file you have selected by clicking on the
          <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button.
          A double left click opens the file directly. Please note that you
          can open image files only.
        </para>
        <para>
          By default, the list of image files is sorted alphabetically based
          on the image filenames. The column names above the image list can be
          used to select how you want the list sorted. Clicking on a column
          will use that column to sort the list. A small triangle in the
          column name shows that it is currently being used to sort the list.
          If the triangle is pointing up, sorting is done ascending. Clicking
          again on the same column, will changing the sort order to descending
          and the triangle will be pointing down.
        </para>
        <para>
          Right-clicking an image or a folder in this list opens a context menu:
        </para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/file-context-menu.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>The image list context menu</caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Open With File Manager</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This is only enabled for folders. If enabled, you can open the
                selected folder in the default file browser on your computer.
                Note: this command currently does not work on Windows.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Copy Location</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This copies the location of the selected file to the clipboard.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to Bookmarks</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This allows you to add the selected folder as a bookmark.
                Bookmarks are shown in the area marked (5). This is disabled
                if you have selected a file instead of an image.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show Hidden Files</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When enabled, hidden files will be shown in the list of
                image files (3).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show Size Column</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When enabled, the size of each image will be shown in the list
                of image files (3).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show Type Column</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When enabled, the file type of each image will be shown in the
                list of image files (3).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show Time</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When enabled, the modified time will be shown for each image in
                the list of image files (3) in addition to the modified date.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Sort Folders before Files</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When enabled, any folders present in the currently selected
                folder, will be shown at the top of the list of image files (3).
                When disabled, the folders will be mixed together with the
                image files based on the selected sorting column.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--4-->
        <para>
          A thumbnail version of the selected image in the image list (3) is
          displayed in the <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> window on the right.
          If it is an image format recognized by <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, file
          size, dimensions and image composition are displayed below the
          preview window.
        </para>

        <tip>
          <para>
            If your image has been modified, but the thumbnail didn't update,
            you can click on the Preview image to update the thumbnail. To
            force updating the thumbnail even if it hasn't changed, use
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + click.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--5-->
        <para>
          This part of the list shows the folders that you have bookmarked.
          You can add bookmarks by using the
          <guilabel>Add to Bookmarks</guilabel> option that is shown
          when you right-click a folder in the image list panel (3).
        </para>
        <para>
          You can remove a bookmark by using the <guilabel>Remove</guilabel>
          command that is shown when you right click on a bookmark. This right
          click menu can also be used to <guilabel>Rename</guilabel> the
          bookmark. Renaming the bookmark does not rename the folder it
          points to.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--6-->
        <para>
          By clicking the <guilabel>Other Locations</guilabel> label, a list
          of other known locations and devices on your computer will open in
          the image list pane. You can use this for easier access to certain
          locations on your computer that may not be directly available in
          the folders list on the left.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--7-->
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Show All Files</guilabel> option, is usually unchecked.
          If you check this option, all files in the selected folder will be
          shown, instead of only the image files that GIMP recognizes.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--8-->
        <para>
          <guilabel>Select File Type</guilabel> can be used to explicitly set
          the image file format. It is a drop-down list that shows all image
          file formats that <acronym>GIMP</acronym> recognizes.
          In general you don't need to worry about this, because in most cases
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can determine the file type automatically.
        </para>
        <para>
          <!-- Added the below anchor to make sure we don't get a help page
               not found when pressing F1 in this part of the dialog. -->
          <anchor id="gimp-file-open-by-extension"/>
          The default is <guilabel>Automatically Detected</guilabel>, which
          causes <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to try to automatically detect
          the correct format.
        </para>
        <para>In the rare cases where neither the file extension nor internal
          information in the file are enough to tell <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          the file type, you can set it by selecting it from this list.
        </para>
        <tip>
          <para>
            Explicitly selecting the file type can be useful in certain cases.
            You can e.g. do this to explicitly load the merged Photoshop image
            as saved in a PSD image (if present). Since Photoshop images can't
            always be correctly loaded in GIMP, this allows you to view the
            image as it was intended by Photoshop.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-image-search-to-open">
    <title>Searching for an image to open</title>
    <para>
      When the Open Image dialog is active, you can type the name of a file or
      subfolder to perform a search. A search field appears and the contents of
      the location are filtered as you type. Any file or subfolder that fully
      or partially matches your search text will be displayed.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can search in <guilabel>Recent</guilabel> or any folder that you
      navigate to. Only the contents of the selected location are included in
      the search. The search will not check within subfolders of the
      selected location.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the Open Image dialog includes a search button (magnifying glass icon),
      you can click it to toggle searching on and off. The search button appears
      only when client-side decorations (CSD) are turned on, such as in some
      versions of the Xfce desktop environment.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The Search Button on the Open Image Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/open-image-search.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-image-color-profile-import">
    <title>Opening an image with a color profile</title>

    <figure>
      <title>The Keep the Embedded Working Space Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/icc-apply-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      When you open a non XCF image that has a color profile attached to it,
      GIMP will open a dialog asking you whether you want to keep the original
      profile, or convert it to GIMP's built-in sRGB color profile.
    </para>
    <para>
      Although we generally recommend to keep the color profile, using either
      choice is fine, since GIMP will do profile conversion in the background
      when needed.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        If you want GIMP to stop asking you this question then check the
        <guilabel>Don't ask me again</guilabel> option. If you change your mind,
        you can always restore the question by going into Preferences,
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-color-management">Color Management</link>,
        Policies, File Open behavior.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
