<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-pattern-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Patterns dialog</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Patterns</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-patterns.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Patterns dialog
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    In GIMP, a <emphasis>pattern</emphasis> is a small image used to
    fill areas by placing copies of side by side.  See the <link
    linkend='gimp-patterns'>Patterns</link> section for basic
    information on patterns and how they can be created and used.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    The Patterns dialog is used to select a pattern, by clicking on
    it in a list or grid view:  the selected pattern will then be shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  A few dozen more or
    less randomly chosen patterns are supplied with GIMP, and you can
    easily add new patterns of your own.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Patterns dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>tterns</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Create New Dock</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brushes, Patterns, and Gradients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        This gives you a dock containing three dialogs, with the
        Patterns dialog one of them.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox, by clicking on the pattern symbol in the
        Brush/Pattern/Gradient area.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>tterns</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>tterns</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tool Options dialog for the <link
        linkend='gimp-tool-clone'>Clone tool</link>, by 
        clicking on the Pattern icon button. This option appears
        because the Clone tool is capable of painting with patterns. 
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the patterns are laid out in a rectangular
      array, making it easy to see many at once and find the one you
      are looking for.  In List mode, the patterns are lined up in a
      list, with the names beside them.  
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Patterns dialog (Grid mode)</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      At the top appears the name of the currently selected patterns, and
      its dimenions in pixels.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the center appears a grid view of all available patterns, with
      the currently selected one outlined.  Clicking on one of them
      sets it as GIMP's current pattern, and causes it to appear in
      the Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Below the grid appear two buttons:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Delete Pattern</title>
          Pressing this button removes the pattern from the list and
          causes the file representing it to be deleted from disk.
          Note that you cannot remove any of the patterns that are
          supplied with GIMP and installed in the system
          <filename>patterns</filename> directory; you can only remove
          patterns that you have added to folders where you have write
          permission. 
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>


      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Refresh Patterns</title>
          Pressing this button causes GIMP to rescan the folders in
          your pattern search path, adding any newly discovered
          patterns to the list.  This button is useful if you add new
          patterns to a folder, and want to make them available
          without having to restart GIMP.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Patterns dialog (List view)</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-patterns-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Patterns dialog (List view)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      In this view, instead of a grid, you see a list of patterns,
      each labeled with its name and size.  Clicking on a row in the
      list sets that pattern as GIMP's current pattern, just as it
      does in the grid view.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      If you <emphasis>double-click</emphasis> on the name of a
      pattern, you will be able to edit the name.  Note that you are
      only allowed to rename patterns that you have added yourself,
      not the ones that are supplied with GIMP.  If you edit a name
      that you don't have permission to change, as soon as you hit
      return or move to a different control, the name will revert back
      to its previous value.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Everything else in the List view works the same way as it does
      in the Grid view.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

</sect1>
