<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-pattern-dialog' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Patterns dialog</title>
  <title lang="fr">Dialogue des motifs</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">图案对话框</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Patterns</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Motifs</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">图案</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure lang="en">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-patterns.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para>
      	  The Patterns dialog
      	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <informalfigure lang="fr">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-patterns.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para>
      	  Le dialogue des motifs
      	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <informalfigure lang="zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-patterns.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para>
	  图案对话框
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    In GIMP, a <emphasis>pattern</emphasis> is a small image used to
    fill areas by placing copies of side by side.  See the <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-patterns'>Patterns</link> section for basic
    information on patterns and how they can be created and used.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les motifs sont de petites images raccordables que vous pouvez 
    accoler en multiples exemplaires de façon à réaliser une image 
    plus grande sans raccord visible. Ils sont très utilisés pour la 
    création de fonds de page Web. Voyez <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-patterns'>Motifs</link> pour de plus amples 
    renseignements.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Vous pouvez les utiliser avec les outils 
    <link linkend='gimp-tool-bucket-fill'>Remplissage</link> et 
    <link linkend='gimp-tool-clone'>Cloner</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 中，<emphasis>图案</emphasis>是一个小图像，用作将它的拷贝一个连一个地填充区域。关于如何创建和使用它们的基本信息请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-patterns'>图案</link>章节。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Patterns dialog is used to select a pattern, by clicking on
    it in a list or grid view:  the selected pattern will then be shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  A few dozen more or
    less randomly chosen patterns are supplied with GIMP, and you can
    easily add new patterns of your own.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    图案对话框通过在以列表或阵列查看中点击图案来选中它：选中的图案然后会在工具箱的画笔/图案/渐变区域显示。GIMP 自带了二十多个有些随机选择的图案，您也可以很容易地添加新的。
  </para>
 
  <para lang='en'>
    The Patterns dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le Dialogue des Motifs est un dialogue attachable; voyez la 
    section <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogues et attachements</link>
    pour plus d'informations. Il peut être appelé de différentes 
    façons:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    图案对话框是一个可停靠对话框；请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>。有多种方式开启它：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>tterns</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>    
        在工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>图案</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>Create New Dock</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brushes, Patterns, and Gradients</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        This gives you a dock containing three dialogs, with the
        Patterns dialog one of them.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>    
        在工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guisubmenu>创建新停靠栏</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>画笔，图案和渐变</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
        将出现一个带三个对话框停靠栏，图案对话框是其中一个。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox, by clicking on the pattern symbol in the
        Brush/Pattern/Gradient area.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        在工具箱的 画笔/图案/渐变 区域点击图案标志。
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>tterns</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">      
      <para>    
        在图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>图案</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>P<accel>a</accel>tterns</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">      
      <para>    
        在任何可停靠对话框的页签菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>添加页签</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>图案</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tool Options dialog for the <link
        linkend='gimp-tool-clone'>Clone tool</link>, by 
        clicking on the Pattern icon button. This option appears
        because the Clone tool is capable of painting with patterns. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        在<link linkend='gimp-tool-clone'>克隆工具</link>的工具选项对话框中，点击图案图标按钮。该选项的出现是由于克隆工具可以使用图案进行涂画。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang="fr">
    <listitem>
      <para>      
      A partir du menu de la Boîte à outils: 
      <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>ichier/<accel>D</accel>ialogues/Moti<accel>f</accel>s</guimenuitem>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>      
      A partir de la Boîte à outils: 
      Clic sur la boîte du motif actif. 
      </para> 
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      A partir du menu Image: 
      <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>ialogues/Moti<accel>f</accel>s</guimenuitem>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      A partir d'un autre dialogue en cliquant sur le petit bouton 
      <inlinegraphic fileref="../images/dialogs/stock-menu-left-12.png"/> 
      représentant un triangle pour l'ajouter comme onglet à ce dialogue. 
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">阵列/列表模式</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the patterns are laid out in a rectangular
      array, making it easy to see many at once and find the one you
      are looking for.  In List mode, the patterns are lined up in a
      list, with the names beside them.  
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans le menu Onglets, vous avez le choix entre <guimenuitem>
      Voir comme une liste</guimenuitem> et <guimenuitem>Voir comme 
      une grille</guimenuitem>. En mode grille, les motifs sont 
      disposés dans un agréable tableau rectangulaire. En mode 
      Liste, les motifs sont alignés verticalement avec leur nom.   
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在页签菜单中，您能在<guimenuitem>以阵列方式列查看</guimenuitem>和<guimenuitem>以列表方式查看</guimenuitem>间选择。阵列模式中，图案形状按矩形阵列排列，这样一次能看到多个并容易寻找。列表模式中，图案在列表中排成一列，其名字对应地列在一旁。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Patterns dialog (Grid mode)</title>
    <title lang="fr">La palette des motifs (en mode Grille)</title> 
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用图案对话框(阵列模式)</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      At the top appears the name of the currently selected patterns, and
      its dimenions in pixels.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En haut apparaît le nom du motif sélectionné, et ses simensions 
      en pixels. 
    </para> 
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在对话框上方显示当前选择图案的名字和画笔的像素大小。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the center appears a grid view of all available patterns, with
      the currently selected one outlined.  Clicking on one of them
      sets it as GIMP's current pattern, and causes it to appear in
      the Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Au centre se trouve une grille contenant tous les motifs 
      disponibles. En cliquant sur l'un d'eux, vous en faites le motif 
      actif qui apparaît dans la zone Brosse/Motif/Dégradé de la Boîte 
      à outils.  
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      正中则是所有可用图案以阵列方式排列，用方框显示当前被选中的图案。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Below the grid appear two buttons:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Sous la grille, on trouve deux boutons:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      阵列下有两个按钮：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id='gimp-pattern-delete' />
        <formalpara>
          <title lang='en'>Delete Pattern</title>
          <title lang='fr'>Supprimer</title>
          <title lang="zh_CN">删除图案</title>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Pressing this button removes the pattern from the list and
	    causes the file representing it to be deleted from disk.  Note
	    that you cannot remove any of the patterns that are supplied
	    with GIMP and installed in the system
	    <filename>patterns</filename> directory; you can only remove
	    patterns that you have added to folders where you have write
	    permission. 
	  </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Supprime le motif de la palette et du disque dur. Ne concerne 
            que les motifs personnels.
          </para>  
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按下该按钮将从列表和磁盘中删除该图案。要注意的是，您不能删除 GIMP 自带的和在系统 <filename>patterns</filename> 目录中的任何图案;只能删除那些您添加到有可写权限文件夹中的图案。
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <anchor id='gimp-pattern-refresh' />
        <formalpara>
          <title lang='en'>Refresh Patterns</title>
          <title lang='fr'>Rafraîchir</title>
          <title lang="zh_CN">刷新图案</title>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Pressing this button causes GIMP to rescan the folders in your
	    pattern search path, adding any newly discovered patterns to
	    the list.  This button is useful if you add new patterns to a
	    folder, and want to make them available without having to
	    restart GIMP.
	  </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Passe en revue les dossiers signalés dans vos chemins de 
            recherche de motifs, et ajoute à la liste ceux qui sont 
            nouveaux. La liste est ainsi mise à jour sans qu'il soit besoin 
            de re-démarrer Gimp.
          </para> 
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按下该按钮使 GIMP 重新扫描图案搜索路径中的文件夹，如果发现新的图案则添加到列表中。通过该按钮可用在您添加新图案到文件夹时，不需要重新启动 GIMP 就是可以使用它们。
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Patterns dialog (List view)</title>
    <title lang="fr">La palette des motifs (en mode Liste)</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用图案对话框(列表模式)</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang='en;zh_CN'>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-patterns-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang='fr'>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-patterns-list.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang='en'>
            The Patterns dialog (List view)
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            Le dialogue des motifs (vue sous forme de liste)
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            图案对话框(列表模式)
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      In this view, instead of a grid, you see a list of patterns,
      each labeled with its name and size.  Clicking on a row in the
      list sets that pattern as GIMP's current pattern, just as it
      does in the grid view.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les motifs sont disposés en liste, chacun avec son nom et sa 
      taille. Le clic sur un des rangs établit le motif correspondant 
      comme motif actif. 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该模式中不同于阵列模式，您可以看到图案的一个列表，每个对应了其名字和大小。点击该列表中的一行则使该图案成为 GIMP 中的当前图案，这是和阵列模式中一样的。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      If you <emphasis>double-click</emphasis> on the name of a
      pattern, you will be able to edit the name.  Note that you are
      only allowed to rename patterns that you have added yourself,
      not the ones that are supplied with GIMP.  If you edit a name
      that you don't have permission to change, as soon as you hit
      return or move to a different control, the name will revert back
      to its previous value.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un double clic sur le nom d'un motif permet d'éditer et de 
      modifier ce nom, à condition qu'il s'agisse d'un motif personnel.
    </para> 
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      如果<emphasis>双击</emphasis>图案的名字，您可以编辑它。注意，您只允许改变您自己创建或安装的画笔的名字，GIMP 自带的则不行。在您对您没有改变权限的图案进行编辑时，当敲下回车或点其它地方时，其名字就会回到原来的名字。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Everything else in the List view works the same way as it does
      in the Grid view.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Tout le reste fonctionne de la même façon qu'en mode Grille.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      列表模式中的其它地方和使用阵列模式一样。
    </para>
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
