<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-canvas-modifiers">
  <title>Canvas Interaction Modifiers</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Modifiers</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Canvas Interaction</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Modifiers Preferences</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-canvas-interaction-modifiers.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This page allows you to change the key modifiers for any of the available
    buttons of your input devices (mouse, stylus, etc.), except for the primary
    button. This can be used to change the actions performed on the canvas when
    a certain button in combination with a key modifier is pressed.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The preferences dialog can be accessed from the main menu, through
      <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
       <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Modifiers</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Click here to set a button's modifiers</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Clicking on this button with one of the buttons of your input devices
            (except the primary button) allows you to change the command that
            each modifier for that button performs when used.
          </para>
          <para>
            When clicked, it shows a list of the current commands assigned to
            each of the modifiers for the button you clicked. Only the modifiers
            that have commands attached to them will be shown. You can add a new
            item to the list by clicking the button below the list, or remove a
            modifier that you don't need by clicking the button to the right of
            each item.
          </para>
          <para>
            To change what a modifier does, click on the list, which will show
            you all available choices. To change the modifier that performs a
            command click on the modifier column on the left and press the
            modifier or modifiers that you would like to use.
            Multiple modifiers are allowed, e.g. Shift+Ctrl+middle mouse button
            (shown as button 2 of System Aggregated Pointer), is by default
            attached to <guilabel>Rotate View by 15 degree steps</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reset Saved Modifiers Settings to Default Values</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Clicking this button resets all modifiers for your input devices to
            their default values.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
