<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-07-17 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2008-02-04 Vérification + compléments par jpl in french
  2007-09-30 AntI: Added 'es'
  2007-03-25 KoSt: added 'no'
  2006-11-01 lexa: make docbook compliant
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-window-management">
  <title>Window Management</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Window management</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image Windows</primary>
    <secondary>Basic settings</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Window Management Preferences</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-window-management.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This page lets you customize the way windows are handled in GIMP. You
    should note that GIMP does not manipulate windows directly, instead it
    sends requests to the window manager (i.e., to Windows if you are running
    in Windows; to Mutter if you are running in a standard GNOME setup in
    Linux; etc). Because there are many window managers, and not all of them
    are well behaved, it cannot be guaranteed that the functions described
    here will actually work as described. However, if you are using a modern,
    standards-compliant window manager, they ought to.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The preferences dialog can be accessed from the main menu, through
      <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
       <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Window Manager Hints</title>
      <varlistentry>
      <!--TO TRANSLATORS: This is for Window Manager Hints, not general hints -->
        <term>Hint for docks and toolbox</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The choices you make here determine how the Toolbox, and the docks
            that hold dialogs, will be treated. You have three possibilities
            for them:
          </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you choose <guilabel>Normal Window</guilabel>, they will
                  be treated like any other windows.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you choose <guilabel>Utility Window</guilabel>, the
                  reduce button in the title bar is absent and the docks will
                  remain permanently on your screen.
                </para>
                <figure>
                  <title>Utility window title bar</title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/preferences/normal-title-bar.png" />
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para>
                        Normal title bar
                      </para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/preferences/utility-title-bar.png" />
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para>
                        The title bar in a utility window
                      </para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you choose <guilabel>Keep above</guilabel>, they will be
                  kept in front of every other window at all times.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            Note that changes you make here will not take effect until the
            next time you start <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Focus</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Activate the focused image</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Normally, when you focus an image window (usually indicated by a
            change in the color of the frame), it becomes the <quote>active
            image</quote> for GIMP, and therefore the target for any
            image-related actions you perform.  Some people, though, prefer
            to set up their window managers such that any window entered by
            the pointer is automatically focused.  If you do this, you
            may find that it is inconvenient for focused images to
            automatically become active, and may be happier if you uncheck
            this option.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Window Positions</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save window positions on exit</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this option is checked, the next time you start GIMP,
            you will see the same set of dialog windows, in the same
            positions they occupied when you last exited.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Open windows on the same monitor they were open before</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will try to restore windows
            on the same monitor they were used previously. When disabled,
            windows will appear on the currently used monitor.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Window Positions Now</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This button is only useful if <quote>Save window positions on
            exit</quote> is unchecked. It allows you to set up your windows
            they way you like, click the button, and then have them come up in
            that arrangement each time you start GIMP.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reset Saved Window Positions to Default Values</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you decide that you are unhappy with the arrangement of windows
            you have saved, and would rather go back to the default
            arrangement than spend time moving them around, you can do so by
            pressing this button.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
