<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2020-04-09 j.h: first version
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-import-export">
  <title>Image Import and Export</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Using</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Image Import and Export</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image Import and Export</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Image Import and Export Preferences</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-import-export.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This page lets you customize settings related to importing and
    exporting images.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The preferences dialog can be accessed from the main menu, through
      <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
       <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Import Policies</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Import Policies</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Promote imported images to floating point precision</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, all imported images have their <link
            linkend="gimp-image-precision">precision</link> changed to
            32-bit floating point.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dither images when promoting to floating point</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When the previous setting is enabled, this setting allows you to
            choose whether
            <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-dithering">dithering</link> should
            be applied when a lower precision image is changed to 32-bit floating
            point.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Add an alpha channel to imported images</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, an alpha channel is automatically added to any imported
            image that doesn't have one yet. This can be useful if you usually
            require an alpha channel to be present for your workflow.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Color profile policy</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When importing an image that has a color profile attached to it,
            you can choose here what action needs to be taken. See
            <link linkend="gimp-prefs-file-open-policy">File Open Behavior</link>
            in the Color Management preferences.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id ="gimp-image-metadata-rotation-import">
        <term>Metadata rotation policy</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When importing an image that has metadata about the rotation of the
            image attached to it, you can choose here what action needs to be
            taken.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Ask what to do</guilabel> This is the default. Every
                time you open an image with rotation metadata, a dialog opens
                that asks you whether to rotate the image according to the
                metadata.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Discard metadata without rotating</guilabel> When
                selecting this, rotation metadata will be ignored when opening
                an image.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Rotate the image then discard metadata</guilabel> When
                selecting this, an image will always be rotated according to the
                metadata when it is opened. After that is done, the rotation
                metadata is discarded and replaced by default values for the
                rotation metadata.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Export Policies</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Export Policies</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <note>
        <para>
          The following export policies define the
          <emphasis role="bold">default</emphasis> values when exporting an
          image. Most formats have image export dialogs where, among other things,
          you can further adjust the relevant setting for that specific format.
          These per format settings are remembered across restarts.
        </para>
        <para>
          Not all image formats support all of the below settings. They are only
          relevant for image formats that support the setting.
        </para>
        <para>
          It is good to be aware of the implications of including certain
          metadata. Metadata can contain sensitive personal information that you
          may want to review first before deciding to include it or not.
          Examples are GPS metadata that can show an exact location, or name and
          address of the creator of the image.
        </para>
      </note>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export the image's color profile by default</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the default for exporting images is to include the
            color profile.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export the image's comment by default</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the default for exporting images is to include the
            comment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export the image's thumbnail by default</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the default for exporting images is to include the
            thumbnail.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export exif metadata by default when available</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the default for exporting images is to include
            exif metadata.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export XMP metadata by default when available</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the default for exporting images is to include
            XMP metadata.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export IPTC metadata by default when available</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the default for exporting images is to include
            IPTC metadata.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Export File Type</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Export File Type</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Default export file type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This setting allows you to select what file format should be used
            by default when exporting an image, without explicitly choosing an
            extension of a known image file format.
          </para>
          <para>
            Note that this is only relevant when exporting a new image created
            in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            When exporting an image that was previously imported,
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses the extension of that imported image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Raw Image Importer</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Raw Image Importer</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Plug-in</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This setting shows a list of known plug-ins that can be used for
            opening and processing RAW image formats. Most common apps used here
            are Darktable and RawTherapee. If no plug-in is registered, GIMP
            will show a placeholder value here.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
