<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--Version history
  2017-02-19 j.h : update
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-input-devices">
  <title>Input Devices</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Preferences</primary>
    <secondary>Input Devices</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Input Devices</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Input Devices Preferences</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/preferences/input-devices.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The preferences dialog can be accessed from the main menu, through
      <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
       <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Pointers and Paint Tools</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Mouse pointers</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pointer mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option has no effect unless <guilabel>Show pointer for paint
            tools</guilabel> is checked.  If it is, you have three choices:
            <guilabel>Tool icon</guilabel>, which causes a small iconic
            representation of the currently active tool to be shown beside
            the cursor; <guilabel>Tool icon with crosshair</guilabel>, which
            shows the icon as well as a crosshair indicating the center of
            the cursor; or <guilabel>Crosshair only</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pointer handedness</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option decides the direction of the pointer. The default is
            <guilabel>Right-handed</guilabel>. When
            <guilabel>Left-handed</guilabel> is chosen, the pointer is flipped
            horizontally.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show brush outline</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this option is checked, then when you use a paint tool, the
            outline of the brush will be shown on the image as you move the
            pointer around. On slow systems, if the brush is very large, this
            could occasionally cause some lag in GIMP's ability to follow your
            movements: if so, switching this off might help. Otherwise, you
            will probably find it quite useful.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Snap brush outline to stroke</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This requires <guilabel>Show brush outline</guilabel> to be enabled.
            When this setting is also enabled, the brush outline will snap to
            individual dabs when painting. The dabs are where the brush paints
            on the canvas.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show pointer for paint tools</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this is checked, a cursor will be shown. This is in addition to
            the brush outline, if the brush outline is being shown. The type
            of cursor is determined by the next option.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Extended Input Devices</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pointer Input API</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">This setting is only present on Windows.</emphasis>
            On Windows, when you use a touch screen, or a pen to draw on a tablet,
            there are two ways for GIMP to interact with it. This setting lets
            you choose which one to use.
          </para>
          <para>
            In general for newer drawing devices, <guilabel>Windows Ink</guilabel>
            is the preferred way. If that doesn't work for you, try the older
            <guilabel>Wintab</guilabel> API.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Share tool and tool options between input devices</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, the same tool and tool options will be used for all
            input devices. No tool switching will occur when the input device
            changes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Configure Extended Input Devices</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-help-input-devices"/>
          <para>
            This button opens a dialog that allows you to configure the input
            devices associated with your computer: tablet, MIDI keyboard, etc.
            If you have a tablet, you will see a dialog like this:
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Preferences for a tablet</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/preferences/input-devices-tablet.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            For each of the input devices you can set its
            <guilabel>Mode</guilabel>. This decides how <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            translates the input from the device to your screen.
            For a mouse this is usually set to <guilabel>disabled</guilabel> and
            for other devices to <guilabel>Screen</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The only other choice for mode is <guilabel>Window</guilabel>.
            Currently there don't seem to be any differences with
            <guilabel>Screen</guilabel>.
            Unless you know what you are doing, this is better left alone.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save input device settings on exit</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you check this box, GIMP remembers the tool, color, pattern, and
            brush you were using the last time you quit.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Input Device Settings Now</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This immediately saves the current input device settings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Reset Saved Input Device Settings to Default Values
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Delete your settings and restore default settings.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
