<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2008-07-20 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2007-01-29 added Spanish content by manuq
  2006-11-01 lexa: made the file docbook compliant
  2008-02-04 Vérification + compléments par jpl in french
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-folders">
  <title>Folders</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Folders</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title>Folders Preferences</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-folders.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This page allows you to set the locations for two important folders used
    by GIMP for temporary files. The pages below it allow you to customize the
    locations searched for resources such as brushes etc.; see
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Data Folders</link>
    for a description that applies to them. You can change the folders here by
    editing the entries, or by pressing the buttons on the right to bring up a
    file chooser window.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The preferences dialog can be accessed from the main menu, through
      <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
       <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Temporary folder</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Swap folder</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Temporary folder</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This folder is used for temporary files: files created for temporary
            storage of working data, and then deleted within the same GIMP
            session. It does not require a lot of space or high performance. By
            default, a subdirectory called <filename>tmp</filename>
            in your personal GIMP directory is used, but if that disk is very
            cramped for space, or has serious performance issues, you can change
            it to a different directory. The directory must exist and be
            writable by you, or bad things will happen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Swap folder</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the folder used as a <quote>memory bank</quote> when the
            total size of images and data open in GIMP exceeds the available
            RAM. If you work
            with very large images, or images with many layers, or have many
            images open at once, GIMP can potentially use a considerable amount
            of swap space, so available disk space and performance are
            definitely things to think about for this folder. By default, it is
            set to your personal GIMP directory, but if you have another disk
            with more free space, or substantially better performance, you may
            see a significant benefit from moving your swap folder there. The
            directory must exist and be writable by you.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
