<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  "2007-08-24 j.h verified v2.4 : no change in "en".
  2007-05-19 ude: fixed calspair coords
  2006-03-06 lexa: reviewed and made docbook compliant
-->
<sect3 id="gimp-qmask" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect3info lang="en;de;es;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="en">2007-08-24</date>
        <authorinitials lang="en">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2006-03-09</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="es">2006-10-22</date>
        <authorinitials lang="es">manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="fr">2007-08-24</date>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect3info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Quick Mask</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Rychlá maska</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Schnellmaske</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Máscara rápida</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Masque rapide</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Maschera veloce</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Snarmaske</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Быстрая маска</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">快速蒙板</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Rychlá maska</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Dialogy</primary><secondary>Rychlá maska</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Schnellmaske</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>QuickMask</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Auswahlmaske</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Máscara rápida</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Diálogos</primary><secondary>Máscara rápida</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Maschera veloce</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestre</primary><secondary>Maschera veloce</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Snarmaske</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Dialogar</primary><secondary>Snarmaske</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Быстрая Маска</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Диалоги</primary><secondary>Быстрая Маска</secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs">Dialog Quick Mask</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Ansicht des Dialoges <quote>Schnellmaske</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Diálogo <quote>Máscara rápida</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">La fenêtre de dialogue <quote>Masque
          Rapide</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">La finestra maschera veloce</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Dialogen for Snarmaske</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Быстрая маска</phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en;cs;de;fr;it'>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="es">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/dialogs/no/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ru">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/dialogs/ru/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/dialogs/zh_CN/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    A <guilabel>Quick Mask</guilabel> is a
    <link linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'>Selection Mask</link>
    intended to be used temporarily to paint a selection. Temporarily means
    that, unlike a normal selection mask, it will be deleted from the
    channel list after its transformation to selection. The
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">selection tools</link>
    sometimes show their limits when they have to be used for doing complex
    drawing selection, as progressive. In this case, using the QuickMask is a
    good idea which can give very good results.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    <guilabel>Rychlá maska</guilabel> je dočasná
    <link linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'>maska výběru</link>
    určená k malbě výběru. Dočasná znamená, že na rozdíl od běžné masky výběru
    nebude po převedení do výběru uložená do seznamu.
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">Nástroje pro výběr</link>
    při tvorbě složitého výběru občas narážejí na hranice svých možností.
    Použití rychlé masky může v takových případech přinést mnohem lepší
    výsledky.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Eine <guilabel>Schnellmaske</guilabel> (engl. <foreignphrase>Quick
    Mask</foreignphrase>) ist eine besondere Form der <link
    linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Auswahlmaske</link> und wird vorrangig
    dafür genutzt, um schnell neue Auswahlen mit einem Pinselwerkzeug zu
    erstellen. So lassen sich vor allem sehr feine und auf ein Bildobjekt
    angepasste Auswahlen erstellen, wo die primären <link
    linkend="gimp-tools-selection">Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> an Ihre Grenzen
    stoßen.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Una <guilabel>máscara rápida</guilabel> es una <!-- PENDING:es link
    linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'-->máscara de selección<!--/link-->
    pensada para usarse temporalmente para pintar una selección.
    Temporalmente significa que, a diferencia de la máscara de selección
    normal, esta no se guarda en la lista luego de transformarse en selección.
    Las <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">herramientas de selección</link>
    a menudo dejan ver sus límites cuando se intentan usar para seleccionar
    formas complicadas, de manera progresiva.  En este caso, el empleo de la
    máscara rápida es una buena idea y puede dar muy buenos resultados.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Un <guilabel>Masque Rapide</guilabel> est un <link
    linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'>Masque de sélection</link> destiné à
    être utilisé temporairement pour réaliser graphiquement une sélection. On
    entend par temporairement qu'il ne sera pas conservé dans la liste des
    canaux après avoir été transformé en sélection contrairement à un masque
    de sélection conventionnel.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">outils de sélection</link>
    montrent parfois leurs limites lorsqu'il s'agit de créer des sélections
    aux contours complexes, voir progressifs. Dans ce cas l'utilisation du
    Masque rapide s'avère particulièrement efficace.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le terme anglais pour Masque rapide est <quote>Quick Mask</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Una <guilabel>Maschera veloce</guilabel> è una
    <link linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'>Maschera di Selezione</link>
    destinata ad essere utilizzata temporaneamente per disegnare una
    selezione. Con il termine temporaneamente si intende che, a differenza
    delle normali maschere di selezione, questa non viene salvata nella lista
    dopo essere stata trasformata in selezione. Alle volte gli
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">strumenti di selezione</link>
    mostrano i loro limiti nel disegnare progressivamente delle selezioni
    complesse. In questi casi, l'utilizzo della maschera veloce è una buona
    idea che può portare a dei risultati molto buoni.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Ei <guilabel>Snarmaske</guilabel> er ei
    <link linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'>Markeringsmaske</link> tenkt
    brukt temporært for å teikne på ei markering. Med temporært meiner ein
    her at, ulikt vanlege markeringsmasker, blir snarmaska ikkje lagra i
    lista etter at ho er omforma til ei markering. Når du arbeider med svært
    komplekse bilete, kan det hende at
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">markeringsverktøya</link> møter
    grensene sine. I slike høve er snarmaska god å ty til, ofte med svært
    godt resultat.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    <guilabel>Быстрая маска</guilabel> - это
    <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">маска выделенной области</link>,
    которая накладывается временно на изображение, чтобы нарисовать границы
    выделения. "Временно" значит, что, в отличие от обычной маски, она не
    будет сохранена в списке масок после преобразования в выделение.
    Возможности
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">инструментов выделения</link>
    велики, но далеко не безграничны. Поэтому для того, чтобы облегчить
    процесс создания сложной выделенной области, имеет смысл
    использовать быструю маску.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <guilabel>快速蒙板</guilabel>是涂画选区时临时使用的一种<link linkend='dialogs-selection-masks'>选区蒙板</link>。由于它是临时的，就不像普通的选区蒙板，它在转变为选区后不会在保存在列表中。<link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">选择工具</link>在进行复杂图形选取时能力非常有限。在这种情况下，使用快速蒙板会使这一切变得简单。
  </para>

  <sect4>
    <title>
      <!-- en cs fr it ru zh_CN FIXME: this is not activating tool, but dialog -->
      <phrase lang="en">Activate dialog</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Dialogaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activación del diálogo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Включение быстрой маски</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">启动工具</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The QuickMask can be activated in the following order, from the
          image-menu: <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>elect/Toggle
            <accel>Q</accel>uickMask</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Rychlou masku lze aktivovat z nabídky obrázku volbou
          <guimenuitem>Vybrat/Přepnout rychlou masku</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Durch einen Mausklick auf die Schaltfläche, die sich in der
          rechten unteren Ecke des Bildfensters befindet, aktivieren Sie
          die <quote>Schnellmaske</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          La máscara rápida se puede activar siguiendo en este orden el menú
          de la imagen: <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>eleccionar/Activar
          máscara rápida</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le Masque rapide peut être activé à partir de la barre de menus
          de l'image : <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>élection/(Dés)
            <accel>a</accel>ctiver le masque rapide</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          La maschera veloce può essere attivata dal menu immagine nel
          seguente ordine:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>S</accel>eleziona</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Commuta maschera <accel>v</accel>eloce</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du kan aktivere snarmaska frå biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Markér</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Slå av/på snarmaske</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Для включения быстрой маски можно воспользоваться пунктом меню
          изображения:
          <guimenuitem><accel>В</accel>ыделение/Переключить быструю
           маску</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          快速蒙板可以通过以下步骤开启，在图像菜单中：
            <guimenuitem>选择/切换快速蒙板</guimenuitem>，
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The QuickMask can also be activated by clicking the left-bottom
          button showed in red on the screenshot.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Rychlou masku lze také aktivovat kliknutím na tlačítko v levém
          dolním rohu obrázku (na snímku obrazovky je červeně zvýrazněné).
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Eine Schnellmaske lässt sich über das Bildmenü aufrufen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>In <accel>K</accel>anal speichern</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          La máscara rápida también se puede activar clicando en el botón de
          la izquierda que se muestra en la captura de pantalla.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le Masque rapide peut aussi être activé en cliquant sur le bouton
          en bas à gauche, en rouge sur la capture d'écran.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          La maschera veloce può essere attivata anche facendo clic sul
          pulsante in basso a sinistra che nell'illustrazione è evidenziato
          in rosso.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          eller enklare ved å klikke på den vesle knappen nede i venstre
          hjørne av biletvindauget, som vist på skjermdumpen.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Однако, гораздо быстрее это делается при помощи кнопки,
          расположенной в левом нижнем углу окна изображения
          (на скриншоте она выделена красным).
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
           也可以点击图像窗口中左下角有红色外框的按钮，
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          It can also be activated by using <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap>
          shortcut.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Rychlou masku lze také aktivovat klávesovou zkratkou
          <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Die Schnellmaske kann ebenfalls über das Tastenkürzel
          <keycombo><keycap>Umschalt</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>
          aufgerufen werden.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          También se puede activar por medio del atajo de teclado
          <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Il peut aussi être activé en utilisant le raccourci
          <keycap>Maj+Q</keycap>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Può anche essere attivata usando la combinazione di tasti
          <keycap>Maiusc+Q</keycap>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du kan også bruke snartastane
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>+<keycap>Q</keycap>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Кроме того, быстрая маска переключается с помощью клавиш
          быстрого доступа <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          或使用快捷键 <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect4>

  <sect4>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Creating a Quick Mask</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Vytvoření rychlé masky</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Erstellen einer <quote>Schnellmaske</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Creación de una máscara rápida</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Créer un Masque rapide</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Creazione di una maschera veloce</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å lage ei snarmaske</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Создание быстрой маски</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">创建快速蒙板</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang='en'>
      To initialize a <guilabel>Quick Mask</guilabel>,
      click the bottom-left button in the image window. If a selection was
      active in your image, then its content appears unchanged while the
      border is covered by a tranlucent red color. If no selection was active
      then all the image is covered by a tranlucent red color. At every
      moment you can hide the mask by clicking on the eye icon
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      in front of the <guilabel>QMask</guilabel>.
      From the channel dialog you can double click on the name or the
      thumbnail to edit the <guilabel>QMask</guilabel>
      attributes. Then you can changethe <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel>
      and its filling color. Once a quick mask is initialized click on it to
      be sure it is selected and blue highlighted in the list, and start to
      paint on it with any GIMP paint tool. The mask is coded in gray tones,
      so you must use white or gray to decrease the area limited by the mask
      and black to increase it. The area painted in light or dark gray will
      be transition areas for the selection like feathering. When your mask
      is ready, click again on the bottom-left button in the image window and
      the quick maskwill be removed from the channel list and converted to
      aselection. Quick mask's purpose is to paint a selection and its
      transitions with the paint tools without worrying about managing
      selection masks. It's a good way to isolate asubject in a picture
      because once the selection is made you only have to remove its content
      (or inverse if the subject is in the selection).
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Režim <guilabel>rychlé masky</guilabel>
      zahájíte kliknutím na tlačítko v levém dolním rohu okna obrázku. Pokud
      ve vašem obrázku byl aktivní výběr, bude jeho obsah zobrazen beze změny,
      zatímco všechno ostatní bude pokryto průsvitnou červenou barvou. Pokud
      aktivní výběr neexistoval, bude touto barvou pokryt celý obrázek. Masku
      můžete kdykoliv skrýt kliknutím na ikonu oka
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> před kanálem <guilabel>Rychlá maska</guilabel>.
      V dialogu Kanály můžete dvojitým poklepáním na jméno kanálu rychlé
      masky nebo jeho náhled zobrazit dialog, ve kterém můžete změnit atributy
      rychlé masky. Můžete zde změnit krytí a barvu použitou k jejímu
      zobrazení. jste-li v režimu rychlé masky, ujistěte se, že je rychlá
      maska v seznamu vybrána a barevně zvýrazněna a začněte ji upravovat
      pomocí libovolných nástrojů. Maska je uložena v podobě šedých tónů, k
      rozšíření vybrané oblasti používejte bílou barvu, černou k jejímu
      zmenšení. Oblasti v šedých odstínech jsou oblasti přechodné, částečně
      vybrané. Jakmile je maska hotova, klikněte znovu na tlačítko v levém
      dolním rohu okna obrázku a rychlá maska bude opět převedena na výběr.
      Smyslem rychlé masky je možnost upravovat výběr pomocí kreslících
      nástrojů bez nutnosti starat se o masky výběru. Hodí se dobře k oddělení
      objektu od pozadí.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Die Schnellmaske wird durch einen Klick auf die Schaltfläche in der
      linken unteren Ecke des Bildfensters aktiviert. Standardmäßig wird das
      Bild nun rötlich eingefärbt, welches die Maske präsentiert. Ist eine
      Auswahl vor Aktivieren der Schnellmaske aktiv, so wird die bestehende
      Auswahl als durchscheinender Bildbestandteil sichtbar. Der Modus
      <quote>Schnellmaske</quote> kann mit einem weiteren Klick auf die
      linke untere Schaltfläche beendet werden. Dann werden die vorgenommenen
      Änderungen in diesem Modus in eine Auswahl konvertiert.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Bei aktiver <quote>Schnellmaske</quote> erscheint ein Eintrag mit dem
      Namen <guilabel>Qmask</guilabel> im Kanaldialog. Die Sichtbarkeit sowie
      andere Kanalattribute können wie alle anderen Auswahlmasken mit einem
      Klick auf das Augensymbol <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> beeinflusst werden. Die Füllfarbe der Schnellmaske kann über
      die Schaltfläche der
      <link linkend='gimp-channel-edit'>Kanaleigenschaften</link> verändert
      werden.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Um eine neue Auswahl über die Schnellmaske anzulegen, benutzen Sie
      einfach ein Pinselwerkzeug ihrer Wahl. Benutzen Sie die Farbe Weiß, um
      die neue Auswahl zu erstellen. Sie werden merken, dass die Deckkraft
      des rötlichen Farbtons der Schnellmaske durch das Malen im Bild
      entfernt wird. Wenn Sie Schwarz als Malfarbe benutzen, wird die Auswahl
      entfernt. Kennzeichnend ist hier wiederum, dass der rötliche Farbton
      der Schnellmaske das Bild füllt.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Para comenzar a hacer una <guilabel>máscara rápida</guilabel>, haga
      clic en el botón que se halla en la esquina inferior izquierda de la
      ventana de la imagen.  Si había una selección activa en su imagen, su
      contenido aparece sin modificación mientras que todo lo demás aparece
      cubierto por un color rojo traslúcido.  Si no había una selección
      activa entonces toda la imagen aparece cubierta con el tinte rojo.
      Puede ocultar en todo momento la máscara clicando en el icono con forma
      de ojo
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      que se encuentra delante de <guilabel>Máscara rápida</guilabel> en el
      diálogo de canales.  Puede hacer doble clic sobre el nombre o sobre la
      previsualización para editar los atributos de la <guilabel>máscara
      rápida</guilabel>.  Luego puede cambiar su opacidad y su color de
      relleno.  Una vez que haya inicializado a la máscara haga clic sobre
      ella para asegurarse de que se encuentra seleccionada en la lista de
      canales, y comienze a pintar con cualquier herramienta de pintura.  La
      máscara es de escala de grises, así que puede emplear blanco o tonos
      claros para disminuir el área limitada por la máscara, y negro o tonos
      oscuros para aumentarla.  Las áreas pintadas en tonos foscuros o claros
      serán partes parcialmente seleccionadas.  Cuando su máscara esté lista,
      haga clic nuevamente en el botón de la esquina inferior izquierda de la
      ventana de la imagen.  Al hacer esto la máscara rápida se quita de la
      lista de canales y se convierte en una selección.  El propósito de la
      máscara rápida es el de poder pintar una selección y sus transiciones
      con las herramientas de pintura, sin preocuparse en manipular máscaras
      de selección.  Es una muy buena forma de aislar un objeto en una
      imagen:
      una vez que la selección esté hecha sólo tiene que borrar su contenido.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour initialiser un <guilabel>Masque Rapide</guilabel>
      cliquez depuis la fenêtre d'image dans le bouton en bas à gauche. Si
      dans votre image une sélection était active alors le contenu de votre
      sélection apparait inchangé tandis que ce qui entoure votre sélection
      est masqué par une couleur rouge semi-transparente. Si aucune sélection
      n'était active, alors tout est recouvert d'une couleur rouge
      semi-transparente. Vous pouvez à tout moment (dés)activer la visibilité
      du Masque en cliquant sur l'icône
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      devant le Masque rapide.
      Depuis le dialogue des Canaux les paramètres du
      Masque Rapide sont accessibles via un double-clic sur son
      nom ou sa vignette
      <guiicon>
         <inlinemediaobject>
           <imageobject>
             <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-edit-16.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      vous pouvez dès lors changer l' <guilabel>Opacité</guilabel>
      et la Couleur de remplissage. Une fois qu'un Masque rapide est
      initialisé, cliquez dessus pour être sûr qu'il soit activé et surligné
      en bleu dans la liste, vous pouvez dessiner dedans avec tous les outils
      de dessin de Gimp. Attention le masque est codé en niveaux de gris, il
      faut donc utiliser du blanc ou du gris pour diminuer la zone délimitée
      par le masque et du noir pour l'augmenter. Les zones dessinées en gris
      clair ou foncé seront des zones de transitions pour la sélection,
      l'équivalent d'un adoucissement. Une fois votre Masque rapide terminé
      cliquez à nouveau dans la fenêtre d'image dans le bouton en bas à
      gauche. Le Masque rapide est supprimé dans la liste des canaux et
      transformé en sélection. Le Masque rapide sert donc à dessiner une
      sélection, y compris les transitions, avec les outils de dessin de Gimp
      sans se soucier d'une quelconque gestion des masques de sélection. Il
      est parfaitement adapté pour détourer un sujet dans une photographie
      car une fois la sélection obtenue il suffit d'effacer son contenu (ou
      l'inverse si le sujet est dans la sélection).
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Per attivare una <guilabel>Maschera veloce</guilabel>,
      è necessario fare clic sul pulsante in basso a sinistra nella finestra
      immagine. Se nell'immagine c'era una selezione attiva, il suo contenuto
      appare immutato, mentre cio che la circonda appare ricoperto da un
      colore rosso trasparente. Se non era attiva alcuna selezione allora
      l'intera immagine appare ricoperta in rosso trasparente. In ogni
      momento si può nascondere la maschera facendo clic sull'icona con
      l'occhio
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      prima della <guilabel>Maschera veloce</guilabel>.
      Nella finestra dei canali si può fare un doppio clic sul nome o sulla
      minatura della <guilabel>Maschera veloce</guilabel>
      per modificarne le proprietà. Inoltre si può modificare la sua
      <guilabel>Opacità</guilabel>
      ed il suo colore di riempimento. Una volta che la maschera veloce è
      stata creata, è meglio farci sopra un clic per assicurarsi che sia
      selezionata ed evidenziata in blu nella lista, dopodichè di si può
      iniziare a dipingergi sopra con qualsiasi strumento di disegno di Gimp.
      La maschera è codificata in toni di grigio, perciò bisogna utilizzare
      il bianco o il grigio per diminuire le zone delimitate dalla maschera
      oppure il nero per aumentarle. Le zone colorate in grigio chiaro o
      scuro, saranno delle aree di transizione per la selezione, come
      sfumate.
      Quando la maschera è pronta, facendo nuovamente clic sul pulsante in
      basso a sinistra nella finestra immagine, la maschera veloce verrà
      rimossa dalla lista dei canali e convertita in una selezione. Lo scopo
      della maschera veloce è quello di disegnare una selezione e le sue
      transizioni, usando gli strumenti di disegno, senza doversi preoccupare
      di dover gestire delle maschere di selezione. E' un buon modo per
      isolare un soggetto in un'immagine, dato che una volta che la selezione
      è stata fatta bisogna solo rimuovere il suo contenuto (o viceversa se
      il soggetto è nella selezione).
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Den enklaste måten å setje startverdiane for
      <guilabel>Snarmaske</guilabel>, er å klikke på den vesle knappen
      nede i venstre hjørne av biletvindauget. Dersom du har ei aktiv
      markering i bietet, vil denne vere uandra, men alt som ikkje er
      markert blir dekka av ei gjennomsiktig, raud maske. Dersom det ikkje
      er ei markering i biletet, blir heile biletet dekka. Du kan skjule
      maska ved å klikke på augeikonet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      framføre <guilabel>Snarmaske</guilabel> i kanaldialogen. Du kan
      også redigere kanaleigenskapane ved å dobbeltklikke på miniatyren
      i kanaldialogen. Då kan du forandra dekkevne og farge for maska.
      Før du teiknar på snarmaska, bør du forsikra deg om at ho er aktiv.
      Sjå etter i kanaldialogen at ho er markert med blå, eller i noen
      system grøn, farge og klikk på maska dersom ho ikkje er markert.
      Du kan teikne på maska med alle teikneverktøya. Sidan maska blir
      koda i gråtoner, er det like greitt å bruke kvit eller grå farge for å
      utvida maska og svart for å avgrense henne. Områda som er teikna
      med lyse eller mørke gråtoner vil vere meir eller mindre markerte,
      omlag som når du bruker fjørkantar. Når maska er ferdig, klikk ein
      gong til på knappen i nedre, venstre hjørne av biletvindauget for å
      fjerne maska frå lista og omforme ho til ei markering. Føremålet med
      snarmaska er å lettvindt kunne teikne ei markering med varierande
      grad av markering utan å bry seg om styret med å bruke
      markeringsmasker. Snarmaska er ein god måte å isolere eit område
      av biletet på. Når du først har laga markeringa, kan du enkelt
      forandra innhaldet i og utsjånaden til maska og såleis maskera bort
      deler av biletet.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Чтобы создать <guilabel>быструю маску</guilabel>,  нажмите на кнопку,
      находящуюся в левом нижнем углу окна изображения. Если в изображении
      есть выделенная область, то ее внешний вид останется без изменений,
      остальная же область изображения  будет окрашена в полупрозрачный
      красный цвет. Если выделенная область отсутствует, то все изображение
      будет окрашено в прозрачный красный цвет. Видимость быстрой маки
      можно отключить, нажав на иконку с изображением глаза <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> находящуюся около названия
      <guilabel>Быстрая маска</guilabel> в диалоге каналов.
      В том же диалоге каналов есть возможность отредактировать атрибуты
      быстрой маски. Для этого дважды нажмите левой кнопкой мыши на
      изображении <guilabel>Быстрой маски</guilabel>. В появившемся окне
      можно изменить <guilabel>Непрозрачность заливки</guilabel> и цвет
      маски. При включении быстрой маски убедитесь, что она активна
      (подсвечена синим в диалоге каналов). После этого ее можно
      редактировать при помощи любых инструментов для рисования.
      Маска всегда находится в режиме градаций серого, поэтому
      для рисования надо использовать либо белый и серый цвета - для
      уменьшения будущей области выделения, либо черный - для увеличения.
      Часть маски, нарисованная серым, будет "полувыделенной" (аналогично
      функции размывания выделения). По окончании работы с маской нажмите
      на кнопку в левом нижнем углу окна изображения - быстрая маска будет
      удалена из списка каналов и преобразована в область выделения.
      Основная цель быстрой маски - дать возможность использовать
      инструменты для рисования при создании областей выделения, и при этом
      не создавать проблем, связанных с управлением обычными
      масками выделения.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      点击图像窗口左下角的按钮就会初始化<guilabel>快速蒙板</guilabel>。如果此时图像中有活动选区，其内容不会变，但选区外都覆盖了一层半透明红色。如果没有选区，所有图像都覆盖一层半透明红色。任何时候都可以通过点击通道对话框中 <guilabel>QMask</guilabel> 前的眼睛图标 <guiicon>
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png' />
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>来隐藏该蒙板。而在通道对话框中则可以双击其名字或缩略图来编辑 <guilabel>QMask</guilabel>的属性，然后能改变快速蒙板的<guilabel>不透明度</guilabel>和填充颜色。一旦完成快速蒙板初始化，点击它确认选中了它，这样它会在列表中高亮为蓝色，现在就可以用任何涂画工具涂画它了。由于蒙板是用灰色调编写的，所以您必须使用白色或灰色减少蒙板限制的区域，而用黑色增加。有浅或深灰色涂画的是选区的过渡区域，其效果和羽化相似。当您的蒙板就绪时，再次点击图像窗口左下方的按钮，蒙板就会从通道列表中移除并转变为选区。快速蒙板的目的就是用涂画工具涂画选区及其过渡区，而不要担心管理选区蒙板。通过这种方法，可以很方便地从图像中独立一个物体，因为一旦产生了选区，您只需要移除其内容。(如果物体在选区中就进行相反的操作。)
    </para>
  </sect4>

  <sect4>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Using Quick Mask's</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Použití rychlé masky</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Benutzen der <quote>Schnellmaske</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Empleo de la máscara rápida</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Utiliser le Masque rapide</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Utilizzo della maschera veloce</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å bruke snarmasker</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Использование быстрой маски</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用快速蒙板</phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobjectco>
      <imageobjectco>
        <!--
          "The coordinates are expressed using the semantics of the CALS
          graphic attributes. The format of the coordinates is 'x1,y1 x2,y2'.
          This identifies a rectangle with the lower-left corner at (x1,y1)
          and the upper-right corner at (x2,y2). The X and Y coordinates are
          integers in the range 0 to 10000; they express a percentage of the
          total distance from 0.00 to 100.00%. The lower-left corner is
          (0,0)."                              DocBook: The Definitive Guide
        -->
        <areaspec units="calspair">
          <area id="co-qmask" coords="840,7275 9295,9310" />
          <area id="co-qmask_to_selection" coords="840,3890 9295,5895" />
          <area id="co-stroke" coords="840,565 9295,2570" />
        </areaspec>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-masks-gradient.png"
            format="PNG" /> <!-- 299 x 319 -->
        </imageobject>
      </imageobjectco>
    </mediaobjectco>

    <calloutlist lang="en;cs;de;es;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en;zh_CN">Description</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Popis</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Beschreibung</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Descripción</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Descrizione</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Beskriving</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Описание</phrase>
      </title>

      <callout arearefs='co-qmask'>
        <para lang='en'>
          Screenshot of the image window with activated QuickMask. The
          QuickMask is filled with a gradient from black (left) to white
          (right).
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Snímek okna obrázku s aktivovanou rychlou maskou.
          Rychlá maska je vyplněna přechodem od černé (vlevo) po bílou
          (vpravo).
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Ansicht des Bildfensters bei eingeschalteter
          <quote>Schnellmaske</quote>
          : Zur Verdeutlichung, wie Grautöne in einer Schnellmaske eingesetzt
          werden können, wurde ein Farbverlauf auf die Schnellmaske
          angewendet. Der Farbverlauf verläuft von Schwarz (links) nach Weiß
          (rechts).
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Una ventana de imagen que tiene activada la máscara rápida.  La
          máscara ha sido rellenada con un degradado que va de negro
          (izquierda) a blanco (derecha).
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Illustrazione della finestra immagine con la maschera veloce
          attivata.
          La maschera veloce è riempita con un gradiente che va dal nero (a
          sinistra) fino al bianco (a destra).
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Skjermdump av biletvindauget med aktivert snarmaske. Snarmaska
          er fylt med ein fargeovergang frå svart (venstre) til kvit (høgre).
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Окно изображения с включенной быстрой маской. Быстрая маска
          залита градиентом от черного (слева) к белому (справа).
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          开启快速蒙板的图像窗口截图。该快速蒙板使用从黑(左)到白(右)的渐变。
        </para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs='co-qmask_to_selection'>
        <para lang='en'>
          The QuickMask is now disabled and a selection is initialised from
          the QuickMask, which was filled by a gradient before. You see the
          selection borders in the middle of the image.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Rychlá maska je opět převedena na výběr. Hranice výběru je vidět
          uprostřed obrázku.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Bildfenster bei ausgeschalteter Schnellmaske und der daraus
          erstellten Auswahl.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Ahora la máscara rápida se ha desactivado y se ha creado una
          selección a partir de ella, la cual había sido rellenada por un
          gradiente antes.  Puede ver el borde de la selección en el medio de
          la imagen.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          La maschera veloce disabilitata e la selezione creata dalla
          maschera veloce, che prima era riempita da un gradiente. Al centro
          dell'immagine è visibile il bordo della selezione.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Snarmaska er nå kopla ifrå og det er blitt laga ei markering frå
          den snarmaska som var fylt med fargeovergangen. Du kan sjå
          skiljet mellom meir og mindre enn 50 % dekkevne for
          markeringa midt i biletet.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Быстрая маска отключена, из нее создана выделенная область.
          Обратите внимание на границу выделения, проходящую по
          центру изображения.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          一个从使用渐变的快速蒙板中得到的选区，现在已经关闭快速蒙板。可以看到图像中间的选区边缘。
        </para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs='co-stroke'>
        <para lang='en'>
          A stroke is now added during the enabled selection. The key is,
          that the black color will have no opacity of the resulting stroke
          (right) and white color will have a full opacity of the stroke
          (left).
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          V režimu výběru je vytvořen tah štětcem.
          Vlevo je čára plně vytvořena, ale směrem vpravo se vytrácí.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Bild wurde bei bestehender Auswahl mit Hilfe des
          Füllwerkzeugs mit Schwarz gefüllt.  Aufgrund des Farbverlaufs
          und der daraus erstellten Auswahl erscheint nun die Füllung
          wie ein Farbverlauf. Wichtig hierbei ist, dass Schwarz in der
          <quote>Schnellmaske</quote> volle Transparenz der Auswahl und
          Weiß volle Deckkraft der Auswahl entspricht.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Ahora se efectúa un trazo manteniendo la selección anterior.  El
          truco está en que a la izquierda no hay opacidad porque para aquel
          lado la selección es menor, mientras que a la derecha hay opacidad
          total porque la selección es mayor.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Una barra aggiunta mentre la selezione è abilitata. Il punto è che
          il colore nero della maschera (a sinistra) non da opacità alla
          barra mentre il colore bianco conferisce una totale opacità alla
          barra (a destra).
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Her er det teikna ein einsfarga sikk-sakk-strek på markeringa.
          Du kan sjå at på høgresida er fargen fullt synleg for så å bli
          mindre og mindre synleg mot venstresida.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          При наличии активной области выделения проведены несколько
          линий. Обратите внимание на то, что слева росчерк прозрачен
          (эта область маски была залита черным), а справа -
          непрозрачен (здесь маска была залита белым).
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          现在对选区添加一个笔划。关键之处在于，白色使生成的笔划有透明度(左)而黑色使笔划完全不透明(右)。
        </para>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

    <para lang='en'>
      After the QuickMask Button is pressed, the command generates a
      temporary 8-bit (0-255) channel, on which the progressive selection
      work is stored. If a selection is already present the mask is
      initialized with the content of the selection. Once QuickMask has been
      activated, the image is covered by a red semi-transparent veil. This
      one representes the non-selected pixels. Any
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">paint tool</link>
      can be used to create the selection on the QuickMask. They should use
      only greyscale color, conforming the channel properties, white enabling
      to define the future selected place. The selection will be displayed as
      soon as the QuickMask will be toggled but its temporary channel will
      not be available anymore.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Po stisknutí tlačítka rychlé masky je vytvořen dočasný 8bitový (0-255)
      kanál, do kterého je uložen stávající výběr. Obrázek se pokryje červeným
      průsvitným závojem, který představuje nevybrané části. K úpravě výběru v
      rychlé masce lze použít libovolný
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">kreslící nástroj</link>.
      Měla by se k tomu používat jen škála odstínů šedi, bílá představuje
      vybrané oblasti. Jakmile rychlou masku vypnete, zobrazí se upravený
      výběr, ale kanál rychlé masky zmizí.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die vorhandenen Auswahlwerkzeuge reichen nicht aus, feine Bildobjekte zu
      selektieren. Mit Hilfe der
      <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>Malwerkzeuge</link>
      ist es möglich, jede mögliche Auswahl zu erstellen, die Sie haben
      möchten. Die Farbe spielt dabei eine besondere Rolle. Es stehen Ihnen
      nicht nur Schwarz und Weiß zur Verfügung, sondern auch alle 254
      Graustufen dazwischen. Durch die Benutzung von grauen Farben können Sie
      zum Beispiel Auswahlen mit weichen Kanten erstellen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Al presionar el botón de máscara rápida, el GIMP genera un canal
      temporario de 8 bits (de 0 a 255), en el cual se conserva el trabajo de
      selección progresivo.  Si ya hay una selección presente, la máscara se
      inicializa con el contenido de esa selección.  Una vez activa la máscara
      rápida, la imagen se cubre con un velo rojizo semitrasparente.  Éste
      representa los píxeles no seleccionados.  Cualquier <link
      linkend="gimp-tools-paint">herramienta de pintura</link> puede usarse
      para crear la selección de la máscara rápida.  Se hará uso solo del tono
      de los colores que se empleen, de acuerdo a las propiedades del canal.
      La selección se muestra luego de desactivar la máscara rápida, y el
      canal temporal ya no se encontrará disponible.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cette commande génère un canal temporaire 8-bit (0-255) sur lequel le
      travail de sélection progressivement établi est peu à peu enregistré.
      Si une sélection est déjà présente, le masque est initialisé avec le
      contenu de la sélection. Une fois le Masque Rapide activé, l'image est
      recouverte d'un voile rouge semi-transparent. Celui-ci représente les
      pixels non-sélectionnés de l'image. N'importe quel
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">outil de dessin</link>
      peut être utilisé pour modifier ce masque et créer la sélection
      résultante. Ces outils devraient être utilisés uniquement en niveaux de
      gris, conformément à la nature des canaux, le blanc permettant de
      définir la future zone à sélectionner. Cette sélection ne sera affichée
      que lorsque le Masque rapide sera desactivé. Mais à partir de ce
      moment, le canal temporaire est définitivement perdu et seul un retour
      immédiat au mode masque permet de la récupérer.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Appena viene premuto il pulsante della maschera veloce, il comando genera
      un canale temporaneo a 8 bit (0-255), nel quale viene salvato il lavoro
      sulla selezione progressiva. Se è già presente una selezione, la maschera
      viene creata con il contenuto della selezione. Una volta che è stata
      attivata la maschera veloce, l'immagine viene ricoperta da un velo rosso
      semitrasparente, che rappresenta i pixel non selezionati.
      Per creare la selezione nella maschera veloce può essere usato qualsiasi
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">strumento di disegno</link>. Questi
      devono utilizzare solo colori in scala di grigio, in conformità alle
      caratteristiche del canale, abilitando in bianco le zone che verranno
      selezionate. Appena la maschera veloce viene disabilitata appare la
      selezione, ma il canale temporaneo non sarà più disponibile.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Etter at du har trykt på knappen for snarmaske blir det laga ein
      temporær 8-bits (0 - 255) kanal der fargeovergangen blir lagra.
      Dersom det finst ei markering i biletet når maska blir laga, vil maska
      hente data frå denne markeringa. Når snarmaska blir aktivert vil
      biletet bli dekka av ei raud, halvgjennomsiktig hinne der det er pikslar
      som ikkje er markerte. Du kan bruke alle
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">teikneverktøya</link> for å lage
      markeringar på snarmaska. Bruk bare ulike gråtoner som farge for å
      lage ulike grader av markering. Teikna med kvit farge der du kan ha
      planar om å legge inn andre grader av markering seinare. Markeringa
      blir verksam så snart du slår av snarmaska, men den temprære kanalen
      forsvinn for alltid.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      При нажатии кнопки, активирующей быструю маску, создается временный
      8-битный канал, в котором хранится создаваемая область выделения. Все
      невыделенные пикселы отмечаются красным полупрозрачным цветом.
      Создавать и редактировать область выделения в быстрой маске можно
      любым
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">инструментом для рисования</link>
      и любым цветом из серой гаммы. Сама область выделения будет
      отображена  после отключения быстрой маски, однако восстановить
      ту же самую быструю маску будет невозможно.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在按下快速蒙板按钮后，该命令就产生一个保存选区的 8 位 (0-255) 临时通道。如果已经有选区，蒙板将初始化为选区内容。一旦快速蒙板被开启，图像就覆盖上一层红色半透明薄膜，它表示没被选中的像素。可以用任何<link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">涂画工具</link>在快速蒙板上创建选区，不过只能使用灰度颜色，与通道属性一样，白色用作定义将被选中的区域。选区在快速蒙板被切换时立即显示出来，但该临时通道就不能再使用了。
    </para>

    <tip>
      <para lang='en'>
        To save in a channel the selection done with the Quickmask select in
        the image menu
        <guimenuitem>Select/Save to Channel</guimenuitem>
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Chcete-li výběr vyrobený pomocí rychlé masky uložit v trvalém kanálu,
        zvolte v nabídce obrázku
        <guimenuitem>Vybrat/Uložit do kanálu</guimenuitem>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Um eine mit einer <quote>Schnellmaske</quote> angelegte Auswahl in
        einen Kanal zu speichern, steht Ihnen das Kommando
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>In <accel>K</accel>anal speichern</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> im Menü des Bildfensters zur Verfügung.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Para guardar en un canal la selección realizada con la máscara rápida,
        seleccione del menú de la imagen
        <guimenuitem>Seleccionar/Guardar en canal</guimenuitem>
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour sauvegarder dans un canal la sélection créée avec le masque
        rapide, sélectionnez dans le menu d'image
        <guimenuitem>Sélection/Enregister dans un canal</guimenuitem>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per salvare in un canale la selezione effettuata con la maschera
        veloce bisogna selezionare
        <guimenuitem>Seleziona/Salva nel canale</guimenuitem>
        dal menu immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dersom du ønskjer å lagra markeringa, kan du bruke
        <guimenuitem>Markér/Lagre til kanal</guimenuitem> i biletmenyen.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Чтобы сохранить выделение, созданное быстрой маской,
        в канале, воспользуйтесь пунктом меню изображения
        <guimenuitem>Выделение/Сохранить в канале</guimenuitem>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        将用快速蒙板创建的选区保存的一个通道中，可以在图像菜单中选取
        <guimenuitem>选择/保存到通道</guimenuitem>。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect4>
  <sect4>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Usage</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Použití</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Benutzung</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Modo de empleo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Utilisation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Modalità di impiego</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Bruk</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Последовательность действий</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">用法</phrase>
    </title>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          <link linkend='gimp-file-open'>Open</link> an image or begin a
          <link linkend='gimp-file-new'>new document</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          <!--FIXME: cs <link linkend='gimp-file-open'>-->Otevřete<!--</link>-->
          obrázek nebo vytvořte <!--FIXCS<link linkend='gimp-file-new'>-->Nový
          dokument<!--</link>-->.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          <link linkend='gimp-file-open'>Öffnen</link>
          Sie ein schon vorhandenes Bild oder legen Sie ein
          <link linkend='gimp-file-new'>neues Bild</link> an.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          <!-- PENDING-ES link linkend='gimp-file-open'-->Abra<!--/link--> una
          imagen o comienze una <!-- PENDING-ES link
          linkend='gimp-file-new'-->imagen nueva<!--/link-->.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Ouvrir une image ou commencer un nouveau document.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          <!--link linkend='gimp-file-open' FIXME: it -->Aprire<!--/link-->
          un'immagine oppure iniziare una<!--link linkend='gimp-file-new' -->
          nuova immagine<!--/link-->.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          <link linkend='gimp-file-open'>Opna</link> eit bilete, eller lag eit
          <link linkend='gimp-file-new'>Nytt</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          <!--link linkend='gimp-file-open'-->Откройте<!--/link--> файл или создайте
          <!--link linkend='gimp-file-new'-->новое изображение<!--/link-->.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <link linkend='gimp-file-open'>打开</link>一个图像或<link linkend='gimp-file-new'>新建</link>图像。
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Activate the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the image
          window. If a selection is present the mask is initialized with the
          content of the selection.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Aktivujte rychlou masku pomocí tlačítka v levém dolním rohu okna
          obrázku. Pokud existuje výběr, rychlá maska se vytvoří podle něj.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Aktivieren Sie die <quote>Schnellmaske</quote>, indem Sie auf die
          Schaltfläche klicken, die sich im Bildfenster links unten befindet.
          Bei einer vorhandener Auswahl wird die Schnellmaske mit der
          bestehenden Auswahl initialisiert.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Active la máscara rápida haciendo clic en el botón de la esquina
          inferior izquierda de la ventana de la imagen.  Si se haya presente
          una selección, la máscaa será inicializada con su contenido.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Activer le Masque Rapide en utilisant le bouton Masque rapide en
          bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image. Si une sélection est présente,
          le masque est initialisé avec le contenu de la sélection.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Attivare la maschera veloce usando il pulsante in basso a sinistra
          nella finestra immagine. Se è presente una selezione la maschera
          viene creata con il contenuto della selezione.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Aktiver snarmaska ved å trykke på knappen i biletvindauget. Dersom
          det finst ei markering i biletet, vil maska bli laga med data frå denne.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Включите быструю маску при помощи кнопки, находящейся в левом
          нижнем углу окна изображения. Если в изображении есть выделенная
          область, она будет отображена в быстрой маске.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          点击图像窗口中左下角有红色外框的按钮来开启快速蒙板。如果已经有选区，蒙板将初始化为选区内容。
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Choose a <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>drawing tool</link>
          and use it with greyscale colors on the QuickMask.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Zvolte libovolný
          <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>kreslící nástroj</link>
          a pomocí černé, bílé a odstínů šedi upravte rychlou masku.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Benutzen Sie ein von Ihnen gewähltes
          <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>Malwerkzeug</link>
          mit Graustufenfarben, um die Schnellmaske zu bearbeiten.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Elija una <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>herramienta de
          pintura</link> y empléela con colores grises sobre la máscara
          rápida.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Choisissez et paramétrez un outil de dessin dans la boite à outils,
          puis utilisez cet outil pour dessiner sur le masque en niveaux de
          gris.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Scegliere uno<!-- FIXME: cs link linkend='gimp-tools-paint' -->
          strumento di disegno<!--/link-->
          ed usarlo sulla maschera veloce con colori in scala di grigio.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Vel eit <!--<link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'-->teikneverktøy<!--/link--> og bruk
          dette med gråskalafarger på snarmaska.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Выберите
          <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>инструмент для рисования</link>
          и, используя серые цвета, нарисуйте нужную область выделения.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          选取任何 <link linkend='gimp-tools-paint'>涂画工具</link>，使用灰度色在快速蒙板上涂画。
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Deactivate the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the image
          window.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Zrušte rychlou masku opětovným kliknutím na tlačítko v levém dolním
          rohu okna obrázku.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Deaktivieren Sie die <quote>Schnellmaske</quote>, indem Sie wieder
          auf die Schaltfläche klicken, die sich links unten im Bildfenster
          befindet.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Desactive la máscara rápida empleando nuevamente el botón de la
          esquina inferior izquierda de la ventana de la imagen.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Désactiver le Masque Rapide en utilisant le bouton Masque rapide en
          bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Disattivare la maschera veloce usando il pulsante in basso a
          sinistra nella finestra immagine.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Deaktiver snarmaska med knappen i biletvindauget.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Отключите быструю маску при помощи кнопки, находящейся в левом
          нижнем углу окна изображения.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">用图像窗口左下角的按钮来关闭快速蒙板。</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect4>
</sect3>
