<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2019-05-25 j.h: update to v-2.10
-->

<sect2 id="gimp-tagging">
  <title>Tagging</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tags</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    In Brushes, Gradients, Patterns and Palettes dialogs and some other
    dockable dialogs, you can define tags and then, you can reorganize items
    according to chosen tags only.
  </para>

  <para>
    Tagging is divided in two parts:
    <figure>
      <title>Tagging</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/tagging1.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A <quote>Filter</quote> field at the top where you can enter or
          select a tag previously defined. Only the resources (Brushes,
          gradients, patterns, palettes, etc.) that have the specified tag,
          will be displayed.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can enter several tags, separated with commas. In which case
          only the resources that have all these tags defined, will be shown.
        </para>
        <para>
          Selecting a tag with the mouse works differently: only a single tag
          can be active at a time. If you want to select another tag, you
          first have to click the active tag to unselect that one, before
          selecting a different tag.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <quote>Enter tag</quote> field, below the list of resources can be
          used to add tags to the selected resource. The tags belonging to the
          current brush, gradient, pattern, palette, etc. are displayed.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can add more tags to the current resource by clicking on one of
          the defined tags in the pop-up list of the field; or you can create
          your own tag for this item by typing its name in the field. The new
          tag will then appear in the tag list.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      The Fonts dialog also has Filter and Enter tag fields.
      But GIMP doesn't yet automatically generate any tags from fonts metadata,
      nor does it save the tags you add to fonts.
    </para>
  </note>

  <figure>
    <title>Example</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/tagging2.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          In this example, we defined a <quote>green</quote> tag for the Pepper
          and Vine brushes. Then, we entered <quote>green</quote> in
          the <guilabel>Filter</guilabel> input field and so, only
          brushes with the green tag are displayed.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <tip>
    <para>
      To give several brushes the same tag at once, display brushes in
      List Mode, and use <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>Mouse
      Left&nbsp;Button</mousebutton></keycombo> on the brushes you want to
      select.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
    You can delete tags: select a brush, then select a tag in the <quote>Enter
    tag</quote> field and press the <keycap>Delete</keycap> key. When this
    tag has been removed from all brushes, it disappears from the list.
  </para>

</sect2>
