<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2012-03-01 Created by j.h
-->

<sect2 id="gimp-tagging">
  <title>Tagging</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tags</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <para>
    In Brushes, Gradients, Patterns and Palettes dialogs and some other
    dockable dialogs, you can define tags and then, you can reorganize items
    according to chosen tags only.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    You have two input fields:
    <figure>
      <title>Tagging</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/tagging.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <quote>Filter</quote> field: There, you can enter a tag previously
          defined or select a tag in the pop list you get by clicking on
          the arrow head at the right end of the field. Brushes, gradients,
          patterns, or palettes are filtered and only these that have this
          chosen tag will be displayed.
          You can enter several tags, separated with commas.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <quote>Enter tag</quote> field: There, tags belonging to the current
          brush, gradient, pattern, or palette are displayed. You can add
          another tag to the current item by clicking on one of the defined
          tag in the pop up list of the field. You can also create your own
          tag for this item by typing its name in the field. Then the new tag
          appears in the tag pop up list.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  
  <figure>
    <title>Example</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/tagging2.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          In this example, we defined a <quote>green</quote> tag for the Pepper
          and Vine brushes. Then, we entered <quote>green</quote> in
          the <guilabel>Filter</guilabel>input field and so, only
          brushes with the green tag are displayed.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <tip>
    <para>
      To give several brushes the same tag at once, display brushes in
      List Mode, and use <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>
      Left click</mousebutton></keycombo> on the brushes you want to
      select.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <para>
    You can delete tags: select a brush, then select a tag in the <quote>Enter
    tag</quote> field and press the <keycap>Delete</keycap> key. When this
    tag has been removed from all brushes, it disappears from the list.
  </para>
  
</sect2>