<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-12-15 j.h: updated en;fr to v2.6
  2007-10-07 j.h: updated en;fr images to v2.4. No change in text.
  2007-04-16 Added Spanish trans lation by AntI
  2006-04-29 lexa: made docbook compliant
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tools-dialog">
  <title><quote>Tools</quote> Dialog</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Dialog</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Customize</primary>
    <secondary>Toolbox</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase>The <quote>Tools</quote> dialog</phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/tools-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The <quote>Tools</quote> dialog is used mainly to control the appearance
    of the Toolbox. It allows you to customize the set of tools for which
    icons are shown in the Toolbox, and the order in which the icons are
    arranged. Probably the most common use for it is to make the Color tools
    available directly from the Toolbox. You can also use the Tools dialog to
    select a tool by clicking on its symbol, but for this purpose you might
    as well just use the Toolbox.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the dialog</title>
    <para>
      The <quote>Tools</quote> dialog is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can access it:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the image menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the Tab menu in any dockable dialog by clicking on
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-menu-left-12.png"/>
          </guiicon> and selecting
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Grid/List modes</title>
    <para>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the tools are laid out in a rectangular
      array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically, with each
      row showing the tool name, tool icon, and an <quote>eye</quote> icon
      if the tool is currently visible in the Toolbox.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo>
        opens a search field.
        See <xref linkend="gimp-dock-view-as-list" />
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Using the <quote>Tools</quote> dialog</title>
    <para>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a tool by clicking on its
      icon: this has the same effect as clicking on an icon in the Toolbox.
      You can do this in either List or Grid mode: the other functions of the
      dialog are available only in List mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      The most important function of the <quote>Tools</quote> dialog is to
      let you choose which tools to make visible in the Toolbox, by toggling
      the <quote>eye</quote> icons that appear on the left side of each row
      in List mode.  In particular, if you use the Color tools a lot, you may
      benefit from toggling visibility on for them here.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also change the order of tools in the Toolbox, by clicking on
      an item in the <quote>Tools</quote> dialog, in List mode, and dragging
      it up or down in the list. If you screw things up, you can always press
      the <quote>Reset</quote> button at the bottom of the dialog, to restore
      the defaults for order and visibility.
    </para>
    <para>
      Right-clicking inside the dialog produces the <quote>Tools</quote>
      menu, which gives you an alternative way of toggling visibility or
      restoring the defaults.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
