<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-tools-dialog' lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Tools dialog</title>
  <title lang="cs">Dialog Nástroje</title>
  <title lang="fr">Le Dialogue Outils</title>
  <title lang="it">Finestra strumenti</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">工具对话框</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang="cs">Dialog</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Dialogue</primary>
    <primary lang="it">Finestra</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Tools</secondary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Nástroje</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Outils</secondary>
    <secondary lang="it">Strumenti</secondary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">工具</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;de;it;zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-tools.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-tools.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
         The Tools dialog
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
         Dialog nástroje
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
         Le dialogue Outils 
        </para>
        <para lang='it'>
         La finestra strumenti
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
        工具对话框
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Tools dialog is used mainly to control the appearance of the
    Toolbox.  It allows you to customize the set of tools for which
    icons are shown in the Toolbox, and the order in which the icons
    are arranged.  Probably the most common use for it is to make the
    Color tools available directly from the Toolbox.  You can also use
    the Tools dialog to select a tool by clicking on its symbol, but
    for this purpose you might as well just use the Toolbox.
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Dialog Nástroje slouží k nastavení Panelu nástrojů. Umožňuje přizůsobit
    si sadu nástrojů, jejichž ikony se v panelu zobrazují, a pořadí ikon
    v panelu. Tento dialog se často používá k přidání ikon nástrojů pro práci
    s barvami do Panelu nástrojů. Lze ho také použít k výběru aktivního
    nástroje, ale k tomu je určen spíše práve Panel nástrojů.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le dialogue Outils est surtout utilisé pour contrôler 
    l'apparence de la Boîte à outils. Il vous permet de personnaliser 
    le lot d'outils figurant sous forme d'icônes dans la Boîte à 
    outils, et l'ordre dans lequel ils sont présentés. L'usage le plus 
    courant est de rendre disponibles les outils de peinture dans la 
    Boîte à outils. Vous pouvez certes activer un outil en cliquant 
    dessus dans ce dialogue, mais il est plus simple d'utiliser la 
    Boîte à outils. 
  </para>
  <para lang='it'>
    La finestra strumenti viene usata principalmente per controllare
    la visualizzazione degli strumenti. Permette di personalizzare
    l'insieme degli strumenti per i quali sono visibili le icone
    nella finestra e l'ordine di visualizzazione delle rispettive icone.
    Probabilmente l'uso più comune è quello di rendere lo strumento colore
    direttamente accessibile dalla finestra. È anche possibile usare la
    finestra strumenti per selezionare lo strumento facendo clic sul suo simbolo
    ma per questo scopo si può anche semplicemente usare la barra degli strumenti.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    工具对话框主要用作控制工具箱的外观。您可以通过定制在工具箱中显示的哪些工具，及其图标排列的顺序。最常见的用法可能是直接在工具箱中使用颜色工具，您也可以点击一个工具标志来使用它，不过使用工具箱就可以达到该目的。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Tools dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Dialog nástrojů je dokovatelný; více viz část
    <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dokování dialogů</link>.
    Lze ho vyvolat různými způsoby:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le Dialogue Outils est un dialogue attachable; voyez la 
    section <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Dialogues et attachements</link>
    pour plus d'informations. Il peut être appelé de différentes 
    façons:
  <para lang='it'>
    La finestra strumenti è una finestra agganciabile; vedere la sezione
    <link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>Finestre e agganciabili</link>
    per le informazioni su come controllarla. Può essere attivata in
    molti modi:
  </para>

  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    工具对话框是可停靠对话框；关于如何使用它，请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>。它有多种方式开启：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>
      <para>    
        Z nabídky Panelu nástrojů:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogy</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Nástroje</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='fr'>
      <para>    
        A partir du menu de la Boîte à outils:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogues</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>O<accel>u</accel>tils</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='it'>
      <para>    
        Dal menu strumenti:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Finestre</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Str<accel>u</accel>menti</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>      
      <para>    
        Z nabídky obrázku:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogy</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Nástroje</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='fr'>      
      <para>    
        A partir du menu de l'image:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogues</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>O<accel>u</accel>tils</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='it'>
      <para>    
        Da un menu immagine:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Finestre</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>S<accel>t</accel>rumenti</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='cs'>
      <para>
        Z nabídky odrážky jakéhokoliv dokovatelného dialogu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Přidat odrážku</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Nástroje</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='fr'>      
      <para>    
        Apartir du menu d'onglets de tout dialogue attachable:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Ajouter un onglet</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang='it'>      
      <para>    
        Dal menu scheda in ogni finestra agganciabile:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Aggiungi scheda</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Str<accel>u</accel>menti</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
   <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从任何可停靠对话框的页签菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>添加页签</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>
    <title lang="cs">Režim mřížky a seznamu</title>
    <title lang="fr">Mode Grille et mode Liste</title>
    <title lang="it">Griglia/List modes</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">阵列/列表模式</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the tools are laid out in a rectangular
      array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically, with each
      row showing the tool name, tool icon, and an "eye" icon if the
      tool is currently visible in the Toolbox.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      V nabídce odrážky lze volit mezi režimy <guimenuitem>Zobrazit jako
      mřížku</guimenuitem> a <guimenuitem>Zobrazit jako seznam</guimenuitem>.
      V režimu mřížky jsou jednotlivé nástroje zobrazeny v pravidelné mřížce.
      V režimu seznamu jsou zobrazeny pod sebou jako seznam, jehož každá řádka
      obsahuje nejen ikonu nástroje, ale i jeho jméno a, pokud je právě
      nástroj viditelný v Panelu nástrojů, ikonku „oka“.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans le menu d'onglets, vous avez le choix entre 
      <guimenuitem>Voir comme une grille</guimenuitem> et 
      <guimenuitem>Voir comme une liste</guimenuitem>. En mode Grille, 
      les outils sont présentés dans un tableau rectangulaire. En mode 
      Liste, ils sont alignés verticalement, avec leur nom, leur icône 
      et un «œil» si l'outil est présent dans la Boîte à outils.      
    </para>
    <para lang='it'>
      Nel menu scheda, si può scegliere tra <guimenuitem>Mostra come
      griglia</guimenuitem> e <guimenuitem>Mostra come elenco</guimenuitem>.
      In modalità griglia, gli strumenti sono disposti in posizione rettangolare.
      In modalità elenco, sono allineati verticalmente, con ogni riga composta dal
      nome dello strumento, icona dello strumento e un'icona a forma di "occhio" se
      lo strumento è attualmente visibile nella barra degli strumenti.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您可以在工具对话框的页签菜单中选择是<guimenuitem>以阵列方式查看</guimenuitem>还是<guimenuitem>以列表方式查看</guimenuitem>。阵列模式中，工具以矩形阵列排列，而列表模式中，它们垂直线性排列，每一行从左到右分别是工具名，工具图标和一个“眼睛”图标(如果该工具当前在工具箱中可见)。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Tools dialog</title>
    <title lang="cs">Použití Dialogu nástrojů</title>
    <title lang="fr">Utilisation du dialogue Outils</title>
    <title lang="it">Using the Tools dialog</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用工具对话框</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a tool by clicking
      on its icon:  this has the same effect as clicking on an icon in
      the Toolbox.  You can do this in either List or Grid mode:  the
      other functions of the dialog are available only in List mode.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Nejjednodušší věc, kterou můžete v tomto dialogu udělat, je aktivování
      nástroje kliknutím na jeho ikonu – je to stejné, jako když kliknete na
      ikonu v Panelu nástrojů. To funguje v obou režimech, další funkce tohoto
      dialogu jsou však k dispozici pouze v režimu seznamu.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le plus simple est la sélection d'un outil en cliquant sur son 
      icône: c'est la même chose qu'en cliquant sur une icône de la 
      Boîte à outils. Vous pouvez faire cela aussi bien en mode Grille 
      qu'en mode Liste. Par contre, les autres options du dialogue ne 
      sont disponibles qu'en mode Liste.
    </para>
    <para lang='it'>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a tool by clicking
      on its icon:  this has the same effect as clicking on an icon in
      the Toolbox.  You can do this in either List or Grid mode:  the
      other functions of the dialog are available only in List mode.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      最基本操作就是点击一个图标并选中该工具：和点击工具箱中的图标效果相同，可以选择是列表模式还是阵列模式：该对话框中其它功能只在列表模式中可用。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most important function of the Tools dialog is to let you
      choose which tools to make visible in the Toolbox, by toggling
      the "eye" icons that appear on the left side of each row in List
      mode.  In particular, if you use the Color tools a lot, you may
      benefit from toggling visibility on for them here.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Nejdůležitější funkcí Dialogu nástrojů je možnost výběru ikon, které se
      mají zobrazovat v Panelu nástrojů, přepínáním ikonky „oka“ v levé části
      každé řádky seznamu. Pokud například používáte často nástroje pro úpravu
      barev, může být pro vás vyhodné zapnout zde jejich zobrazování v Panelu
      nástrojů.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La fonction principale du dialogue Outils est de faire passer un 
      outil dans la Boîte à outils. Il suffit de cliquer pour faire 
      apparaître l'œil à côté de l'outil désiré
    </para>
    <para lang='it'>
      The most important function of the Tools dialog is to let you
      choose which tools to make visible in the Toolbox, by toggling
      the "eye" icons that appear on the left side of each row in List
      mode.  In particular, if you use the Color tools a lot, you may
      benefit from toggling visibility on for them here.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      工具对话框最重要的功能是通过点击“眼睛”图标来选择哪些工具在工具箱中可见。特别是，当您使用颜色工具特别多时，使它们在工具箱中可见会非常方便。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      You can also change the order of tools in the Toolbox, by
      clicking on an item in the Tools dialog, in List mode, and
      dragging it up or down in the list.  If you screw things up, you
      can always press the "Reset" button at the bottom of the dialog,
      to restore the defaults for order and visibility.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Můžete také upravit pořadí, v jakém jsou ikonky nástrojů v panelu
      zobrazeny. Chcete-li to udělat, klikněte na ikonku v režimu seznamu
      a táhněte ji v seznamu nahoru nebo dolů na požadované místo. Pokud
      něco pokazíte, můžete zobrazení nástrojů vrátit k výchozímu nastavení
      kliknutím na nulovací tlačítko v dolní části dialogu.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez aussi changer l'ordre des outils dans la Boîte à 
      outils, en cliquant sur un des outils et en le faisant glisser 
      vers le haut ou vers le bas dans la Liste. En cas d'erreur, le 
      bouton Ré-initialiser vous permet de restaurer l'état par défaut. 
    </para>
    <para lang='it'>
      You can also change the order of tools in the Toolbox, by
      clicking on an item in the Tools dialog, in List mode, and
      dragging it up or down in the list.  If you screw things up, you
      can always press the "Reset" button at the bottom of the dialog,
      to restore the defaults for order and visibility.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您也可以通过点击工具对话框中一个工具并在列表模式中像向上或向下拖动，来改变工具箱中工具顺序。如果把顺序搞乱了，常常可以用对话框底部的“重置”按钮恢复顺序和可见性的默认值。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Right-clicking inside the dialog produces the Tools menu, which
      gives you an alternative way of toggling visibility or restoring
      the defaults.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Kliknutím pravého tlačítka myši v dialogu zobrazíte nabídku, která
      rovněž umožňuje přepínat viditelnost jednotlivých nástrojů a obnovení
      výchozího nastavení.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un clic droit dans le dialogue ouvre le menu local vous permettant 
      également d'agir sur la visibilité.
    </para>
    <para lang='it'>
      Right-clicking inside the dialog produces the Tools menu, which
      gives you an alternative way of toggling visibility or restoring
      the defaults.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在对话框中对工具点右键会出现工具菜单，其中也可以切换可见性和恢复默认值。
    </para>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
