<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-tools-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Tools dialog</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">工具对话框</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">对话框</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">工具</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-tools.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para lang='en'>
	  The Tools dialog
	</para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  工具对话框
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Tools dialog is used mainly to control the appearance of the
    Toolbox.  It allows you to customize the set of tools for which
    icons are shown in the Toolbox, and the order in which the icons
    are arranged.  Probably the most common use for it is to make the
    Color tools available directly from the Toolbox.  You can also use
    the Tools dialog to select a tool by clicking on its symbol, but
    for this purpose you might as well just use the Toolbox.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    工具对话框主要用作控制工具箱的外观。您可以通过定制在工具箱中显示的哪些工具，及其图标排列的顺序。最常见的用法可能是直接在工具箱中使用颜色工具，您也可以点击一个工具标志来使用它，不过使用工具箱就可以达到该目的。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Tools dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    工具对话框是可停靠对话框；关于如何使用它，请看<link linkend='gimp-docks'>对话框和停靠栏</link>。它有多种方式开启：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从工具箱菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>对话框</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从图像菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>对话框</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        从任何可停靠对话框的页签菜单中：
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>添加页签</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">阵列/列表模式</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the tools are laid out in a rectangular
      array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically, with each
      row showing the tool name, tool icon, and an "eye" icon if the
      tool is currently visible in the Toolbox.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您可以在工具对话框的页签菜单中选择是<guimenuitem>以阵列方式查看</guimenuitem>还是<guimenuitem>以列表方式查看</guimenuitem>。阵列模式中，工具以矩形阵列排列，而列表模式中，它们垂直线性排列，每一行从左到右分别是工具名，工具图标和一个“眼睛”图标(如果该工具当前在工具箱中可见)。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Tools dialog</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">使用工具对话框</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a tool by clicking
      on its icon:  this has the same effect as clicking on an icon in
      the Toolbox.  You can do this in either List or Grid mode:  the
      other functions of the dialog are available only in List mode.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      最基本操作就是点击一个图标并选中该工具：和点击工具箱中的图标效果相同，可以选择是列表模式还是阵列模式：该对话框中其它功能只在列表模式中可用。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most important function of the Tools dialog is to let you
      choose which tools to make visible in the Toolbox, by toggling
      the "eye" icons that appear on the left side of each row in List
      mode.  In particular, if you use the Color tools a lot, you may
      benefit from toggling visibility on for them here.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      工具对话框最重要的功能是通过点击“眼睛”图标来选择哪些工具在工具箱中可见。特别是，当您使用颜色工具特别多时，使它们在工具箱中可见会非常方便。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      You can also change the order of tools in the Toolbox, by
      clicking on an item in the Tools dialog, in List mode, and
      dragging it up or down in the list.  If you screw things up, you
      can always press the "Reset" button at the bottom of the dialog,
      to restore the defaults for order and visibility.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您也可以通过点击工具对话框中一个工具并在列表模式中像向上或向下拖动，来改变工具箱中工具顺序。如果把顺序搞乱了，常常可以用对话框底部的“重置”按钮恢复顺序和可见性的默认值。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Right-clicking inside the dialog produces the Tools menu, which
      gives you an alternative way of toggling visibility or restoring
      the defaults.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在对话框中对工具点右键会出现工具菜单，其中也可以切换可见性和恢复默认值。
    </para>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
