<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect1 id='gimp-tools-dialog'>
  <title lang="en">Tools dialog</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Dialog</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-tools.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Tools dialog
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Tools dialog is used mainly to control the appearance of the
    Toolbox.  It allows you to customize the set of tools for which
    icons are shown in the Toolbox, and the order in which the icons
    are arranged.  Probably the most common use for it is to make the
    Color tools available directly from the Toolbox.  You can also use
    the Tools dialog to select a tool by clicking on its symbol, but
    for this purpose you might as well just use the Toolbox.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Tools dialog is a dockable dialog; see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-docks'>Dialogs and Docking</link> for help on
    manipulating it.  It can be activated in several ways:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang='en'>
      <para>    
        From the Toolbox menu:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Dialogs</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From an image menu:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Dialogs</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem lang='en'>      
      <para>    
        From the Tab menu in any dockable dialog:
        <menuchoice>
           <guimenu>Add Tab</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>T<accel>o</accel>ols</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Grid/List modes</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      In the Tab menu, you can choose between <guimenuitem>View as
      Grid</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>View as List</guimenuitem>.
      In Grid mode, the tools are laid out in a rectangular
      array.  In List mode, they are lined up vertically, with each
      row showing the tool name, tool icon, and an "eye" icon if the
      tool is currently visible in the Toolbox.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Using the Tools dialog</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most basic thing you can do is to select a tool by clicking
      on its icon:  this has the same effect as clicking on an icon in
      the Toolbox.  You can do this in either List or Grid mode:  the
      other functions of the dialog are available only in List mode.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The most important function of the Tools dialog is to let you
      choose which tools to make visible in the Toolbox, by toggling
      the "eye" icons that appear on the left side of each row in List
      mode.  In particular, if you use the Color tools a lot, you may
      benefit from toggling visibility on for them here.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      You can also change the order of tools in the Toolbox, by
      clicking on an item in the Tools dialog, in List mode, and
      dragging it up or down in the list.  If you screw things up, you
      can always press the "Reset" button at the bottom of the dialog,
      to restore the defaults for order and visibility.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Right-clicking inside the dialog produces the Tools menu, which
      gives you an alternative way of toggling visibility or restoring
      the defaults.
    </para>

  </simplesect>

</sect1>
