<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--Section history
  2012-03-29 j.h: created
-->

<sect2 id="gimp-presets-dialog">
  <title>Tool Presets Dialog</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Presets</primary>
    <secondary>Presets Dialog</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.6, tool presets were not easy to use. You had
    to click on a tool first, and then click on the <guibutton>Restore
    Presets...</guibutton> button in the button bar at the bottom of the Tool
    options dialog... if you had not disabled this button bar in the Tab menu
    to make place on your desk! Now, with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.8, a
    dockable Tool Presets Dialog is available where you just have to click on a
    preset to open the corresponding tool with its saved options.
  </para>
  
  <figure>
    <title>The Tool Presets Dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/tool-presets-dialog.png"
format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The <quote>Tool Presets Dialog</quote> is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can access it:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            from an image menu:
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Tool Presets</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            or, as a tab in Toolbox window, through
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Tab Menu</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Add Tab</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Tool Presets</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Using the Tool Presets Dialog</title>
    <para>
      This dialog comes with a list of predefined presets. Each of them has an
      icon representing the tool presets will be applied to and a name.
    </para>
    <para>
      Presets can be tagged so that you can arrange presets display as
      you want. Please see <xref linkend="gimp-tagging"/> for more information
      about tagging.
    </para>
    <para>
      Double-clicking on a preset icon opens the Tool Preset Editor.
    </para>
    <para>
      Double-clicking on preset name allows you to edit this name.
    </para>
    <para>
      At the bottom of the dialog appear four buttons:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem >
          <para>
            <guilabel>Edit this tool preset</guilabel>: clicking on this button
            opens the Tool Preset Editor for the selected preset. You can
            actually edit presets you have created; predefined presets options
            are all grayed out and inactive. But you can create a new preset
            from a predefined preset and edit its options.
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/tool-preset-editor.png"
    format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            The Tool Preset Editor is described in
              <xref linkend="tool-preset-editor"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Create a new tool preset</guilabel>: before clicking on
            this button, you can either select an existing preset, or select a
            tool in Toolbox, for example the Healing Tool which is not in the 
            presets list. A new preset is created at the top of the dialog and
            the Tool Preset Editor is opened. Please see
            <xref linkend="tool-preset-editor"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Delete this tool preset</guilabel>: this button is active
            only for presets you have created.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Refresh tool presets</guilabel>: If you have added a
            preset manually in gimp/2.0/tool-presets folder, you have to click
            on this button to include it in the presets list.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
            With <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.8, tool presets are saved in a new
            format (.gtp). To use your 2.6 presets, you have to convert them
            using
       <ulink url="http://wiki.gimp.org/index.php/Mindstorm:Preset_converter"/>,
            until it is included in GIMP.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>The Tool Presets Dialog Context Menu</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/menus/presets-dialog-context-menu.png"
format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
      Right-clicking on the Presets Dialog opens a context menu where you find
      some commands already described with buttons: Edit tool preset, New tool
      preset, Refresh tool presets. You also find two new commands:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Duplicate Tool Preset</guilabel>: this command is always
            disabled. It is not necessary since, as we saw above, a duplicate
            is automatically created when you create a new preset from an
            existing preset.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Copy Tool Preset Location</guilabel>: this command copies
            the path to the tool preset file into clipboard.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
    