<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-07-01 j.h: create
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-welcome-dialog">
  <title>Welcome Dialog</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Welcome</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Welcome Dialog</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <quote>Welcome Dialog</quote> is shown when starting
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, unless you have disabled that. After updating to a
    new version, it will first show the Welcome page. After that first time,
    it will start with the Create page opened. This allows you to quickly
    continue with what you were working on before.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>The Welcome Dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/welcome-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <para>
      You can access it:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Welcome Dialog</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Using the Welcome Dialog</title>
    <para>
      The Welcome Dialog consists of five pages that you can switch between by
      clicking on their name at the top of the dialog. The most important ones
      are <guilabel>Personalize</guilabel>, which allows you to quickly adjust
      some settings; and <guilabel>Create</guilabel>, to select which images
      you want to open when starting <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following pages are part of the dialog.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Welcome</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the first page shown after you have updated your version of
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. It shows the exact version that you just
            installed.
          </para>
          <para>
            Below it are important links to <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s main
            website, tutorials, documentation, how to contribute, and making
            donations to support the development of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Personalize</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>The Personalize page</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/welcome-dialog-personalize.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            The Personalize page gives you quick access to a selection of
            settings that you may find useful to adjust to your personal
            preferences. All of these settings can also be accessed from the
            <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Preferences Dialog</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            These settings are divided in several groups, which will be
            explained below. The settings in the first three groups take effect
            immediately, which allows you to preview the changes.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Theme</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The settings here allow you to adjust the colors and icons
                  used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to your liking.
                  See also
                  <link linkend="gimp-prefs-theme">Theme</link> and
                  <link linkend="gimp-prefs-icon-theme">Icon</link>
                  settings in the Preferences Dialog.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Color scheme</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This allows you to choose which color scheme to use for
                        the current theme in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s interface.
                        Our own themes have a choice between <guilabel>Light
                        Colors</guilabel>, <guilabel>Middle Gray</guilabel>, and
                        <guilabel>Dark Colors</guilabel>.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Icon Theme</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This allows you to choose which icon theme to use in
                        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s interface. By default, there
                        is a choice between <guilabel>Default</guilabel> and
                        <guilabel>Legacy</guilabel>. The Legacy icons are here
                        for backwards compatibility. They are generally not
                        well suited to higher resolution screens and are only
                        available in a colored variant.
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        If you have installed custom themes, they will show up
                        in this list too.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Use symbolic icons if available</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This allows you to choose whether you prefer the
                        symbolic variant of the icon theme (if available).
                        The symbolic version is a grayscale flat variant, while
                        the non-symbolic variant has colored icons.
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        Note that this setting will only take effect if the icon
                        theme supports a symbolic variant.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Icon Scaling</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This group allows you to adjust the size of the icons.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Override icon sizes set by theme</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        Usually each icon theme sets the size of the icons.
                        By enabling this, you can override the size set by the
                        icon theme and adjust it with the setting below.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Icon sizes</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This slider allows you to adjust the size of the icons
                        in several steps between small and huge.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Font Scaling</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This allows you to adjust the size of the fonts.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Font sizes</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This slider allows you to adjust the size of the fonts
                        used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s interface between
                        50% and 200%, where 100% is the default size set by
                        the theme.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>GUI Language</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This drop-down list allows you to select the interface
                  language used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Note that this
                  change will only take effect after restarting
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Additional Customizations</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  These additional settings allow you to adjust several
                  unrelated preferences.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Merge menu and titlebar</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        When enabled the titlebar and the menu will be shown
                        together in one bar. This can be useful to save some
                        vertical space on your screen.
                        This requires a restart before it takes effect.
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        See also <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window">Image
                        Windows</link> preferences.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Enable check for updates</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This setting is not available when <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                        is installed as a package that is automatically updated.
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        This requires a working internet connection.
                        When enabled <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will regularly
                        check its website to see if a new version is available.
                        If there is, you will be notified, and can decide
                        whether you want to update or not. No personal info
                        is shared with our website.
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        See also <link linkend="gimp-prefs-system-resources">System
                        Resources</link>, <guilabel>Network Access</guilabel>
                        preferences.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Use tool groups</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        By default, tools in the toolbox are grouped together
                        to save space. A different tool in a group can be
                        selected by hovering or long-clicking on a group.
                        When you prefer to have all tools available directly,
                        instead of in groups, you can disable this setting here.
                      </para>
                      <para>
                        See also <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Toolbox</link>
                        preferences.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Contribute</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The contribute page has helpful links if you want to report bugs,
            help improving GIMP's code, translate the interface of GIMP, or if
            you want to donate money to help with the development of GIMP.
          </para>
          <!-- Since this is mostly text and links, let's not add an image, at least for now.
          <figure>
            <title>The Contribute page</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/welcome-dialog-contribute.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          -->
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Create</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Create page allows you to quickly open one or more of your
            last used images, to continue where you left off.
          </para>
          <para>
            From this page you can also choose to <guibutton>Create</guibutton>
            a new image, or <guibutton>Open</guibutton> the file dialog to look
            for a different image.
          </para>
          <para>
            If you just want to open one of your recently used images, you can
            double-click the image in the list.
            To open multiple images, select the ones you want in the list, then
            click the <guibutton>Open Selected Images</guibutton> button below
            the list.
          </para>
          <para>
            At the bottom of this page you will see the <guilabel>Show On
            Start</guilabel> setting. By default this page is shown every time
            you start <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You can disable this by
            unchecking this option. After that you can always enable it again
            by opening this dialog from the Help menu and going to the Create
            page.
          </para>
          <!-- Do we need an image here?
          <figure>
            <title>The Create page</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/welcome-dialog-create.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          -->
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Release Notes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This page shows a list of the most important changes in the latest
            version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The changes that have a triangle icon in front of them can be
            clicked to show where these changes can be found.
            Clicking the triangle starts a short animation that highlights the
            locations in the interface related to the change.
          </para>
          <!-- Since this is mostly text, let's not add an image, at least for now.
          <figure>
            <title>The Release Notes page</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/welcome-dialog-release-notes.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          -->
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
