<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--Section History
  2008-04-09 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2007-09-29 AntI: Added 'es'
  2006-01-02: fixed image scaling and made the file docbook compliant by lexa
  2008-01-28 jpl: update text & images
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-theme">
  <title>Theme</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Theme</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Theme</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Theme Preference</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/preferences/prefs-theme.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This page lets you select a theme, which determines many aspects of
    the appearance of the GIMP user interface, including the set of
    icons used, their sizes, fonts, spacing allowed in dialogs, etc.
    Two themes are supplied with GIMP: <guilabel>Default</guilabel>,
    which is probably best for most people, and
    <guilabel>Small</guilabel>, which may be preferable for those with
    small or low-resolution monitors.  Clicking on a theme in the list
    causes it to be applied immediately, so it is easy to see the result
    and change your mind if you don't like it.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can also use custom themes, either by downloading them from the
    net, or by copying one of the supplied themes and modifying it.
    Custom themes should be places in the <filename>themes</filename>
    subdirectory of your personal GIMP directory:  if they are, they
    will appear in the list here.  Each theme is actually a directory
    containing ASCII files that you can edit.  They are pretty
    complicated, and the meaning of the contents goes beyond the scope
    of this documentation, but you should feel free to experiment:  in
    the worst case, if you mess things up completely, you can always
    revert back to one of the supplied themes.
  </para>
  <para>
    You cannot edit the supplied themes unless you have administrator
    permissions, and even if you do, you shouldn't:  if you want to
    customize a theme, make a copy in your personal directory and work
    on it.  If you make a change and would like to see the result <quote>on
    the fly</quote>, you can do so by saving the edited theme file and then
    pressing <guilabel>Reload Current Theme</guilabel>.
  </para>
</sect2>
