<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2008-04-08 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2006-11-01 lexa: made the file docbook compliant
  2008-01-28 jpl: update text & images
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-interface">
  <title>
    <phrase>Interface</phrase>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  </title>

  <indexterm significance="normal">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Interface</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm significance="normal">
    <primary>Interface</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm significance="normal">
    <primary>Navigation</primary>
    <secondary>Preview size</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm significance="normal">
    <primary>Preview</primary>
    <secondary>Navigation preview size</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  
  

  
  

  
  

  
  
  
  

  
  

  
  
  
  

  
  

  
  

  
  

  <figure float="0">
    <title>
      <phrase>Assorted Interface Preferences</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/prefs-interface.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <caption>
        <para>
          This page lets you customize layer/channel previews and keyboard
          shortcuts.
        </para>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
    <title>
      <phrase>Options</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </title>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Previews</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Keyboard Shortcuts</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Previews</term>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <listitem>
        <para>
          By default, GIMP shows miniature previews of the contents of
          layers and channels in several places, including the Layers
          dialog.  If for some reason you would prefer to disable
          these, you can do it by unchecking <quote>Enable layer and
          channel previews</quote>.  If you do want previews to be shown,
          you can customize their sizes using the menus for <quote>Default
          layer and channel preview size</quote> and <quote>Navigation
          preview size</quote>.
        </para>
        

        
        

        
        
        
        
        
        
        
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Keyboard Shortcuts</term>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Any menu item can be activated by holding down
          <keycap moreinfo="none">Alt</keycap> and pressing a sequence of keys.
          Normally, the key associated with each menu entry is shown
          as an underlined letter in the text, called <emphasis>
          accelerator</emphasis>.  If for some reason you
          would prefer the underlines to go away (maybe because you
          think they're ugly and you don't use them anyway), then you
          can make this happen by unchecking <quote>Show menu
          mnemonics</quote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          GIMP can give you the ability to create keyboard shortcuts
          (key combinations that activate a menu entry) dynamically,
          by pressing the keys while the pointer hovers over the
          desired menu entry.  However, this capability is disabled by
          default, because it might lead novice users to accidentally
          overwrite the standard keyboard shortcuts.  If you want to
          enable it, check <quote>Use dynamics keyboard shortcuts</quote>
          here.
        </para>
        <para>
          Pressing the button for <quote>Configure Keyboard
          Shortcuts</quote> brings up the Shortcut Editor, which gives you
          a graphical interface to select menu items and assign shortcuts
          to them.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you change shortcuts, you will probably want your changes
          to continue to apply in future GIMP sessions.  If not,
          uncheck <quote>Save keyboard shortcuts on exit</quote>. But
          remember that you have done this, or you may be frustrated
          later. If you don't want to save shortcuts on exit every
          session, you can save the current settings at any time using the
          <quote>Save Keyboard Shortcuts Now</quote> button, and they will
          be applied to future sessions.  If you decide that you have made
          some bad decisions concerning shortcuts, you can reset them to
          their original state by pressing <quote>Reset Saved Keyboard
          Shortcuts to Default Values</quote>.
        </para>

        
        
        
        

        
        
        

        
        
        
        

        
        
        
        

        
        
        
        

        
        
        
        

        
        
        

        
        
        
        

        
        
        
        
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
