<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  Section history:
  2008-07-13 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2008-02-11 kost: added 'no'
  2007-12-26 lexa: initial version for en and de
  2008-01-28 jpl: update text & images
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-color-management">
  <title>Color Management</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Color Management</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Color Management</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Color Profile</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Color Management Preferences</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/preferences/prefs-color-management.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <para>
      This page lets you customize the GIMP color management.
    </para>
    <para>
      Some of the options let you choose a color profile from a menu. If the
      desired profile is not in the menu yet, you can add it by clicking on
      the <guimenuitem>Select color profile from disk...</guimenuitem> item.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        Files containing color profiles are easily recognizable by their
        <filename>.icc</filename> suffix. In addition to that they are
        usually stored all together in only a few places. If you are running
        GIMP on Mac OS X, you should try
        <filename>/Library/ColorSync/Profiles/</filename> and
        <filename>Library/Printers/[manufacturer]/Profiles</filename>.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <variablelist>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Color Management</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode of operation</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Using this option you can decide how the GIMP color management
            operates. There are three modes you can choose from:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guimenuitem>No color management</guimenuitem>: choosing this
                selection shuts down the color management in GIMP completely.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guimenuitem>Color managed display</guimenuitem>: with this
                selection you can enable the GIMP color management to
                provide a fully corrected display of the images according to
                the given color profile for the display.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guimenuitem>Print simulation</guimenuitem>: when choosing
                this selection, you enable the GIMP color management not only
                to apply the profile for the display, but also the selected
                printer simulation profile. Doing so, you can preview the
                color results of a print with that printer.
              </para>
              <note>
                <para>
                  Please note, that the GIMP color management is used to
                  enhance the display of images and the embedding of profiles
                  to image files only. Especially are the options you choose
                  in this dialog in no way used for printing from within GIMP.
                  This is because the printing is a special task done by a
                  more specialized printing engine that is no part of GIMP.
                </para>
              </note>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>RGB profile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Select the default color profile for working with RGB images.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>CMYK profile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Select the default color profile for conversion between RGB 
            for the screen work and CMYK for printing.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Monitor profile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option gives you two elements for interaction:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                You should select a display profile for this option. The
                selected color profile is used to display GIMP on the screen.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you activate the <guilabel>Try to use the system monitor
                profile</guilabel> option, GIMP will use the color profile
                provided for the displays by the operating systems color
                management system.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Display rendering intent</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rendering intents, as the one you can configure with this option,
            are ways of dealing with colors that are
            out-of-<xref linkend="glossary-gamut"/> colors
            present in the source space that the destination space is
            incapable of producing. There are four method rendering intents to
            choose from:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Perceptual</guimenuitem>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Relative colorimetric</guimenuitem>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Saturation</guimenuitem>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guimenuitem>Absolute colorimetric</guimenuitem>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            A description of the individual methods can be found at
            <xref linkend="glossary-rendering-intent"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Print simulation mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You should select a printer profile for this option. The selected
            color profile is used for the print simulation mode.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Softproof rendering intent</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option again provides two different elements for interaction:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                You can use the menu to select the rendering intent for the
                soft proof. They are the same as already described for the
                display rendering intent.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you enable the <guilabel>Mark out of gamut
                colors</guilabel> option, all pixels that have a color that
                is not printable are marked by a special color. Which color is
                used for this can also be chosen by you. You can do this
                simply by clicking on the color icon on the right besides the
                checkbox.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File Open behaviour</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Using this menu you can determine how GIMP behaves when opening a
            file that contains an embedded color profile that does not match
            the workspace sRGB. You can choose from the following entries:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guimenuitem>Ask what to do</guimenuitem>: if selected, GIMP
                will ask every time what to do.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guimenuitem>Keep embedded profile</guimenuitem>: if you
                choose this, GIMP will keep the attached profile and not
                convert the image to the workspace. The image is displayed
                correctly anyways, because the attached profile will be
                applied for display.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guimenuitem>Convert to RGB workspace</guimenuitem>: by
                choosing this entry GIMP will automatically use the attached
                color profile to convert the image to the workspace.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <note>
      <para>For more explanations:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ICC Profiles are explained in Wikipedia
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-icc"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            See OpenICC project
            (<xref linkend="bibliography-online-openicc"/>) where GIMP and
            others great names of free infography contribute to.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Many profiles to load from the web:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ICC sRGB Workspace:
            <productname>ICCsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-iccsrgb"/>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Microsoft sRGB Workspace:
            <productname>MsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-microsoft-srgb"/>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Adobe RGB98 Workspace :
            <productname>Adobe RGB (1998)</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-adobrgb"/>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ECI (European Color Initiative) Profiles:
            <productname>ECI</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-eci"/>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
