<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--  Section history:
  2008-02-11 kost: added 'no'
  2007-12-26 lexa: initial version for en and de
  2008-01-28 jpl: update text & images
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-color-management" lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Color Management</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Farbmanagement</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Gestion des couleurs</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Gestione del colore</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Fargestyring</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Color Management</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Color Management</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Color Profile</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Dialog</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Farbmanagement</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbmanagement</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbprofil</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogues</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Gestion de la couleur</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Color Management</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Color Profile</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestre</primary>
    <secondary>Preferenze</secondary>
    <tertiary>Gestione del colore</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Gestione del colore</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Profilo colore</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Dialogar</primary>
    <secondary>Brukarinnstillingar</secondary>
    <tertiary>Fargestyring</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fargestyring</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fargeprofil</primary></indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Color Management Preferences</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Die Einstellungsansicht, um das Farbmanagement anzupassen
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Réglage des profils colorimétriques ICC dans Gimp</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Preferenze della gestione del colore</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Brukarinnstillingane for fargestyring</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en">
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-color-management.png' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="../images/preferences/de/prefs-color-management.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="../images/preferences/fr/prefs-color-management.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref='../images/preferences/it/prefs-color-management.png' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref='../images/preferences/no/prefs-color-management.png' />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingane</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang='en'>
      This page lets you customize the GIMP color management.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      In der Einstellungsansicht können Sie Einstellungen zum
      GIMP-Farbmanagement vornehmen.
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Cette page permet de choisir les paramètres de la gestion des couleurs.
      Les profils ICC permettent de caractériser tout type de matériel
      d'infographie, qu'il soit en RVB (basé sur un fond noir) comme un écran
      ou un appareil photographique ou qu'il soit en CMJN (basé sur un fond
      blanc) comme une imprimante. Une fois les matériel caractérisés, il
      devient aisé de reproduire fidèlement les couleurs d'un appareil à
      l'autre.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questa pagina permette di personalizzare la gestione del colore in
      GIMP.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I dette dialogvindauget kan du tilpassa fargestyringa etter dine
      eigne behov og ønskjer.
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Some of the options let you choose a color profile from a menu. If the
      desired profile is not in the menu yet, you can add it by clicking on
      the <guimenuitem>Select color profile from disk...</guimenuitem> item.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Manche der im Folgenden beschriebenen Eigenschaften erfordern die
      Auswahl eines Farbprofils. Hierzu steht zunächst einmal ein Klappmenü
      zur Verfügung. Dieses enthält die bereits bekannten Farbprofile. Sollte
      das gesuchte Profil nicht in der Liste enthalten sein, hilft der
      unterste Menüeintrag <guimenuitem>Farbprofil von Festplatte
      wählen...</guimenuitem> weiter. Er erlaubt es, eine Farbprofildatei
      direkt auszuwählen.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Certaines options permettent de choisir un profil colorimètrique à partir
      d'un menu. Si le profil désiré n'est pas disponible, il est possible de
      l'ajouter en cliquant sur
      <guimenuitem>Choisir un profil de couleurs sur le disque...</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Alcune delle opzioni permettono di scegliere un profilo colore da un
      menu. Se il profilo desiderato non è ancora presente nel menu è
      possibile aggiungerlo facendo clic sulla voce <guimenuitem>Seleziona
      il profilo di colore da disco...</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I ein del av innstillingane har du bruk for å bestemme kva for 
      fargeprofil du vil bruke. Dette gjer du ved hjelp av nedtrekksmenyane.
      Dersom den ønskte fargeprofilen ikkje finst i menyen, kan du hente
      han med kommandoen <guimenuitem>Vel fargeprofil frå 
      disk...</guimenuitem> i nedtrekksmenyen.
    </para>

    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        Files containing color profiles are easily recognizable by their
        <filename>.icc</filename> suffix. In addition to that they are
        usually stored all together in only a few places. If you are running
        GIMP on Mac OS X, you should try
        <filename>/Library/ColorSync/Profiles/</filename> and
        <filename>Library/Printers/[manufacturer]/Profiles</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die Dateien mit Farbprofilen sind in der Regel leicht an der Endung
        <filename>.icc</filename> zu erkennen. Außerdem befinden sie sich
        oftmals an einheitlichen, jedoch betriebssystemabhängigen Orten.
        Unter Mac OS X zum Beispiel finden sich viele Profile unter
        <filename>/Library/ColorSync/Profiles/</filename> bzw.
        <filename>Library/Printers/[Herstellername]/Profiles</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les fichiers de profil colorimètriques sont repérables grâce à leur
        extension <filename>.icc</filename>. De plus ils sont stockés à des
        emplacements particuliers. Les utilisateurs du GIMP sur Mac OS X,
        regarderont dans :
        <filename>/Library/ColorSync/Profiles/</filename> et
        <filename>Library/Printers/[manufacturer]/Profiles</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        I file contenenti profili di colore sono facilmente riconoscibili
        dalla loro estensione del file: <filename>.icc</filename>. Inoltre
        essi sono normalmente memorizzati tutti assieme in pochi posti. Se
        si sta usando GIMP su Mac OS X, si dovrebbe cercare in 
        <filename>/Library/ColorSync/Profiles/</filename> e in
        <filename>Library/Printers/[costruttore]/Profiles</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Filer som inneheld fargeprofilar har filutvidinga 
        <filename>.icc</filename> og er som oftast lagra i maskinen 
        på noen få stader i samband med ein del programvare. Du finn
        dei enklast ved å søke etter <filename>*.icc</filename> på 
        maskinen din. For GIMP på Mac OS X kan du kikke på katalogane 
        <filename>/Library/ColorSync/Profiles/</filename> og
        <filename>Library/Printers/[produsent]/Profiles</filename>.
      </para>
    </tip>

    <variablelist>
      <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Color Management</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbmanagement</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Gestion de la couleur</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Gestione del colore</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fargestyring</primary></indexterm>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mode of operation</term>
        <term lang="de">Arbeitsmodus</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mode d'opération</term>
        <term lang="it">Modalità di lavoro</term>
        <term lang="no">Operasjonsmodus</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Using this option you can decide how the GIMP color management
            operates. There are three modes you can choose from:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, wie das
            Farbmanagement in GIMP angewendet wird. Hierzu stehen Ihnen in
            einem Klappmenü verschiedene Einstellungen zur Auswahl:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette option détermine si la gestion de la couleur par le GIMP est
            active ou non. Il existe trois modes de gestion :
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Usando quest'opzione è possibile decidere come far operare la
            gestione del colore di GIMP. Ci sono tre modalità fra cui
            scegliere:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her bestemmer du korleis fargestyringa for GIMP skal arbeide.
            Du har tre val:
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>No color management</guimenuitem>: choosing this
                selection shuts down the color management in GIMP completely.
               </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Keine Farbverwaltung</guimenuitem>: Mit dieser
                Einstellung können Sie das Farbmanagement in GIMP komplett
                ausschalten.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guimenuitem>Pas de gestion des couleurs</guimenuitem>:
                désactive la gestion des couleurs dans toutes les fonctions du
                GIMP.
               </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Nessuna gestione del colore</guimenuitem>:
                scegliendo questa selezione si disabilita completamente
                ogni operazione relativa alla gestione del colore in GIMP.
               </para>
               <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Ingen fargestyring</guimenuitem>: Betyr at
                GIMP ikkje bruker noen form for fargestyring.
               </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Color managed display</guimenuitem>: with this
                selection you can enable the GIMP color management to
                provide a fully corrected display of the images according to
                the given color profile for the display.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Farbkorrigierte Darstellung</guimenuitem>: Wenn
                Sie diese Einstellung auswählen, wird das Farbmanagement in
                GIMP aktiviert und die Darstellung auf dem Bildschirm erfolgt
                farbkorrigiert.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guimenuitem>Affichage en couleur gérée</guimenuitem>:
                applique la gestion des couleurs de base permettant un rendu
                fidèle à l'écran. L'affichage des images sera entièrement
                corrigé en accord avec le profil colorimètrique correspondant.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Display con gestione del colore</guimenuitem>:
                con questa selezione si abilita la gestione del colore in
                GIMP fornendo una visualizzazione delle immagini
                completamente corretta secondo il profilo del display
                selezionato dall'utente.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Fargestyrt vising</guimenuitem>: Dette valet
                aktiviserer GIMP si fargestyring. Dette gjer at skjermvisinga
                av bileta blir korrigert i høve til den fargeprofilen du har vald.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Print simulation</guimenuitem>: when choosing
                this selection, you enable the GIMP color management not only
                to apply the profile for the display, but also the selected
                printer simulation profile. Doing so, you can preview the
                color results of a print with that printer.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Drucksimulation</guimenuitem>: Durch Auswählen
                dieser Einstellung können Sie das Farbmanagement in GIMP so
                aktivieren, dass die Ausgabe auf dem Bildschirm farbgetreu die
                Ausgabe auf einem Drucker simuliert. Hierzu wird neben dem
                angegebenen Farbprofil für die Anzeige auch das eingestellte
                Farbprofil für die Druckersimulation verwendet.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guimenuitem>Simulation d'impression</guimenuitem>: permet la
                gestion de la couleur par GIMP, en utilisant un profil
                colorimètrique non seulement pour l'affichage vidéo, mais aussi
                pour l'impression permettant un rendu à l'écran de ce qui sera
                imprimé.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Simulazione di stampa</guimenuitem>: quando si
                sceglie questa selezione, si abilita la gestione del colore
                di GIMP non solo applicata al profilo di visualizzazione ma
                anche per la simulazione di stampa. Con ciò, è possibile
                visualizzare l'anteprima di stampa dei colori di una data
                stampante.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Utskriftsimulering</guimenuitem>: Dette valet
                gjer at GIMP vil bruke fargeprofilen for skrivaren i tillegg til
                fargeprofilen for visinga. Dette gjer at du kan førehandsvise
                utskriftene slik dei blir sjåande ut i utskrifta.
              </para>

              <note>
                <para lang="en">
                  Please note, that the GIMP color management is used to
                  enhance the display of images and the embedding of profiles
                  to image files only. Especially are the options you choose
                  in this dialog in no way used for printing from within GIMP.
                  This is because the printing is a special task done by a
                  more specialized printing engine that is no part of GIMP.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Bitte beachten Sie, dass sich das Farbmanagement in GIMP
                  lediglich auf die Darstellung beim Bearbeiten und die
                  Einbettung von Farbprofilen in Bilddateien auswirkt.
                  Insbesondere wirken sich die hier vorgenommen Einstellungen
                  <emphasis>nicht</emphasis>
                  auf das Drucken von Bildern aus GIMP heraus aus. Dies ist
                  eine Aufgabe des Druckmoduls, welches nicht Bestandteil von
                  GIMP ist.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Notez que la gestion de la couleur par GIMP est utilisée pour
                  l'amélioration de l'affichage des images et des profils
                  incorporés dans celles-ci. Les options choisies dans ce
                  dialogue ne sont en aucun cas utilisées pour des impressions
                  à partir du GIMP parce que l'impression est une tâche obtenue
                  par l'utilisation d'un moteur spécial ne faisant pas partie
                  du GIMP.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  La gestione del colore di GIMP viene usata solamente per
                  migliorare la resa della visualizzazione delle immagini e
                  dei profili di colore incorporati ad esse. Le opzioni
                  di GIMP non sono in alcun modo utilizzate per
                  la stampa. Ciò è dovuto al fatto che la stampa è un
                  compito particolare affidato a motori di elaborazione
                  specializzati e indipendenti da GIMP.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Legg merke til at fargestyringa i GIMP bare blir brukt for
                  å forbetra <emphasis>visinga</emphasis> av bileta på
                  skjermen og for å legge inn fargeprofilar i biletfilene.
                  Ingen av desse innstillingane blir brukte når du skriv ut
                  papirkopiar. Utskrivinga blir utført med spesialprogram,
                  utskrivingsmodular, som ikkje er ein del av GIMP.
                </para>
              </note>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry><!-- end: mode of operation -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">RGB profile</term>
        <term lang="de">RGB-Profil</term>
        <term lang="fr">Profil RVB</term>
        <term lang="it">Profilo RGB</term>
        <term lang="no">RGB-profil</term>

        <listitem>
          <!-- TODO: en de it some help needed here -->
          <para lang="en">
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
          </para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
          <para lang="fr">
            Le profil d'epace de travail RVB servant de référence à Gimp. On
            doit indiquer ici un profil sRGB (conseillé avec Gimp qui
            travaille sur 8 bits/canal) ou un profil Adobe RGB 98 plus large.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
          </para>
          <para lang="no"> <!--Someone able to write this?-->
            [Noen som kan skrive denne?]
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry><!-- end: RGB profile -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">CMYK profile</term>
        <term lang="de">CMYK-Profil</term>
        <term lang="fr">Profil CMYK</term>
        <term lang="it">Profilo CMYK</term>
        <term lang="no">CMYK-profil</term>

        <listitem>
          <!-- TODO: en de it some help needed here -->
          <para lang="en">
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
          </para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
          <para lang="fr">
            Le profil CMJN permettant de convertir les images de RVB vers CMJN.
            La séparation d'une image RVB en calques CMJN dans une image au
            format TIFF nécessite toujours un greffon additionnel appelé
            Separate+.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
          </para>
          <para lang="no"> <!--Someone able to write this?-->
            [Noen som kan skrive denne?]
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry><!-- end: CMYK profile -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Monitor profile</term>
        <term lang="de">Bildschirmprofil</term>
        <term lang="fr">Profil moniteur</term>
        <term lang="it">Profilo monitor</term>
        <term lang="no">Skjermprofil</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option gives you two elements for interaction:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese Eigenschaft stellt Ihnen zwei Eingabeelemente zur Verfügung: 
          </para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
          <para lang="fr">
            Le profil caractérisant le moniteur. Dans l'idéal le profil est
            obtenu après un calibrage colorimétrique par sonde de l'écran. Les
            écrans vieillissant assez rapidement il est conseillé de faire une
            recalibration chaque semestre. Le profil peut généralement être
            aussi obtenu depuis le système d'exploitation (ou système de
            fenêtrage) mais la qualité est inférieure.
            Cette option a deux éléments d'interaction:
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Quest'opzione fornisce due elementi di interazione:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her har du to val:
          </para>
          
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                You should select a display profile for this option. The
                selected color profile is used to display GIMP on the screen.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Im Klappmenü sollten Sie das Farbprofil eines Anzeigegerätes
                wählen. Dieses wird von GIMP für die Ausgabe auf dem
                Bildschirm verwendet.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Vous pouvez choisir un profil d'affichage lequel sera utilisé
                par GIMP à l'écran.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Tramite quest'opzione si dovrebbe selezionare un profilo
                per lo schermo. Il profilo di colore selezionato viene
                usato per mostrare GIMP sullo schermo al meglio.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Du kan velje ein visingsprofil på same måten som ovanfor.
                Den valde fargeprofilen blir brukt for visingar på skjermen..
              </para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <!-- TODO: en de lexa asks: how do I see whether the system
                   provides a profile or not?? ciampix is curious about it
                   too :-) -->
              <para lang="en">
                If you activate the <guilabel>Try to use the system monitor
                profile</guilabel> option, GIMP will use the color profile
                provided for the displays by the operating systems color
                management system.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Wenn Sie die Eigenschaft <guilabel>Wenn möglich das
                System-Bildschirmprofil verwenden</guilabel> aktivieren, so
                wird GIMP versuchen dasjenige Farbprofil zur Anzeige
                verwenden, welches vom Farbmanagement des Betriebssystems zur
                Verfügung gestellt wird.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Si vous cochez l'option <guilabel>Try to use the system monitor
                profile</guilabel>, GIMP utilisera le profil du système
                d'exploitation (ou système de fenêtrage).
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Se si attiva l'opzione <guilabel>prova a usare il profilo
                del monitor di sistema</guilabel>, GIMP userà il profilo di
                colore fornito per il display dalla gestione del colore del
                sistema operativo in uso.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Dersom du aktiviserer <guilabel>Prøv å bruke skjermprofilen i
                systemet</guilabel> vil GIMP bruke operativsystemet si 
                fargestyring.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry><!-- end: monitor profile -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Display rendering intent</term>
        <term lang="de">Farbanpassung des Bildschirms</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mode de rendu de l'affichage</term>
        <term lang="it">Intento di rendering per il display</term>
        <term lang="no">Fargetilpassinga for skjermen</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Rendering intents, as the one you can configure with this option,
            are ways of dealing with colors that are
            out-of-<xref linkend="glossary-gamut"/> colors
            present in the source space that the destination space is
            incapable of producing. There are four method rendering intents to
            chose from:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können sie die Methode der Farbanpassung
            für die Darstellung auf dem Bildschirm wählen. Die Farbanpassung
            wird immer dann verwendet, wenn Farben wegen der technischen
            Beschränkungen eines Ausgabegerätes nicht korrekt wiedergegeben
            werden können, da sie sich außerhalb des
            <xref linkend="glossary-gamut" /> befinden.
            In einem solchen Fall muss die entsprechende Farbe
            durch eine auf dem Gerät darstellbare ersetzt werden. In einem
            Klappmenü können Sie die Art der Farbanpassung auswählen, die für
            die Bildschirmdarstellung verwendet wird:
          </para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
          <para lang="fr">
            Utilisé pour la conversion du RVB vers le moniteur. Il détermine
            comment les couleurs sont converties d'un profil à l'autre et en
            particulier comment seront traitées les couleurs qui sont dans le
            profil source et pas dans le profil de destination.
            (Voir <xref linkend="glossary-gamut"/>)
            Il y a quatre méthodes de rendu :
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            L'intento di rendering è un'opzione con la quale è possibile
            suggerire come gestire i colori fuori <xref
            linkend="glossary-gamut"/>, cioè presenti nello spazio
            sorgente ma che lo spazio destinazione non è in grado di
            riprodurre. Ci sono quattro intenti di rendering tra cui
            scegliere:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her bestemmer du korleis fargar som fell utanom fargeområdet
            for fargemodellen skal behandlast (<xref 
            linkend="glossary-gamut"/>). Du har fire ulike metodar å
            velje mellom:
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en"><guimenuitem>Perceptual</guimenuitem></para>
              <para lang="de"><guimenuitem>Wahrnehmung</guimenuitem></para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
              <para lang="fr">
                Le rendu <guimenuitem>Perceptif</guimenuitem>
                conserve les écarts entre couleurs, adopté souvent pour la
                conversion RGB vers CMJN.
              </para>
              <para lang="it"><guimenuitem>Percettivo</guimenuitem></para>
              <para lang="no"><guimenuitem>Perseptuell</guimenuitem></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Relative colorimetric</guimenuitem>
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Kolorimetrisch (relativ)</guimenuitem>
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Le rendu <guimenuitem>Colorimétrie relative</guimenuitem>
                choisit la couleur voisine la plus proche pour une couleur qui
                ne peut être rendue en réajustant en final toutes les couleurs
                pour conserver le point blanc
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Colorimetrico relativo</guimenuitem>
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Relativt kolorimetrisk</guimenuitem>
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en"><guimenuitem>Saturation</guimenuitem></para>
              <para lang="de"><guimenuitem>Sättigung</guimenuitem></para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
              <para lang="fr">
                Le rendu <guimenuitem>Saturation</guimenuitem> conserve en
                priorité les couleurs vives.
              </para>
              <para lang="it"><guimenuitem>Saturazione</guimenuitem></para>
              <para lang="no"><guimenuitem>Metning</guimenuitem></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Absolute colorimetric</guimenuitem>
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Kolorimetrisch (absolut)</guimenuitem>
              </para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
              <para lang="fr">
                Le rendu <guimenuitem>Colorimétrie absolue</guimenuitem> choisit
                la couleur voisine la plus proche pour une couleur qui ne peut
                être rendue mais sans tenir compte du point blanc.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Colorimetrico assoluto</guimenuitem>
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Absolutt kolorimetrisk</guimenuitem>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang="en">
            A description of the individual methods can be found at
            <xref linkend="glossary-rendering-intent" />.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Eine Beschreibung der einzelnen Methoden finden Sie im Glossar
            unter <xref linkend="glossary-rendering-intent" />.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Une description de caque méthode est accessible à
            <xref linkend="glossary-rendering-intent" />.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Una descrizione dei singoli metodi la si può trovare su
            <xref linkend="glossary-rendering-intent" />.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Alle desse metodane er omtalte i ordlista under 
            <xref linkend="glossary-rendering-intent" />.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry><!-- end: display rendering intent -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Print simulation mode</term>
        <term lang="de">Drucksimulationsprofil</term>
        <term lang="fr">Profil de simulation d'impression</term>
        <term lang="it">Modalità di simulazione di stampa</term>
        <term lang="no">Skrivarsimuleringsprofil</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You should select a printer profile for this option. The selected
            color profile is used for the print simulation mode.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Für diese Eigenschaft sollten Sie das Farbprofil eines Druckers
            auswählen. Das hier ausgewählte Farbprofil wird für die
            Drucksimulation auf dem Bildschirm verwendet.
          </para>
<!--(Référence : http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/FonctionsFaqGimp24icc)-->
          <para lang="fr">
            Profil caractérisant un matériel et un papier d'impression à
            simuler. A obtenir chez le fabricant du matériel quand vous imprimez
            à la maison ou auprès de l'imprimeur si vous imprimez à l'extérieur.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Per usare quest'opzione è necessario prima selezionare un
            profilo di colore per la stampante. Il profilo di colore
            selezionato verrà poi utilizzato per la modalità di simulazione
            di stampa.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her bestemmer du kva fargeprofil som skal brukast for å
            simulera utskrifta. Bruk helst ein profil som stemmer med
            den skrivaren du har tenkt å bruke.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry><!-- print simulation mode -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Softproof rendering intent</term>
        <term lang="de">Farbanpassung der Drucksimulation</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mode de rendu de la simulation</term>
        <term lang="it">Intento di rendering per la simulazione a video
        (softproof)</term>
        <term lang="no">Førehandsvising på skjermen</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option again provides two different elements for interaction:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese Eigenschaft stellt Ihnen zwei Eingabeelemente zur Verfügung: 
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette option aussi quatre éléments d'interaction.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Anche quest'opzione prevede due differenti elementi di interazione:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Også her kan du velje mellom to ulike metodar for fargetilpassing:
          </para>
          
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                You can use the menu to select the rendering intent for the
                soft proof. They are the same as already described for the
                display rendering intent.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                In einem Klappmenü können Sie die Art der Farbanpassung
                auswählen, die für die Drucksimulation verwendet wird. Die
                verfügbaren Methoden gleichen denen für die Anzeige.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Ce sont les mêmes que pour le mode de rendu de l'affichage.
                Sélectionnez-en une à l'aide du menu déroulant.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                È possibile usare il menu per selezionare l'intento di
                rendering per la simulazione a video della stampa (soft
                proof). Sono le stesse voci descritte per l'intento di
                rendering per il monitor.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Du kan velje metode for fargetilpassinga i
                nedtrekksmenyen. Vala her er dei same som omtalte
                ovanfor.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                If you enable the <guilabel>Mark out of gamut
                colors</guilabel> option, all pixels that have a color that
                is not printable are marked by a special color. Which color is
                used for this can also be chosen by you. You can do this
                simply by clicking on the color icon on the right besides the
                checkbox.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Wenn Sie die Checkbox
                <guilabel>Farben außerhalb des Gamut markieren</guilabel>
                aktivieren, so werden die nicht druckbaren Bildbereich
                farblich markiert. Die hierzu verwendete Farbe können Sie
                mittels eines Farbwählers festlegen, der neben der Checkbox
                durch Anklicken aufgerufen werden kann. 
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Si vous cochez l'option <guilabel>Mark out of gamut
                colors</guilabel>, tous les pixels ayant une couleur
                non-imprimable seront marqués d'une couleur spéciale. Il est
                possible de choisir celle-ci en cliquant sur l'icône de couleur
                à droite.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Se si abilita l'opzione <guilabel>evidenzia i colori fuori
                gamut</guilabel>, tutti i pixel con un colore non
                stampabile verranno marchiati con un colore speciale. Il
                colore per questa funzione può essere selezionato
                dall'utente. Per far ciò basta fare clic sull'icona
                colorata presente a destra della casella di selezione
                dell'opzione.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Dersom du aktiviserer <guilabel>Merk fargane som er
                utanfor fargekartet</guilabel> vil alle pikslane som har
                ein farge som ikkje kan skrivast ut bli sett til ein bestemt
                farge som du kan bestemma ved å klikke i fargeruta.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">File Open behaviour</term>
        <term lang="de">Verhalten des Datei-Öffnen-Dialogs</term>
        <term lang="fr">Comportement à l'ouverture d'un fichier</term>
        <term lang="it">Comportamento apertura file</term>
        <term lang="no">Oppførsel ved opning av fila</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Using this menu you can determine how GIMP behaves when opening a
            file that contains an embedded color profile that is not matches
            the workspace sRGB. You can choose from the following entries:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In einem Klappmenü können Sie einstellen, wie GIMP beim Öffnen von
            Bilddateien vorgeht, wenn diese ein eigebettetes Farbprofil
            beinhalten, welches <emphasis>nicht</emphasis> dem Arbeitsfarbraum
            sRGB entspricht. Folgende Möglichkeiten stehen zur Auswahl:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Détermine le comportement de Gimp lorsqu'est ouverte une image
            contenant un profil ICC ne correspondant pas à l'espace de travail
            sRGB. Vous pouvez choisir:
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Con questo menu è possibile impostare il comportamento di GIMP
            all'apertura di file contenenti un profilo colore incorporato
            che non corrisponda allo spazio di lavoro sRGB. È possibile
            scegliere tra le seguenti voci:
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her bestemmer du kva GIMP skal gjere når du opnar ei fil som
            inneheld ein fargeprofil som ikkje er heilt i samsvar med
            arbeidsprofilen sRGB. Du har desse vala:
          </para>
          
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Ask what to do</guimenuitem>: if selected, GIMP
                will ask every time what to do.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Nachfragen</guimenuitem>: Wenn Sie diesen
                Menüeintrag auswählen, wird GIMP jedesmal, wenn eine Bilddatei
                mit eingebettetem Farbprofil geladen wird nachfragen. Sie
                müssen dann entscheiden, ob das eingebettete Profil erhalten
                werden, oder das Bild in den Arbeitsfarbraum konvertiert
                werden soll.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guimenuitem>Demander quoi faire</guimenuitem>: GIMP pose la
                question chaque fois.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Domanda cosa fare</guimenuitem>: se
                selezionato, GIMP chiederà ogni volta il da farsi.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Spør om kva som skal gjerast</guimenuitem>:
                GIMP vil spørje deg om biletet skal bruke den innebygde
                fargeprofilen eller omforme biletet til gjeldande profil.
              </para>
            </listitem>
    
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Keep embedded profile</guimenuitem>: if you
                choose this, GIMP will keep the attached profile and not
                convert the image to the workspace. The image is displayed
                correctly anyways, because the attached profile will be
                applied for display.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>Eingebettetes Profil behalten</guimenuitem>: Wenn
                Sie diese Einstellung auswählen, wird GIMP automatisch beim
                Laden eines Bildes mit eingebettetem Farbprofil dieses
                erhalten und das Bild nicht nicht in den Arbeitsfarbraum
                überführen. Die Anzeige ist dabei trotzdem farbgetreu, da das
                Profil bei der Darstellung berücksichtigt wird.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guimenuitem>Conserver le profil embarqué</guimenuitem>: GIMP
                conservera ce profil et ne convertira pas l'image vers l'espace
                de travail. Quel que soit le cas, l'affichage sera correct car
                car le profil embarqué sera appliqué pour l'affichage.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Mantieni il profilo incorporato</guimenuitem>:
                se si sceglie questa opzione, GIMP manterrà il profilo
                allegato e non convertirà l'immagine allo spazio di
                lavoro. L'immagine verrà mostrata comunque correttamente,
                dato che il profilo allegato verrà applicato per la
                visualizzazione.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Behald innlagt profil</guimenuitem>: 
                Dette betyr at GIMP vil bruke den profilen som følgjer med
                biletet. Fargane blir viste korrekt same kva du vel fordi biletet
                alltid blir vist med den innebygde profilen.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guimenuitem>Convert to RGB workspace</guimenuitem>: by
                choosing this entry GIMP will automatically use the attached
                color profile to convert the image to the workspace.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guimenuitem>In RGB-Farbraum umwandeln</guimenuitem>: Sobald
                diese Einstellung aktiviert ist, wird GIMP automatisch beim
                Laden eines Bildes mit eingebettetem Farbprofil das Bild in
                den Arbeitsfarbraum überführen. Dabei wird das beigefügte
                Farbprofil entfernt.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guimenuitem>Convertir vers l'espace RVB</guimenuitem>:
                GIMP utilisera automatiquement le profil embarqué pour convertir
                l'image vers l'espace de travail.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                <guimenuitem>Converti allo spazio di lavoro
                RGB</guimenuitem>: scegliendo questa voce GIMP userà
                automaticamente il profilo di colore allegato per
                convertire l'immagine allo spazio di lavoro.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guimenuitem>Konverter til RGB-fargeområdet</guimenuitem>:
                Gjer at GIMP automatisk vil konvertere den medfølgjande
                fargeprofilen til den gjeldande profilen du har sett for maskinen.                
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        For more expanations :
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <!--TODO-->
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour de plus amples explications :
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <!--TODO-->
      </para>
      <para lang="no">Vidare utdjuping:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            ICC Profils are explained in Wikipedia.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les Profils ICC sont expliqués dans Wikipedia.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            ICC-profilane er forklarte i Wikipedia. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            See Open ICCprojet where GIMP and others great names of free
            infography contribute to.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Voir le projet OpenICC auquel participent GIMP et tous les grands
            noms de l'infographie libre.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Sjå innan prosjektet OpenICC og andre store namn innan fri
            grafisk programvare.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para lang="en">
        Many profils to load from the web :
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <!--TODO-->
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quelques profils à télécharger :
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <!--TODO-->
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Du kan også laste ned mange profilar frå:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            ICC sRGB Workspace :
            <productname>ICCsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-iccsrgb" />
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Profil d'espace de travail ICC sRVB :
            <productname>ICCsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-iccsrgb" />
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            ICC sRGB Workspace:
            <productname>ICCsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-iccsrgb" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Microsoft sRVB Workspace :
            <productname>MsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-microsoft-srgb" />
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Profil d'espace de travail Microsoft sRVB :
            <productname>MsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-microsoft-srgb" />
          </para>
          <para lang="it">Ms
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Microsoft sRVB Workspace:
            <productname>MsRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-microsoft-srgb" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Adobe RVB98 Workspace :
            <productname>ADOBRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-adobrgb" />
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Profil d'espace de travail Adobe RVB98 :
            <productname>ADOBRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-adobrgb" />
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Adobe RVB98 Workspace:
            <productname>ADOBRGB</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-adobrgb" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            ECI (European Color Initiative) Profils :
            <productname>ECI</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-eci" />
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Profils de l'ECI (European Color Initiative) :
            <productname>ECI</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-eci" />
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <!--TODO-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            ECI (European Color Initiative) Profils:
            <productname>ECI</productname>
            <xref linkend="bibliography-online-eci" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>