<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-09-30 AntI: Added 'es'
  2007-03-25 KoSt: added 'no'
  2006-11-01 lexa: make docbook compliant
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
  2008-02-04 Vérification + compléments par jpl in french
-->
<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-window-management' lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="de">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-18</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-00-30</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang='en'>Window Managment</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Správa oken</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Fensterverwaltung</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Gestión de la ventana</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Gestion des fenêtres</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Gestione finestre</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Vindaugehandtering</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Управление внешним видом окон</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">窗口管理</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Window management</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image Windows</primary>
    <secondary>Basic settings</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>dialogy</primary>
    <secondary>Předvolby</secondary>
    <tertiary>Správa oken</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Správa oken</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Dialog</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Fensterverwaltung</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Fensterverwaltung</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Diálogos</primary>
    <secondary>Preferencias</secondary>
    <tertiary>Gestión de la ventana</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Ventanas de la imagen</primary>
    <secondary>Configuración básica</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogues</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Gestion des fenêtres</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Fenêtres d'image</primary>
    <secondary>Réglages de base</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestre</primary>
    <secondary>Preferenze</secondary>
    <tertiary>Gestione finestre</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Gestione finestre</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Dialogar</primary>
    <secondary>Innstillingar</secondary>
    <tertiary>Vindaugehandtering</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Vindaugehandtering</primary>
    <secondary>Innstillingar</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Диалоги</primary>
    <secondary>Настройки</secondary>
    <tertiary>Управление внешним видом окон</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Управление внешним видом окон</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>窗口管理</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>窗口管理</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang='en'>Window Management Preferences</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Předvolby pro správu oken</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Die Ansicht in den Einstellungen zum Anpassen der Fensterverwaltung
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Preferencias Gestión de la ventana</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Préférences pour la gestion des fenêtres</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Preferenze della gestione finestre</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Настройка внешнего вида и поведения окон</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Innstillingar for å tilpasse vindaugebehandlinga
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">窗口管理首选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs;en;ru;zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/prefs-window-management.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/preferences/de/prefs-window-management.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/preferences/it/prefs-window-management.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="es">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/es/prefs-window-management.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/preferences/fr/prefs-window-managment.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/preferences/no/prefs-window-management.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you customize the way windows are handled in GIMP. You
    should note that GIMP does not manipulate windows directly, instead it
    sends requests to the window manager (i. e., to Windows if you are running
    in Windows; to Metacity if you are running in a standard Gnome setup in
    Linux; etc). Because there are many window managers, and not all of them
    are well behaved, it cannot be guaranteed that the functions described
    here will actually work as described. However, if you are using a modern,
    standards-compliant window manager, they ought to.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Na této kartě lze nastavit způsob, jakým GIMP zachází se svými okny. GIMP
    ovšem s okny nezachází přímo, pouze posílá žádosti správci oken (tedy
    například Metacity ve standardním GNOME na Linuxu). Protože existuje mnoho
    různých správců oken, a ne každý se chová jak by měl, nelze zaručit, že
    následující funkce budou pracovat, jak je zde popsáno. Pokud však
    používáte moderního správce oken podporujícího standardy, mělo by být vše
    v pořádku.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    In dieser Ansicht können Sie durch Vorgabeeinstellungen das
    Zusammenspiel zwischen <acronym>GIMP</acronym> und Window-Manager
    beeinflussen. Da es sehr viele Window-Manager gibt und sich nicht
    alle ordnungsgemäß verhalten, kann nicht garantiert werden, dass
    die hier aufgeführten Funktionen tatsächlich so wie beschrieben
    reagieren.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Esta página permite personalizar la manera en que el GIMP gestiona las
    ventanas. Debería tener en cuenta que el GIMP no manipula directamente
    las ventanas, en lugar de esto envia peticiones al gestor de ventanas
    (Windows si está en Windows, Metacity si está en una en una
    instalación estandar de Gnome en Linux; etc.). Debido a que hay muchos
    gestores de ventanas, y no todos tienen un comportamiento bueno, no se
    puede garantizar que las funciones descritas aquí funcionarán como se
    describe. Si está utilizando un gestor de ventanas moderno, todo
    debería funcionar como está previsto.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette page permet de changer certains comportements relatifs aux
    fenêtres de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Vous devez savoir que
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ne gère pas directement les fenêtres, il envoie des
    requêtes au gestionnaire de fenêtre du système (par exemple: à Windows si
    vous êtes sous Windows; à Métacity si vous êtes sous Gnome standard; etc...
    Comme il existe de nombreux gestionnaires de fenêtres, il n'est pas certain
    que toutes les fonctions décrites ici fonctionnent toutes correctement. Mais
    si vous avez un gestionnaire de fenêtres moderne respectant les standards de
    gestion des fenêtre tout ira bien.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Questa pagina permette di personalizzare la modalità si gestione delle
    finestre in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Da notare
    che <acronym>GIMP</acronym> non gestisce direttamente le finestre, ma
    si limita a dare delle indicazioni al gestore delle finestre (cioè a
    Explorer se ci si trova sotto MSWindows; a Metacity se si sta lavorando
    sotto un'installazione standard di Gnome in Linux; ecc). Dato che
    esistono molti gestori finestre diversi, e non tutti quanti si
    comportano correttamente, non è garantito che le funzionalità elencate
    qui, funzionino come descritto. Comunque, se si sta utilizzando un
    moderno gestore di finestre, aderente agli standard, tutto dovrebbe
    funzionare come previsto.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Her kan du bestemma litt av korleis <acronym>GIMP</acronym> skal visa
    ulike vindauge. Ulempen er at <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ikkje kan
    behandla vindauga direkte, men må gå vegen om biletbehandlaren i
    systemet maskinen bruker. Utsjånaden på vindauga er altså mykje styrt
    av om du bruker Windows, ei eller anna form for Linux eller eit anna
    system. Sjølv om innstillingane i denne dialogen verkar nokolunde
    brukbart i dei fleste systema, må du ikkje bli skuffa om dei ikkje gjer det.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    С помощью этой страницы определяются различные параметры окон GIMP.
    Не забывайте, что GIMP не управляет окнами напрямую,
    вместо этого он посылает запросы к оконному менеджеру
    (например, к Windows если вы запускаете его в Windows; к Metacity если
    запускаете Gnome стандартной конфигурации в Linux; и т.д.).
    Поскольку существует множество оконных менеджеров,
    и не все они работают корректно, невозможно гарантировать, что
    все функции действительно будут работать
    в соответствии с описанием.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以在该页定制在 GIMP 中处理窗口的方式。需要注意的是 GIMP 并不直接处理
    窗口，而是发送请求给窗口管理器(比如，Windows 中就是 Windows；标准安装
    Gnome 的 Linux 中是 Metacity。)。由于有很多窗口管理器,有些可能表现不好，
    因此我们不能保证这里描述的功能都能正确工作。尽管如此，现代，标准的窗口管
    理器应该能正确工作。
  </para>

  <note lang="de;fr">
    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> verwaltet die Fenster nicht selbständig,
      sondern überlässt diese mehr oder weniger dem Fenstersystem.
      Mittels Kommunikation mit dem Fenstersystem ist es so möglich, dass
      jeder Benutzer plattformübergreifend seinen eigenen Fenstermanager
      (<foreignphrase>Window Manager</foreignphrase> im Englischen) benutzen
      kann.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ne manipule pas les fenêtres directement :
      il envoie des requêtes à votre gestionnaire de fenêtres (Window
      Manager en anglais). Parce qu'il existe beaucoup de gestionnaires
      de fenêtres, les options décrites ici peuvent être inopérantes avec
      certains d'entre eux. Toutefois, si votre gestionnaire de fenêtres est
      suffisamment moderne et conforme au standard, ces options devraient
      être acceptées.
    </para>
  </note>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingane</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <variablelist>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Window Manager Hints</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Nápovědy správce oken</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Fenstertyp-Hints</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Hints del gestor de ventanas</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Envois au gestionnaire des fenêtres</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">indicazioni per il gestore finestre</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Melding til vindaugebehandlaren</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Управление внешним видом окон</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">窗口管理器提示</phrase>
      </title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Window type hints for the toolbox and the docks</term>
        <term lang="cs">Nápověda pro nástroje</term>
        <term lang="de">
          Fenstertyp-Hints für das Werkzeugfenster und den Docks
        </term>
        <term lang="es">
          Hints para la caja de herramientas y los empotrables
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">
          Type d'astuce de fenêtre pour la boîte à outils et les fenêtres
          attachables
        </term>
        <term lang="it">
          Indicazioni per il comportamento degli strumenti e dei pannelli
          agganciabili
        </term>
        <term lang="no">Plassering av verktøy- og innlimingsvindauge</term>
        <term lang="ru">Стиль окна для панели инструментов</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">工具箱和停靠栏提示</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The choices you make here determine how the Toolbox, and the docks
            that hold dialogs, will be treated. If you choose "Normal Window",
            they will be treated like any other windows. If you choose
            "Utility Window", they will be raised into visibility whenever you
            activate an image window, and kept in front of every image window.
            If you choose "Keep above", they will be kept in front of every
            other window at all times. Note that changes you make here will
            not take effect until the next time you start GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Zde provedené změny určují, jak správce oken zachází s oknem
            Panelu nástrojů a doky. Pokud je zvoleno <guilabel>Normální
            okno</guilabel>, správce oken s nimi zachází jako s obyčejnými
            okny. Pokud je zvoleno <guilabel>Okno nástrojů</guilabel>, tato
            okna vyzvednuta do popředí při každé aktivaci okna obrázku a jsou
            držena nad všemi okny obrázku. Pokud je zvoleno <guilabel>Udržovat
            nahoře</guilabel>, jsou stále udržována nad všemi ostatními okny
            za všech okolností. Zde provedené změny mají účinek až po příštím
            spuštění Gimpu.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wählen Sie hier, wie sich das Werkzeugfenster und die Docks
            gegenüber dem Fensterverwaltungssystem (<foreignphrase>Window
            Manager</foreignphrase>) verhalten soll.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <emphasis>Normales Fenster:</emphasis> Fenster werden wie
            jedes andere Fenster verwaltet ohne spezielles Verhalten.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <emphasis>Werkzeugfenster:</emphasis> Sollten andere
            Fenster das Werkzeugfenster überdecken, wird das
            darunter liegende Werkzeugfenster wieder sichtbar gemacht.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <emphasis>Oben behalten:</emphasis> Diese Fenster werden immer
            über jedem Fenster gehalten.
          </para>

          <note lang="de">
            <para lang="de">
              Veränderungen werden erst nach dem Neustart von
              <acronym>GIMP</acronym> wirksam.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="es">
            Sus elecciones determinan como se tratarán la caja de
            herramientas, y los empotrables que tienen diálogos. Si elige
            "Ventana normal", se tratará como cualquier otra ventana. Si
            elige "Ventana de utilidades", se harán visibles cuando active
            una ventana de imagen, y se mantendrá delante de cada ventana
            de la imagen. Si elige "Mantener por encima", se mantendrá por
            encima de cada ventana en todo momento. Notese que los cambios
            que se hacen aquí no tomarán efecto hasta la próxima vea que
            inicie el GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ces options permettent de changer la façon dont votre
            gestionnaire de fenêtres affiche les fenêtres attachables et la
            Boîte à outils.
            Elles peuvent aussi influencer la décoration (ou bordure) de ces
            fenêtres.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <emphasis>Fenêtre normale :</emphasis> ces fenêtres seront traitées
            comme n'importe quelle autre fenêtre.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <emphasis>Fenêtre utilitaire :</emphasis> ces fenêtres seront
            rendues visibles à chaque activation d'une fenêtre d'image et
            resteront au-dessus de toutes les fenêtres d'image.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <emphasis>Garder au-dessus :</emphasis> La boîte à outils et les
            dialogues sont conservés par dessus la fenêtre d'image.
          </para>
          <note lang="fr">
            <para lang="fr">
              Les changements apportés à ces options ne seront effectifs qu'au
              prochain lancement de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="it">
            Le scelte che si fanno in questa sede determinano la gestione del
            pannello degli strumenti e dei pannelli agganciabili. Se si
            sceglie "Finestra normale", essi saranno trattati come qualsiasi
            altra finestra. Se si sceglie "Finestra utilità", essi verranno
            messi in evidenza ogni volta che si attiva una finestra, e
            mantenuti sopra ogni finestra immagine. Se si sceglie "Mantieni
            sopra", essi verranno mantenuti in primo piano sopra ogni altra
            finestra per tutto il tempo. Notare che i cambiamenti effettuati a
            queste opzioni necessitano del riavvio di GIMP per avere effetto.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Innstillingane her bestemmer korleis verktøyskrinet og
            innlimingsvindauga for dialogar, (<quote>tavler</quote>), skal
            sjå ut. Valet <quote>Normalvindauge</quote> gjer at desse
            vindauga blir behandla som andre vindauge. Valet
            <quote>Verktøyvindauge</quote> gjer at vindauget blir gjort
            synleg, dvs. løfta framføre dei andre vindauga, også
            biletvindauga, når du aktiverer eit biletvindauge.
            <quote>Alltid øvst</quote> gjer at vindauget alltid blir vist
            framføre allae andre vindauge som måtte vere på skjermen.
            Legg merke til at innstillingane ikkje blir aktiverte før du opnar
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> på nytt.
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Эти параметры определяют, как будет обрабатываться панель
            инструментов и окна других панелей. Если вы выберите 
            <quote>Стандартное окно</quote>, то они будут обрабатываться как и
            любые другие окна. Если вы выберите <quote>Вспомогательное</quote>,
            то они будут перекрываться окном
            изображения каждый раз при активации окна изображения, и держаться
            позади любого окна изображения. Если вы выберите <quote>Всегда
            наверху</quote>,
            то они будут держаться поверх любых других окон всё время. Имейте
            ввиду, что все изменения параметров будут видны только после
            перезапуска GIMP.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这里选择如何对待工具箱和有对话框的停靠栏，选“普通窗口”将把它象其
            它们窗口一样对待；选“工具窗口”，在激活图像窗口时，它们将可见，并
            保持在每个图像窗口前方。而选择“保持在上方”时，它将一直显示在所有
            窗口上方。需要注意的是，这些改变只有在下次启动 GIMP 后才会生效。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>
        <phrase lang='en'>Focus</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Fokus</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Foco</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Focus</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Focus</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Fokus</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Фокус</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">焦点</phrase>
      </title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Activate the focused image</term>
        <term lang="cs">Aktivovat obrázek podle okna</term>
        <term lang="de">Das fokussierte Bild aktivieren</term>
        <term lang="es">Activar la imagen con el foco</term>
        <term lang="fr">Activer le focus sur image</term>
        <term lang="it">Attiva l'immagine in focus</term>
        <term lang="no">Aktiver biletet som har fokus</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сделать активным изображение под фокусом</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">激活获得焦点的图像</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Normally, when you focus an image window (usually indicated by a
            change in the color of the frame), it becomes the "active image"
            for GIMP, and therefore the target for any image-related actions
            you perform.  Some people, though, prefer to set up their window
            managers such that any window entered by the pointer is
            automatically focused.  If you do this, you may find that it is
            inconvenient for focused images to automatically become active,
            and may be happier if you uncheck this option.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Za běžných okolností se při aktivaci okna obrázku (což se obvykle
            projeví změnou barvy jeho dekorací) aktivuje i v něm obsažený
            obrázek, který se tak stane aktivním obrázkem Gimpu, na který se
            aplikují veškeré prováděné operace. Někteří uživatelé ale
            upřednostňují takové nastavení svých správců oken, které aktivuje
            okna pouhým umístěním ukazatele myši nad ně. V takovém případě je
            automatická aktivace obrázku v aktivním okně často nepohodlná
            a lze ji proto vypnout touto volbou.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Normalerweise erhalten fokussierte Fenster alle Maus- und
            Tastatureingaben. Die Fokussierung kann auf verschiedenen Wegen
            erfolgen, z.B. durch Mausklick (<foreignphrase>Click to
            Focus</foreignphrase>) oder durch Überfahren des Fensters mit dem
            Mauszeiger (<foreignphrase>Sloppy Focus</foreignphrase>). Sollten
            Sie Ihren Fenstermanager auf die erste Variante eingestellt haben,
            sollte das Kontrollkästchen aktiviert sein.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Normalmente, cuando se enfoca una ventana de la imagen (se
            indica, normalmente , por un cambio de color en el marco), se
            convierte en  la "imagen activa" para el GIMP, y por lo tanto
            es el objetivo para las acciones relacionadas con la imagen
            que ejecute. Algunos prefieren configurar su gestor de
            ventanas para que la ventana coga el foco, automaticamente,
            cuando el puntero del ratón este sobre ella. Si hace esto,
            podría encontra que es un inconvente que las imágenes con
            foco, automaticamente, se conviertan en activas, y podría ser
            mejor desmarcar esta opción.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Habituellement, lorsque vous cliquez sur une fenêtre d'image,
            celle-ci devient "l'image active" (matérialisée par une bordure de
            couleur différente). Cette image deviendra la cible de toutes les
            opérations portant sur une image. Certaines personnes préfèrent
            que la fenêtre active soit celle survolée par le pointeur de la
            souris (configuration spécifique du gestionnaire de fenêtres).
            Dans ce cas, le changement d'image active par simple survol du
            pointeur peut devenir un inconvénient : si tel est votre cas, il
            vous suffit de décocher cette option pour éviter un changement
            d'image active intempestif.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Normalmente, quando si 'passa il focus' su una finestra immagine
            (questo viene tipicamente indicato con un cambiamento nel colore
            del bordo esterno della finestra), questa diventa l'"immagine
            attiva" di GIMP, obbiettivo corrente di tutte le operazioni che si
            eseguono. Alcuni preferiscono impostare il proprio gestore
            finestre in maniera tale che ogni finestra che si trovi sotto il
            puntatore del mouse 'prenda il focus' automaticamente. Se ci si
            trova tra questi ultimi, probabilmente si troverà scomodo che ogni
            immagine che abbia il focus sia automaticamente resa l'immagine
            attiva e quindi probabilmente si troverà comodo disabilitare
            quest'opzione.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Når du fokuserer på eit biletvindauge, altså at du klikkar ein eller
            annan stad innanfor biletramma, vil dette normalt også bli det
            aktive vindauget og såleis det vindauget som alle biletrelaterte
            funksjonar verkar på. Kva vindauge som har fokus, blir indikert
            ved at ramma skifter farge. Dersom du avmarkerer for denne
            funksjonen, vil det vindauget som er under musepeikaren få
            fokus. (Denne funksjonen verkar ikkje på min maskin,
            Windows XP).
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Когда вы наводите фокус на окно изображения (обычно определяется
            сменой цвета рамки окна), для GIMP оно становится "активным
            изображением", и следовательно целью для любых связанных с
            изображением действий. Однако некоторые пользователи предпочитают
            настроить свой оконный менеджер таким образом, что любое
            изображение с наведённым на него указателем автоматически
            фокусируется. Если это так, то данная функция может показаться вам
            неудобной, и ее лучше будет отключить.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            一般地，当您移动(聚焦)到一个图像窗口时(常常用窗口框颜色变化表示)，
            它就变为了 GIMP 的“活动图像”，其后的所有操作都将对它进行。不过有
            些人却喜欢让窗口管理器把被光标点击了的窗口作为焦点窗口。如果您这
            样做了，可能会发现焦点窗口中的图像自动变为活动图像不方便，这时最
            好不要勾选该选项。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>
        <phrase lang='en'>Window Positions</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Polohy oken</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Fensterpositionen</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Posiciones de las ventanas</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Emplacements des fenêtres</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Posizione finestre</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Vindaugeposisjonar</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Позиция окна</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">窗口位置</phrase>
      </title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Save window positions on exit</term>
        <term lang="cs">Ukládat polohy oken při skončení</term>
        <term lang="de">Fensterpositionen beim Beenden speichern</term>
        <term lang="es">Guardar posiciones de ventanas al salir</term>
        <term lang="fr">Enregistrer à la sortie l'emplacement des
          fenêtres</term>
        <term lang="it">Salva le posizioni delle finestre all'uscita</term>
        <term lang="no">Lagra vindaugeposisjonane ved avslutning</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сохранять позицию окон при выходе</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">退出时保存窗口位置</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If this option is checked, the next time you start GIMP,
            you will see the same set of dialog windows, in the same
            positions they occupied when you last exited.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud je tato volba zaškrtnuta, uloží se automaticky při ukončení
            Gimpu polohy jeho oken, takže při příštím spuštění Gimpu se objeví
            stejná okna na stejných místech na obrazovce.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Bei aktiviertem Kontrollkästchen wird
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> die Dialoge und Docks an den Positionen
            öffnen, wo sie beim letzten Mal waren.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Si esta opción está marcada, la próxima vez que inicie el
            GIMP, verá la misma configuración de las ventanas de diálogo,
            en la misma posición que en la última salida.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si cette option est active, les dialogues et fenêtres
            attachables de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> réapparaîtront au
            démarrage aux endroits où vous les avez laissés à la session
            précédente.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se quest'opzione è spuntata, la prossima volta che si avvia GIMP,
            si osserverà lo stesso insieme di finestre nella stessa posizione
            occupata dell'instante in cui si è usciti l'ultima volta da GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom denne er avkryssa, vil du (stort sett) når du opnar
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> få dei same dialogvindauga i dei
            same posisjonane på skjermen som du hadde då
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sist blei avslutta.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Если этот параметр отмечен, при следующем запуске GIMP вы увидите
            такой же набор диалоговых окон, в такой же позиции, в какой они
            находились, когда вы последний раз выходили из программы.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            勾选该选项，下次启动 GIMP 时，会使用和上次退出时相同的对话框窗口布局。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Save Window Positions Now</term>
        <term lang="cs">Uložit polohy oken okamžitě</term>
        <term lang="de">Fensterposition jetzt speichern</term>
        <term lang="es">Guardar las posiciones de las ventanas ahora</term>
        <term lang="fr">Enregistrer maintenant la position des fenêtres</term>
        <term lang="it">Salva ora la posizione delle finestre</term>
        <term lang="no">Lagra vindaugeposisjonane nå</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сохранить позицию окон</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">现在保存窗口位置</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This button is only useful if "Save window positions on exit" is
            unchecked. It allows you to set up your windows they way you like,
            click the button, and then have them come up in that arrangement
            each time you start GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Toto tlačítko je užitečné pouze v případě, je-li volba
            <guilabel>Ukládat polohy oken při skončení</guilabel> neaktivní.
            Umožňuje totiž uložit polohy oken ručně v určitém okamžiku
            a jejich následné obnovení při dalším spuštění Gimpu, bez ohledu
            na polohy oken při ukončení.
          </para>

          <note lang="de">
            <para lang="de">
              Diese Schaltfläche hat nur einen Effekt, wenn "Fensterposition
              beim Beenden speichern" aktiviert ist.
            </para>
          </note>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Schaltfläche erlaubt es Ihnen, die Fenster so zu
            positionieren, wie Sie möchten. Klicken Sie einmal auf die
            Schaltfläche, damit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sich die
            Position der Fenster merkt.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            Este botón es útil si "Guardar las posiciones de las ventanas
            al salir" está sin marcar. Permite configurar las ventanas de
            la manera que se quiera, pulsar  el botón, y así tenerlas en
            esa disposición cada vez que inicie el GIMP.
          </para>

          <note lang="fr">
            <para lang="fr">
              Cette opération n'a d'effet que si l'option "Enregistrer à la
              sortie l'emplacement des fenêtres" est désactivée.
            </para>
          </note>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette opération vous permet d'organiser vos fenêtres GIMP à votre
            convenance et de sauvegarder leurs positions pour les lancements
            suivants.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Questo pulsante è utile solo se la casella "Salva le posizioni
            delle finestre all'uscita" non è spuntata. Essa permette di
            impostare le finestre come si vuole e, facendo clic sul pulsante,
            fare in modo di avere sempre la stessa disposizione delle
            finestere all'avvio di GIMP.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Denne knappen blir helst brukt når valet <quote>Lagra
            vindaugeposisjonane ved avslutning </quote> ikkje er aktivisert.
            Du kan setje opp dei ulike vindauga slik du ønskjer det, trykke på
            knappen og håpe på at <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opnar neste
            gong med det same oppsettet.
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Эта кнопка полезна лишь в том случае, если не отмечен параметр
            <quote>Сохранять позицию окон при выходе</quote>. Она позволяет вам
            установить расположение ваших окон в желаемой последовательности.
            После нажатия на эту кнопку, при каждом запуске GIMP окна будут
            располагаться в указанном порядке.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该按钮只在未勾选“退出时保存窗口位置”时有用。它允许您设定所喜欢的
            窗口方式，然后点击该按钮，这样每次启动 GIMP 都会使用当前的布局。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Reset Saved Window Positions to Default Values</term>
        <term lang="cs">Obnovit uložené polohy oken na implicitní hodnoty</term>
        <term lang="de">Fensterpositionen jetzt auf Vorgabewerte setzen</term>
        <term lang="es">
          Restaurar las posiciones de la ventana a los valores
          predeterminados
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">Restaurer les positions enregistrées aux
          valeurs par défaut</term>
        <term lang="it">Reimposta la posizione delle finestre salvata ai
        valori predefiniti</term>
        <term lang="no">
          Tilbakestill lagra vindaugeposisjonar til standardverdiar
        </term>
        <term lang="ru">Восстановить позицию окон по умолчанию</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">重置已保存的窗口位置到默认值</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If you decide that you are unhappy with the arrangement of windows
            you have saved, and would rather go back to the default
            arrangement than spend time moving them around, you can do so by
            pressing this button.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud uložené polohy oken nevyhovují, lze se vrátit k výchozím
            polohám jednoduchým kliknutím na toto tlačítko.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sollten sie wieder zu den Vorgabeeinstellungen für die
            Fensterpositionierung zurückkehren wollen, klicken Sie auf diese
            Schaltfläche.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Si no está conforme con la disposiciones de las ventanas que
            tiene guardada, puede volver a la disposición predeterminada
            pulsando este botón.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si l'arrangement des fenêtres sauvegardé ne vous convient pas,
            vous pouvez revenir à l'arrangement par défaut en utilisant cette
            opération.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se non si è soddisfatti della disposizione delle finestre salvata
            e si preferisce reimpostare quella predefinita piuttosto che
            perdere tempo a riposizionare tutto, basta premere questo
            pulsante.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du av ein eller annan grunn ikkje er nøgd med
            skjermoppsettet du har lagra, kan du raskare setje dei tilbake til
            normalinnstillingane enn å arrangere alt på nytt.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Если вы решили, что ваша сохранённая расстановка окон неудачна, и
            будет лучше вернуться к первоначальной расстановке, чем тратить
            время на создание новой удобной схемы, вы можете это сделать
            нажатием кнопки <quote>Восстановить позицию окон по умолчанию</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">该选项不需要解释。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
