<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="plug-in-gegl-filter-browser">
  <title>GEGL Filter Browser</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>GEGL Filter Browser</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Browser</primary>
    <secondary>GEGL Filter</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>GEGL Filter Browser</guimenuitem> command displays the
    available <acronym>GEGL</acronym> filters that can be called by plug-ins
    or scripts. These filters perform image related actions and may have
    one or more parameters that can be adjusted.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <para>
      You can access this command from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>GEGL Filter Browser</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      Description of the <quote>GEGL Filter Browser</quote> dialog window
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        The <quote>GEGL Filter Browser</quote> dialog window
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/help/gegl-filter-browser-dialog.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The figure above shows the <guilabel>GEGL Filter Browser</guilabel>
      dialog window. If you click on an item in the list on the
      left, information about the filter is displayed on the right.
    </para>
    <para>
      For the selected filter it first shows basic information: the name by
      which it can be called, the category it belongs to, and a description
      of what the filter does.
      Following that, information of its parameters (if any) is shown. For each
      parameter it shows its name, the required datatype, its default value,
      and minimum and maximum values allowed.
      Below that, it will show additional information, like the license.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can search for a specific filter by querying the filter database
      in the Search text box. You can choose on what part of the filter
      information the search is performed:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>by name</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Searches only the name of the filter. It shows a list of filters
            which have the text you entered at the start of a word that is
            part of the name.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>by title</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Searches the title of the filter. It shows a list of filters
            which have the text you entered anywhere as part of the title.
          </para>
          <para>
            The difference with searching by name is, that the title is how you
            would write about the filter, e.g. <quote>Gaussian Blur</quote>,
            while the name is how you would call the filter in your code, e.g.
            <quote>gegl:gaussian-blur</quote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>by description</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Searches the description of what the filter does. The text entered
            can be anywhere in the description.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
