<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-05-06 ude: changed (help-)id [was: gimp-xtns-plug-in-browser]
  2005-11-24 split of from menus-toolbox.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-plug-in-details">
  <title>Plug-In Browser</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Plug-ins</primary>
    <secondary>Browser</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Browser</primary>
    <secondary>Plug-in</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Plug-In Browser</guimenuitem> command displays a
    dialog window which shows all of the extensions (plug-ins) which are
    currently loaded in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, both as a list and
    as a hierarchical tree structure. Since many of the filters are actually
    plug-ins, you will certainly see many familiar names here. Please note
    that you do not run the extensions from this dialog window. Use the
    appropriate menu entry to do that instead. For example, you can run
    filter plug-ins by using the <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem> command
    on the main menu.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this command from the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Plug-in Browser</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      Description of the <quote>Plug-In Browser</quote> dialog window
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        The list view of the <quote>Plug-In Browser</quote> dialog window
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/help/plug-in-browser-list.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The figure above shows the list view of the
      <guilabel>Plug-In Browser</guilabel>. You can click on the name of
      a plug-in in the scrolled window to display more information about
      it. Select the <guilabel>List View</guilabel> by clicking
      on the tab at the top of the dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can search for a plug-in by name by entering part or all of the
      name in the <guilabel>Search:</guilabel> text box.  The left part of
      the dialog then displays the matches found.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        The tree view of the <quote>Plug-In Browser</quote> dialog window
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/help/plug-in-browser-tree.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The figure above shows the tree view of the
      <guilabel>Plug-In Browser</guilabel>. You can click on the name of
      a plug-in in the scrolled window to display more information about
      it. You can click on the arrowheads to expand or contract parts of
      the tree. Select the <guilabel>Tree View</guilabel> by clicking on
      the tab at the top of the dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can search for a plug-in by name by entering part or all of the
      name in the <guilabel>Search:</guilabel> text box.  The left part of
      the dialog then displays the matches found.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Not everything in these huge dialog windows is visible at the same
        time. Use the scroll bars to view their content.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
