<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[]>
<!--  section history:
  2019-10-31 Julien: fix issue #187 : rearrange display
  2015-12-19 Julien: adapted save -> export
  2011-04-02 Michael: rewrote tutorial
  2007-05-11 lexa: initial version
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-tutorial-quickies">
  <title>Common Tasks</title>
  <indexterm significance="normal">
    <primary>Tutorial</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>This tutorial is based on text Copyright &#169; 2004
  Carol Spears. The original tutorial can be found online:
  <xref linkend="bibliography-online-tutorial02" />.</para>
  <sect2>
    <title>Intention</title>
    <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>  is a powerful image editing program with many
    options and tools. However, it is also well suited for smaller tasks. The
    following tutorials are meant for those who want to achieve these common
    tasks without having to learn all the intricacies of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    and computer graphics in general.</para>
    <para>Hopefully, these tutorials will not only help you with your current
    task, but also get you ready to learn more complex tools and methods later,
    when you have the time and inspiration.</para>

    <para>Open an image via
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Open…</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> from the image window.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-scale">
    <title>Change the Size of an Image for the screen</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>Scale</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>You have a huge image, possibly from a digital camera, and you want
    to resize it so that it displays nicely on a web page, online board or
    email message.</para>

    <para>The first thing that you might notice after opening the image, is that
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opens the image at a logical size for viewing. If
    your image is very large, like the sample image,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sets the zoom so that it displays nicely on the
    screen. The zoom level is shown in the
    <link linkend="gimp-image-window-zoom">status bar</link> at the bottom of
    the image window. This does not change the actual image.</para>

    <para>The other thing to look at in the title bar is the mode. If the mode
    shows as RGB in the title bar, you are fine. If the mode says <guilabel>
    Indexed</guilabel> or <guilabel>Grayscale</guilabel>, read the
    <xref linkend="gimp-tutorial-quickie-change-mode" />.</para>

    <para>Select
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Image</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Scale Image…</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>. You can right click on the image to open the menu, or use
    the menu along the top of the Image window.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Dialog for Image Scaling in Pixels</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/menus/image/scale-image.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The unit of size for the purpose of displaying an image on a screen
    is the pixel. You can see the dialog has two sections: one for
    <guilabel moreinfo="none">width</guilabel> and
    <guilabel moreinfo="none">height</guilabel> and another for
    <guilabel moreinfo="none">resolution</guilabel>. Resolution applies to
    printing only and has no effect on the image's size when it is displayed on
    a monitor or a mobile device. The reason is that different devices have
    different pixels sizes and so, an image that displays on one device (such
    as a smartphone) with a certain physical size, might display on other
    devices (such as an LCD projector) in another size altogether. For the
    purpose of displaying an image on a screen, you can ignore the resolution
    parameter. For the same reason, do not use any size unit other than the
    pixel in the height / width fields.</para>

    <para>If you know the desired width, enter it in the dialog at the top
    where it says
    <guilabel moreinfo="none">Width</guilabel>. This is shown in the figure
    above. If you don't have such a number in mind, choose an appropriate width
    for the desired use. Common screen sizes range between 600 pixels for simpler
    phones and 1920 pixels for an HD screen.</para>

    <para>When you change one of the image's dimensions,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> changes the other dimension proportionally. To
    change the other dimension, see
    <xref linkend="gimp-tutorial-quickie-crop" />. Bear in mind that when you
    change the two dimensions arbitrarily, the image might become stretched or
    squashed.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-scale-print">
    <title>Change the Size of an Image for print</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>scale</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>As discussed before, pixels don't have a set size in the real world.
    When you set out to print an image on paper,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> needs to know how big each pixel is. We use a
    parameter called resolution to set the ratio between pixels and real-world
    units such as inches.</para>
    <para>By default, most images open with the resolution set to 72. This
    number was chosen for historical reasons as it was the resolution of
    screens in the past, and means that when printed, every pixel is 1/72 of an
    inch wide. When printing images that are taken with modern digital cameras,
    this produces very large but chunky images with visible pixels. What we
    want to do is tell <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to print it with the size we
    have in mind, but not alter the pixel data so as not to lose
    quality.</para>

    <para>To change the print size, select
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Image</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Print Size…</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>. Select a size
    unit you are comfortable with, such as <quote>inches</quote>. Set one
    dimension, and let <acronym>GIMP</acronym> change the other one
    proportionally. Now examine the change in resolution. If the resolution is
    300 pixels per Inch or more, the printed image's quality will be very high
    and pixels will not be noticeable. With a resolution of between 200 and
    150 ppi, pixels will be somewhat noticeable, but the image will be fine as
    long as its not inspected too closely. Values lower than 100 are visibly
    coarse and should only be used for material that is seen from a distance,
    such as signs or large posters.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Dialog for Setting Print Size</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/menus/image/print-size.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-jpeg">
    <title>Compressing Images</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>save</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>Example Image for JPEG Saving</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-example.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you have images that take up a large space on disk, you can reduce
    that space even without changing the image dimensions. One of the best
    image compressions is achieved by using the <acronym>JPG</acronym> format,
    but even if the image is already in this format, you can usually still make
    it take up less space, as the JPG format has an adaptive compression
    scheme that allows saving in varying levels of compression. The trade-off
    is that the less space an image takes, the more detail from the original
    image you lose. You should also be aware that repeated saving in the JPG
    format causes more and more image degradation.
    </para>

    <para>
      Images are loaded and saved as .XCF files. Your JPG
      image has been loaded as XCF. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> offers you to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Overwrite image-name.jpg</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> or
      <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
        <guimenu moreinfo="none">File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Export As</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> to open the <quote>Export Image</quote> dialog.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title><quote>Export Image</quote> Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/export-image-dialog.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The dialog opens with the file name already selected in the
      <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field, with the default extension.
      Delete the existing extension and type <quote>.jpg</quote>
      instead. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will determine the file type from the
      extension.
      Click <guibutton>Export</guibutton>. This opens the
      <link linkend="file-jpeg-export"><guilabel>Export Image as JPEG</guilabel>
      dialog</link> that contains the <guilabel>Quality</guilabel> control.
    </para>
    
    <para>The <guilabel>Export Image as JPEG</guilabel> dialog uses default
    values that reduce size in memory while retaining good visual quality;
    this is the safest and quickest thing to do.</para>
    
    <figure float="0">
      <title>Example for Moderate JPEG Compression</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-dialog-preview.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Quality: 90 (default); Size: 33.7 KiloBytes</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-dialog2-preview.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Quality: 75; Size: 20.1 KiloBytes</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Reduce the image <guilabel>Quality</guilabel> to make the image even
    smaller. Reduced quality degrades the image, so be certain to check
    <quote>Show preview in image window</quote> to visually gauge the
    degradation. A <guilabel>Quality</guilabel> setting of 10 produces a very
    poor quality image that uses very little disk space.
    A quality of 75 produces a reasonable image using
    much less disk space, which will, in turn, load much faster on a web page.
    Although the image is somewhat degraded, it is acceptable for the intended
    purpose.</para>

    <para>Finally, here is a comparison of the same picture with varying
    degrees of compression:</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Example for High JPEG Compression</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-010.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Quality: 10; Size: 3.4 KiloBytes</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-040.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Quality: 40; Size: 9.3 KiloBytes</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>Example for Moderate JPEG Compression</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-070.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Quality: 70; Size: 15.2 KiloBytes</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-jpeg-100.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Quality: 100; Size: 72.6 KiloBytes</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-crop">
    <title>Crop An Image</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>crop</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Example Image for Cropping</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-crop-example-source.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Source image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-crop-example-result.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Image after cropping</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>There are many reasons to crop an image; for example, fitting an
    image to fill a frame, removing a portion of the background to emphasize
    the subject, etc. There are two methods to activate the crop tool. Click
    the
    <guiicon moreinfo="none">
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-crop.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon> button in the Toolbox, or use
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Tools</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Transform Tools</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Crop</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> in the image window. This changes the cursor and allow you to
    click and drag a rectangular shape. The button in the toolbox is the
    easiest way to get to any of the tools.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Select a Region to Crop</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-crop-step1.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click on one corner of the desired crop area and drag your mouse to
    create the crop rectangle. You don't have to be accurate as you can change
    the exact shape of the rectangle later.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Dialog for Cropping</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-crop.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Crop tool options with the Fixed Aspect ratio option
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-crop-step2.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Crop rectangle with a fixed aspect ratio
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>After completing the click and drag motion, a rectangle with special
    regions is shown on the canvas. As the cursor is moved over the different
    areas of the selected crop area, the cursor changes. You can then drag the
    rectangle's corners or edges to change the dimensions of the selected area.
    As shown in the figure above, as the crop area is resized, the dimensions
    and ratio are shown in the status bar. Double-click inside the rectangle
    or press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to complete cropping. See
    <xref linkend="gimp-tool-crop" /> for more information on cropping in
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.</para>
    <para>If you would like to crop the image in a specific
    aspect ratio, such as a square, make sure the tool options are visible
    (<menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Windows</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Tool Options</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>). In the <link linkend="gimp-tool-crop">Tool Options</link>
    dockable, check the mark next to
    <guilabel>Fixed Aspect Ratio</guilabel>. Type the desired aspect ratio
    in the text field below, such as <quote>1:1</quote>.</para>
    <para>You also have buttons to change the aspect from landscape to
    portrait. After you set the aspect ratio, drag one of the corners of the
    crop rectangle to update it. The rectangle changes to the chosen ratio,
    and when you drag it should maintain that ratio.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-info">
    <title>Find Info About Your Image</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>information</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>When you need to find out information about your image, select
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Image</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Image Properties</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> from the main menu. The <quote>Image Properties</quote>
    dialog contains information about the image size, resolution, mode
    and much more.</para>
    <para>
      See also <xref linkend="gimp-image-properties"/>.
    </para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title><quote>Image Properties</quote> Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/menus/image/properties.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-change-mode">
    <title>Change the Mode</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>change Mode</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>As with anything else, images come in different kinds and serve
    different purposes. Sometimes, a small size is important (for web sites)
    and at other times, retaining a high color depth (e.g., a family portrait)
    is what you want.
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can handle all of this, primarily by converting
    between three fundamental image modes, via <menuchoice><guimenu>Image</guimenu>
    <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu></menuchoice> in the main menu.
    These three available modes are:</para>

    <para>
    <guilabel>RGB</guilabel>: This is the default mode, used for high-quality
    images, and able to display millions of colors. This is also the mode for
    most of your image work including scaling, cropping, and even flipping. In
    RGB mode, each pixel consists of three different components: R-&gt;Red,
    G-&gt;Green, B-&gt;Blue. Each of these in turn can have an intensity value
    of 0-255. What you see at every pixel is an additive combination of these
    three components.</para>

    <para>
    <guilabel>Indexed</guilabel>: This is the mode usually used when file size
    is of concern, or when you are working with images with few colors. It
    involves using a fixed number of colors (256 or less) for the entire image
    to represent colors. By default, when you change an image to a paletted
    image, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> generates an <quote>optimum palette</quote>
    to best represent your image.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>The <quote>Convert Image to Indexed Colors</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/image-mode-indexed.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>As you might expect, since the information needed to represent the
    color at each pixel is less, the file size is smaller. However, sometimes,
    there are options in the various menus that are disabled for no apparent
    reason. This usually means that the filter or option cannot be applied when
    your image is in its current mode. Changing the mode to RGB, as outlined
    above, should solve this issue. If RGB mode doesn't work either, perhaps
    the option you're trying requires your layer to have the ability to be
    transparent. This can be done just as easily via
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Layer</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Transparency</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Add Alpha Channel</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.</para>

    <para>
    <guilabel>Grayscale</guilabel>: Grayscale images have only shades of gray.
    This mode has some specific uses and takes less space on the hard drive in
    some formats, but is not recommended for general use as reading it is not
    supported by many applications.</para>

    <para>There is no need to convert an image to a specific mode before saving
    it in your favorite format, as <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is smart enough to
    properly export the image.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-flip">
    <title>Flip An Image</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>Flip</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Use this option when you need the person in the photo looking in the
    other direction, or you need the top of the image to be the bottom. Select
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Tools</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Transform Tools</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Flip</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> from the main menu, or use the
    <guiicon moreinfo="none">
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-flip.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon> button on the toolbox. After selecting the flip tool from the
    toolbox, click inside the canvas. Controls in the Tool Options dockable let
    you switch between Horizontal and Vertical modes.</para>

    <para>After selecting the flip tool from the toolbox, click inside the
    canvas. The tool flips the image horizontally. Use the options dialog to
    switch between horizontal and vertical. If it is not already displayed in
    the dock under the toolbox, double click the toolbox button. You can also
    use the <keycap moreinfo="none">Ctrl</keycap> key to switch between
    horizontal and vertical.</para>

    <para>In the images below, all possible flips are demonstrated:</para>

    <figure id="quickie-flip-images" float="0">
      <title>Example Image to Flip</title>
      <informalfigure float="0">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-flip-example-source.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Source image</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-flip-example-horizontal.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Horizontal flipped image</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <informalfigure float="0">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-flip-example-vertical.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Vertical flipped image</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-flip-example-horizontal-and-vertical.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Horizontal and vertical flipped image</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-rotate">
    <title>Rotate An Image</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Image</primary>
      <secondary>Rotate</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Images that are taken with digital cameras sometimes need to be
    rotated. To do this, select
    <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
      <guimenu moreinfo="none">Image</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Transform</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Rotate 90&#176; clockwise</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> (or counter-clockwise) from the main menu. The images
    below demonstrate a 90 degrees CCW rotation.</para>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Example for
      <quote>Rotate An Image</quote> </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-rotate-example-source.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Source Image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-rotate-example-90-CCW.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Rotated image 90 degree CCW</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-tutorial-quickie-separate">
    <title>Separating an Object From Its Background</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Tutorial</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure float="0">
      <title>Object with Background</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
          fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-remove-background-source.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Sometimes you need to separate the subject of an image from its
      background. You may want to have the subject on a flat color, or keep the
      background transparent so you can use it on an existing background, or
      any other thing you have in mind. To do this, you must first use
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s selection tools to draw a selection around your
      subject. This is not an easy task, and selecting the correct tool is
      crucial. You have several tools to accomplish this:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role = "bold">The <quote>Free Select
            Tool</quote></emphasis> allows you to draw a border using either
            freehand or straight lines. Use this when the subject has a
            relatively simple shape. Read more about this tool here:
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-free-select" />
          </para>
          <figure float="0">
            <title>Free Select Tool</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-free-select.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="JPG"
                fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-background-free-select.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">The <quote>Scissors Select
            tool</quote></emphasis> lets you select a freehand border and uses
            edge-recognition algorithms to better fit the border around the
            object. Use this when the subject is complex but distinct enough
            against its current background. Read more about this tool here:
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-iscissors" />
          </para>
          <figure float="0">
            <title>Scissors Select Tool</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-iscissors.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="JPG"
                fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-background-scissors.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">The <quote>Foreground Select
            Tool</quote></emphasis> lets you mark areas as
            <quote>Foreground</quote> or <quote>Background</quote> and refines
            the selection automatically. Read more about this tool here:
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-foreground-select" />
          </para>
          <figure float="0">
            <title>Foreground Select Tool</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-foreground-select.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-background-foreground-select.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <sect3><title>Once you have selected your subject</title>
    <para>
      Once you have selected your subject successfully, use
      <menuchoice moreinfo="none"><guimenu moreinfo="none">Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Invert</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Now,
      instead of the subject, the background is selected. What you do now
      depends on what you intended to do with the background:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To fill the background with a single color:</para>
          <para>
            Click the foreground color swatch (the top left of the two
            overlapping colored rectangles) in the toolbox and select the
            desired color. Next, use <xref linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill"/>
            to replace the background with your chosen color.
          </para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Result of Adding a Plain Color Background</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-background-color-result.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            To make a black-and-white background while keeping the subject in
            color:
          </para>
          <para>
            Use
            <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
            <guimenu moreinfo="none">Colors</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Desaturate</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>. In the dialog that opens, cycle between the modes
            and select the best-looking one, then click OK.
          </para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Result of Desaturating the Background</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
        fileref="images/tutorials/quickie-background-desaturate-result.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
