<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-blur' lang="de;en;fr">
  <title lang="en">Blur</title>
  <title lang="de">Weichzeichnen</title>
  <title lang="fr">Flou</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Blur</secondary>
    
    <primary lang="de">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="de">Weichzeichnen</secondary>
    
    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Flou</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject lang="en">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-blur-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject lang="de">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-blur-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject lang="fr">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-blur-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="de">Allgemeines</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
  
    <para lang="en">
      The Blur filter produces an effect similar to that of an out of
      focus camera shot. To produce this blur effect, the filter takes
      the average of the present pixel value and the value of adjacent
      pixels and sets the present pixel to that average value. All
      pixels of the active layer or selection are not concerned by
      blurring. For each pixel, a random number is generated based on
      the seed value and compared against the randomization percentage.
      If the random value is less than the randomization percentage,
      then the pixel is blurred. A 100% randomization, blurs all the
      pixels and blurred pixel number is at the most equal to
      randomization percentage.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der Weichzeichnen Filter erzeugt den Effekt eines unscharfen
      Kamerabildes. 
      Die Zufallssaat, wird mit dem berechneten
      Zufallswert eines jeden Pixels verglichen. Ist der Zufallswert
      kleiner als die Zufallssaat, wird der Pixel wie folgt weichgezeichnet:
      Der Filter bildet einen Mittelwert von angrenzenden Pixeln
      eines Pixels.  Danach wird der errechnete Mittelwert dem
      aktuellen Pixel zugewiesen.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Flou produit le même effet qu'un appareil photo qui
      n'est pas au point. Pour produire cet effet de flou, ce filtre
      donne au pixel étudié la Valeur moyenne de ce pixel et des pixels
      adjacents. De nombreux auteurs de guides parlent de déplacement
      des pixels. Sans doute s'agit-il d'un déplacement dans
      l'intervalle des Valeurs? Tous les pixels ne sont pas forcément
      affectés par le flou. Pour chaque pixel, un nombre est généré sur
      la base d'un germe aléatoire. Il est comparé à l'Aléa% et si ce
      nombre est inférieur à l'Aléa%, le flou est appliqué au pixel. Un
      Aléa de 100% entraîne un flou maximum, car le nombre est toujours
      inférieur à l'Aléa. Et le pourcentage de pixels concernés est au
      maximum égal à l'Aléa%.
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Activate the dialog</title>
    <title lang="de">Dialogaufruf</title>
    <title lang="fr">Ouverture du dialogue</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter can be called from the image menu:
      <guimenuitem>Filters</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Blur</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>lur</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieser Filter läßt sich aus dem Bildmenü öffnen:
      <guimenuitem>Filter</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Weichzeichnen</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Blur</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filtres/Flou/<accel>F</accel>lou</guimenuitem>
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Random Seed</term>
        <term lang="de">Zufallssaat</term>
        <term lang="fr">Germe aléatoire</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Random Seed</guilabel> controls the randomization
            element of the blur. The <guibutton>Time</guibutton> button will
            set the seed using the hardware clock of the computer. Using
            <guibutton>Time</guibutton> is the preferred method for
            initializing Blur as it will provide a higher chance of differing
            values over many uses.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die <guilabel>Zufallssaat</guilabel> bestimmt den
            Zufallswert des Weichzeichners. Durch einen Klick auf die
            <guibutton>Neu Würfeln</guibutton> Schaltfläche wird ein
            neuer Zufallswert berechnet.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guibutton>Graine aléatoire</guibutton> contrôle le
            caractère aléatoire du déplacement des pixels. Le bouton
            <guibutton>Aléatoire </guibutton> permet d'ensemencer le
            générateur avec un nombre tiré de l'horloge et qui sera donc
            bien différent à chaque utilisation.
          </para>   
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Randomization %</term>
        <term lang="de">Zufallsanteil in %</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aléa %</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Randomization</guilabel> slider represents
            the percentage of pixels of the active layer or selection
            which may be blurred. Higher value result in more blurring.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Der <guilabel>Zufallsanteil in %</guilabel>-Schieberegler
            beeinflußt den Anteil des Bildes der weichgezeichnet wird.
            Je größer der Wert, desto mehr wird weichgezeichnet.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guilabel>Aléa</guilabel> représente le
            pourcentage de pixels de la sélection ou du calque actif qui
            peuvent être affectés par le filtre.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Repeat</term>
        <term lang="de">Wiederholen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Répétition</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Repeat</guilabel> slider represents the
            number of times the active layer will be blurred. Higher
            values result in more blurring.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Der <guilabel>Wiederholen</guilabel> Schieberegler bestimmt
            wie oft die aktive Ebene weichgezeichnet wird. Je höher der
            Wert, desto mehr wird weichgezeichnet.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guilabel>Répétition</guilabel> représente le
            nombre de fois où le filtre sera appliqué.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
  
</sect2>
