<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='filters-blur'>
  <title lang="en">Blur</title>
  <title lang="fr">Flou</title>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Blur</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Flou</primary></indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="fr">Vue d'ensemble</title>
    <para lang="en">
      The Blur filter produces an effect similar to that of an out of focus camera shot. To produce this 
      blur effect, the filter takes the average of the present pixel value and the value of adjacent pixels 
      and sets the present pixel to that average value. All pixels of the active layer or selection are not 
      concerned by blurring. For each pixel, a random number is generated based on the seed value and 
      compared against the randomization percentage. If the random value is less than the randomization 
      percentage, then the pixel is blurred. A 100% randomization blur all the pixels and blurred pixel 
      number is at the most equal to randomization percentage.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Flou produit le même effet qu'un appareil photo qui n'est pas au point. Pour produire 
      cet effet de flou, ce filtre donne au pixel étudié la Valeur moyenne de ce pixel et des 
      pixels adjacents. De nombreux auteurs de guides parlent de déplacement des pixels. Sans doute 
      s'agit-il d'un déplacement dans l'intervalle des Valeurs? Tous les pixels ne sont pas 
      forcément affectés par le flou. Pour chaque pixel, un nombre est 
      généré sur la base d'un germe aléatoire. Il est comparé à 
      l'Aléa% et si ce nombre est inférieur à l'Aléa%, le flou est 
      appliqué au pixel. Un Aléa de 100% entraîne un flou maximum, car le nombre est 
      toujours inférieur à l'Aléa. Et le pourcentage de pixels concernés est au 
      maximum égal à l'Aléa%.
    </para>

    <!--
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref='images/filters/blur/blur.png' format='PNG' content-width="2cm" content-height="5cm"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    -->
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
       <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Random Seed</term>
        <term lang="fr">Germe aléatoire</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Random Seed</guilabel> controls the randomization
            element of the blur. The <guibutton>Time</guibutton> button will
            set the seed using the hardware clock of the computer. Using
            <guibutton>Time</guibutton> is the preferred method for
            initializing Blur as it will provide a higher chance of differing
            values over many uses.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guibutton>Graine aléatoire</guibutton> contrôle le caractère 
            aléatoire du déplacement des pixels. Le bouton <guibutton>Aléatoire
            </guibutton> permet d'ensemencer le générateur avec un nombre tiré de 
            l'horloge et qui sera donc bien différent à chaque utilisation.
          </para>   
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Alea %</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aléa %</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guibutton>Randomization</guibutton> slider represents the percentage of pixels of the 
            active layer or selection which may be blurred. Higher value result in more blurring.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guibutton>Aléa</guibutton> représente le pourcentage de pixels de la 
            sélection ou du calque actif qui peuvent être affectés par le filtre.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Repeat</term>
        <term lang="fr">Répétition</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guibutton>Repeat</guibutton> slider represents the number of
            times the active layer will be blurred. Higher values result in
            more blurring.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guibutton>Répétition</guibutton> représente le nombre de fois 
            où le filtre sera appliqué.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">See also...</title>
    <title lang="fr">Voir aussi...</title>
<!-- These will eventually be links :: syngin -->
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang ="en">Gaussian Blur (IIR)</para>
        <para lang ="fr">Flou Gaussien (IIR)</para> 
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Gaussian Blur (RLE)</para>
        <para lang="fr">Flou Gaussien (RLE)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Selective Gaussian Blur</para>
        <para lang="fr">Flou Gaussien Sélectif</para> 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
