<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='filters-blur-introduction' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Blur filters introduction</title>
  <title lang="fr">Introduction aux filtres de flou</title> 
  <title lang="zh_CN">模糊滤镜简介</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Blur</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduction</tertiary>    
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Flou</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduction</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>滤镜</primary>
    <secondary>模糊</secondary>
    <tertiary>简介</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
    <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-orig.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang="en">
	    Original for demo
	  </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            范例的原始图像
          </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    This is a set of filters that blur images, or parts of them,
    in various ways.  If there is a selection, only the selected parts
    of an image will be blurred.  There may, however, be some leakage
    of colors from the unblurred area into the blurred area.  To help
    you pick the one you want, we will illustrate what each does when
    applied to the image shown at right.  These are, of course, only
    examples:  most of the filters have parameter settings that allow
    you to vary the magnitude or type of blurring.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    这些滤镜用多种方式模糊图像或其部分。当选区存在时，只有图像中选中的部分会被模糊。不过可能有些未模糊区域中的颜色会泄漏到模糊区域中。为了帮助您选取正确的模糊滤镜，下面有它们应用到同一个图像中的效果。当然它们只是范例：大部分滤镜都有改变模糊放大率或类型的参数设置。
  </para>

     <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;zh_CN">
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-gauss10.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Gaussian blur (radius 10)
	  </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            高斯模糊(半径 10)
          </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  
  <para lang="en">
    The most broadly useful of these is the Gaussian blur.  (Don't let
    the word "Gaussian" throw you: this filter makes an image blurry
    in the most basic way.)  It has an efficient implementation that
    allows it to create a very blurry blur in a relatively short
    time. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    用处最广泛的是高斯模糊。(不要被“高斯”吓着了：该滤镜对图像只是进行最基本的模糊。)它的实现非常有效率，可以是图像非常模糊却只需要相对少的时间。
  </para>

    <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;zh_CN">
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-blur.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Simple blur
	  </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            简单模糊
          </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    If you only want to blur the image a little bit--to
    soften it, as it were--you might use the simple "Blur" filter.  In
    Gimp 2.2 this runs automatically, without creating a dialog.  The
    effect is subtle enough that you might not even notice it, but you
    can get a stronger effect by repeating it.  In Gimp 2.0 the filter
    shows a dialog that allows you to set a "repeat count".
    If you want a strong blurring effect, this filter
    is too slow to be a good choice: use a Gaussian blur instead.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果只要图像模糊一点--柔化图像--您可以用简单的“模糊”滤镜。在 GIMP 2.2 中它没有对话框而是自动运行。其效果不明显，您甚至可以注意不到，反复进行就能产生强烈的效果。当然要产生强烈效果，该滤镜并不是最好选择：请使用高斯模糊。
   </para>

    <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;zh_CN">
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-selective.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Selective blur
	  </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            选择性模糊
          </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Selective Blur filter allows you to set a threshold so that
    only pixels that are similar to each other are blurred together.
    It is often useful as a tool for reducing graininess in photos
    without blurring sharp edges.  (In the example, note that the
    graininess of the background has been reduced.)  The
    implementation is much slower 
    than a Gaussian blur, though, so you should not use it unless you
    really need the selectivity.
  </para>
  
    <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;zh_CN">
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-pixelize.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Pixelize
	  </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            像素化
          </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Pixelize filter produces the well-known "Abraham Lincoln"
    effect by turning the image into a set of large square pixels.
    (The <link linkend='plug-in-oilify'>Oilify</link> filter, in
    the Artistic Filters group, has a similar effect, but with
    irregular blobs instead of perfectly square pixels.)
  </para>

    <informalfigure lang="en;zh_CN">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;zh_CN">
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-mblur.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Motion blur
	  </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            动态模糊
          </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Motion Blur filter blurs in a specific direction at each
    point, which allows you to create a sense of motion:  either
    linear, radial, or rotational.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Finally, the Tileable Blur filter is really the same thing as a
    Gaussian blur, except that it wraps around the edges of an image
    to help you reduce edge effects when you create a pattern by
    tiling multiple copies of the image side by side.
  </para>
  <note lang='en'>
    <para>
      Tileable Blur is actually implemented by a Script-Fu script that
      invokes the Gaussian blur plug-in.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang="de">
    Für jeden Pixel des Bildes werden Farbwerte benachbartert Pixel
    hinzugezogen. Dabei vermischen sich die Farbinformationen und ein
    unscharfes Bild entsteht. Die Weichzeichnen Filter unterscheiden
    sich in der Art wieviel benachbarte Farbwerte in die Berechnung mit
    einfließen oder andere Informationen hinzugezogen werden.
  </para>
</sect2>
