<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-08-01 prokoudine: improved Russian content
  2007-03-27 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-08-18 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="filters-blur-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Blur</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Original for demo</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/filters/examples/blur-demo-orig.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This is a set of filters that blur images, or parts of them,
    in various ways.  If there is a selection, only the selected parts
    of an image will be blurred. There may, however, be some leakage
    of colors from the unblurred area into the blurred area.  To help
    you pick the one you want, we will illustrate what each does when
    applied to the image shown at right.  These are, of course, only
    examples:  most of the filters have parameter settings that allow
    you to vary the magnitude or type of blurring.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Gaussian blur (radius 10)</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/filters/examples/blur-demo-gauss10.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The most broadly useful of these is the Gaussian blur. (Don't let
    the word "Gaussian" throw you: this filter makes an image blurry
    in the most basic way.)  It has an efficient implementation that
    allows it to create a very blurry blur in a relatively short
    time.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Simple blur</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/filters/examples/blur-demo-blur.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    If you only want to blur the image a little bit — to soften it, as it were — 
    you might use the simple "Blur" filter. This filter runs automatically, 
    without creating a dialog. The effect is subtle enough that you might not 
    even notice it, but you can get a stronger effect by repeating it.  In GIMP 
    2.0 the filter shows a dialog that allows you to set a "repeat count". If 
    you want a strong blurring effect, this filter is too slow to be a good 
    choice: use a Gaussian blur instead.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Selective blur</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/filters/examples/blur-demo-selective.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Selective Blur filter allows you to set a threshold so that
    only pixels that are similar to each other are blurred together.
    It is often useful as a tool for reducing graininess in photos
    without blurring sharp edges.  (In the example, note that the
    graininess of the background has been reduced.)  The
    implementation is much slower
    than a Gaussian blur, though, so you should not use it unless you
    really need the selectivity.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Pixelize</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/filters/examples/blur-demo-pixelize.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Pixelize filter produces the well-known "Abraham Lincoln"
    effect by turning the image into a set of large square pixels.
    (The <link linkend="plug-in-oilify">Oilify</link> filter, in
    the Artistic Filters group, has a similar effect, but with
    irregular blobs instead of perfectly square pixels.)
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      You can find a nice explanation of the Abraham Lincoln effect
      at <xref linkend="bibliography-online-bach"/>. You will see the
      Salvador Dali's painting <quote>Gala Contemplating the
      Mediterranean Sea</quote> turning to an Abraham Lincoln's portrait
      when looking at it from a distance.
    </para>
  </note>

  <figure>
    <title>Motion blur</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/filters/examples/blur-demo-mblur.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Motion Blur filter blurs in a specific direction at each point, which
    allows you to create a sense of motion: either linear, radial, or
    rotational.
  </para>

  <para>
    Finally, the Tileable Blur filter is really the same thing as a Gaussian
    blur, except that it wraps around the edges of an image to help you reduce
    edge effects when you create a pattern by tiling multiple copies of the
    image side by side.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      Tileable Blur is actually implemented by a Script-Fu script that invokes
      the Gaussian blur plug-in.
    </para>
  </note>
</sect2>
