<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='filters-blur-introduction' lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Úvod do rozostřovacích filtrů</title>
  <title lang="en">Blur filters introduction</title>
  <title lang="fr">Introduction aux filtres de flou</title> 
  <title lang="it">Introduzione ai filtri di sfocatura</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">模糊滤镜简介</title>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Filtry</primary>
    <secondary>Rozostření</secondary>
    <tertiary>Úvod</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Blur</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduction</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Flou</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduction</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary>
    <secondary>Sfocatura</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduzione</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>滤镜</primary>
    <secondary>模糊</secondary>
    <tertiary>简介</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-orig.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="cs">
          Originální obrázek
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Original for demo
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Original pour démonstration
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Originale per dimostrazione
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          范例的原始图像
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    This is a set of filters that blur images, or parts of them,
    in various ways.  If there is a selection, only the selected parts
    of an image will be blurred.  There may, however, be some leakage
    of colors from the unblurred area into the blurred area.  To help
    you pick the one you want, we will illustrate what each does when
    applied to the image shown at right.  These are, of course, only
    examples:  most of the filters have parameter settings that allow
    you to vary the magnitude or type of blurring.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Filtry z této sady různým způsobem rozostřují obrázky nebo jejich části.
    Pokud je v obrázku aktivní výběr, jsou rozostřeny pouze vybrané oblasti.
    Může však dojít k zanesení barev z nerozostřené oblasti do oblasti
    rozostřené. Abychom usnadnili výběr správného filtru, ukážeme zde efekt
    každého rozostřovacího filtru na výše zobrazeném obrázku. Jedná se však
    pouze o příklady, většina filtrů má různé parametry umožňující nastavit
    typ či míru rozostření.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    Il s'agit là d'un lot de filtres pour donner du flou à une image, ou à 
    une partie d'image, de différentes façons. Si une sélection est 
    présente, le flou ne portera que sur cette sélection. Il peut néanmoins 
    y avoir quelques fuites de la partie non sélectionnée vers la 
    sélectionnée. Pour vous aider à choisir entre les différentes méthodes, 
    nous allons montrer ce que donne leur application à l'image ci-dessus.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Questo è un insieme di filtri che sfocano le immagini, o parte di esse,
    in varie modalità. Se c'è una selezione, solo le parti selezionate
    dell'immagine verranno sfocate. Attenzione al fatto che un po' di colore
    della sfocatura potrebbe "macchiare" le parti non sfocate. Per aiutare a
    selezionare quello che si desidera, illustreremo uno a uno cosa fanno
    se applicati all'immagine mostrata sulla destra. Naturalmente questi sono
    solo esempi: molti filtri hanno delle impostazioni di parametri che permettono
    di variare l'intensità o il tipo di sfocatura.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    这些滤镜用多种方式模糊图像或其部分。当选区存在时，只有图像中选中的部分会被模糊。不过可能有些未模糊区域中的颜色会泄漏到模糊区域中。为了帮助您选取正确的模糊滤镜，下面有它们应用到同一个图像中的效果。当然它们只是范例：大部分滤镜都有改变模糊放大率或类型的参数设置。
  </para>

  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-gauss10.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Gaussian blur (radius 10)
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Gaussiovo rozostření (poloměr 10)
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Flou Gaussien (Rayon 10)
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Sfocatura Gaussiana (raggio 10)
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          高斯模糊(半径 10)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The most broadly useful of these is the Gaussian blur. (Don't let
    the word "Gaussian" throw you: this filter makes an image blurry
    in the most basic way.)  It has an efficient implementation that
    allows it to create a very blurry blur in a relatively short
    time.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nejpoužívanější ze všech rozostřovacích filtrů je Gaussovo rozostření.
    (Nenechte se vystrašit jménem slavného matematika, použití filtru je
    opravdu jednoduché.) Tento filtr je velmi efektivní a umožňuje rychle
    vytvořit velmi silné rozosření (pokud je takové žádáno).
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    C'est le plus utilisé des filres de flou. Ne soyez pas effrayé par le 
    terme «Gaussien»: ce filtre agit de la façon la plus simple. Il fournit 
    rapidement un flou marqué.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il più utile di questi filtri è la sfocatura Gaussiana. (Non spaventatevi
    dal termine "Gaussiana": questo filtro crea una sfocatura alla maniera più
    semplice.) Ha un'efficiente implementazione che permette di creare immagini
    molto sfocate in un tempo relativamente breve.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    用处最广泛的是高斯模糊。(不要被“高斯”吓着了：该滤镜对图像只是进行最基本的模糊。)它的实现非常有效率，可以是图像非常模糊却只需要相对少的时间。
  </para>

  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-blur.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="cs">
          Jednoduché rozostření
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Simple blur
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Flou simple
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Sfocatura semplice
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          简单模糊
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para lang="en">
    If you only want to blur the image a little bit--to
    soften it, as it were--you might use the simple "Blur" filter.  In
    Gimp 2.2 this runs automatically, without creating a dialog.  The
    effect is subtle enough that you might not even notice it, but you
    can get a stronger effect by repeating it.  In Gimp 2.0 the filter
    shows a dialog that allows you to set a "repeat count".
    If you want a strong blurring effect, this filter
    is too slow to be a good choice: use a Gaussian blur instead.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Pokud je zapotřebí obrázek rozostřit jen trošku – lehce ho změkčit, hodí
    se k tomu jednoduchý filtr Rozostření. V Gimpu 2.2 tento filtr běží
    automaticky, bez zobrazené jakéhokoliv dialogu. Účinek filtru je natolik
    jemný, že si ho možná ani nevšimnete, lze ale zesílit opakovanou
    aplikací. V Gimpu 2.0 k tomu napomáhal dialog s volbou počtu opakovaných
    aplikací filtru, ale bylo to příliš pomalé. K vytvoření silnějšího
    rozostření je vhodnější použít filtr Gaussovo rozostření.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    C'est le filtre à utiliser si vous ne voulez qu'un léger flou. Ce filtre 
    agit de façon immédiate, sans passer par une fenêtre de dialogue. 
    L'effet est si léger qu'il peut être imperceptible et que vous serez 
    amené à répéter l'action du filtre (Dans Gimp-2.0, on disposait d'un 
    réglage «Répétition»).
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Se solo si vuole sfocare poco l'immagine --renderla più morbida--
    potete usare il filtro di sfocatura semplice. In Gimp 2.2 viene
    eseguito direttamente senza creare una finestra di dialogo.
    L'effetto è così delicato che potreste non accorgervi di averlo 
    eseguito ma è possibile ottenere un effetto più forte ripetendone
    l'applicazione. In Gimp 2.0 il filtro mostrava una finestra che
    permetteva un conteggio delle applicazioni. Se si vuole un effetto
    più forte, questo filtro è troppo lento per essere una buona scelta:
    usate invece la sfocatura Gaussiana.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果只要图像模糊一点--柔化图像--您可以用简单的“模糊”滤镜。在 GIMP 2.2 中它没有对话框而是自动运行。其效果不明显，您甚至可以注意不到，反复进行就能产生强烈的效果。当然要产生强烈效果，该滤镜并不是最好选择：请使用高斯模糊。
  </para>

  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-selective.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Selective blur
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Selektivní rozostření
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Flou sélectif
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Sfocatura selettiva
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          选择性模糊
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Selective Blur filter allows you to set a threshold so that
    only pixels that are similar to each other are blurred together.
    It is often useful as a tool for reducing graininess in photos
    without blurring sharp edges.  (In the example, note that the
    graininess of the background has been reduced.)  The
    implementation is much slower 
    than a Gaussian blur, though, so you should not use it unless you
    really need the selectivity.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Filtr Selektivní Gaussovo rozostření umožňuje nastavit práh – pozue
    pixely, které jsou si dostatečně podobné jsou vzájemně rozostřeny.
    To je užitečné například pro snížení zrnitosti fotografií bez rozostření
    ostrých hran. (Všimněte si snížené zrnitosti pozadí v příkladu.) Filtr je
    ovšem mnohem pomalejší než Gaussovo rozostření, takže se nehodí v
    případech, kdy selektivita není potřebná.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    Le Flou Sélectif vous permet de fixer un seuil de telle sorte que seuls 
    les pixels qui atteignent ce seuil seront rendus flous. Il est souvent 
    utilisé pour réduire le grain des photos, sans toucher aux bords nets. 
    (Sur l'exemple, vous noterez que que le grains du fond a été réduit). 
    La mise en œuvre est beaucoup plus longue que pour un flou gaussien.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    The Selective Blur filter allows you to set a threshold so that
    only pixels that are similar to each other are blurred together.
    It is often useful as a tool for reducing graininess in photos
    without blurring sharp edges.  (In the example, note that the
    graininess of the background has been reduced.)  The
    implementation is much slower 
    than a Gaussian blur, though, so you should not use it unless you
    really need the selectivity.
  </para>

  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-pixelize.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Pixelize
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Pixelizace
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Pixéliser
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Effetto pixel
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          像素化
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Pixelize filter produces the well-known "Abraham Lincoln"
    effect by turning the image into a set of large square pixels.
    (The <link linkend='plug-in-oilify'>Oilify</link> filter, in
    the Artistic Filters group, has a similar effect, but with
    irregular blobs instead of perfectly square pixels.)
  </para>
  <note lang="en">
    <para>
      You can find a nice explanation of the Abraham Lincoln effect
      at <ulink url="http://www.michaelbach.de/ot/fcs_mosaic/"></ulink>.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang="cs">
    Filtr Pixelizace vytváří známý mozaikový efekt používaný například
    k zakrytí obličejů osob, jejichž identita nesmí být prozrazena.
    Obrázek je přeměněn na mozaiku složenou z velkých čtvercových
    (Filtr <link linkend='plug-in-oilify'>Olejomalba</link> ze skupiny
    uměleckých filtrů funguje podobně, místo praviídelných čtverců včak
    vytváří nepravidelné skvrny.)
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    Le Filtre Pixéliser donne à l'image un aspect de mosaïque composée de 
    tesselles carrées. ( Le filtre  
    <link linkend='plug-in-oilify'>Peinture à l'huile</link> a un peu le 
    même effet, mais avec des éléments irréguliers.). Il permet de réaliser 
    un effet «Abraham Lincoln» bien expliqué (en anglais) à
    <ulink url="http://www.michaelbach.de/ot/fcs_mosaic/"></ulink>.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il filtro effetto pixel produce il famoso effetto "Abramo Lincoln"
    trasformando l'immagine in un insieme di grandi e squadrati pixel.
    (Il filtro <!--link linkend='plug-in-oilify' FIXME -->Pittura 
    a olio<!--/link-->, nel gruppo dei filtri artistici, ha un effetto 
    simile ma con forme arrotondate irregolari invece che pixel 
    perfettamente squadrati.)
  </para>

  <informalfigure lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;fr;it;zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/blur-demo-mblur.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Motion blur
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Rozmáznutí pohybem
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Flou cinétique
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Sfocatura movimento
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          动态模糊
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Motion Blur filter blurs in a specific direction at each
    point, which allows you to create a sense of motion:  either
    linear, radial, or rotational.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Finally, the Tileable Blur filter is really the same thing as a
    Gaussian blur, except that it wraps around the edges of an image
    to help you reduce edge effects when you create a pattern by
    tiling multiple copies of the image side by side.
  </para>
  <note lang="en">
    <para>
      Tileable Blur is actually implemented by a Script-Fu script that
      invokes the Gaussian blur plug-in.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang="cs">
    Rozmáznutí pohybem rozostřuje každý pixel v určitém směru, čímž vytváří
    dojem pohybu, ať už přímořarého, kruhového nebo přiblížení.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Dlaždicovatelné rozostření je v podstatě totéž, co Gaussovo rozostření.
    Jediným rozdílem je, že pracuje i přes okraje obrázku, čímž snižuje
    viditelnost okrajů při skládání více kopií obrázku vedle sebe.
  </para>
  <note lang="cs">
    <para>
      Dlaždicovatelné rozostření je implementováno jako Skript-Fu, které volá
      zásuvný modul Gaussovo rozostření.
    </para>
  </note>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    Le flou cinétique ne porte que sur une direction particulière, donnant 
    un effet de mouvement       
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il filtro di sfocatura movimento sfoca in una specifica direzione
    per ogni punto dando un senso di movimento: sia lineare che radiale o
    rotazionale.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Infine, il filtro di sfocatura piastrellabile è proprio uguale alla 
    sfocatura Gaussiana eccetto il fatto che gira intorno ai bordi
    dell'immagine per aiutare a ridurre l'effetto bordo quando si
    crea un motivo allineando tra loro più copie dell'immagine.
  </para>
  <note lang="it">
    <para>
      Il filtro sfocatura piastrellabile è attualmente implementato tramite
      uno script Script-Fu che invoca il plug-in di sfocatura Gaussiana.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang="de">
    Für jeden Pixel des Bildes werden Farbwerte benachbartert Pixel
    hinzugezogen. Dabei vermischen sich die Farbinformationen und ein
    unscharfes Bild entsteht. Die Weichzeichnen Filter unterscheiden
    sich in der Art wieviel benachbarte Farbwerte in die Berechnung mit
    einfließen oder andere Informationen hinzugezogen werden.
  </para>
</sect2>
