<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='filters-blur-mblur' lang="en;fr">
  <title lang="de">Bewegungsunschärfe</title>
  <title lang="en">Motion Blur</title>
  <title lang="fr">Flou cinétique</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Blur</secondary>
    <tertiary>Motion</tertiary>  
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Weichzeichnen</secondary> 
    <tertiary>Bewegungsunschärfe</tertiary> 
  </indexterm>
    
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtre</primary>
    <secondary>Flou</secondary>
    <tertiary>Cinétique</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-blur-mblur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-blur-mblur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filters/Blur/<accel>M</accel>otion Blur</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Motion Blur filter creates a movement blur. The filter is capable
      of Linear, Radial, and Zoom movements. Each of these movements can be
      further adjusted, with Length, or Angle  settings available.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filtres/Flou/Flou <accel>c</accel>inétique</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre donne une impression de mouvement. Le déplacement
      peut être Linéaire, Radial ou en Zoom. Chacun de ces
      déplacements peut être ajusté selon la Longueur
      ou l'Angle.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect> 
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Blur Type</term>
        <term lang="fr">Type de flou</term> 
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Linear</guilabel> motion is a blur that travels in a
            single direction, horizontally, for example. In this case,
            Length means as Radius in other filters:it represents the blur
            intensity. More Length will result in more blurring. Angle
            describes the actual angle of the movement. Thus, a setting of
            90 will produce a vertical blur, and a setting of 0 will
            produce a horizontal blur.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Radial</guilabel> motion blur creates a circular
            blur. The Length slider is not important with this type of
            blur. Angle on the other hand, is the primary setting that will
            affect the blur. More Angle will result in more blurring in a
            circular direction. The Radial motion blur is similar to the
            effect of a spinning object. The center of the spin in this
            case, is the center of the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">      
            <guilabel>Zoom</guilabel> blurring produces a blur that
            radiates out from the center of the image. The center of the
            image remains relatively calm, whilst the outer areas become
            blurred toward the center. This filter option produces a
            perceived forward movement, into the image.  Length is the main
            setting here, and affects the amount of speed, as it were,
            toward the center of the image.
          </para>
           <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Linéaire</guilabel>: c'est un flou qui ne va
            que dans une seule direction, par exemple  horizontalement.
            Dans ce cas, Longueur a la même signification que le
            Rayon des autres filtres: elle indique l'intensité du flou.
            Angle désigne la direction du mouvement: 90 donne un
            flou vertical et 0 un flou horizontal.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Radial</guilabel>: c'est un flou circulaire. Longueur
            importe peu dans ce cas.  Angle est primordial: une forte
            valeur donnera un flou plus étendu circulairement.Le
            flou circulaire donne l'effet d'un objet tournoyant où
            le centre de rotation est le centre de l'image. 
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Zoom</guilabel>: produit un flou qui irradie à
            partir du centre de l'image. Le centre de l'image demeure
            relativement calme tandis que les zones
            périphériques deviennent floues. Cette option
            donne un effet de mouvement vers l'avant à
            l'intérieur de l'image, comme si un objet ou un
            personnage venait vers vous. Longueur est le paramètre
            qui conditionne l'effet de vitesse de déplacement.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
 
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Blur settings</term>
        <term lang="fr">Paramètres de flou</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Length</guilabel>: This slider controls the distance
            pixels are moved (0 - 256)
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: (0 - 360) As seen above, Angle
            slider effect depends on Blur type.
          </para>
 
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Longueur</guilabel>: Ce curseur contrôle la
            distance de déplacement des pixels (0 - 256).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: (0 - 360). Comme vu ci-dessus,
            l'effet de ce curseur dépend du Type de flou.
          </para> 
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
