<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-mblur' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Rozmáznutí pohybem</title>
  <title lang="de">Bewegungsunschärfe</title>
  <title lang="en">Motion Blur</title>
  <title lang="fr">Flou cinétique</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">动态模糊</title> 
  
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Blur</secondary>
    <tertiary>Motion</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>filtry</primary>
    <secondary>rozostření</secondary>
    <tertiary>Rozmazání pohybem</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Weichzeichnen</secondary> 
    <tertiary>Bewegungsunschärfe</tertiary> 
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtre</primary>
    <secondary>Flou</secondary>
    <tertiary>Cinétique</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>滤镜</primary>
    <secondary>模糊</secondary>
    <tertiary>动态</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-blur-mblur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-blur-mblur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-blur-mblur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/zh_CN/filters-blur-mblur.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filters/Blur/<accel>M</accel>otion Blur</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Motion Blur filter creates a movement blur. The filter is capable
      of Linear, Radial, and Zoom movements. Each of these movements can be
      further adjusted, with Length, or Angle  settings available.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr je dostupný z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Rozostření</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Rozmáznutí pohybem</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr Rozmáznutí pohybem vytváří efekt napodobující pohybové rozostření.
      Umožňuje napodobit lineární, radiální nebo přibližovací pohybové
      rozostření. U všech typů lze nastavit délku a/nebo úhel rozmáznutí.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      On accède à ce filtre par le menu d'image en suivant
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Flou</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Flou Cinétique</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre donne une impression de mouvement. Le déplacement
      peut être Linéaire, Radial ou en Zoom. Chacun de ces
      déplacements peut être ajusté selon la Longueur
      ou l'Angle.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这个滤镜在: 
      <guimenuitem>图像&gt;滤镜/模糊/动态模糊</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      动态模糊可以对图像产生动态化的模糊效果。这个滤镜可以产生线性、转向、缩放等不同的动态化模糊效果、每一种动态化模糊效果都可以通过可用到的长度和角度的条件来获得最佳的效果。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect> 
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Blur Type</term>
        <term lang="cs">Typ rozostření</term>
        <term lang="fr">Type de flou</term> 
        <term lang="zh_CN">模糊类型</term>
  <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Linear</guilabel> motion is a blur that travels in a
            single direction, horizontally, for example. In this case,
            Length means as Radius in other filters:it represents the blur
            intensity. More Length will result in more blurring. Angle
            describes the actual angle of the movement. Thus, a setting of
            90 will produce a vertical blur, and a setting of 0 will
            produce a horizontal blur.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Lineární</guilabel> pohybové rozostření rozmázne pixely
            v jednom směru, například vodorovně. V tomto případě slouží délka
            k podobnému účelu jako poloměr u ostatních rozostřovacích filtrů
            – určuje intenzitu rozostření. Větší délka odpovídá silnějšímu
            rozostření. Úhel určuje skutečný úhel pohybu. 90° vytvoří svislé
            rozostření, 0° vytvoří vodorovné rozostření.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Linéaire</guilabel>: c'est un flou qui ne va
            que dans une seule direction, par exemple  horizontalement.
            Dans ce cas, Longueur a la même signification que le
            Rayon des autres filtres: elle indique l'intensité du flou.
            Angle désigne la direction du mouvement: 90 donne un
            flou vertical et 0 un flou horizontal.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
      <guilabel>线性</guilabel>动态模糊是一种作用在单一方向，水平的模糊。例如，在这种情况下，长度就是相当于其他滤镜中的半径：它决定了模糊的强度。长度值越大就会产生越强烈的模糊效果。角度值决定了模糊中的实际角度。因此，角度值为 90 会产生垂直的模糊，设置为 0 度时则会产生水平的模糊。
          </para>

    <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Radial</guilabel> motion blur creates a circular
            blur. The Length slider is not important with this type of
            blur. Angle on the other hand, is the primary setting that will
            affect the blur. More Angle will result in more blurring in a
            circular direction. The Radial motion blur is similar to the
            effect of a spinning object. The center of the spin in this
            case, is the center of the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Radialní</guilabel> pohybové rozostření vytvoří kruhové
            rozostření. Délka zde není důležitá. Podstatný je úhel, který
            určuje intenzitu rozostření. Radiální rozostření vytváří efekt
            otáčejícího se objektu. Střed otáčení je uprostřed obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Radial</guilabel>: c'est un flou circulaire. Longueur
            importe peu dans ce cas.  Angle est primordial: une forte
            valeur donnera un flou plus étendu circulairement.Le
            flou circulaire donne l'effet d'un objet tournoyant où
            le centre de rotation est le centre de l'image. 
          </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <guilabel>转向</guilabel>型动态模糊产生的是一种环状的模糊。长度在这个类型的模糊就显的不是那么重要了。角度的设置将是决定这个模糊基本因素。更大的角度值，将会在圆环方向上产生更强烈的模糊效果。旋转型动态模糊就类似于一个旋转的物体，旋转的中心就相当于这个滤镜所作用的图片的中心。
          </para>
    
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Zoom</guilabel> blurring produces a blur that
            radiates out from the center of the image. The center of the
            image remains relatively calm, whilst the outer areas become
            blurred toward the center. This filter option produces a
            perceived forward movement, into the image.  Length is the main
            setting here, and affects the amount of speed, as it were,
            toward the center of the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Přibližovací</guilabel> pohybové rozostření vytváří
            rozostření, které vyzařuje ze středu obrázku. Střed zůstává
            relativnmě klidný, zatímco vnější oblasti jsou rozmáznuté směrem
            ke středu. Vzniká tak dojem dopředného pohybu, dovnitř obrázku.
            Důležitým parametrem je zde délka, která určuje intenzitu
            rozostření, tedy zdánlivou rychlost pohybu ke středu obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Zoom</guilabel>: produit un flou qui irradie à
            partir du centre de l'image. Le centre de l'image demeure
            relativement calme tandis que les zones
            périphériques deviennent floues. Cette option
            donne un effet de mouvement vers l'avant à
            l'intérieur de l'image, comme si un objet ou un
            personnage venait vers vous. Longueur est le paramètre
            qui conditionne l'effet de vitesse de déplacement.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
      <guilabel>缩放</guilabel>型动态模糊会产生一种从图片中心的辐射性模糊。图片的中心不会被模糊，而图片的外围相对于中心会显的模糊。这个滤镜给图像一种很突出的动态感觉。长度是主要的选项，影响着总体的速度，好比是向着图像的中心。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Blur settings</term>
        <term lang="cs">Parametry rozmáznutí</term>
        <term lang="fr">Paramètres de flou</term>
  <term lang="zh_CN">模糊选项</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Length</guilabel>: This slider controls the distance
            pixels are moved (0 - 256)
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: (0 - 360) As seen above, Angle
            slider effect depends on Blur type.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Délka</guilabel>: Tento posuvník nastavuje délku
            dráhy pixelů (0-255).
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Úhel</guilabel>: (0 - 360), jak je uvedeno výše,
            vliv nastavení úhlu závisí na typu rozostření.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Longueur</guilabel>: Ce curseur contrôle la
            distance de déplacement des pixels (0 - 256).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: (0 - 360). Comme vu ci-dessus,
            l'effet de ce curseur dépend du Type de flou.
          </para> 

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <guilabel>长度</guilabel>：移动控制条控制间隔的像素（0 - 256）
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <guilabel>角度</guilabel>：（0 - 360） 参照上面的，角度控制的不同影响取决于不同的模糊类型。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
