<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-05-27 j.h fix issue #126: rearrange floating selection
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-selection-float">
  <title>Float</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selection</primary>
    <secondary>Floating selection (command)</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Float</guimenuitem> command converts a normal selection
    into a <quote>floating selection</quote>.
  </para>
  <para>
    A floating selection (sometimes called a <quote>floating layer</quote>) is
    a type of temporary layer which is similar in function to a normal layer,
    except that before you can resume working on any other layers in the
    image, a floating selection must be <emphasis>anchored</emphasis>.
    That is, you have to attach it to a normal (non-floating) layer, usually
    the original layer (the one which was active previously), for instance, by
    clicking on the image outside of the floating selection (see below).
  </para>
  <important>
    <para>
      You cannot perform any operations on other layers while the image has a
      floating selection!
    </para>
  </important>
  <para>
    You can use various operations to change the image data on the floating
    selection. There can only be one floating selection in an image at a time.
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      If you display the layer boundary by using the
      <link linkend="gimp-view-show-layer-boundary">Show Layer Boundary</link>
      command, you may have difficulty selecting a precise area of the
      image which you want in a layer. To avoid this problem, you can make a
      rectangular selection, transform it into a floating selection and
      anchor it to a new layer. Then simply remove the original layer.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
    In early versions of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, floating
    selections were used for performing operations on a limited part of an
    image. You can do that more easily now with layers, but you can still
    use this way of working with images.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this command from the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Float</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap>
          </keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Creating a Floating Selection Automatically</title>
    <para>
      Some image operations create a floating selection automatically:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <quote>paste</quote> operations,
          <link linkend="gimp-buffer-dialog">Paste Named Buffer</link>,
          <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Paste</link> or
          <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste-into">Paste Into</link>, also
          create a floating selection.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In addition, the Transform tools,
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-flip">Flip</link>,
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-shear">Shear</link>,
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scale</link>,
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-rotate">Rotate</link> and
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-perspective">Perspective</link>,
          create a floating selection when they are used on a selection,
          rather than a layer. When the <guilabel>Affect</guilabel> mode is
          <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis> and a selection already exists,
          these tools transform the selection and create a floating selection
          with the result. If a selection does not exist, they transform the
          current layer and do not create a floating selection. (If the
          <guilabel>Affect</guilabel> mode is <emphasis>Transform
          Selection</emphasis>, they also do not create a floating selection.)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By click-and-dragging a selection while pressing the
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> keys
          (see <xref linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving"/>) you also
          automatically create a floating selection.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="anchor-floating-selection">
    <title>Anchor a Floating Selection</title>
    <para>You can anchor a floating selection in various ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can anchor the floating selection to the current layer the
          selection is originating from. To do this, click anywhere on the
          image except on the floating selection. This merges the floating
          selection with the current layer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Or you can use the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">Anchor layer</link> command
          (<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can also anchor the floating selection to the current layer by
          clicking on the anchor button
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-anchor.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>
                <phrase>Anchor the floating Layer</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          of the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers dialog</link>, that 
          appears, since GIMP-2.10.18, when the floating selection is created, 
          instead of the default Merge layers icon.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you create a <link linkend="gimp-layer-new">New Layer</link>
          while there is a floating selection, the floating selection is
          anchored to this newly created layer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
