<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-environment'>
  <title lang='en'>Environment</title>
  <title lang='de'>Umgebung</title>
  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>environment</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Umgebung</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary></primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-environment.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='de'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-environment.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-environment.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        Environment Preferences
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='de'>
    Beeinflussen Sie den Ressourcenverbrauch, sowie das Verhalten beim
    Speichern von Dateien von GIMP in dieser
    Einstellungsansicht.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you customize the amount of system memory allocated
    for various purposes.  It also allows you to disable the
    confirmation dialogs that appear when you close unsaved images,
    and to set the size of thumbnail files that GIMP produces.
  </para>

  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
  <variablelist>
    <title lang="en">Resource Consumption</title>
    <title lang="de">Ressourcenverbrauch</title>
 
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Minimal number of undo levels</term>
      <term lang="de">Minimale Anzahl an Schritten</term>
      <term lang="fr"/>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          GIMP allows you to undo most actions by maintaining an "Undo
          History" for each image, for which a certain amount of
          memory is allocated.  Regardless of memory usage, however,
          GIMP always permits some minimal number of the most recent
          actions to be undone:  this is the number specified here.
          See <link linkend='gimp-undo'>Undoing</link> for more
          information about GIMP's Undo mechanism.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Verändern sie wie oft sie Operationen rückgängig machen
          möchten.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Maximum undo memory</term>
      <term lang='de'>Maximaler Speicher für Rückgängigmachung</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This is the amount of undo memory allocated for each image.
          If the Undo History size exceeds this, the oldest points are
          deleted, unless this would result in fewer points being
          present than the minimal number specified above.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Beeinflussen sie die Bereitstellung von Speicher, um die
          <guilabel>Minimale Anzahl an Schritten</guilabel> rückgängig
          zu machen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Tile cache size</term>
      <term lang='de'>Größe des Datenspeichers</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This is the amount of system RAM allocated for GIMP image
          data.  If GIMP requires more memory than this, it begins to
          swap to disk, which may in some circumstances cause a
          dramatic slowdown.  You are given an opportunity to set this
          number when you install GIMP, but you can alter it here. See
          <link linkend='gimp-using-setup-tile-cache'>How to Set Your
          Tile Cache</link> for more information. 
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Beeinflussen sie die Größe des Speichers, welcher für ein
          geladenes Bild zur Verfügung steht.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Maximum new image size</term>
      <term lang='de'>Zurückhaltende Speichernutzung</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          This is not a hard contraint:  if you try to create a new
          image larger than the specified size, you are asked to
          confirm that you really want to do it.  This is to prevent
          you from accidentally creating images much larger than you
          intend, which can either crash GIMP or cause it to respond
          verrrrrrrry slowwwwwwwwly.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>File Saving</title>
      <title lang='de'>Dateien speichern</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Confirm closing of unsaved images</term>
        <term lang='de'>Schließen ungespeicherter Bilder bestätigen</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Closing an image is not undoable, so by default GIMP asks
            you to confirm that you really want to do it, whenever it
            would lead to a loss of unsaved changes.  You can disable
            this if you find it annoying; but then of course you are
            responsible for remembering what you have and have not
            saved. 
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Aktivieren sie dieses Kontrollkästchen, damit
            <acronym>Gimp</acronym> sie nochmal vor dem Beenden des
            Programmes erinnert, dass Bilder geöffnet sind, die noch
            abgespeichert werden müssen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='de'>"Datei->Speichern" speichert das Bild</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Beeinflussen Sie das Verhalten beim Speichern von Bildern.
            Steht die Auswahl auf <guilabel>Immer</guilabel>, wird das
            Bild immer auf die Festplatte gespeichert, auch wenn keine
            Operationen das Bild verändert haben. Steht die Auswahl auf
            <guilabel>Nur wenn geändert</guilabel>, wird das Bild nur
            dann auf die Festplatte gespeichert, wenn auch wirklich
            Operationen das Bild verändert haben.
          </para>
          <note>
            Verschiedene Operationen oder Funktionen werden von
            <acronym>Gimp</acronym> nicht als Veränderung des Bildes
            angesehen. Mit der Auswahl von <guilabel>Immer</guilabel>,
            können Sie sicher sein, dass jegliche Veränderungen am Bild
            auch auf die Festplatte geschrieben werden.
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Size of thumbnail files</term>
        <term lang='de'>Größe der Vorschaudateien</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Here you can set the size of thumbnail files that GIMP
            generates.  Regardless of this value, GIMP will still be
            capable of <emphasis>reading</emphasis> thumbnail files of
            any size.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Bestimmen Sie die Größe der Vorschaubilder, die in den <link
            linkend='gimp-file-open'>Öffnen</link> und <link
            linkend='gimp-file-save'>Speichern</link> Dialogen angezeigt
            werden.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </simplesect>
</sect2>
