<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-theme' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Theme</title>
  <title lang='de'>Thema</title>
  <title lang="fr">Thème</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">主题</title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>theme</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Thema</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Thème</tertiary>
  </indexterm>  
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>主题</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role='html'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png'
        format="PNG" lang='en;zh_CN' />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png'
        format="PNG" lang='de' />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-theme.png'
        format="PNG" lang='fr' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role='tex'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png'
        format="PNG" lang='en;zh_CN' />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png'
        format="PNG" lang='de' />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-theme.png'
        format="PNG" lang='fr' />
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Theme Preference
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Choix du thème
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          主题首选项
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>  

  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you select a theme, which determines many aspects of
    the appearance of the GIMP user interface, including the set of
    icons used, their sizes, fonts, spacing allowed in dialogs, etc.
    Two themes are supplied with GIMP: <guilabel>Default</guilabel>,
    which is probably best for most people, and
    <guilabel>Small</guilabel>, which may be preferable for those with
    small or low-resolution monitors.  Clicking on a theme in the list
    causes it to be applied immediately, so it is easy to see the result
    and change your mind if you don't like it.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    GIMP bietet Ihnen die Möglichkeit, zwischen zwei Standardthemen zu
    wählen. Themen haben Auswirkung auf das Aussehen der
    Benutzeroberfläche. Es beeinflußt die zu benutzenden Symbole (oder
    auch Icons genannt), Schriftarten oder Elementeanordnung in
    Dialogen. <acronym>Gimp</acronym> erscheint mit zwei Standardthemen:
    Default und Small. <guilabel>Default</guilabel> wird für die meisten
    Benutzer genau das richtige sein, wobei <guilabel>Small</guilabel>
    Symbole für kleinere Montiorauflösungen bietet. Sobald Sie auf ein
    Theme klicken, findet dieses sofort Anwendungen. Sie können sich
    gleich entscheiden, ob es Ihnen gefällt oder nicht.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette page permet de changer l'apparence de GIMP en utilisant des
    thèmes. Un thème contient un ensemble de caractéristiques de
    l'interface comme les icones, leurs tailles, les polices,
    l'agencement des boîtes de dialogues, etc.
    GIMP est livré avec deux thèmes: <guilabel>Default</guilabel>
    probablement adapté aux plus grands nombres, et
    <guilabel>Small</guilabel> avec des icones plus petites adapté
    aux moniteurs de faibles résolutions. La sélection d'un thème dans
    la liste est applicable immédiatement: on peut donc voir facilement
    à quoi ressemble un thème et en changer immédiatement s'il ne
    convient pas.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以在该页选择一个主题，它影响 GIMP 用户界面的很多方面的外观，包括使用的一系列图标，及其大小，字体和对话框中允许的间隔等。GIMP 自带了两个主题：<guilabel>Default</guilabel>，对大多数可能是最好的。和<guilabel>Small</guilabel>，那些有小的或分辨率低的监视器的用户可能喜欢。点击列表中的一个主题，就立即使用它，因此很容易就能看到结果，如果您不喜欢也能很快换为其它的。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    You can also use custom themes, either by downloading them from the
    net, or by copying one of the supplied themes and modifying it.
    Custom themes should be places in the <filename>themes</filename>
    subdirectory of your personal GIMP directory:  if they are, they
    will appear in the list here.  Each theme is actually a directory
    containing ASCII files that you can edit.  They are pretty
    complicated, and the meaning of the contents goes beyond the scope
    of this documentation, but you should feel free to experiment:  in
    the worst case, if you mess things up completely, you can always
    revert back to one of the supplied themes.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Es steht Ihnen somit frei, welche Themen sie verwenden. Sie können
    verfügbare Themen aus dem Internet herunterladen, oder einfach
    selber eines erstellen, indem Sie eins der vorhandenen kopieren und
    anpassen.  Angepaßte Themen sollten in das
    <filename>themes</filename> Verzeichnis in ihrem lokalen
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> Verzeichnis plaziert werden. Sobald das
    Thema dort plaziert ist, erscheint es in der Liste nach dem nächsten
    Start. Jedes Thema ist eine Menge an Bild- und ASCII Dateien. Die
    Anpassung dieser gehört leider nicht mehr zu dieser
    Benutzerdokumentation. Sie selber sind jedoch dazu angespornt herum
    zu experimentieren. Im schlimmsten Fall, können Sie wieder zu einem
    der Standardthemen zurückkehren.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Vous pouvez aussi utiliser d'autres thèmes téléchargés sur Internet,
    ou en copiant un thème existant et en le modifiant. Vous devez placer
    les thèmes supplémentaires dans le répertoire <filename>themes
    </filename> de votre dossier personnel GIMP: les thèmes apparaîtront
    alors dans cette liste. Chaque thème est en fait un répertoire
    contenant des fichiers ASCII que vous pouvez modifier. Ils sont
    plutôt complexes et la signification de leur contenu dépasse le
    cadre de ce document. Toutefois, vous pouvez mener vos propres
    essais sans danger: dans le pire des cas, vous pourrez toujours
    revenir à l'un des thèmes fournis.
  </para>  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您也可以通过从网上下载或修改 GIMP 自带主题的一份拷贝来使用自定义主题。自定义主题应该放在您的个人 GIMP 目录中的 <filename>themes</filename> 子文件夹中：如果是这样，它们会在列表中显示。每个主题实际上是包含可编辑 ASCII 文件的一个目录，它们相同复杂，其内容超过该文档介绍的范围。当您将主题搞乱时，只需要再回到其中一个自带主题。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    You cannot edit the supplied themes unless you have administrator
    permissions, and even if you do, you shouldn't:  if you want to
    customize a theme, make a copy in your personal directory and work
    on it.  If you make a change and would like to see the result "on
    the fly", you can do so by saving the edited theme file and then
    pressing <guilabel>Reload Current Theme</guilabel>.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Beim editieren von Themen können Sie <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
    mitteilen, die veränderten Themendaten wieder zu aktualisieren damit
    ihre Änderungen auch sichtbar werden. Durch einen Klick auf die
    <guilabel>Momentan verwendetes Thema neuladen</guilabel>
    Schaltfläche können Sie die Themendaten aktualisieren.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Vous ne pouvez pas modifier les thèmes par défaut. Et même si vous
    avez les droits administrateurs, vous de devriez pas les modifier.
    Si vous voulez créer un thème personnalisé, copiez le thème original
    dans votre dossier personnel et modifiez la copie. Si vous avez
    modifier votre thème et que vous voulez voir le résultat immédiatement,
    sauvegardez vos modifications et utilisez le bouton<guilabel>
    Recharger le thème actuel</guilabel>
  </para>  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您无法编辑自带主题，除非有管理员权限，即使您有，也不应当那样：可以在个人目录中创建一份自带主题的拷贝，在其上进行修改，然后保存主题文件并按“重新加载当前主题”按钮，这样就能立即看到修改后的结果。
  </para>
  
</sect2>
