<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-folders-data' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Data Folders</title>
  <title lang='de'>Datenordner</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Dossiers des données</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">数据文件夹</title>

  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-brushes' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-patterns' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-palettes' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-gradients' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-fonts' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-plug-ins' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-scripts' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-modules' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-environment' />
  <anchor id='gimp-prefs-folders-themes' />

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>data folders</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Datenordner</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Dossiers des données</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>数据文件夹</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role='html'>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-folders-brush.png'
        format="PNG" lang='en;de;zh_CN'/> 
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-folders-brush.png'
        format="PNG" lang='fr' /> 
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role='tex'>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-folders-brush.png'
        format="PNG" lang='en;de;zh_CN' scalefit='1' width='14cm' /> 
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-folders-brush.png'
        format="PNG" lang='fr' scalefit='1' width='14cm'/> 
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Preferences: Brush Folders
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Préférences: Dossier des brosses
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          首选项：画笔文件夹
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Einstellungsdialog: Ansicht des Pinselordners, welcher einer von
          verschiedenen Datenordnern ist.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP uses several types of resources – such as brushes, patterns,
    gradients, etc. – for which a basic set are supplied by GIMP when
    it is installed, and others can be created or downloaded by the
    user.  For each such resource type, there is a Preference page
    that allows you to specify the <emphasis>search path</emphasis>:
    the set of directories from which items of the type in question
    are automatically loaded when GIMP starts.  These pages all look
    very much the same:  the page for brushes is shown to the right as
    an example.
  </para>
  
  <para lang='fr'>
    GIMP utilise plusieurs types de ressources comme les brosses, les motifs,
    les dégradés, etc. La distribution de GIMP inclus un ensemble de ressources
    de base, mais l'utilisateur peut créer ou télécharger de nouvelles
    ressources. Pour chaque type de ressources, il existe un <emphasis>chemin
    de recherche</emphasis>: ce chemin est constitué d'un ensemble de dossiers
    dans lesquelles GIMP cherchera ses ressources au démarrage. Toutes les
    pages concernant les dossiers de données ont les mêmes caractéristiques:
    la page des brosses est utilisée comme exemple.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 使用多种类型的资源，比如画笔，图案和渐变等。GIMP 安装是就自带了一些基本的，而其它的可以通过用户自己创建或下载。对每种类型的资源，都有一个首选项页，在其中可以设定其<emphasis>搜索路径</emphasis>：即一系列目录，在这些目录中各种类型的资源随 GIMP 启动时自动加载。这些页看上去都差不多：我们把右边的画笔页作为例子。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    By default, the search path includes two folders:  a
    <emphasis>system</emphasis> folder, where items installed along
    with GIMP are placed, and a <emphasis>personal</emphasis> folder,
    inside your personal GIMP directory, where items added by you
    should be placed.  The system folder should not be marked as
    writable, and you should not try to alter its contents.  The
    personal folder must be marked as writable or it is useless,
    because there is nothing inside it except what you put there.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">  
    搜索路径默认包括两个文件夹：<emphasis>系统</emphasis>文件夹--随 GIMP 一起安装的；<emphasis>个人</emphasis>文件夹--在您的个人 GIMP 目录中，添加资源时就应该放在这里。系统文件夹不该设为可写，并且您也不应该尝试改变其内容；而个人文件夹则相反，否则就不可用，在您添加资源以前它是空的。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    You can customize the search path with the buttons at the top of
    the dialog.
  </para>
  
  <para lang='fr'>
    Vous pouvez modifier le chemin de recherche à l'aide des boutons en haut
    de la boîte de dialogue.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">  
    您可以通过对话框顶部的按钮定制搜索路径。
  </para>
  
  <para lang='de'>
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> benutzt verschiedene Arten von Ressourcen,
    wie Pinsel, Muster, Farbverläufe. Solche Daten werden beim ersten
    Start von <acronym>Gimp</acronym> in ihren persönlichen Ordner
    installiert. Wenn Sie selber aus dem Internet Ihre Pinselsammlung
    erweitern wollen, können Sie entweder die Pinsel in ihr persönliches
    Pinselverzeichnis legen oder sie benutzen ein eigenes Verzeichnis
    welches ausserhalb ihres persönlichen Gimp Ordners ist. Letzteres
    erfordert eine Anpassung der Pfade, welches sie in den Ansichten der
    Datenordner machen können.
  </para>

  <variablelist lang='en;fr;zh_CN'>
    <title lang='en'>Options</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Select a Folder</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Sélectionner un dossier</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">选中一个文件夹</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          If you click on one of the folders in the list, it is
          selected for whatever action comes next.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Si vous cliquez sur un dossier dans la liste, il deviendra le
          dossier sur lequel portera l'action ultérieure.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          通过点击列表中一个文件夹来选中它。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Add/Replace Folder</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Ajoujer/Remplacer un dossier</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">添加/替换文件夹</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          If you type the name of a folder in the entry space, or
          navigate to it using the file chooser button on the right,
          and then click the left button, this will replace the
          selected folder with the one you have specified.  If nothing
          in the list is selected, the folder you specify will be
          added to the list.  If the light-symbol to the left of the
          text entry area is red instead of green, it means that the
          folder you have specified does not exist.  GIMP will not
          create it for you, so you should do this immediately.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Vous pouvez choisir un dossier en tapant le chemin dans le
          champ de saisie ou bien en utilisant le sélecteur de dossier
          accessible avec le bouton à droite. Si vous cliquez sur le
          bouton de gauche, le dossier sélectionné sera remplacé; si
          aucun dossier n'était sélectionné, le nouveau sera ajouté à la
          liste. Si le voyant à gauche du champ de saisie est rouge au lieu
          de vert, le dossier spécifié n'existe pas; il faut alors
          créer ce dossier car GIMP ne le créera pas à votre place.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          在输入空间输入一个文件夹名字或使用文件右边的选择按钮，然后点击左边按钮就可以用您指定的来替换选中的文件夹。当没有在列表中选中任何文件夹时，您指定的文件夹将添加到列表中。当指定的文件夹不存在时，输入空间左边的灯就从绿色变为红色，GIMP 不会帮您创建该文件夹。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Move Up/Down</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Déplacer vers le haut/vers le bas</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">升高/降低</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          If you click on the up-arrow or down-arrow buttons, the
          selected folder will be changed to the following or
          preceding one in the list.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Si vous cliquez sur les boutons représentant une fléche vers le
          haut ou vers le bas, le dossier sélectionné sera échangé avec le
          dossier précédant ou le dossier suivant dans la liste.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          点击向上箭头或向下箭头按钮时，所选中的文件夹的位置将在列表中升高或降低。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Delete Folder</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Effacer le dossier</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">删除文件夹</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          If you click the trash-can button, the selected folder will
          be deleted from the list.  (The folder itself is not
          affected; it is merely removed from the search path.)
          Deleting the system folder is probably a bad idea, but
          nothing prevents you from doing it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Si vous cliquez sur le bouton représentant une poubelle, le dossier
          sélectionné sera effacé de la liste (le répertoire lui-même reste
          intact sur le disque; il est juste effacé du chemin de recherche).
          Effacer le dossier systéme est probablement une mauvaise idée, mais
          rien ne vous empêche de le faire.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          点击回收站图标，所选中的文件夹将从列表中删除。(只是从搜索路径中，而文件夹不受影响。)删除系统文件夹也许是个坏主意，不过没有什么可以限制您那样做。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

</sect2>
