<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN'
         'http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd'>

<!--  section history:
  2006-11-01 lexa: made the file docbook compliant
-->
<sect3 id='gimp-prefs-folders' lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;ru;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Folders</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Adresáře</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Datenordner</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Dossiers</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Cartelle</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Каталоги</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">文件夹</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Folders</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>dialogy</primary>
    <secondary>předvolby</secondary>
    <tertiary>adresáře</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Datenordner</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Dossiers</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestre</primary>
    <secondary>Preferenze</secondary>
    <tertiary>Cartelle</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Диалоги</primary>
    <secondary>Настройка</secondary>
    <tertiary>Каталоги</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>文件夹</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Basic Folder Preferences</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Předvolby adresářů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Einstellungsdialog: Ordneransicht</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Préférences pour les dossiers généraux</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Preferenze base delle cartelle</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Основные параметры каталогов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">基本文件夹首选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs;de;en">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-folders.png'
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-folders.png'
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/it/prefs-folders.png'
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/ru/prefs-folders.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/zh_CN/prefs-folders.png'
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    This page allows you to set the locations for two important folders used
    by GIMP for temporary files. The pages below it allow you to customize the
    locations searched for resources such as brushes etc.; see
    <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Data Folders</link>
    for a description that applies to them. You can change the folders here by
    editing the entries, or by pressing the buttons on the right to bring up a
    file chooser window.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Na této kartě předvoleb lze nastavit umístění dvou důležitých adresářů
    používaných pro uchovávání dočasných souborů Gimpu. Dceřiné karty pak
    umožňují upravit umístění adresářů, ve kterých GIMP hledá své zdroje,
    například stopy (viz <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Adresáře s
    daty</link>). Adresáře lze změnit přímou editací cesty nebo kliknutím na
    tlačítka vpravo a použitím dialogu pro výběr souborů.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die Ordnervewaltung in den Einstellungen ermöglicht es ihnen Ordner für
    temporäre Daten anzupassen.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette page permet de choisir l'emplacement dede deux dossiers importants
    utilisés par GIMP pour les fichiers temporaires.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Questa pagina permette di impostare le posizioni su disco di due
    importanti cartelle usate da GIMP per i file temporanei. Le pagine che
    seguono permettono di personalizzare le posizioni ricercate per la
    presenza di risorse come i pennelli o simili; vedere a tal proposito la
    sezione <!-- FIXME: it link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data' -->Cartelle
    dati<!-- /link --> per una descrizione di queste. È possibile cambiare
    la posizione delle cartelle ricercate agendo sul queste voci, o
    premendo i pulsanti presenti sulla destra per portare in evidenza una
    finestra di selezione file e cartelle.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Эта страница дает возможность установить расположение двух важных
    каталогов, которые GIMP использует для временных файлов. Страницы,
    расположенные в настройках ниже этой, позволяют изменить расположение
    таких ресурсов, как кисти и прочее; более подробно об этом написано в
    разделе <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Каталоги данных</link>.
    Здесь вы можете изменить имена каталогов, воспользовавшись полем ввода
    или кнопкой справа от него. При нажатии на кнопку появится диалог выбора
    файла.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以在该页中设定 GIMP 中两个针对临时文件的重要文件夹的位置。下面这些页
    可以定制搜索资源的位置；请看<link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>数据
    文件夹</link>。这里，您可以通过编辑输入项或点击右边按钮并打开选择窗口来
    改变文件夹。
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Folders</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Adresáře</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Ordner</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Dossiers</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Cartelle</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Каталоги</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">文件夹</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Temp folder</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Swap folder</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="cs">
      <primary>Dočasný adresář</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="cs">
      <primary>Odkládací adresář</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Temporärer Ordner</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Auslagerungsordner</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Dossier temporaire</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Dossier d'échange</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="it">
      <primary>Cartella file temporanei</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it">
      <primary>Cartella file di scambio</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="ru">
      <primary>Временный каталог</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ru">
      <primary>Каталог подкачки</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
      <primary>临时文件夹</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
      <primary>交换文件夹</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Temp folder</term>
      <term lang="cs">Dočasný adresář</term>
      <term lang="de">Temporärer Ordner</term>
      <term lang="fr">Répertoire temporaire</term>
      <term lang="it">Cartella file temporanei</term>
      <term lang="ru">Временный каталог</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">临时文件夹</term>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This folder is used for temporary files: files created for temporary
          storage of working data, and then deleted within the same GIMP
          session. It does not require a lot of space or high performance. By
          default, a subdirectory called <filename>tmp</filename>
          in your personal GIMP directory is used, but if that disk is very
          cramped for space, or has serious performance issues, you can change
          it to a different directory. The directory must exist and be
          writable by you, or bad things will happen.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento adresář se používá pro dočasné soubory, tj. soubory, které se
          automaticky vytváří k dočasnému uložení pracovních dat a jsou
          smazány ještě během stejného pracovního sezení s Gimpem. Není k tomu
          zapotřebí mnoho prostoru ani vysoký výkon. Ve výchozím nastavení se
          k tomuto účelu používá podadresář <filename>tmp</filename>
          uživatelského GIMP adresáře. Pokud je však disk plný nebo trpí
          vážnými výkonnostními problémy, lze použít jiný adresář, na jiném
          disku. Zvolený adresář musí existovat a uživatel do něj musí mít
          právo k zápisu, jinak se budou dít velmi ošklivé věci.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der temporäre Ordner bewahrt Dateien auf, die nur während einer GIMP
          Sitzung gebraucht werden. Das geschieht zum Beispiel beim erstellen
          eines neuen Bildes. Die Voreinstellung benutzt das
          <filename>tmp</filename> Verzeichnis in ihrem persönlichen
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          Ordner. Wenn Sie ein anderes Verzeichnis wünschen, geben Sie einfach
          einen neuen Pfad fuer temporäre Dateien an.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Ce répertoire est utilisé pour les fichiers temporaires. Les
          fichiers temporaires sont créés pour travailler sur des données dans
          une session GIMP et ils sont supprimés au cours de la même session.
          Ce dossier ne nécessite pas beaucoup d'espace ni de très hautes
          performances. Par défaut, un sous-répertoire
          <filename>tmp</filename> de votre dossier personnel
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          est utilisé. Vous pouvez changer cet emplacement si l'espace
          contenant votre répertoire personnel est très restreint ou si
          l'accès à ce disque pose de graves problèmes de performance. Le
          répertoire temporaire doit exister et être accessible en écriture,
          sous peine de plantage.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Questa cartella viene usata per i file temporanei: file creati per
          memorizzazioni temporanee di dati di lavoro e cancellati durante la
          stessa sessione di lavoro di GIMP. Non richiede molto spazio o alta
          velocità. Il valore predefinito è la cartella
          <filename>tmp</filename>
          presente nella cartella personale di GIMP, ma se il disco è molto
          pieno o è molto lento, è consigliabile farla puntare a qualche altro
          dispositivo con caratteristiche migliori. La cartella deve esistere
          e essere scrivibile dall'utente o possono succedere problemi
          imprevisti.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Этот каталог используется для временных файлов, которые создаются
          для временного хранения рабочих данных, а по окончании сессии GIMP
          удаляются. Для этого не требуется много места или высокая
          производительность. По умолчанию используется поддиректория в вашем
          персональном каталоге под названием <filename>tmp</filename>,
          но если на этом диске мало места, или существуют серьезные
          проблемы с производительностью, вы можете сменить ее на другую
          директорию. Директория должна существовать и быть доступной для
          записи, иначе могут произойти неприятные вещи.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          临时文件使用该文件夹：临时文件被创建临时地保存工作数据，然后在同一
          个 GIMP 进程中被删除。默认是使用个人 GIMP 目录中的叫
          作 <filename>tmp</filename>的子目录，但当该磁盘空间有限或有严重的
          性能问题时，也可以改变为其它目录。该目录必须存在并且您有写的权限，
          否则后果严重。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Swap folder</term>
      <term lang="cs">Odkládací adresář</term>
      <term lang="de">Auslagerungsordner</term>
      <term lang="fr">Dossier d'échange</term>
      <term lang="it">Cartella di scambio</term>
      <term lang="ru">Каталог подкачки</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">交换文件夹</term>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This is the folder used as a "memory bank" when the total size of
          images and data open in GIMP exceeds the available RAM. If you work
          with very large images, or images with many layers, or have many
          images open at once, GIMP can potentially require hundreds of
          megabytes of swap space, so available disk space and performance are
          definitely things to think about for this folder. By default, it is
          set to your personal GIMP directory, but if you have another disk
          with more free space, or substantially better performance, you may
          see a significant benefit from moving your swap folder there. The
          directory must exist and be writable by you.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento adresář se používá jako virtuální paměť, pokud celková
          velikost obrázků a dat otevřených v GIMPu překročí velikost dostupné
          paměti RAM. Při práci s velmi velkými obrázky, obrázky s velkým
          množstvím vrstev nebo velkým množstvím obrázků může GIMP vyžadovat
          stovky megabytů odkládacího prostoru. Proto je při výběru
          odkládacího adresáře důležité zvážit dostupný diskový prostor a
          výkon disku. Ve výchozím nastavení je jako odkládací adresář
          používán uživatelský adresář Gimpu, pokud je ale k dispozici jiný
          disk s vyšším výkonem, může být výhodné na něj odkládací adresář
          přesunout. Adresář musí existovat a uživatel do něj musí mít právo k
          zápisu.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Auslagerungsordner wird benutzt um mehr Speicher zur Verfügung
          zu stellen, als Arbeitsspeicher(RAM) im Computer zur benutzbar ist.
          Wenn Sie mit sehr grossen oder ressourcenintensiven Bildern
          arbeiten, ist es nötig ungebrauchte Bildbestandteile in diesem
          Ordner auszulagern.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Ce dossier doit être considéré comme une
          <quote>réserve de mémoire</quote>.
          Il est utilisé lorsque la taille des données utilisées dans GIMP
          dépasse la quantité de RAM disponible. Si vous travaillez sur des
          images très grandes, ou sur des images contenant un nombre de
          calques important, ou bien avec beaucoup d'images à la fois, GIMP
          peut utiliser plusieurs centaines de Mo dans ce dossier: le dossier
          d'échange placé sur un disque avec beaucoup d'espace disponible ou
          dont les accès sont plus rapides améliorera sensiblement les
          performances de GIMP. Ce dossier doit exister et être accessible en
          écriture.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Questa è la cartella usata come "riserva di memoria" quando la
          dimensione delle immagini aperte in GIMP supera la dimensione della
          RAM disponibile. Se si lavora con immagini molto grandi, o con
          immagini con molti livello, oppure ci sono molte immagini aperte
          contemporaneamente, GIMP può potenzialmente richiedere centinaia di
          megabyte di memoria di scambio, per cui la disponibilità di spazio e
          la velocità del dispositivo usato per l'area di scambio sono dati
          importanti da considerare durante la scelta della posizione di
          questa cartella. Il valore predefinito è impostato sulla cartella
          personale di GIMP, ma se si possiede un dispositivo di
          memorizzazione con più spazio libero e più performante, può rendere
          il lavoro più veloce utilizzarlo. La cartella naturalmente deve
          esistere ed essere scrivibile dall'utente.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Этот каталог используется как "хранилище памяти", когда общий размер
          изображений и данных открытых в GIMP превышает размер доступной
          памяти. Если вы работаете с очень большими изображениями, или
          изображениями с множеством слоев, или держите открытыми множество
          изображений одновременно, потенциально GIMP требует сотни мегабайт
          подкачки. Поэтому такие вещи, как доступное дисковое пространство и
          производительность заставляют задуматься об этом каталоге. По
          умолчанию он должен находиться в вашем персональном каталоге GIMP,
          но если вы имеете другой диск с бОльшим количеством свободного места
          или лучшей производительностью, можете получить существенную выгоду
          переместив этот каталог туда. В любом случае, он должен существовать
          и быть доступным для записи.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          当 GIMP 打开的图像和数据的总大小超过可用的 RAM 时，该文件夹就被作
          为一个“内存仓库”来使用。在处理非常大的或有很多个图层的图像，以及同 时打开许多图像时，GIMP
          可能需要上百兆交换空间，所以要考虑该文件夹 所在磁盘的可用空间和性能。默认是使用个人 GIMP 目录，不过当有另一个
          有更多空闲空间或更好性能的磁盘，您会发现将交换文件夹移到那儿去会有 很明显的好处。该目录必须存在并且您有写的权限。
        </para>

        <warning lang="de">
          <para lang="de">
            Beide Pfadangaben zu Verzeichnissen sollten lesbar und gültig
            sein, da es sonst zum Absturz von <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            kommen kann.
          </para>
        </warning>

     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>
