<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-folders' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Folders</title>
  <title lang='de'>Ordner</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Dossiers</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">文件夹</title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>folders</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Ordner</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Dossiers</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>文件夹</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en;de;zh_CN'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-folders.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-folder.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Basic Folder Preferences
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Einstellungsdialog: Ordneransicht
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Préférences pour les dossiers généraux
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          基本文件夹首选项
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    This page allows you to set the locations for two important
    folders used by GIMP for temporary files.  The pages below it
    allow you to customize the locations searched for resources such
    as brushes etc.; see <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Data
    Folders</link> for a description that applies to them.  You 
    can change the folders here by editing the entries, or by pressing
    the buttons on the right to bring up a file chooser window.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Die Ordnervewaltung in den Einstellungen ermöglicht es ihnen Ordner
    für temporäre Daten anzupassen.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette page permet de choisir l'emplacement des dossiers destinés
    aux fichiers temporaires.
  </para>  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以在该页中设定 GIMP 中两个针对临时文件的重要文件夹的位置。下面这些页可以定制搜索资源的位置；请看<link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>数据文件夹</link>。这里，您可以通过编辑输入项或点击右边按钮并打开选择窗口来改变文件夹。
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title lang='en'>Folders</title>
    <title lang='de'>Ordner</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Dossiers</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">文件夹</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Temp folder</term>
      <term lang='de'>Temporärer Ordner</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Répertoire temporaire</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">临时文件夹</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          This folder is used for temporary files:  files created for
          temporary storage of working data, and then deleted within
          the same GIMP session.  It does not require a lot of space
          or high performance.  By default, a subdirectory called
          <filename>tmp</filename> in your personal GIMP directory is
          used, but if that disk is very cramped for space, or has
          serious performance issues, you can change it to a different
          directory.  The directory must exist and be writable by
          you, or bad things will happen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='de'>
        <para>
          Der temporäre Ordner bewahrt Dateien auf, die nur während
          einer GIMP Sitzung gebraucht werden. Das geschieht zum
          Beispiel beim erstellen eines neuen Bildes. Die
          Voreinstellung benutzt das <filename>tmp</filename>
          Verzeichnis in ihrem persönlichen <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
          Ordner. Wenn Sie ein anderes Verzeichnis wünschen, geben Sie
          einfach einen neuen Pfad fuer temporäre Dateien an.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Ce répertoire est utilisé pour les fichiers temporaires. Les fichiers
          temporaires sont créés pour travailler sur des données dans une
          session Gimp et ils sont supprimés au cours de la même session.
          Ce dossier ne nécessite pas beaucoup d'espace ni de très hautes
          performances. Par défaut, un sous-répertoire <filename>tmp</filename>
          de votre dossier personnel <acronym>Gimp</acronym> est utilisé.
          Vous pouvez changer cet emplacement si l'espace contenant votre
          répertoire personnel est très restreint ou si l'accès à ce
          disque pose de graves problèmes de performance. Le dossier
          choisi comme répertoire temporaire doit être accessible en écriture.
        </para>
      </listitem>      
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          临时文件使用该文件夹：临时文件被创建临时地保存工作数据，然后在同一个 GIMP 进程中被删除。默认是使用个人 GIMP 目录中的叫作 <filename>tmp</filename>的子目录，但当该磁盘空间有限或有严重的性能问题时，也可以改变为其它目录。该目录必须存在并且您有写的权限，否则后果严重。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Swap folder</term>
      <term lang='de'>Auslagerungsordner</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Dossier d'échange</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">交换文件夹</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          This is the folder used as a "memory bank" when the total
          size of images and data open in GIMP exceeds the available
          RAM.  If you work with very large images, or images with
          many layers, or have many images open at once, GIMP can
          potentially require hundreds of megabytes of swap space, so
          available disk space and performance are definitely things
          to think about for this folder.  By default, it is set to
          your personal GIMP directory, but if you have another disk
          with more free space, or substantially better performance,
          you may see a significant benefit from moving your swap
          folder there.  The directory must exist and be writable by
          you.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='de'>
        <para>
          Der Auslagerungsordner wird benutzt um mehr Speicher zur
          Verfügung zu stellen, als Arbeitsspeicher(RAM) im Computer zur
          benutzbar ist. Wenn Sie mit sehr grossen oder
          ressourcenintensiven Bildern arbeiten, ist es nötig
          ungebrauchte Bildbestandteile in diesem Ordner auszulagern.
        </para>
        <warning>
          <para>
            Beide Pfadangaben zu Verzeichnissen sollten lesbar und gültig
            sein, da es sonst zum Absturz von <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
            kommen kann.
          </para>
        </warning>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Ce dossier doit être considéré comme un "réserve de mémoire".
          Il est utilisé lorsque la taille des données utilisées dans
          Gimp dépasse la quantité de RAM disponible. Si vous travaillez
          sur des images très grandes, ou sur des images contenant un nombre
          de calques important, ou bien avec beaucoup d'images à la fois,
          GIMP peut utiliser plusieurs centaines de Mo dans ce dossier:
          le dossier d'échange placé sur un disque avec beaucoup d'espace
          disponible ou dont les accès sont plus rapides améliorera
          sensiblement les performances de Gimp. Le dossier
          choisi comme répertoire temporaire doit être accessible en écriture.
        </para>
      </listitem>      
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          当 GIMP 打开的图像和数据的总大小超过可用的 RAM 时，该文件夹就被作为一个“内存仓库”来使用。在处理非常大的或有很多个图层的图像，以及同时打开许多图像时，GIMP 可能需要上百兆交换空间，所以要考虑该文件夹所在磁盘的可用空间和性能。默认是使用个人 GIMP 目录，不过当有另一个有更多空闲空间或更好性能的磁盘，您会发现将交换文件夹移到那儿去会有很明显的好处。该目录必须存在并且您有写的权限。
        </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

</sect2>
