<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN'
         'http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd'>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-image-window-appearance' lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang='en'>Image Window Appearance</phrase>
    <phrase lang='cs'>Vzhled okna obrázku</phrase>
    <phrase lang='de'>Erscheinungsbild des Bildfensters</phrase>
    <phrase lang='fr'>Apparence de la fenêtre d'images</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">图像窗口外观</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Image Windows</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='cs'>
    <primary>dialogy</primary>
    <secondary>předvolby</secondary>
    <tertiary>okna obrázku</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Bildfenster</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Fenêtres d'images</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>图像窗口</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang='en'>
        Image Window Appearance Defaults
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang='cs'>
        Výchozí nastavení předvoleb Vzhled okna obrázku
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang='de'>
        Die Einstellungsansicht zum Anpassen des Bildfensters
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang='fr'>
        Préférences pour l'apparence des fenêtres d'image
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">
        图像窗口默认外观
      </phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-image-window-appearance.png'
          format="PNG" lang="cs;de;en" scalefit="1" />
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-image-window-appearance.png'
          format="PNG" lang="fr" scalefit="1" />
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/zh_CN/prefs-image-window-appearance.png'
          format="PNG" lang="zh_CN" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          This page lets you customize the default appearance of image
          windows, for normal mode and for fullscreen mode.  All of the
          settings here can be altered on an image-specific basis using
          entries in the View menu.  See the <link
          linkend='gimp-concepts-image-window'> Image Window </link>
          section for information on the meaning of the entries.
        </para>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Tato karta předvoleb umožňuje nastavit výchozí vzhled oken
          obrázku, zvlášť pro normální a pro celoobrazovkový režim.
          Všechny zde nastavené hodnoty lze přenastavit pro každé okno
          obrázku individuálně příkazy z nabídky Zobrazení. Více
          informací o významu jednotlivých položek naleznete v části
          <link linkend='gimp-concepts-image-window'>Okno
          obrázku</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          In dieser Ansicht können Sie die Vorgabeeinstellungen des
          Bildfensters anpassen (Vollbild oder normales Fenster).
          Zusätzlich lassen sich Einstellungen für ein spezifisches
          Bildfenster im <link
          linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>Ansichtmenü</link>
          verändern.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Cette page permet de définir l'apparence par défaut pour les
          fenêtres d'images, qu'elles soient en mode Normal ou en mode
          Plein écran.  Ces paramètres peuvent être changés pour une
          image donnée en utilisant les entrées du menu <link
          linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>Affichage</link>.
        </para>  
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          您可以在该页中定制图像窗口在普通和全屏模式下的默认外观，在对特定图像时，这里所有的选项可以在查看菜单中修改。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>


  <para lang='en'>
    The only parts that may need further explanation are the ones
    related to padding.  "Padding" is the color shown around the edges
    of the image, if it does not occupy all of the display area (shown
    in light gray in all the figures here).  You can choose among four
    colors for the padding color:  to use the color specified by the
    current theme; to use the light or dark colors specified for
    checks, such as represent transparent parts of the image; or to
    use a custom color, which can be set using the color button for
    "Custom padding color".
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Jediné, co může vyžadovat další vysvětlení, jsou položky související s
    doplňováním plátna. Doplňování se týká oblasti okolo obrázku, pokud
    obrázek nevyplňuje celou zobrazovací oblast (na snímcích obrazovky
    v této příručce je světle šedá). Pro barvu dopňování existují čtyři možné
    volby: použití barvy určené aktivním tématem; použítí světlé nebo tmavé
    barvu šachovnice určené pro znázorňování průhlednosti a konečně použití
    vlastní barvy, nastavené v položce <guilabel>Vlastní barva
    doplňování</guilabel>.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Die wohl einzigen Einstellungen die einer Erklärung bedürfen sind
    die Einstellungen der Rahmenfarbe. Die Rahmenfarbe ist der
    (Hintergrund-)Bereich des aktiven Bildes<footnote>
      <para>
        Das aktive Bild bezeichnet hier den Bereich des Bildfensters,
        auf den Bildoperationen und Werkzeuge angewendet werden können um
        das eigentliche Bild zu verändern.
      </para>
    </footnote>. Für die Rahmenfarbe stehen ihnen vier verschiedene
    Optionen zur Verfügung. Letztere läßt ihnen eine eigene Farbe für
    die Rahmenfarbe einstellen.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Seules les options liées au remplissage ne peuvent pas être appliquées
    à une image donnée. La couleur de remplissage est utilisée pour
    combler les zones autour de l'image. Quatre modes de remplissage sont
    disponibles: utilisation de la couleur spécifiée par le thème,
    utilisation de la couleur claire ou de la couleur sombre du damier
    symbolisant la transparence, ou utilisation d'une couleur personnalisée
    définie par "Couleur de remplissage personnalisée".
  </para>  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    唯一需要解释部分就是“衬垫”，它是在图像边缘外面显示的颜色，假如图像没占据整个显示区域您能看到。衬垫有四种颜色可供选择：使用当前主题中指定的颜色；使用方格中指定的浅色或深色；使用自定义颜色，然后用下面的“自定义画布衬垫颜色”来指定。
  </para>
</sect2>
