<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-interface'>
  <title lang='en'>Interface</title>
  <title lang='de'>Benutzeroberfläche</title>
  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>interface</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Benutzeroberfläche</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary></primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-interface.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='de'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-interface.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-interface.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        Assorted Interface Preferences
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>  

  <para lang='de'>
    Verändern Sie das Verhalten von Dialogen oder Menüs in dieser
    Einstellungsansicht. 
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you customize several assorted aspects of the user
    interface; they are something of a hodgepodge.
  </para>

  
  <simplesect>
  <variablelist>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Previews</term>
      <term lang="de">Vorschaubilder</term>
      <term lang="fr"/>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Durch das standardmässig aktivierte Kontrollkästchen unter
          <guilabel><accel>V</accel>orschau von Ebenen und Kanälen
          aktivieren</guilabel> werden im <link
          linkend='gimp-layer-dialog'>Ebenen</link>- und<link
          linkend='gimp-channel-dialog'>Kanaldialog</link> automatisch
          Miniaturbilder angezeigt.
        </para>
        <para>
          Sie können die Standardgrösse der
          Miniaturbilder in Dialogen vorbestimmen. Wählen Sie eine
          Grössenordnung zwischen <guilabel>Winzig</guilabel> und
          <guilabel>Gigantisch</guilabel>.  
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          By default, GIMP shows miniature previews of the contents of
          layers and channels in several places, including the Layers
          dialog.  If for some reason you would prefer to disable
          these, you can do it by unchecking "Enable layer and channel
          previews".  If you do want previews to be shown, you can
          customize their sizes using the menus for "Default layer and
          channel preview size" and "Navigation preview size".
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='de'>Tastenkürzel</term>
      <term lang='en'>Keyboard Shortcuts</term>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Aktivieren Sie das Kontrollkästchen um Tastaturkürzel in Menüs
          dynamisch zuordnen zu können. 
        </para>
        <para>
          Wählen Sie mit der Maus einen Menüpunkt, dem Sie einen neuen
          Tastaturkürzel zuordnen möchten; klicken dabei aber nicht den
          Menüpunkt an.  Durch betätigen der Tasten Ihres
          Tastaturkürzels weisen Sie einen neuen Tastaturkürzel dem
          Menüpunkt zu.
        </para>
        <note>
          Nachdem Sie neue Tastaturkürzel zugeordnet haben, werden die
          GIMP eigenen Standardtastaturkürzel überschrieben.
        </note>
        <!-- wie auf standardtastaturkürzel zurücksetzen? -->
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          Any menu item can be activated by holding down 
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> and pressing a sequence of keys.
          Normally, the key associated with each menu entry is shown
          as an underlined letter in the text.  If for some reason you
          would prefer the underlines to go away (maybe because you
          think they're ugly and you don't use them anyway), then you
          can make this happen by unchecking "Show menu mnemonics".
        </para>
        <para>
          GIMP can give you the ability to create keyboard shortcuts
          (key combinations that activate a menu entry) dynamically,
          by pressing the keys while the pointer hovers over the
          desired menu entry.  However, this capability is disabled by
          default, because it might lead novice users to accidentally
          overwrite the standard keyboard shortcuts.  If you want to
          enable it, check "Use dynamics keyboard shortcuts" here.
        </para>
        <para>
          Pressing the button for "Configure Keyboard Shortcuts"
          brings up the Shortcut Editor, which gives you a graphical
          interface to select menu items and assign shortcuts to them.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you change shortcuts, you will probably want your changes
          to continue to apply in future GIMP sessions.  If not,
          uncheck "Save keyboard shortcuts on exit".  But remember
          that you have done this, or you may be frustrated later.  If
          you don't want to save shortcuts on exit every session, you
          can save the current settings at any time using the "Save
          Keyborad Shortcuts Now" button, and they will be applied to
          future sessions.  If you decide that you have made some bad
          decisions concerning shortcuts, you can reset them to their
          original state by pressing "Reset Saved Keyboard Shortcuts
          to Default Values".
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='de'>Verhalten von Dialoge</term>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Bei aktiviertem Kontrollkästchen, wird für jedes Bildfenster
          ein seperates Fenster zum Anzeigen Informationen verwendet. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='de'>Menüs</term>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Bei aktiviertem Kontrollkästchen, erscheint bei jedem
          Menüeintrag des Bildmenüs im oberen Menübereich eine
          Trennlinie. Mit Hilfe dieser Trennlinie können Sie die Menüs
          trennen und als normale Fenster behandeln. Das bietet Ihnen
          die Möglichkeit, oft benutzte Funktionen immer angezeigt zu
          lassen.
        </para>
        <note>
          Abreißbare Menüs stehen ihnen nur im Bildmenü zur Verfügung.
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='de'>Größe des zuletzt geöffnet-Menüs</term>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Bestimmen Sie die Anzahl der Einträge, die im Menü der zuletzt
          geöffneten Dokumente erscheinen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='de'>Wählen Sie ein Thema</term>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          GIMP bietet Ihnen die Möglichkeit, zwischen zwei
          Standardthemen zu wählen. Standardmässig benutzt
          <acronym>Gimp</acronym> das Standard-Theme (Default) mit
          grossen Icons.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </simplesect>
</sect2>
