<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-theme'>
  <title lang='en'>Theme</title>
  <title lang='de'>Thema</title>
  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>theme</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Thema</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='de'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-theme.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        Theme Preference
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>  

  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you select a theme, which determines many aspects
    of the appearance of the GIMP user interface, including the set of
    icons used, their sizes, fonts and their sizes, spacing alloted in
    dialogs, etc.  Two themes are supplied with GIMP: "Default", which
    is probably best for most people, and "Small", which may be
    preferable for those with small or low-resolution monitors.
    Clicking on a theme in the list causes it to be applied
    immediately, so it is easy to see the results and change your mind
    if you don't like them.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You can also use custom themes, either by downloading them from
    the net, or by copying one of the supplied themes and modifying
    it.  Custom themes should be places in the
    <filename>themes</filename> subdirectory of your personal GIMP
    directory:  if 
    they are, they will appear in the list here.  Each theme is
    actually a directory containing ASCII files that you can edit.
    They are pretty complicated, and the meaning of the contents goes
    beyond the scope of this documentation, but you should feel free
    to experiment:  in the worst case, if you mess things up
    completely, you can always revert back to one of the supplied
    themes.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You cannot edit the supplied themes unless you have administrator
    permissions, and even if you do, you shouldn't:  if you want to
    customize a theme, make a copy in your personal directory and work
    on it.  If you make a change and would like to see the result "on
    the fly", you can do so by saving the edited theme file and then
    pressing "Reload Current Theme".
  </para>
  
  <para lang='de'>
    GIMP bietet Ihnen die Möglichkeit, zwischen zwei
    Standardthemen zu wählen. Standardmässig benutzt
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> das Standard-Theme (Default) mit
    grossen Icons.
  </para>
</sect2>
