<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-help' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Help System</title>
  <title lang='de'>Hilesystem</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Système d'aide</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">帮助系统</title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Help System</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Hilfesystem</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Système d'aide</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>帮助系统</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en;zh_CN'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-help.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='de'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-help.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-help.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Help System Preferences
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Préférences du système d'aide
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          帮助系统首选项
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>  

  <para lang='de'>
    Diese Ansicht lässt Sie das Verhalten und den Gebrauch der
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> Hilfe verändern.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you customize the behaviour of the
    <acronym>gimp</acronym> help system.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette page permet de modifier le comportement du système d'aide
    de <acronym>gimp</acronym>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以在这页定制 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 帮助系统的行为。
  </para>

  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">General</title>
      <title lang="de">Allgemein</title>
      <title lang="fr">Général</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">常规</title>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Show tool tips</term>
        <term lang="de">
          <guilabel>Minihilfen anzeigen</guilabel>
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">
          Afficher les <guilabel><accel>b</accel>ulles d'aide</guilabel>
        </term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">显示工具提示</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Bei aktiviertem Kontrollkästchen, werden Ihnen Minihilfen
            (sog. Tooltips) angezeigt. Bewegen sie den Mauszeiger über
            Bedienelemente von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> und warten wenige
            Sekunden um Minihilfen zu sehen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Tool tips are small text bubbles that appear when the
            pointer hovers for a moment over some element of the
            interface, such as a button or icon.  Sometimes they explain
            what the element does; sometimes they give you hints about
            non-obvious ways to use it.  If you find them too
            distracting, you can disable them here by unchecking this
            option.  We recommend that you leave them enabled unless you
            are a very advanced user.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            Les bulles d'aide sont de petits textes qui lorsque pointeur de
            la souris reste un moment au dessus d'un élément de l'interface.
            Les éléments concernés sont les boutons ou les icones. Les bulles
            d'aide explique la fonction de l'élément ou bien elles donnent des
            astuces sur une utilisation non triviale. Si les bulles d'aide vous
            dérangent, vous pouvez les désactiver avec cette option. Toutefois,
            il est recommandé de les laisser actives sauf si vous êtes un
            utilisateur très expérimenté.
          </para>
        </listitem>         
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            工具提示是当光标在界面一些组件上(比如按钮或图标)停留片刻显示的悬浮文字，有点是解释该组件如何使用，有的是给您该组件不很明显的使用方法的提示。如果觉得它们让您感到烦恼，可以不要勾选该选项。我们推荐让它一直开启除非您是个非常高级的用户。
          </para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry> <!--Changed fr 2004-10-31 -->
        <term lang='en'>[GIMP 2.0] "F1" shows context-dependent help</term>
        <term lang='de'>"F1" zeigt kontextabhängige Hilfe
        an</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Afficher les boutons d'Aide</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">“F1”弹出上下文帮助</term>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            In GIMP 2.0, this options controls whether pressing the "F1" key
            will evoke Help information for the object in which the mouse
            pointer is currently located.  GIMP 2.2 no longer gives you the
            ability to disable this function.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Es wird Ihnen bei drücken der
            F1-Taste eine Hilfe angezeigt. Die angezeigte Hilfe richtet
            sich nach dem Bedienelement, über dem sich der Mauszeiger bei
            aktivieren der Hilfe, befindet.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            Chaque dialogue affiche un bouton d'aide lorsque cette option est
            cochée. Eb cliquant sur ce bouton d'aide, la page correspondant 
            au dialogue s'affichera dans le navigateur d'aide. 
            L'autre façon d'accéder de façon contextuelle aux
            pages d'aide est la traditionnelle touche «F1»
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            FIXME
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Show tips on startup</term>
        <term lang='de'>Tipps beim Start anzeigen</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Afficher les astuces au démarrage</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">启动时显示提示</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Bei jedem Start von <acronym>Gimp</acronym> wird ihnen in
            einem Dialog, ein Tipp über die Benutzung von
            <acronym>Gimp</acronym> angezeigt.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Startup tips are helpful hints that appear each time you
            start GIMP.  You can switch them on or off here.  If you
            have switched them off by unchecking "Show tip next time
            GIMP starts" in the tip window, you can switch them back on
            by checking here.  Whatever you decide to do, at some point
            you should take the time to go through the list of tips:
            they are considered to be very useful, and the things they
            tell you are not easy to discover by experimenting.  If you
            prefer, you can read them at any time by choosing
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Tip of the Day</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            in the Toolbox menu.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            A chaque démarrage, <acronym>Gimp</acronym> ouvre une fenêtre
            proposant l'astuce du jour. Cette option désactice l'affichage
            de l'astuce au démarrage.
            Vous pouvez consultez les astuces du jour à tout moment dans le menu
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Aide</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Conseil du jour</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            de la Boîte à outils.
          </para>
        </listitem>  
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            启动提示是每次 GIMP 启动时显示的帮助提示，可以这里打开或关闭它，不过我们建议您花点时间看看这些提示：它们是常常非常有用的，而且其中所讲的在实践中也不容易发现。您可以在任何时候，在工具箱菜单中
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>帮助</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>每日提示</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>来阅读它们。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>Help Browser</title>
      <title lang='de'>Hilfe-Browser</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Navigateur d'aide</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">帮助浏览器</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Help browser to use</term>
        <term lang='de'>Zu verwendender Hilfe-Browser</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Navigateur d'aide à utiliser</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">要使用的帮助浏览器</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Wählen Sie als Anzeigeprogramm zwischen den
            Gimp internen Hilfebrowser oder den Web
            Browser, den sie nachfolgend einstellen können.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
	            Es wird empfohlen, den internen Hilfe-Browser zu verwenden.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            GIMP Help is supplied in the form of HTML files, i. e.,
            web pages.  You can view them using either a special help
            browser that comes with GIMP, or a web browser of your
            choice.  Here you choose which option to use.  Because the
            help pages were carefully checked to make sure they work
            well with GIMP's browser, whereas other web browsers are
            somewhat variable in their support of features, the safer
            option is to use the internal browser; but really any
            modern web browser should be okay.
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
           Choisissez ici le navigateur utilisé pour l'aide de Gimp.
           L'aide de Gimp est fournie sous forme de pages HTML, donc
           similaires aux pages Web. Elles peuvent être visualisées à
           partir d'un navigateur interne à Gimp ou bien à partir de
           n'importe quel navigateur moderne. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
         <para>
           GIMP 帮助是以 HTML 文件的形式提供，您可以使用 GIMP 带的一个特殊浏览器或 Web 浏览器来查看它们。这里即是选择要使用哪个选项。由于帮助页都被仔细检查过能很好地与 GIMP 浏览器工作，而其它 Web 浏览器支持的特性则或多或少有所不同，所以最安全的选项还是使用内部浏览器；不过实际上任何现代 Web 浏览器都能工作地比较好。
         </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang='en'>Web Browser</title>
      <title lang='de'>Webbrowser</title>
      <title lang='fr'>Navigateur Web</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">Web 浏览器</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Web browser to use</term>
        <term lang='de'>Zu verwendender Hilfe-Browser</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Navigateur web à utiliser</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">要使用的 Web 浏览器</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Wählen Sie einen Webbrowser, der die Hilfeseiten anzeigen
            soll.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              Vergessen Sie den optionalen Parameter "%s" nicht.
              <acronym>Gimp</acronym> ist ohne diesen Parameter nicht in
              der Lage dem Webbrowser mitzuteilen, welche Hilfeseite
              angezeigt werden soll.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            If you selected "Internal" for the Help browser, this
            option has no effect.  If you selected "Web browser", you
            can decide here which browser to use, and how to invoke
            it, by entering the command that will be used to run the
            browser.  The button to the right brings up a file
            selector, which you can use to locate the executable file
            for the browser if you like, but in most cases it is
            probably easier to enter a command by hand.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              The command should look something like "mozilla %s".  If you
              leave out the "%s", then the browser will open with your
              default starting page rather than the desired help page, so
              don't do that.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            Si vous avez séléctionné "Navigateur Web" pour visualiser l'aide
            de Gimp, il vous faut spécifier la commande pour lancer ce
            navigateur externe. Le bouton à droite permet d'utiliser un
            sélecteur de fichiers pour choisir l'exécutable. Vous pouvez
            aussi taper la commande directement dans le champ.
            Cette option n'a aucune influence si vous avez choisi le
            navigateur interne pour le système d'aide.
          </para>
          <note>
            La commande doit ressembler à quelque chose comme "mozilla %s".
            Si vous oubliez le "%s", votre navigateur va démarrer avec sa
            page d'accueil par défaut.
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            当您在上面选择内部浏览器时，该选项无效。而选择“Web 浏览器”时，这里就可以输入启动该浏览器的命令和参数，右边的按钮会唤出一个文件选择器，来定位您所喜欢的浏览器执行文件，大多数情况下，直接输入命名可能更方便。
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
	      命令看上去是“mozilla %s”这种形式,如果没有“%s”，浏览器会打开它自己的默认起始页，而不是想要的帮助页，因此不要忘了“%s”。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
