<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history
  2006-11-01 lexa: made the file docbook compliant
  2006-08-04: added italian translation by ciampix
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-dialog" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Preferences Dialog</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Předvolby</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Einstellungen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Preferencias</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Préférences</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Finestra preferenze</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Voorkeursinstellingen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Brukarinnstillingar</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Настройка</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">首选项</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>dialogy</primary>
    <secondary>Předvolby</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Dialog</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Diálogos</primary>
    <secondary>Preferencias</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Dialogues</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>Dialogen</primary>
    <secondary>Voorkeursinstellingen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Finestra</primary>
    <secondary>Preferenze</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Dialogar</primary>
    <secondary>Brukarinnstillingar</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Диалоги</primary>
    <secondary>Настройка</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>Preferences</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Předvolby</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Einstellungen</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Preferencias</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Préférences</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Preferenze</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>Voorkeursinstellingen</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Brukarinnstillingar</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Настройка</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>首选项</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Introduction</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Úvod</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Einführung</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Introducción</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Introduction</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Introduzione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">inleiding</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innleiing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Введение</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">概述</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang='en'>List of preference pages</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Seznam stránek předvoleb</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Die Liste der verschiedenen Einstellungsansichten
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Listado de páginas de preferencias</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Liste des préférences</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Elenco delle pagine delle preferenze</phrase>
        <phrase lang="nl">Lijst van voorkeurbladen</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Liste over dei ulike innstillingane</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Список страниц диалога настройки</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">首选项页列表</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang='cs;en;es'>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-list.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-list.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/fr/prefs-list.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/it/prefs-list.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="nl">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/nl/prefs-list.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/no/prefs-list.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/preferences/ru/prefs-list.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/zh_CN/prefs-list.png'
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      The preferences dialog can be accessed from the Toolbox menu, as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>references</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      It lets you customize many aspects of the way
      GIMP works.  The following sections detail the settings that you
      can customize, and what they affect.  This information applies
      specifically to GIMP 2.2, but the settings for GIMP 2.0 are
      similar enough that you should be able to understand them
      based on the explanations here.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Dialog s předvolbami je přístupný z nabídky Panelu nástrojů volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Předvolby</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Umožňuje nastavit mnoho různých aspektů Gimpu. Následující části
      popisují, jaká nastavení jsou k dispozici a co ovlivňují. Informace
      jsou určeny pro GIMP 2.2, ale nastavení v Gimpu 2.0 jsou podobná.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Im Einstellungsdialog können Sie <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in vielerlei
      Hinsicht Ihren Wünschen anpassen.  Der Dialog kann nur im
      Werkzeugfenster erreicht werden:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>instellungen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Se puede acceder al diálogo de preferencias desde el menú de la
      caja de herramientas, mediante
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Archivo</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>referencias</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.  Permite personalizar muchos aspectos del
        comportamiento del GIMP.  Las siguientes secciones detallan
        las opciones que puedes personalizar, y qué elementos afectan.
        Esta información se aplica específicamente a GIMP 2.2, pero
        las opciones de GIMP 2.0 son bastante similares, y puede
        entenderlas basándose en las explicaciones que se encuentran
        aquí.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Le dialogue des préférences est accessible à partir du menu de la
      boîte à outils sous
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ichier</guimenu>
        <guimenu><accel>P</accel>références</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>.
      Il permet de modifier une grande partie du comportement de GIMP.
      Chacune des sections suivantes détaille les options que vous pouvez
      modifier. Ces informations sont relatives à GIMP 2.2 mais les options
      de GIMP 2.0 sont suffisamment similaires pour que vous vous y
      retrouviez facilement.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      La finestra delle preferenze è accessibile dal menu degli strumenti
      facendo
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>referenze</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.  Essa permette di personalizzare molte impostazioni di
      lavoro di GIMP.  Le seguenti sezioni descriveranno in dettaglio le
      impostazioni personalizzabili e ciò che vanno a modificare. Queste
      informazioni sono specifiche di GIMP 2.2, ma le impostazioni per GIMP
      2.0 sono abbastanza simili da poter considerare questa sezione
      abbastanza utile anche per la vecchia versione.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Het voorkeuren dialoogvenster kan geopend worden vanuit het menu
      boven het gereedschapsvenster met:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>B</accel>estand</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>V</accel>oorkeuren</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Hierin kunt u vele opties waarmee <acronym>GIMP</acronym> werkt
      instellen. De volgende hoofdstukken vertellen in meer detail welke
      instellingen u kunt wijzigen en wat de gevolgen daarvan zijn.  De
      informatie is gebaseerd op de werking van
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.2; versie 2.0 lijkt zodanig veel op deze
      versie dat deze uitleg u ook veel over de situatie daar kan
      verduidelijken.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Dialogane for brukarinnstillingane er tilgjengeleg frå verktøykassa via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Innstillingar</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Desse dialogane blir brukte for å tilpassa
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> etter personleg behov. Nedanfor finn du
      ein omtale av dei ulike innstillingane, kva dei gjer og korleis du
      kan tilpassa desse til eigne ønskje. Informasjonen er sett opp for
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2, men det skulle ikkje vere noe
      problem å tilpassa dette for andre utgåver av
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Диалог настройки доступен через меню панели инструментов:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Файл</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>Н</accel>астройка</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      С его помощью можно настроить множество параметров
      GIMP. В данном разделе подробно описываются настройки GIMP,
      а так же то, на что они влияют. Эта информация относится, в основном,
      к GIMP 2.2, однако настройки GIMP 2.0 достаточно схожи, поэтому
      понять общие принципы будет несложно.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      从工具箱菜单中
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>首选项</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      开启首选项对话框，它让您定制影响 GIMP 工作方式的很多方面。下面章节详细
      介绍您能定制的选项，以及它们的作用，这些内容是针对 GIMP 2.2，不过对
      GIMP 2.0 也大同小异。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      All of the Preferences information is stored in a file called
      <filename>gimprc</filename>  in your personal GIMP directory, so
      if you are a <quote>power user</quote> who would rather work with a
      text editor than a graphical interface, you can alter preferences by
      editing that file.  If you do, and you are on a Linux system,
      then <command>man gimprc</command> will give you a lot of
      technical information about the contents of the file and what
      they are used for.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Všechny předvolby jsou ukládány do souboru <filename>gimprc</filename>
      v uživatelském osobním GIMP adresáři. Jeho editací tak může pokročilý
      uživatel upřednostňující textové konfigurační soubory nastavovat vše
      ručně a přímo. Pokud pracujete na Linuxu (a doufáme, že ano), získáte
      technické informace o obsahu tohoto souboru příkazem
      <command>man gimprc</command>.
    </para>
    <note lang="de">
      <para lang="de">
        Die Informationen bezüglich der gewählten Einstellungen wird in der
        Datei <filename>gimprc</filename> in Ihrem persönlichen
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Verzeichnis gespeichert. Falls Sie also damit
        vertraut sind, Konfigurationsdateien mit einem Editor zu bearbeiten,
        können Sie Ihre Einstellungen einfach durch Editieren dieser Datei
        ändern. Unter Linux gibt Ihnen <command>man gimprc</command> das
        nötige Wissen um Aufbau der Datei und Bedeutung und Syntax der
        einzelnen Optionen.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para lang="es">
      Toda la información de preferencias se conserva en un archivo
      llamado <filename>gimprc</filename> que se encuentra en su
      directorio personal del GIMP.  Así que si Ud. es un
      <quote>superusuario</quote>, que prefiere trabajar con un editor
      de textos en lugar de una interfaz gráfica, puede alterar las
      preferencias editando el archivo.  Si lo hace, y se encuentra en
      un sistema Linux, el comando <command>man gimprc</command>
      proporciona una gran cantidad de información técnica sobre los
      contenidos del archivo, y para qué se utilizan.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Toutes les préférences sont enregistrées dans le fichier
      <filename>gimprc</filename> de votre répertoire GIMP personnel :
      si vous êtes un <quote>utilisateur avancé</quote> préférant les
      éditeurs de
      texte aux interfaces graphiques, vous pouvez changer vos préférences
      en éditant ce fichier. Si vous êtes dans ce cas et que vous
      travaillez sous Linux, la commande <command>man gimprc</command>
      vous donnera des informations sur le contenu de ce fichier.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Tutte le informazioni sulle preferenze sono memorizzate in un file di
      nome <filename>gimprc</filename> presente nella cartella personale di
      GIMP, perciò se siete un cosiddetto <quote>power user</quote> o
      utente esperto, uno di quelli che si trova più a suo agio con un
      editor di testo che con un'interfaccia grafica, potete alterare le
      preferenze direttamente modificando questo file. Se lo fate, e state
      lavorando su un sistema Linux, allora il comando <command>man
      gimprc</command> potrà fornire molte informazioni tecniche sui
      contenuti del file e sul loro significato.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Alle voorkeursinstellingen zijn in het bestand genaamd
      <filename>gimprc</filename> in uw eigen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      werkmap opgeslagen. Als u dus een Gevorderde gebruiker bent en liever
      met een tekstscherm werkt dan met een grafisch bedieningspaneel kunt
      u de voorkeuren in dat bestand wijzigen. Meer informatie hierover
      kunt u op <acronym>Linux</acronym>-systemen met behulp van het
      het commando <command>man gimprc</command> opvragen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      All informasjonen om desse dialogane blir lagra i fila
      <filename>gimprc</filename> i den private
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-katalogen din. Dersom du er oppsett som
      <quote>administrator</quote> på maskinen din, kan du også redigere
      denne fila ved hjelp av ein tekstbehandlar. Dersom du gjer dette, og
      arbeider i Linux, vil du finne mykje teknisk informasjon om innhaldet
      i denne fila og kva dei ulike innslaga står for i kommandoen
      <command>man gimprc</command>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Вся информация о настройках хранится в файле под названием
      <filename>gimprc</filename>, находящемся  в вашем персональном
      каталоге GIMP. Если вы "продвинутый пользователь",  и предпочитаете
      работать с текстовым файлом, а не с графическим интерфейсом, то
      изменяйте параметры GIMP  редактируя этот файл. Если вы работаете в
      системе Linux, то с помощью команды
      <command>man gimprc</command> вы сможете получить исчерпывающую
      информацию о содержимом файла настройки.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      所有的首选项信息都保存在您个人 GIMP 文件夹
      的 <filename>gimprc</filename> 文件中，如果您是一个喜欢有文本编辑胜于
      图像界面的“power user”，就可以通过编辑该文件来改变首选项，假如在
      Linux 系统中，使用 <command>man gimprc</command>来获取更详细的信息。
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <xi:include href="prefs-environment.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-interface.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-theme.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-help.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-tool-options.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-toolbox.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-default-image.xml" /> <!-- was: prefs-new-image.xml -->
  <xi:include href="prefs-default-grid.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-image-window.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-image-window-appearance.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-image-window-title.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-display.xml" />
  <!--TODO all:  xi:include href="prefs-color-management.xml" /-->
  <xi:include href="prefs-input-devices.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-input-controllers.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-window-management.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-folders.xml" />
  <xi:include href="prefs-folders-data.xml" />
</sect2>
