<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-environment' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Environment</title>
  <title lang='de'>Umgebung</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Environnement</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">环境</title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>environment</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Umgebung</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Environnement</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>环境</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role='html'>
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-environment.png'
          format="PNG" lang='en;zh_CN' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-environment.png'
          format="PNG" lang='de' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-environment.png'
          format="PNG" lang='fr' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role='tex'>
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-environment.png'
          format="PNG" lang='en;zh_CN' scalefit='1' width='14cm' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-environment.png'
          format="PNG" lang='de' scalefit='1' width='14cm' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-environment.png'
          format="PNG" lang='fr' scalefit='1' width='14cm' />
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        Environment Preferences
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        Die Einstellungsansicht für die GIMP Umgebung.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        Préférences pour l'environnement
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        环境首选项
      </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='de'>
    Beeinflussen Sie den Ressourcenverbrauch, sowie das Verhalten beim
    Speichern von Dateien von GIMP in dieser
    Einstellungsansicht.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you customize the amount of system memory allocated
    for various purposes.  It also allows you to disable the
    confirmation dialogs that appear when you close unsaved images,
    and to set the size of thumbnail files that GIMP produces.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette page permet de configurer la quantité de ressources utilisée par
    Gimp. Elle permet aussi de désactiver la demande de confirmation, qui
    apparaît lorsque qu'une image non sauvegardée est fermée. Enfin, elle
    permet de choisir la taille des vignettes générées par GIMP.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以通过该页定制进行多种操作的系统内存数量，还可以在关闭未保存图像时让它不出现确认对话框，以及设置 GIMP 生成的缩略图文件的大小。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">Resource Consumption</title>
      <title lang="de">Ressourcenverbrauch</title>
      <title lang="fr">Configuration des ressources</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">资源消耗</title>
   
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Minimal number of undo levels</term>
        <term lang="de">Minimale Anzahl an Schritten</term>
        <term lang="fr">Nombre minimal de niveaux d'annulation</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">最小撤消次数</term>
  
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            GIMP allows you to undo most actions by maintaining an "Undo
            History" for each image, for which a certain amount of
            memory is allocated.  Regardless of memory usage, however,
            GIMP always permits some minimal number of the most recent
            actions to be undone:  this is the number specified here.
            See <link linkend='gimp-concepts-undo'>Undoing</link> for more
            information about GIMP's Undo mechanism.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Verändern sie wie oft sie Operationen rückgängig machen
            möchten.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Ce nombre indique le nombre minimum d'opérations qui pourront être
            annulées. Tant que la taille limite de la mémoire d'annulation n'est
            pas atteinte, des opérations supplémentaires seront conservées dans
            l'Historique d'annulation.
          </para>
      
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            您可以通过每个图像的“撤消历史”来撤消 GIMP 中大部分操作，当然要分配一定的内存给它。尽管如此，GIMP 常常会有一个让撤消最近操作的最小次数，而不管内存的使用量：这里设定的值就是这个意思。请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-undo'>撤消</link>来获取更多有关 GIMP 撤消机制的信息。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Maximum undo memory</term>
        <term lang='de'>Maximaler Speicher für Rückgängigmachung</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Mémoire maximale pour l'annulation</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">最大撤消内存</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This is the amount of undo memory allocated for each image.
            If the Undo History size exceeds this, the oldest points are
            deleted, unless this would result in fewer points being
            present than the minimal number specified above.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Beeinflussen sie die Bereitstellung von Speicher, um die
            <guilabel>Minimale Anzahl an Schritten</guilabel> rückgängig
            zu machen.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Ce nombre fixe la limite supérieure de la mémoire utilisée par
            l'image pour conserver les opérations de la pile d'annulation.
            Toutefois, une image conservera toujours un minimum d'opérations
            dans sa pile d'annulation (voir option ci-dessus).
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
          这是分配给每个图像的撤消内存数量，当撤消历史大小操过该值，最旧的记录点将被删除，除非记录数比上面所提到的最小值还要少。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Tile cache size</term>
        <term lang='de'>Größe des Datenspeichers</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Taille du cache d'image</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">平铺缓存大小</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This is the amount of system RAM allocated for GIMP image
            data.  If GIMP requires more memory than this, it begins to
            swap to disk, which may in some circumstances cause a
            dramatic slowdown.  You are given an opportunity to set this
            number when you install GIMP, but you can alter it here. See
            <link linkend='gimp-using-setup-tile-cache'>How to Set Your
            Tile Cache</link> for more information.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Beeinflussen sie die Größe des Speichers, welcher für ein
            geladenes Bild zur Verfügung steht.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            C'est la quantité de mémoire dans le système que Gimp réservera
            pour les images. Si Gimp demande plus de mémoire que cette valeur,
            il commencera à utiliser un cache sur disque, ce qui peut provoquer
            un ralentissement de l'application. Vous pouvez changer ici la valeur
            que Gimp réservera en mémoire pour les images.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这是分配给 GIMP 图像数据的系统 RAM 大小，如果 GIMP 还要求更多内存，数据就开始交换到磁盘上，在一些情况下就会出现很明显的停滞。在安装 GIMP 时就可以设置该数量，不过在这里能改变。请看<link linkend='gimp-using-setup-tile-cache'>如何设置平铺缓存</link>。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Maximum new image size</term>
        <term lang='de'>Zurückhaltende Speichernutzung</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Taille maximale des nouvelles images</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">最大新建图像大小</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            This is not a hard contraint:  if you try to create a new
            image larger than the specified size, you are asked to
            confirm that you really want to do it.  This is to prevent
            you from accidentally creating images much larger than you
            intend, which can either crash GIMP or cause it to respond
            verrrrrrrry slowwwwwwwwly.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Hier stellen sie die Größe in Megabyte ein, die ein neues
            Bild maximal benutzen darf. Wird das neue Bild mehr als ihr
            eingetragener Wert an Hauptspeicher belegen, wird GIMP
            nochmals nachfragen.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            Cette valeur n'est pas une contrainte forte: si vous essayez de
            créer une nouvelle image plus grande que cette taille, vous
            devrez confirmer que c'est bien une image de cette taille que
            vous désirez. Cette confirmation est une sécurité qui empêche
            d'ouvrir par hasard des images si grandes que Gimp n'en devienne
            instable (crash ou temps de traitement extrèmement long).
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这并不是一个硬性限制：当您新建一个超过该值的图像时，会询问您是否确认想这样做。这样可以防止由于意外地创建比您设想要大很多的文件而导致 GIMP 崩溃或反应极度迟缓。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <title lang='de'>Bild Vorschau</title>
        <title lang='fr'>Vignettes d'image</title>
        <title lang='en'>Image Thumbnails</title>
        <title lang="zh_CN">图像缩略图</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='fr'>Taille des vignettes</term>
          <term lang='de'>Größe der Vorschaubilder</term>
          <term lang='en'>Size of thumbnails</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">缩略图大小</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>
              This options allows you to set the size of the thumbnails
              shown in the File Open dialog (and also saved for possible
              use by other programs).  The options are "None", 
              "Normal (128x128)", and "Large (256x256)".
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Cette option permet de choisir la taille des vignettes
              visibles dans les dialogues <link linkend='gimp-file-open'>
              Ouvrir une image</link> et <link linkend='gimp-file-save'>
              Enregistrer l'image</link>.
            </para>
            <para lang='de'>
              Die Standardbildgröße die verwendet werden soll, um
              Miniaturbilder im Öffnendialog anzuzeigen.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              FIXME
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='fr'>Taille maximale pour les fichiers de vignette</term>
          <term lang='de'>Maximale Dateigröße für Vorschaubilder</term>
          <term lang='en'>Maximum filesize for thumbnailing</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">缩略图最大文件大小</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>
              If an image file is larger than the specified maximum size,
              GIMP will not generate a thumbnail for it.  This options 
              allows you to prevent thumbnailing of extremely large
              image files from slowing GIMP to a crawl.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Déterminez ici la taille maximale en Méga-oOctets que vous
              octroyez pour une vignette. Au delà de cette taille maximale
              la vignette ne sera pas enregistrée.
            </para>
            <para lang='de'>
              Legt fest, ab welcher Dateigrösse ein Miniaturbild im
              Öffnendialog aktualisiert wird.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              FIXME
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <title lang='en'>Saving Images</title>
        <title lang='de'>Bilder speichern</title>
        <title lang='fr'>Enregistrer les images</title>
        <title lang="zh_CN">文件保存</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Confirm closing of unsaved images</term>
          <term lang='de'>Schließen ungespeicherter Bilder bestätigen</term>
          <term lang='fr'>
            Confirmer la fermeture des images non enregistrées
          </term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">关闭未保存的图像时需要确认</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              Closing an image is not undoable, so by default GIMP asks
              you to confirm that you really want to do it, whenever it
              would lead to a loss of unsaved changes.  You can disable
              this if you find it annoying; but then of course you are
              responsible for remembering what you have and have not
              saved.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              La fermeture d'une image n'est pas réversible: il n'y a pas
              d'annulation possible. Par défaut, <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
              demande une confirmation pour la fermeture d'une image modifiée
              qui n'aurait pas été sauvegardée. Si ces confirmations vous
              gênent, vous pouvez les éviter en désactivant cette option;
              mais vous devrez vous souvenir des images que vous devez
              sauvegarder.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Aktivieren sie dieses Kontrollkästchen, damit
              <acronym>Gimp</acronym> sie nochmal vor dem Beenden des
              Programmes erinnert, dass Bilder geöffnet sind, die noch
              abgespeichert werden müssen.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              由于关闭图像无法撤消，可能导致未保存的变动丢失，因此 GIMP 默认会询问您确认是否真想那样做，如果您觉得这样比较烦，可以在这里让它不出现，不过这样您就要记得哪些变动保存了哪些没有。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang='en'>Size of thumbnail files</term>
          <term lang='de'>Größe der Vorschaudateien</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">缩略图文件大小</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              Here you can set the size of thumbnail files that GIMP
              generates.  Regardless of this value, GIMP will still be
              capable of <emphasis>reading</emphasis> thumbnail files of
              any size.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Bestimmen Sie die Größe der Vorschaubilder, die in den <link
              linkend='gimp-file-open'>Öffnen</link> und <link
              linkend='gimp-file-save'>Speichern</link> Dialogen angezeigt
              werden.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              可以在这里设置 GIMP 缩略图文件大小，但是不管该值多大，GIMP 仍然有能力<emphasis>读取</emphasis>任何大小的缩略图文件。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
    </simplesect>
</sect2>
