<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-folders'>
  <title lang='en'>Folders</title>
  <title lang='de'>Ordner</title>
  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>folders</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Ordner</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary></primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-folders.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        Basic Folder Preferences
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        Einstellungsdialog: Ordneransicht
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    This page allows you to set the locations for two important
    folders used by GIMP for temporary files.  The pages below it
    allow you to customize the locations searched for resources such
    as brushes etc.; see <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Data
    Folders</link> for a description that applies to them.  You 
    can change the folders here by editing the entries, or by pressing
    the buttons on the right to bring up a file chooser window.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Die Ordnervewaltung in den Einstellungen ermöglicht es ihnen Ordner
    für temporäre Daten anzupassen.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title lang='en'>Folders</title>
    <title lang='de'>Ordner</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Temp folder</term>
      <term lang='de'>Temporärer Ordner</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          This folder is used for temporary files:  files created for
          temporary storage of working data, and then deleted within
          the same GIMP session.  It does not require a lot of space
          or high performance.  By default, a subdirectory called
          <filename>tmp</filename> in your personal GIMP directory is
          used, but if that disk is very cramped for space, or has
          serious performance issues, you can change it to a different
          directory.  The directory must exist and be writable by
          you, or bad things will happen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='de'>
        <para>
          Der temporäre Ordner bewahrt Dateien auf, die nur während
          einer GIMP Sitzung gebraucht werden. Das geschieht zum
          Beispiel beim erstellen eines neuen Bildes. Die
          Voreinstellung benutzt das <filename>tmp</filename>
          Verzeichnis in ihrem persönlichen <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
          Ordner. Wenn Sie ein anderes Verzeichnis wünschen, geben Sie
          einfach einen neuen Pfad fuer temporäre Dateien an.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Swap folder</term>
      <term lang='de'>Auslagerungsordner</term>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          This is the folder used as a "memory bank" when the total
          size of images and data open in GIMP exceeds the available
          RAM.  If you work with very large images, or images with
          many layers, or have many images open at once, GIMP can
          potentially require hundreds of megabytes of swap space, so
          available disk space and performance are definitely things
          to think about for this folder.  By default, it is set to
          your personal GIMP directory, but if you have another disk
          with more free space, or substantially better performance,
          you may see a significant benefit from moving your swap
          folder there.  The directory must exist and be writable by
          you.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='de'>
        <para>
          Der Auslagerungsordner wird benutzt um mehr Speicher zur
          Verfügung zu stellen, als Arbeitsspeicher(RAM) im Computer zur
          benutzbar ist. Wenn Sie mit sehr grossen oder
          ressourcenintensiven Bildern arbeiten, ist es nötig
          ungebrauchte Bildbestandteile in diesem Ordner auszulagern.
        </para>
        <warning>
          Beide Pfadangaben zu Verzeichnissen sollten lesbar und gültig
          sein, da es sonst zum Absturz von <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
          kommen kann.
        </warning>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

</sect2>
