<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-prefs-interface' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='en'>Interface</title>
  <title lang='de'>Benutzeroberfläche</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Interface</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">界面</title>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>interface</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='de'>
    <primary>Dialoge</primary>
    <secondary>Einstellungen</secondary>
    <tertiary>Benutzeroberfläche</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang='fr'>
    <primary>Dialogue</primary>
    <secondary>Préférences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Interface</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>对话框</primary>
    <secondary>首选项</secondary>
    <tertiary>界面</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role='html'>
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-interface.png'
          format="PNG" lang='en;zh_CN' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-interface.png'
          format="PNG" lang='de' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-interface.png'
          format="PNG" lang='fr' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role='tex'>
        <imagedata 
          fileref='../images/preferences/prefs-interface.png'
          format="PNG" lang='en;zh_CN' width='14cm' scalefit='1' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/de/prefs-interface.png'
          format="PNG" lang='de' width='14cm' scalefit='1' />
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/preferences/fr/prefs-interface.png'
          format="PNG" lang='fr' width='14cm' scalefit='1' />
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Assorted Interface Preferences
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Les préférences de l'interface utilisateur
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          分类界面首选项
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='de'>
    Verändern Sie das Verhalten von Dialogen oder Menüs in dieser
    Einstellungsansicht. 
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    This page lets you customize layer/channel previews and keyboard shortcuts.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cette page permet de changer le comportement et l'apparence de
    l'interface utilisateur.
  </para>  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您可以在该页定制图层/通道预览和快捷键。
  </para>

  
    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">Options</title>
      <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
      <title lang="fr">Options</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Previews</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschaubilder</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçus</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">预览</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Durch das standardmässig aktivierte Kontrollkästchen unter
            <guilabel><accel>V</accel>orschau von Ebenen und Kanälen
            aktivieren</guilabel> werden im <link
            linkend='gimp-layer-dialog'>Ebenen</link>- und<link
            linkend='gimp-channel-dialog'>Kanaldialog</link> automatisch
            Miniaturbilder angezeigt.
          </para>
          <para>
            Sie können die Standardgrösse der
            Miniaturbilder in Dialogen vorbestimmen. Wählen Sie eine
            Grössenordnung zwischen <guilabel>Winzig</guilabel> und
            <guilabel>Gigantisch</guilabel>.  
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang='en'>
          <para>
            By default, GIMP shows miniature previews of the contents of
            layers and channels in several places, including the Layers
            dialog.  If for some reason you would prefer to disable
            these, you can do it by unchecking "Enable layer and channel
            previews".  If you do want previews to be shown, you can
            customize their sizes using the menus for "Default layer and
            channel preview size" and "Navigation preview size".
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang='fr'>
          <para>
            Par défaut, GIMP affiche des aperçus miniatures des calques
            et des canaux. Ces aperçus sont visible à différents endroits,
            notamment dans le dialogue Calques. Vous pouvez désactiver ces
            aperçus en décochant la case "Activer les aperçus de Calque et Canal". 
            Si vous utilisez ces aperçus, vous pouvez changer leur
            taille pour chaque endroit où ils apparaissent avec
            "Aperçu de Calque de Canal" et"Aperçu de navigation".
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            GIMP 默认是在多个地方(包括图层对话框)显示图层和通道内容的缩略预览。如果由于某些原因不想这样做，可以勾掉“启用图层和通道预览”。当显示预览时，用“默认图层和同通道预览大小”和“导航预览大小”菜单定制预览的大小。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='de'>Tastenkürzel</term>
        <term lang='en'>Keyboard Shortcuts</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Raccourcis clavier</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">快捷键</term>
        <listitem lang="de">
          <para>
            Aktivieren Sie das Kontrollkästchen um Tastaturkürzel in Menüs
            dynamisch zuordnen zu können. 
          </para>
          <para>
            Wählen Sie mit der Maus einen Menüpunkt, dem Sie einen neuen
            Tastaturkürzel zuordnen möchten; klicken dabei aber nicht den
            Menüpunkt an.  Durch betätigen der Tasten Ihres
            Tastaturkürzels weisen Sie einen neuen Tastaturkürzel dem
            Menüpunkt zu.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              Nachdem Sie neue Tastaturkürzel zugeordnet haben, werden die
              GIMP eigenen Standardtastaturkürzel überschrieben.
            </para>
          </note>
          <!-- wie auf standardtastaturkürzel zurücksetzen? -->
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Any menu item can be activated by holding down 
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> and pressing a sequence of keys.
            Normally, the key associated with each menu entry is shown
            as an underlined letter in the text.  If for some reason you
            would prefer the underlines to go away (maybe because you
            think they're ugly and you don't use them anyway), then you
            can make this happen by unchecking "Show menu mnemonics".
          </para>
          <para>
            GIMP can give you the ability to create keyboard shortcuts
            (key combinations that activate a menu entry) dynamically,
            by pressing the keys while the pointer hovers over the
            desired menu entry.  However, this capability is disabled by
            default, because it might lead novice users to accidentally
            overwrite the standard keyboard shortcuts.  If you want to
            enable it, check "Use dynamics keyboard shortcuts" here.
          </para>
          <para>
            Pressing the button for "Configure Keyboard Shortcuts"
            brings up the Shortcut Editor, which gives you a graphical
            interface to select menu items and assign shortcuts to them.
          </para>
          <para>
            If you change shortcuts, you will probably want your changes
            to continue to apply in future GIMP sessions.  If not,
            uncheck "Save keyboard shortcuts on exit".  But remember
            that you have done this, or you may be frustrated later.  If
            you don't want to save shortcuts on exit every session, you
            can save the current settings at any time using the "Save
            Keyborad Shortcuts Now" button, and they will be applied to
            future sessions.  If you decide that you have made some bad
            decisions concerning shortcuts, you can reset them to their
            original state by pressing "Reset Saved Keyboard Shortcuts
            to Default Values".
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            GIMP offre la possibilité de créer dynamiquement des raccourcis
            clavier (une combinaison de touches activant une entrée dans un
            menu). Pour créer une combinaison, il suffit de saisir la
            combinaison de touches en laissant le pointeur de la souris
            au dessus de l'entrée voulue dans un menu.
            Toutefois, cette fonctionnalité est désactivé par défaut, car un
            utilisateur débutant peut accidentellement remplacer les raccourcis
            standard. Si vous voulez utilisez cette fonctionnalité, activez
            l'option "Utiliser les raccourcis clavier dynamiques".
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            按住 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 和一系列键能够开启任何菜单项，一般情况下每个菜单项的键都以一个文字中带下划线的字母表示，由于某种原因(也许决定它们丑陋或您重来不用它们)不想要这些下划线，就可以勾掉“显示菜单记忆法”。
          </para>
          <para>
            GIMP 能够通过在想要的菜单项上停留同时按键来动态地生成键盘快捷键。由于它可能使新手不小心覆盖标准的默认快捷键，因此该功能默认是关闭的。可以勾选“使用动态快捷键”来开启它。
          </para>
          <para>
            点击“配置快捷键”会唤出快捷键编辑器，可以在这个图形界面中选取菜单项并赋予它们快捷键。
          </para>
          <para>
            当改变快捷键后，您可以想让它在以后的 GIMP 进程中使用；如果不想，勾掉“退出时保存快捷键”，不过您要记住这样做了，否则后面您可能会感到迷惑。可以在任何时候用“现在保存快捷键”来保存当前设定，它们会应用在以后的进程。用“重置保存的快捷键到默认值”让快捷键回到初始状态。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
             
    </variablelist>
</sect2>
