<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../../stylesheets/entities.xml">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- section history:
  2009-07-02 ude: fixed bug #573267 (Angular selection: clockwise)
  2009-02-17 j.h: reviewed for v2.6
  2007-05-08 Added Spanish translation by AntI
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-using-animated-brushes">
  <title>Creating animated brushes</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Animation</primary>
    <secondary>Creating an animated brush</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Just like for normal brushes, these animated brushes can also be either
    grayscale or color. For grayscale images, where the actual brush will use
    the current foreground color, you use white for transparency. For color
    images, transparent parts are used as such and when making brush strokes,
    the actual colors will be used instead of the foreground color.
  </para>
  <para>
    To create a new animated brush, create either a grayscale or color image,
    based on whether you want the brush to use the user's foreground color,
    or the actual colors in the image.
    Then create the images for your animation steps.
    To save the brush into gih format, select
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Export As…</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>,
    name your work with the gih extension, and press the
    <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button. The following window is displayed:
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Dialog to export an image as Brush Pipe</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/file-gih-export.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Dialog to export an image as GIMP image hose
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
    This dialog box has several options that allow you to select how your brush
    is animated.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Spacing (Percent)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <quote>Spacing</quote> is the distance between consecutive brush
          marks when you trace out a brushstroke with the pointer. You must
          consider drawing with a brush, whatever the paint tool, like
          stamping. If Spacing is low, stamps will be very close and stroke
          look continuous. If spacing is high, stamps will be separated:
          that's interesting with a color brush (like <quote>green
          pepper</quote> for instance). Value varies from 1 to 200 and this
          percentage refers to brush <quote>diameter</quote>: 100% is one
          diameter.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It's the brush name that will appear at the top of Brush Dialog
          (grid mode) when the brush is selected.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Cell Size</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          That is size of cells you will cut up in layers. Default is one
          cell per layer and size is that of the layer. Then there is only
          one brush aspect per layer.
        </para>
        <para>
          We could have only one big layer and cut up in it the cells that
          will be used for the different aspects of the animated brush.
        </para>
        <para>
          For instance, we want a 100×100 pixels brush with 8 different
          aspects. We can take these 8 aspects from a 400×200 pixels layer,
          or from a 300×300 pixels layer but with one cell unused.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Number of cells</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          That's the number of cells (one cell per aspect) that will be cut
          in every layer. Default is the number of layers as there is only
          one layer per aspect.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Display as</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This tells how cells have been arranged in layers. If, for example,
          you have placed height cells at the rate of two cells per layer on
          four layers, GIMP will display:
          <computeroutput>1 rows of 2 columns on each layer</computeroutput>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Dimension</term>
      <term>Ranks</term>
      <term>Selection dropdown</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There things are getting complicated! Explanations are necessary to
          understand how to arrange cell and layers.
        </para>
        <para>
          GIMP starts retrieving cells from each layer and stacks them into a
          FIFO stack (First In First Out: the first in is at the top of the
          stack and so can be first out). In our example 4 layers with 2 cells
          in each, we'll have, from top to bottom: first cell of first layer,
          second cell of first layer, first cell of second layer, second cell
          of second layer, …, second cell of fourth layer. With one cell per
          layer or with several cells per layer, result is the same. You can
          see this stack in the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>
          of the resulting
          <filename class="extension">.gih</filename> image file.
        </para>
        <para>
          Then GIMP creates a computer array from this stack with the
          <guilabel>Dimensions</guilabel>
          you have set. You can use four dimensions.
        </para>
        <para>
          In computer science an array has a <quote>myarray(x,y,z)</quote>
          form for a 3 dimensions array (3D). It's easy to imagine a 2D array:
          on a paper it's an array with rows and columns
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/gih-array2D.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          With a 3d array we don't talk rows and columns but
          <guilabel>Dimensions</guilabel> and
          <guilabel>Ranks</guilabel>.
          The first dimension is along x axis, the second dimension along y
          axis, the third along z axis. Each dimension has ranks of cells.
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/gih-array3D.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>
          To fill up this array, GIMP starts retrieving cells from the top of
          stack. The way it fills the array reminds that of an odometer: right
          rank digits turn first and, when they reach their maximum, left rank
          digits start running. If you have some memories of Basic programming
          you will have, with an array(4,2,2), the following succession:
          (1,1,1),(1,1,2),(1,2,1),(1,2,2),(2,1,1),(2,1,2),(2,2,2),(3,1,1),…,
          (4,2,2). We will see this later in an example.
        </para>
        <para>
          Besides the rank number that you can give to each dimension, you can
          also give them a <guilabel>Selection</guilabel> mode. You have
          several modes that will be applied when drawing:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Incremental</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <acronym>GIMP</acronym> selects a rank from the concerned
                dimension according to the order ranks have in that dimension.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Angular</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <acronym>GIMP</acronym> selects a rank in the concerned
                dimension according to the moving angle of the brush.
              </para>
              <para>
                The first rank is for the direction 0°, upwards. The other
                ranks are affected, clockwise, to an angle whose value
                is 360/number of ranks. So, with 4 ranks in the concerned
                dimension, the angle will move 90° clockwise for each
                direction change: second rank will be affected to 90°
                (rightwards), third rank to 180° (downwards) and fourth rank to
                270° (-90°) (leftwards).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Random</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <acronym>GIMP</acronym> selects a rank at random from the
                concerned dimension.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Velocity</term>
            <term>Pressure</term>
            <term>X tilt</term>
            <term>Y tilt</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                These options are for sophisticated drawing tablets.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>A one dimension image pipe</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Well! What is all this useful for? We'll see that gradually with
          examples. You can actually place in each dimension cases that will
          give your brush a particular action.
        </para>
        <para>
          Let us start with a 1D brush which will allow us to study selection
          modes action. We can imagine it like this:
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/gih-array1D.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Follow these steps:
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>
              Select
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>File</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>New…</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> from the main menu.
            </para>
            <para>
              Set <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and <guilabel>Height</guilabel> for example to 30 pixels.
            </para>
            <para>
              In the <guilabel>Advanced Options</guilabel>, set the
              <guilabel>Color space</guilabel> to
              <guilabel>RGB color</guilabel> and set
              <guilabel>Fill with</guilabel> to <guilabel>Transparency</guilabel>.
            </para>
            <para>
              Using the Text tool create 4 layers <quote>1</quote>,
              <quote>2</quote>, <quote>3</quote>, <quote>4</quote>. Delete the
              <quote>background</quote> layer.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Select
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>File</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Save…</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> from the main menu to first save your image as an
              <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> file to keep its properties.
            </para>
            <para>
              Select
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>File</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Export As…</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> from the main menu to export the image as an animated brush
              with the <filename class="extension">.gih</filename> extension.
            </para>
            <para>
              Export the image with a <filename class="extension">.gbr</filename> extension in the
              <filename class="directory">brushes</filename> directory located inside
              <link linkend="gimp-concepts-setup">your personal GIMP configuration folder</link>.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the <guilabel>Export Image as Brush Pipe</guilabel> dialog, provide a <guilabel>Description</guilabel>,
              set the <guilabel>Spacing (percent)</guilabel> to 100, set the <guilabel>Cell size</guilabel> to 30×30,
              set <guilabel>Dimension</guilabel> to 1, and set <guilabel>Ranks</guilabel> to 4, and the <guilabel>Selection</guilabel>
              drop-down to <guilabel>incremental</guilabel>.
              Then click the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              In the <link linkend="gimp-brush-dialog">Brush Dialog</link>, click on
              the button <guibutton>Refresh brushes</guibutton>
              <guiicon>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/view-refresh.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
              </guiicon>.
            </para>
            <para>
               Your brush appears among the other brushes. You can use it immediately,
               without restarting <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            </para>
            <para>
              Select your brush. Select pencil tool for instance and
              click and hold with it on a new image:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/gih1234incr.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    You see 1, 2, 3, 4 digits following one another in order.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Take your <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> image file
              back and export it as <filename class="extension">.gih</filename>
              setting the <guilabel>Selection</guilabel> drop-down to <guilabel>random</guilabel>:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/gih1234rand.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    Digits will be displayed at random order.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Now set the <guilabel>Selection</guilabel> drop-down to <guilabel>angular</guilabel>:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/gih1234angl.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </para>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>A 3 dimensions image hose</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We are now going to create a 3D animated brush: its orientation will
          vary according to brush direction, it will alternate Left/Right
          hands regularly and its color will vary at random between black and
          blue.
        </para>
        <para>
          The first question we have to answer to is the number of images that
          is necessary. We reserve the first dimension (x) to the brush
          direction (4 directions). The second dimension (y) is for Left/Right
          alternation and the third dimension (z) for color variation. Such a
          brush is represented in a 3D array <quote>myarray(4,2,2)</quote>:
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/gih-3Dnum.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          There are 4 ranks in first dimension (x), 2 ranks in second
          dimension (y) and 2 ranks in third dimension (z). Thus there
          are 4×2×2 = 16 cells. We need 16 images.
        </para>
        <procedure>
          <step>
            <title>Creating images of dimension 1 (x)</title>
            <para>
              Open a new 30×30 pixels image, RGB with Transparent Fill Type.
              Using the zoom draw a left hand with fingers upwards.<footnote>
              <para>
                Ok, we are cheating here: our hand is borrowed from <ulink
                url="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Stop_hand.png"/>.
              </para></footnote>
              Save it as <filename>handL0k.xcf</filename> (hand Left 0°
              Black).
            </para>
            <para>
              Open the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>.
              Double click on the layer to open the
              Layer Attributes Dialog and rename it to handL0k.
            </para>
            <para>
              Duplicate the layer. Let visible only the duplicated layer,
              select it and apply <menuchoice><guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Transform</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Rotate 90° clockwise</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>. Rename it to handL90k.
            </para>
            <para>
              Repeat the same operations to create handL180k and handL-90k (or
              handL270k).
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <title>Creating images of dimension 2 (y)</title>
            <para>
              This dimension in our example has two ranks, one for left hand
              and the other for right hand. The left hand rank exists yet. We
              shall build right hand images by flipping it horizontally.
            </para>
            <para>
              Duplicate the handL0k layer. Let it visible only and select it.
              Rename it to handR0K. Apply <menuchoice><guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Transform</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Flip Horizontally</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>.

            </para>
            <para>
              Repeat the same operation on the other left hand layers to
              create their right hand equivalent.
            </para>
            <para>
              Re-order layers to have a clockwise rotation from top to
              bottom, alternating Left and Right: handL0k, handR0k, handL90k,
              handR90k, …, handR-90k.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <title>Creating images of dimension 3 (z)</title>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Creating images of dimension 3 (z)</emphasis>:
              The third dimension has two ranks, one for black color and the
              other for blue color. The first rank, black, exists yet. We well
              see that images of dimension 3 will be a copy, in blue, of the
              images of dimension 2. So we will have our 16 images. But a row
              of 16 layers is not easy to manage: we will use layers with two
              images.
            </para>
            <para>
              Select the handL0k layer and let it visible only. Use
              <menuchoice><guimenu>Image</guimenu><guimenuitem>Canvas Size…</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> to <link linkend="gimp-image-resize">change the
              canvas size</link> to 60×30 pixels.
            </para>
            <para>
              Duplicate handL0k layer. On the copy, fill the hand with blue
              using Bucket Fill tool.
            </para>
            <para>
              Now, select the Move tool. Double click on it to accede to its
              properties: check <guilabel>Move the Current Layer</guilabel>
              option. Move the blue hand into the right part of the layer
              precisely with the help of <guisubmenu>Zoom</guisubmenu>.
            </para>
            <para>
              Make sure only handL0k and its blue copy are visible. Right
              click on the Layers dialog: Apply the <guimenuitem>Merge Visible
              Layers</guimenuitem> command with the option <guilabel>Expand as
              Necessary</guilabel>. You get a 60×30 pixels layer with the
              black hand on the left and the blue hand on the right. Rename it
              to <quote>handsL0</quote>.
            </para>
            <para>
              Repeat the same operations on the other layers.
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <title>Set layers in order</title>
            <para>
              Layers must be set in
              order so that GIMP can find the required image at some point
              of using the brush. Our layers are yet in order but we must
              understand more generally how to have them in order. There are
              two ways to imagine this setting in order. The first method is
              mathematical: GIMP divides the 16 layers first by 4; that gives
              4 groups of 4 layers for the first dimension. Each group
              represents a direction of the brush. Then, it divides each group
              by 2; that gives 8 groups of 2 layers for the second dimension:
              each group represents a L/R alternation. Then another division
              by 2 for the third dimension to represent a color at random
              between black and blue.
            </para>
            <para>
              The other method is visual, by using the array representation.
              Correlation between two methods is represented in next image:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/gih-correlation.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
              <emphasis>How will GIMP read this array?</emphasis>: GIMP
              starts with the first dimension which is programmed for
              <quote>angular</quote>, for instance 90°. In this 90°
              rank, in yellow, in the second dimension, it selects a L/R
              alternation, in an <quote>incremental</quote> way. Then,
              in the third dimension, in a random way, it chooses a color.
              Finally, our layers must be in the following order:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/gih-hands-layers.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </para>
          </step>
          <step>
            <para>
              Voilà. Your brush is ready. Save it as
              <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> first, then export as
              <filename class="extension">.gih</filename> with the following
              parameters:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Spacing: 100</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Description: Hands</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Cell Size: 30×30</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Number of cells: 16</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Dimensions: 3</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Dimension 1: 4 ranks Selection: Angular</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Dimension 2: 2 ranks Selection: Incremental</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Dimension 3: 2 ranks Selection: Random</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
              Place your <filename class="extension">.gih</filename> file into
              the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> brush directory and refresh the brush
              box (see steps above). You can now use your brush.
            </para>
            <figure>
              <title>
                Here is the result by stroking an elliptical selection
                with the brush:
              </title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/gih-hands-stroke.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    This brush alternates right hand and left hand regularly,
                    black and blue color at random, direction according to
                    four brush directions.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </step>
        </procedure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
