<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:

-->
<sect2 id="gimp-using-brushes">
  <title>Adding New Brushes</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Brushes</primary>
    <secondary>Add New</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <note>
    <para>
      There is a quick method to add a new brush:
        <xref linkend="gimp-creating-brush-quickly"/>.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    To add a new brush, after either creating or downloading it, you need to
    save it in a format GIMP can use. The brush file needs to be placed in the
    GIMP's brush search path, so that GIMP is able to index and display it in
    the Brushes dialog. You can hit the <guibutton>Refresh</guibutton>
    button, which reindexes the brush directory. GIMP uses three file formats
    for brushes:
  </para>

  <variablelist id="brushes-file-formats">
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Brushes</primary>
      <secondary>File formats</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>GBR</term>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>GBR</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Formats</primary>
          <secondary>GBR</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
          The <filename>.gbr</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>br</emphasis>ush") format is used for ordinary and
          color brushes.  You can convert many other types of images,
          including many brushes used by other programs, into GIMP
          brushes by opening them in GIMP and saving them with file
          names ending in <filename>.gbr</filename>.  This brings up a
          dialog box in which you can set the default Spacing for the
          brush.
        </para>
        <para>
          A technical specification of the GBR file format can be found on
          <ulink url='https://developer.gimp.org/core/standards/gbr/'>
          developer.gimp.org</ulink>.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            Save a <filename class="extension">.gbr</filename> brush
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/file-gbr-export.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>GIH</term>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>GIH</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Formats</primary>
          <secondary>GIH</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
          The <filename>.gih</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>i</emphasis>mage <emphasis>h</emphasis>ose") format
          is used for animated brushes.  These brushes are constructed
          from images containing multiple layers:  each layer may
          contain multiple brush-shapes, arranged in a grid.  When you
          save an image as a <filename>.gih</filename> file, a dialog
          comes up that allows you to describe the format of the brush.
          See <xref linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes"/> for more
          information about the dialog.
        </para>
        <para>
          A technical specification of the GIH file format can be found on
          <ulink url='https://developer.gimp.org/core/standards/gih/'>
          developer.gimp.org</ulink>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>VBR</term>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>VBR</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Formats</primary>
          <secondary>VBR</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
          The <filename>.vbr</filename> format is used for parametric
          brushes, i. e., brushes created using the Brush Editor.
          There is really no other meaningful way of obtaining files
          in this format.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>MYB</term>
      <listitem>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>MYB</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Formats</primary>
          <secondary>MYB</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
          The <filename>.myb</filename> format is used for MyPaint brushes.
          Please refer to <xref linkend="gimp-tool-mypaint-brush"/> for more
          information.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    To make a brush available, place it in one of the folders in GIMP's brush
    search path. By default, the brush search path includes two folders, the
    system <filename>brushes</filename> folder, which you should not use or
    alter, and the <filename>brushes</filename> folder inside your personal
    GIMP directory. You can add new folders to the brush search path using the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Brush Folders</link>
    page of the Preferences dialog. Any GBR, GIH, or VBR file included in a
    folder in the brush search path will show up in the Brushes dialog the
    next time you start GIMP, or as soon as you press the
    <guibutton>Refresh</guibutton> button in the Brushes dialog.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      When you create a new parametric brush using the Brush Editor, it
      is automatically saved in your personal
      <filename>brushes</filename> folder.
    </para>
  </note>
  <para>
    There are a number of web sites with downloadable collections of GIMP
    brushes. Rather than supplying a list of links that will soon be out of
    date, the best advice is to do a search with your favorite search engine
    for <quote>GIMP brushes</quote>.
    There are also many collections of brushes for other programs with
    painting functionality. Some can be converted easily into GIMP brushes,
    some require special conversion utilities, and some cannot be converted at
    all. Most fancy procedural brush types fall into the last category. If you
    need to know, look around on the web, and if you don't find anything, look
    for an expert to ask.
  </para>
</sect2>
