<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-brushes' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Brushes</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Brushes</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/brush-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         A number of examples of brushstrokes painted using different
         brushes from the set supplied with GIMP.  All were painted
         using the Paintbrush tool.
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>brush</emphasis> is a pixmap or set of pixmaps used for
    painting.  GIMP includes a set of 10 "paint tools, which not
    only perform operations that you would think of as painting, but
    also operations such as erasing, copying, smudging, lightening or
    darkening, etc.  All of the paint tools, except the ink tool, use
    the same set of brushes.  The brush pixmaps represent the
    marks that are made 
    by single "touches" of the brush to the image.  A brush stroke,
    usually made by moving the pointer across the image with the mouse
    button held down, produces a series of marks spaced along the
    trajectory, in a way specified by the characteristics of the brush
    and the paint tool being used.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Brushes can be selected by clicking on an icon in the <link
    linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>Brushes dialog</link>.  GIMP's
    <emphasis>current brush</emphasis> is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the brush
    symbol there is one way of activating the Brushes dialog.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a number of basic
    brushes, plus a few bizarre ones that serve mainly to give you
    examples of what is possible (i. e., the "green pepper" brush in
    the illustration).  You can also create new brushes, or
    download them and install them so that GIMP will recognize them.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP can use several different types of brushes.  All of them,
    however, are used in the same way, and for most purposes you don't
    need to be aware of the differences when you paint with them.
    Here are the available types of brushes:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Ordinary brushes</title>
        Most of the brushes supplied with GIMP fall into this
        category.  They are represented in the Brushes dialog by
        grayscale pixmaps.  When you paint using them, the current
        foreground color (as shown in the Color Area of the Toolbox)
        is substituted for black, and the pixmap shown in the brushes
        dialog represents the mark that the brush makes on the image.
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Color brushes</title>
        Brushes in this category are represented by colored images in
        the Brushes dialog.  When you paint with them, the colors are
        used as shown; the current foreground color does not come into
        play.  Otherwise they work the same way as ordinary brushes.
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Image hoses / Image pipes</title>
        Brushes in this category can make more than one kind of mark
        on an image.  They are indicated by small red triangles at th
        lower right corner of the brush symbol in the Brushes dialog.
        They are sometimes called "animated brushes" 
        because the marks change as you trace out a brushstroke. In
        principle, image hose brushes can be very sophisticated,
        especially if you use a tablet, changing shape as a function
        of pressure, angle, etc.  These possibilities have never
        really been exploited, however; and the ones supplied with
        GIMP are relatively simple (but still quite useful). 
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Parametric brushes</title>
        These are brushes created using the <link
        linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Brush Editor</link>, which
        allows you to generate a wide variety of brush shapes by
        using a simple graphical interface.  A nice feature of
        parametric brushes is that they are
        <emphasis>resizable</emphasis>.  In GIMP 2.2, it is possible,
        using the Preferences dialog, to make key presses or mouse
        wheel rotations cause the current brush to become larger or
        smaller, if it is a parametric brush.
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    One category that GIMP does not have is full-fledged
    <emphasis>procedural</emphasis> brushes:  brushes whose marks are
    calculated procedurally, instead of being taken from a fixed
    pixmap.  (Actually this is not quite correct:  the Ink tool uses a
    procedural brush, but it is the only one available in GIMP.)  A
    more extensive implementation of procedural brushes is a goal of
    future development for GIMP.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    In addition to the brush pixmap, each GIMP brush has one other
    important property:  the brush <emphasis>Spacing</emphasis>. This
    represents the distance between consecutive brush-marks when a
    continuous brushstroke is painted.  Each brush has an assigned
    default value for this, which can be modified using the Brushes
    dialog. 
  </para>
 
  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Adding New Brushes</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      To add a new brush so that it shows up in the Brushes dialog, you 
      need to save it in a format GIMP can use, in a folder included in
      GIMP's brush search path.  GIMP uses three file formats for
      brushes: 
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>GBR</title>
          The <filename>.gbr</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>br</emphasis>ush") format is used for ordinary and
          color brushes.  You can convert many other types of images,
          including many brushes used by other programs, into GIMP
          brushes by opening them in GIMP and saving them with file
          names ending in <filename>.gbr</filename>.  This brings up a
          dialog box in which you can set the default Spacing for the
          brush.  A more complete description of the GBR file format
          can be found in the file <filename>gbr.txt</filename> in the
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> directory of the GIMP source
          distribution. 
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>GIH</title>
          The <filename>.gih</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>i</emphasis>mage <emphasis>h</emphasis>ose")
          format is used for animated brushes.  These brushes are
          constructed from images containing multiple layers:  each
          layer may contain multiple brush-shapes, arranged in a
          grid.  When you save an image as a <filename>.gih</filename>
          file, a dialog comes up that allows you to describe the
          format of the brush.  The GIH format is rather complicated,
          and an explanation is beyond the scope of this
          documentation:  a complete description can be found in the
          file <filename>gih.txt</filename> in the 
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> directory of the GIMP source
          distribution. 
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>VBR</title>
          The <filename>.vbr</filename> format is used for parametric
          brushes, i. e., brushes created using the Brush Editor.
          There is really no other meaningful way of obtaining files
          in this format.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang='en'>
      To make a brush available, place it in one of the folders in
      GIMP's brush search path. By default, the brush search path
      includes two folders, the system <filename>brushes</filename>
      folder, which you should not use or alter, and the
      <filename>brushes</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP
      directory.  You can add new folders to the brush search path
      using the <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Brush
      Folders</link> page of the Preferences dialog.  Any GBR, GIH, or
      VBR file included in a folder in the brush search path will show
      up in the Brushes dialog the next time you start GIMP, or as soon
      as you press the Refresh button in the Brushes dialog.
    </para>

    <note lang='en'>
      When you create a new parametric brush using the Brush Editor, it
      is automatically saved in your personal
      <filename>brushes</filename> folder.
    </note>

    <para lang='en'>
      There are a number of web sites with downloadable collections of
      GIMP brushes.  Rather than supplying a list of links that will
      soon be out of date, the best advice is to do a Google search for
      "Gimp brushes".  There are also many collections of brushes for
      other programs with painting functionality.  Some can be converted
      easily into GIMP brushes, some require special conversion
      utilities, and some cannot be converted at all.  Most fancy
      procedural brush types fall into the last category.  If you need
      to know, look around on the web, and if you don't find anything,
      look for an expert to ask. 
    </para>

  </simplesect>
  
</sect2>
