<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-brushes' lang="cs;en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='cs'>Přidávání nových stop</title>
  <title lang='en'>Adding New Brushes</title>
  <title lang='de'>Hinzufügen neuer Pinsel</title>
  <title lang="fr">Ajouter des brosses</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">添加新画笔</title>

  <indexterm lang='cs'>
    <primary>stopy</primary>
    <secondary>nové</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang='en'>
    <primary>Using</primary>
    <secondary>New brushes</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP benutzen</primary>
    <secondary>Hinzufügen neuer Pinsel</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Novou stopu, ať už jste si ji vytvořili sami nebo stáhli z Internetu,
    je nutné uložit ve formátu, který Gimp umí používat. Soubor se stopou musí
    být uložen do cesty pro hledání stop, aby Gimp mohl stopu zpřístupnit
    v dialogu Stopy. Nově přidané stopy lze načíst tlačítkem
    <guibutton>Obnovit</guibutton> v dialogu Stopy (jinak se automaticky
    načtou při příštím spuštění Gimpu). Gimp pro stopy používá tři různé
    souborové formáty:
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>        <!--changed 040927-->
    To add a new brush, after either creating or downloading it, you
    need to save it in a format GIMP can use. The brush file need to be
    placed in the GIMP's brush search path, so that GIMP is able to
    index and display it in the Brushes dialog. You can hit the
    <guibutton>Refresh</guibutton> button, which reindexes the brush
    directory.
    GIMP uses three file formats for brushes: 
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Pinselformen können Sie für <acronym>Gimp</acronym> erstellen oder
    im Internet als Dateien herunterladen. Um die Dateien im
    Pinseldialog auch auswählbar zu haben, muss die Datei mit den
    Pinselformen in einen <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Ordner
    im Suchpfad</link> von <acronym>Gimp</acronym> platziert werden. Sie
    können Dateien mit Pinselformen im laufenden Betrieb in die Ordner
    platzieren. Drücken sie die <guibutton>Pinsel neu laden</guibutton>
    Schaltfläche, um die neue Pinselform auswählen zu können.
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> kann drei Dateiformate für Pinsel lesen:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    要添加一个将在画笔对话框中显示的新画笔，您需要保存为 GIMP 能使用的格式。其所在文件夹要在 GIMP 画笔搜索路径中，然后<emphasis>刷新</emphasis>画笔对话框(或重新启动 GIMP)。GIMP 中的画笔可以使用三种文件格式：
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Pour ajouter une brosse, après l'avoir créée ou l'avoir téléchargée, 
    de façon à ce qu'elle apparaisse dans le dialogue des brosses, vous 
    devez l'enregistrer dans un format que GIMP sait reconnaître, dans un 
    des dossiers où GIMP sait trouver les brosses. GIMP utilise trois 
    formats de brosse:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>GBR</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Formát <emphasis>GBR</emphasis>
          (<foreignphrase><emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>br</emphasis>ush</foreignphrase>) se používá pro běžné
          a barevné stopy. Různé obrázky, včetně stop určených pro jiné
          programy, můžete proměnit ve stopy pro Gimp jejich otevřením
          v Gimpu a uložením do souboru s příponou <filename>.gbr</filename>.
          Otevře se přitom dialog, ve kterém je potřeba zadat výchozí rozestup
          stopy a její popis. Podrobnější popis formátu GBR naleznete
          v souboru <filename>gbr.txt</filename> v adresáři
          <filename class="directory">devel-docs</filename> zdrojových kódů
          Gimpu.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          The <filename>.gbr</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>br</emphasis>ush") format is used for ordinary and
          color brushes.  You can convert many other types of images,
          including many brushes used by other programs, into GIMP
          brushes by opening them in GIMP and saving them with file
          names ending in <filename>.gbr</filename>.  This brings up a
          dialog box in which you can set the default Spacing for the
          brush.  A more complete description of the GBR file format
          can be found in the file <filename>gbr.txt</filename> in the
          <filename class="directory">devel-docs</filename> directory of the GIMP source
          distribution. 
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Das <acronym><emphasis role='bold'>G</emphasis>imp</acronym>
          <emphasis role='bold'>br</emphasis>ush Format (kurz
          <filename>gbr</filename>) wird für gewöhnliche Graustufen und
          Farbpinsel verwendet. Es ist möglich, Pinsel anderer Programme
          oder Bilder in das <acronym>Gimp</acronym> eigene Pinselformat
          zu konvertieren.  Durch Öffnen und Speichern mit der Endung
          <filename>.gbr</filename> wird das Bild als Pinsel
          gespeichert. Mehr Informationen finden Sie im <filename
          class="directory">devel-docs</filename> Verzeichnis unter
          <filename>gbr.txt</filename> der <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
          Quellcode Distribution.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <filename>.gbr</filename> 格式用在普通和彩色画笔中。您可以通过在 GIMP 打开图像并保存为后缀为 <filename>.gbr</filename> 的文件，来将许多其它格式的图像包括其它程序中使用的画笔转变为 GIMP 画笔。其间会弹出一个能够设置画笔默认间隔的一个对话框。关于 GBR 更详细的描述可以在 GIMP 源文件的 <filename>devel-docs</filename> 目录的 <filename>gbr.txt</filename> 文件中找到。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Le format <emphasis>.gbr</emphasis> est utilisé pour les brosses 
          ordinaires et les brosses figurées. Vous pouvez convertir d'autres 
          types d'image simplement en les enregistrant au format .gbr. Ceci 
          ouvre le boîte de dialogue où vous pouvez régler l'Espacement. Une 
          description complète du format GBR se trouve dans le fichier 
          <filename>gbr.txt</filename> dans le répertoire 
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> dans la distribution Source de 
          GIMP.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>GIH</term>
      <listitem>
      <figure lang="cs;en;de">
        <title lang='cs'>
          Dialog pro popis animovaného štětce.
        </title>
        <title lang='en'>
          The dialog to describe the animated brush.
        </title>
        <title lang='de'>
          Der Dialog um eine animierte Pinselform zu beschreiben.
        </title>
        <mediaobject lang="cs;en;de">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/using/file-gih-save.png'
              format="PNG"/>
           </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Formát <emphasis>GIH</emphasis>
          (<foreignphrase><emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>i</emphasis>mage
          <emphasis>h</emphasis>ose</foreignphrase>) se používá pro animované
          stopy. Tyto stopy se vytváří z vícevrstvých obrázků, každá vrstva
          může obsahovat několik tvarů stop uspořádaných v mřížce. Při
          ukládání do souboru s příponou <filename>.gih</filename> se otevře
          dialog, ve kterém je třeba popsat použitý formát stopy. Více se o
          tomto dialogu dozvíte v části <link linkend="gimp-GIH-dialog">Dialog
          GIH</link>. Formát GIH je poměrně kompplikovaný, úplný popis
          naleznete v souboru <filename>gih.txt</filename> v adresáři
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> zdrojových kódů Gimpu.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>         <!--changed 040927-->
          The <filename>.gih</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>i</emphasis>mage <emphasis>h</emphasis>ose") format
          is used for animated brushes.  These brushes are constructed
          from images containing multiple layers:  each layer may
          contain multiple brush-shapes, arranged in a grid.  When you
          save an image as a <filename>.gih</filename> file, a dialog
          comes up that allows you to describe the format of the brush.
          Look at <link linkend="gimp-GIH-dialog">The GIH dialog
          box</link> for more information about the dialog.  The GIH
          format is rather complicated: a complete description can be
          found in the file <filename>gih.txt</filename> in the
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> directory of the GIMP source
          distribution.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das <quote><acronym><emphasis
          role="bold">G</emphasis>imp</acronym> <emphasis
          role="bold">i</emphasis>mage <emphasis>h</emphasis>ose</quote>
          Format (kurz <filename>gih</filename>) wird benutzt, um
          animierte Pinsel zu speichern. Diese Pinsel werden mittels
          mehreren Ebenen konstruiert, wobei jede Ebene eine
          verschiedene Pinselform wiederspiegelt.  Wenn Sie eine
          animierte Pinselform als <filename>.gih</filename>
          abspeichern, erscheint ein Dialog um das Format zu
          beschreiben. Das Format selber ist etwas kompliziert, wird
          aber in <filename>gih.txt</filename> in den <filename
          class="directory">devel-docs</filename> der <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
          Quellcode Distribution beschrieben.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <filename>.gih</filename> 格式用在动画画笔中。这些画笔由包含多个图层的图像构成：每个图层可能包括多个在一个网格中对齐的画笔形状。保存一个图像为 <filename>.gih</filename> 时，将弹出一个允许您描述画笔格式的对话框。GIH 格式非常复杂，对它的解释已超过该文档范围：关于 GIH 更详细的描述可以在 GIMP 源文件的 <filename>devel-docs</filename> 目录的 <filename>gih.txt</filename> 文件中找到。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Le format <filename>.gih</filename> est utilisé pour les brosses 
          animées. Ces brosses sont constituées d'images contenant 
          plusieurs calques, chaque calque pouvant contenir un à plusieurs 
          dessins de la brosse dans différents aspects. Quand vous 
          enregistrez une image au format GIH, la boîte de Dialogue GIH 
          s'ouvre. Le format GIH est décrit en détail dans le fichier 
          <filename>gih.txt</filename> du répertoire 
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> de la distribution Source de GIMP.
          Voyez 
          <link linkend='gimp-GIH-dialog'>Enregistrer en tant que brosse 
          animée</link> 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>VBR</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Formát <filename>VBR</filename> (soubory <filename>.vbr</filename>)
          se používá pro tzv. parametrické stopy, tj. stopy vytvořené Editorem
          stop. Jiný praktický způsob vytvoření stop ve formátu VBR neexistuje.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          The <filename>.vbr</filename> format is used for parametric
          brushes, i. e., brushes created using the Brush Editor.
          There is really no other meaningful way of obtaining files
          in this format.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das <filename>.vbr</filename> Format wird benutzt um
          parametrische Pinselinformationen zu behalten, welche durch
          den Pinseleditor abgespeichert werden. 
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <filename>.vbr</filename> 格式用在参数画笔中，比如用画笔编辑器创建画笔。也没有其它真正有意义的方式获取该格式。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Le format <filename>.vbr</filename> est utilisé pour les brosses 
          paramétriques, càd les brosses créées avec l'Éditeur de brosse. Il 
          n'y a vraiment pas d'autre façon valable d'obtenir les fichiers de 
          ce format.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Aby byla stopa v Gimpu dostupná, uložte soubor do některého z adresářů
    v cestě Gimpu pro hledání stop. Ve výchozím nastavení tato cesta obsahuje
    dva adresáře, systémový adresář <filename>brushes</filename>, který byste
    neměli měnit, a uživatelský adresář <filename>brushes</filename> uvnitř
    vašeho osobního adresáře pro Gimp. Přidávat další adresáře do této cesty
    lze v předvolbách na kartě <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Adresáře</link>. Všechny
    <filename>.gbr</filename>, <filename>.gih</filename> a
    <filename>.vbr</filename> soubory obsažené v těchto adresářích se načtou
    a zobrazí v dialogu Stopy buď po příštím spuštění Gimpu, nebo po stisknutí
    tlačítka <guibutton>Obnovit</guibutton> v tomto dialogu.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    To make a brush available, place it in one of the folders in
    GIMP's brush search path. By default, the brush search path
    includes two folders, the system <filename>brushes</filename>
    folder, which you should not use or alter, and the
    <filename>brushes</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP
    directory.  You can add new folders to the brush search path
    using the <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Brush
    Folders</link> page of the Preferences dialog.  Any GBR, GIH, or
    VBR file included in a folder in the brush search path will show
    up in the Brushes dialog the next time you start GIMP, or as soon
    as you press the <guibutton>Refresh</guibutton> button in the
    Brushes dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Wie in der Einführung beschrieben, können Sie eine Pinseldatei in einen
    der Pinselordner von <acronym>Gimp</acronym> legen. Standardmäßig
    werden zwei Ordner nach neuen Pinseln durchsucht: den systemweiten
    <filename class="directory">brushes</filename> Ordner, den Sie
    besser nicht verändern und den <filename
    class="directory">brushes</filename> Ordner in ihrem persöhnlichen
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> Verzeichnis. Sie können neue Ordner zu
    diesen beiden in den <link
    linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Einstellungen</link> hinzufügen.
    Jede Datei die auf <filename>gbr</filename>,
    <filename>gih</filename> oder <filename>vbr</filename> endet wird
    von <acronym>Gimp</acronym> indiziert und im Pinseldialog angezeigt.
    Voreinstellung
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    要使一个画笔可用，将其放在 GIMP 画笔搜索路径中的一个文件夹中。画笔搜索路径默认包括两个文件夹，系统的 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹--您不应该使用或修改。和个人 GIMP 目录中的 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹。您能在首选项对话框的<link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>画笔文件夹</link>页中添加新文件夹到画笔搜索路径。画笔搜索路径中文件夹中包含的任何 GBR，GIH 或 VBR 文件都会在下次启动 GIMP 时显示在画笔对话框中。
   </para>
   <para lang="fr">
     Pour rendre une brosse utilisable, vous devez l'enregistrer dans un 
     dossier où GIMP saura la retrouver. Par défaut, il existe deux 
     dossiers pour les brosses: voyez Fichier/Préférences/Dossiers/Brosses. 
     Le répertoire usr/share/gimp-2.2/brushes est réservé à GIMP et vous 
     ne devriez pas y toucher. Le répertoire home/nom de login/gimp-2.2/
     brushes est votre répertoire de brosses personnel (vous devez cocher 
     la case <guilabel>Modifiable</guilabel>); c'est là que vous 
     devez placer les brosses que vous ajoutez. Ces brosses apparaîtront  
     dans le dialogue des brosses si vous redémarrez GIMP ou plus 
     simplement si vous cliquez sur le bouton <guibutton>Rafraîchir
     </guibutton> dans le dialogue des brosses.
   </para>
  <note>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Parametrické stopy vytvořené pomocí Editoru stop se automaticky ukládají
      do uživatelského <filename>brushes</filename> adresáře.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      When you create a new parametric brush using the Brush Editor, it
      is automatically saved in your personal
      <filename>brushes</filename> folder.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie Pinsel über den Pinseleditor erstellen, werden diese
      automatisch im <filename class="directory">brushes</filename>
      Verzeichnis abgespeichert.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
    当用画笔编辑器新建一个参数画笔时，它将自动保存在您的个人 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹。
    </para> 
    <para lang='fr'>
      Quand vous créez une nouvelle brosse paramétrique en utilisant 
      l'Éditeur de brosse, elle est automatiquement enregistrée dans votre 
      répertoire des brosses personnel.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Existuje řada webových stránek nabízejících ke stažení celé sbírky stop
    pro Gimp. Nemá smysl uvádět seznam odkazů, neboť se rychle mění. Nejlepší
    je prostě do vašeho oblíbeného vyhledávače zadat frázi <quote>Gimp
    brushes</quote> (stopy pro Gimp). Existuje také řada sbírek stop pro jiné
    grafické rastrové editory. Některé z nich lze snadno převést na stopy pro
    Gimp, jiné vyžadují speciální konverzní programy a některé nelze použít
    vůbec. Většina složitějších procedurálních stop spadá bohužel do poslední
    kategorie.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    There are a number of web sites with downloadable collections of
    GIMP brushes.  Rather than supplying a list of links that will soon
    be out of date, the best advice is to do a search with your favorite
    search engine for <quote>Gimp brushes</quote>.  There are also many
    collections of brushes for other programs with painting
    functionality.  Some can be converted easily into GIMP brushes, some
    require special conversion utilities, and some cannot be converted
    at all.  Most fancy procedural brush types fall into the last
    category.  If you need to know, look around on the web, and if you
    don't find anything, look for an expert to ask. 
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Es gibt eine Reihe von Webseiten die eine ganze Kollektion von
    Pinseln zum Herunterladen anbieten. Anstatt Ihnen eine Liste von
    Verweisen anzubieten, möchten wir Sie ermutigen mit einer
    Suchmaschine Ihrer Wahl nach <quote>GIMP brushes</quote>  zu suchen.
    Es gibt zudem eine Menge von Pinseln die Sie konvertieren können.
    Manche davon lassen sich leicht, schwer oder gar nicht konvertieren.
    Leider gehören die wohl schönsten immer zur letzten Gruppe.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    有大量含有能下载的 GIMP 画笔资源的网站。这里给您个列表可能其链接很快就会过时，因此我们建议最好是在 Google 上搜索“Gimp brushes”。还有大量其它有画图功能的软件的画笔。一些可以容易地转换为 GIMP 画笔，有些需要专门的转换工具，而有些则完全无法转换。大部分不成熟的过程画笔就属于最后一类。假如您需要知道能否转换，可以在网上寻找，如果您没有找到任何东西，可以寻求专家的帮助。
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Il existe de nombreux sites sur le Web où vous pouvez trouver des 
    brosses. Plutôt que de vous donner une liste de sites qui sera vite 
    périmée, je vous conseille de faire une recherche avec un moteur de 
    recherche avec le thème "GIMP brushes". Beaucoup sont destinées à 
    d'autres programmes de graphisme et il n'est pas certain que vous 
    pourrez aisément les adapter à GIMP.
  </para>

</sect1>

