<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-brushes' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Brushes</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">画笔</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Brushes</primary>
    <para lang="zh_CN">画笔</para>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/brush-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/brush-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         A number of examples of brushstrokes painted using different
         brushes from the set supplied with GIMP.  All were painted
         using the Paintbrush tool.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
         下面是一些使用 GIMP 提供的一系列不同画笔所产生的笔划的范例。全都是使用画笔工具来进行涂画的。
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>brush</emphasis> is a pixmap or set of pixmaps used for
    painting.  GIMP includes a set of 10 "paint tools, which not
    only perform operations that you would think of as painting, but
    also operations such as erasing, copying, smudging, lightening or
    darkening, etc.  All of the paint tools, except the ink tool, use
    the same set of brushes.  The brush pixmaps represent the
    marks that are made 
    by single "touches" of the brush to the image.  A brush stroke,
    usually made by moving the pointer across the image with the mouse
    button held down, produces a series of marks spaced along the
    trajectory, in a way specified by the characteristics of the brush
    and the paint tool being used.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
   一个<emphasis>画笔</emphasis>是一个或一系列点阵图 (pixmap) 用做涂画。GIMP 包含一套 10 个涂画工具，它们不光完成您想象中的涂画操作，还包括擦除，拷贝，涂抹，减淡或加深等。除了墨水工具外的所以涂画工具都使用同一套画笔。这些画笔点阵图由该画笔在图像上的一个“压痕”的标志来表示。一个画笔笔划，通常是由按住鼠标键同时在图像上拖动光标产生，它根据使用的涂画工具其选取的画笔特性产生一系列随着轨迹间排列的一个一个斑点。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Brushes can be selected by clicking on an icon in the <link
    linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>Brushes dialog</link>.  GIMP's
    <emphasis>current brush</emphasis> is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the brush
    symbol there is one way of activating the Brushes dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    画笔能够在<link linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>画笔对话框</link>中通过点击一个其中图标来选取。GIMP <emphasis>当前画笔</emphasis>显示在工具箱的 画笔/图案/渐变 区域。点击画笔标志是开启画笔对话框的一种方式。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a number of basic
    brushes, plus a few bizarre ones that serve mainly to give you
    examples of what is possible (i. e., the "green pepper" brush in
    the illustration).  You can also create new brushes, or
    download them and install them so that GIMP will recognize them.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    安装 GIMP 时，它自带了一系列基本的画笔外加一些主要提供当例子的怪异画笔(比如“绿色青椒”画笔)。您也能够新建画笔，或下载它们并安装，这样 GIMP 就会加载它们。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP can use several different types of brushes.  All of them,
    however, are used in the same way, and for most purposes you don't
    need to be aware of the differences when you paint with them.
    Here are the available types of brushes:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 可以使用许多不同类型的画笔。尽管如此，所以这些画笔使用方法都相同，对大部分目的，没有必要在用它们进行涂画时意识到这些不同。下面时可用的画笔类型：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Ordinary brushes</title>
        Most of the brushes supplied with GIMP fall into this
        category.  They are represented in the Brushes dialog by
        grayscale pixmaps.  When you paint using them, the current
        foreground color (as shown in the Color Area of the Toolbox)
        is substituted for black, and the pixmap shown in the brushes
        dialog represents the mark that the brush makes on the image.
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>普通画笔</title>
        大部分 GIMP 自带的画笔属于这类，它们在画笔对话框中表现为灰度点阵图。当您使用它们时，当前前景色(在工具箱颜色区域显示)被换成黑色，而在画笔对话框中显示的点阵图表示画笔将在图像上产生的印记行踪。
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Color brushes</title>
        Brushes in this category are represented by colored images in
        the Brushes dialog.  When you paint with them, the colors are
        used as shown; the current foreground color does not come into
        play.  Otherwise they work the same way as ordinary brushes.
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>彩色画笔</title>
        属于这类的画笔在画笔对话框中表现为彩色图像。使用它们涂画时，将使用其显示的颜色；当前前景色就不起作用，其它地方都和普通画笔一样。
    </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Image hoses / Image pipes</title>
        Brushes in this category can make more than one kind of mark
        on an image.  They are indicated by small red triangles at th
        lower right corner of the brush symbol in the Brushes dialog.
        They are sometimes called "animated brushes" 
        because the marks change as you trace out a brushstroke. In
        principle, image hose brushes can be very sophisticated,
        especially if you use a tablet, changing shape as a function
        of pressure, angle, etc.  These possibilities have never
        really been exploited, however; and the ones supplied with
        GIMP are relatively simple (but still quite useful). 
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>图像管 (Image hoses) / (Image pipes)</title>
        属于这类的画笔能在一个图像上产生一种以上类型的印记。它们在画笔对话框的画笔标志右下方显示一个红色小三角。由于它们随着您勾画笔划时其印记也在改变，因此有时也把它们被叫作“动画画笔”。原则上，图像管会非常复杂，特别是使用一个平面板，在压力，角度等方面改变其形状。尽管如此，这些可能性并没有真正被挖掘；GIMP 自带的图像管就相对简单(不过仍然非常有用)。
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Parametric brushes</title>
        These are brushes created using the <link
        linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Brush Editor</link>, which
        allows you to generate a wide variety of brush shapes by
        using a simple graphical interface.  A nice feature of
        parametric brushes is that they are
        <emphasis>resizable</emphasis>.  In GIMP 2.2, it is possible,
        using the Preferences dialog, to make key presses or mouse
        wheel rotations cause the current brush to become larger or
        smaller, if it is a parametric brush.
     </formalpara>
     <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>参数画笔</title>
        它们是用<link linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>画笔编辑器</link>创建，允许您使用一个简单的图形界面产生大量不通的画笔形状。参数画笔的一个很好的特性就是其<emphasis>可缩放性</emphasis>。在 GIMP 2.2 中，在首选项对话框中使通过按键或滚动鼠标滑轮让参赛画笔变大变小成为可能。
     </formalpara>
        
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    One category that GIMP does not have is full-fledged
    <emphasis>procedural</emphasis> brushes:  brushes whose marks are
    calculated procedurally, instead of being taken from a fixed
    pixmap.  (Actually this is not quite correct:  the Ink tool uses a
    procedural brush, but it is the only one available in GIMP.)  A
    more extensive implementation of procedural brushes is a goal of
    future development for GIMP.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 中没有成熟的<emphasis>过程</emphasis>画笔：其印记是根据过程计算的，而不是使用是个固定的点阵图。(实际上这么说也不正确：墨水工具是 GIMP 中唯一可以使用过程画笔的工具。)对过程画笔更进一步的实现是 GIMP 将来发展的一个目标。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    In addition to the brush pixmap, each GIMP brush has one other
    important property:  the brush <emphasis>Spacing</emphasis>. This
    represents the distance between consecutive brush-marks when a
    continuous brushstroke is painted.  Each brush has an assigned
    default value for this, which can be modified using the Brushes
    dialog. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    每个 GIMP 画笔除了画笔点阵图还有另外一个重要属性：画笔<emphasis>间隔</emphasis>。它表示画一个连续笔划时相邻画笔印记间的距离。每个画笔都有一个给定的默认间距值，它可以通过画笔对话框修改。
  </para>
 
  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Adding New Brushes</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">添加新画笔</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      To add a new brush so that it shows up in the Brushes dialog, you 
      need to save it in a format GIMP can use, in a folder included in
      GIMP's brush search path.  GIMP uses three file formats for
      brushes: 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      要添加一个将在画笔对话框中显示的新画笔，您需要保存为 GIMP 能使用的格式，其所在文件夹要在 GIMP 画笔搜索路径中。GIMP 中的画笔可以使用三种文件格式：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>GBR</title>
          The <filename>.gbr</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>br</emphasis>ush") format is used for ordinary and
          color brushes.  You can convert many other types of images,
          including many brushes used by other programs, into GIMP
          brushes by opening them in GIMP and saving them with file
          names ending in <filename>.gbr</filename>.  This brings up a
          dialog box in which you can set the default Spacing for the
          brush.  A more complete description of the GBR file format
          can be found in the file <filename>gbr.txt</filename> in the
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> directory of the GIMP source
          distribution. 
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>GBR</title>
          <filename>.gbr</filename> 格式用在普通和彩色画笔中。您可以通过在 GIMP 打开图像并保存为后缀为 <filename>.gbr</filename> 的文件，来将许多其它格式的图像包括其它程序中使用的画笔转变为 GIMP 画笔。其间会弹出一个能够设置画笔默认间隔的一个对话框。关于 GBR 更详细的描述可以在 GIMP 源文件的 <filename>devel-docs</filename> 目录的 <filename>gbr.txt</filename> 文件中找到。
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>GIH</title>
          The <filename>.gih</filename> ("<emphasis>g</emphasis>imp
          <emphasis>i</emphasis>mage <emphasis>h</emphasis>ose")
          format is used for animated brushes.  These brushes are
          constructed from images containing multiple layers:  each
          layer may contain multiple brush-shapes, arranged in a
          grid.  When you save an image as a <filename>.gih</filename>
          file, a dialog comes up that allows you to describe the
          format of the brush.  The GIH format is rather complicated,
          and an explanation is beyond the scope of this
          documentation:  a complete description can be found in the
          file <filename>gih.txt</filename> in the 
          <filename>devel-docs</filename> directory of the GIMP source
          distribution. 
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>GIH</title>
          <filename>.gih</filename> 格式用在动画画笔中。这些画笔由包含多个图层的图像构成：每个图层可能包括多个在一个网格中对齐的画笔形状。保存一个图像为 <filename>.gih</filename> 时，将弹出一个允许您描述画笔格式的对话框。GIH 格式非常复杂，对它的解释已超过该文档范围：关于 GIH 更详细的描述可以在 GIMP 源文件的 <filename>devel-docs</filename> 目录的 <filename>gih.txt</filename> 文件中找到。
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>VBR</title>
          The <filename>.vbr</filename> format is used for parametric
          brushes, i. e., brushes created using the Brush Editor.
          There is really no other meaningful way of obtaining files
          in this format.
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>VBR</title>
          <filename>.vbr</filename> 格式用在参数画笔中，比如用画笔编辑器创建画笔。也没有其它真正有意义的方式获取该格式。
       </formalpara>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang='en'>
      To make a brush available, place it in one of the folders in
      GIMP's brush search path. By default, the brush search path
      includes two folders, the system <filename>brushes</filename>
      folder, which you should not use or alter, and the
      <filename>brushes</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP
      directory.  You can add new folders to the brush search path
      using the <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Brush
      Folders</link> page of the Preferences dialog.  Any GBR, GIH, or
      VBR file included in a folder in the brush search path will show
      up in the Brushes dialog the next time you start GIMP, or as soon
      as you press the Refresh button in the Brushes dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      要使一个画笔可用，将其放在 GIMP 画笔搜索路径中的一个文件夹中。画笔搜索路径默认包括两个文件夹，系统的 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹--您不应该使用或修改。和个人 GIMP 目录中的 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹。您能在首选项对话框的<link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>画笔文件夹</link>页中添加新文件夹到画笔搜索路径。画笔搜索路径中文件夹中包含的任何 GBR，GIH 或 VBR 文件都会在下次启动 GIMP 时显示在画笔对话框中。
     </para>

    <note lang='en'>
      When you create a new parametric brush using the Brush Editor, it
      is automatically saved in your personal
      <filename>brushes</filename> folder.
    </note>
    <note lang="zh_CN">
      当用画笔编辑器新建一个参赛画笔时，它将自动保存在您的个人 <filename>brushes</filename> 文件夹。
    </note>

    <para lang='en'>
      There are a number of web sites with downloadable collections of
      GIMP brushes.  Rather than supplying a list of links that will
      soon be out of date, the best advice is to do a Google search for
      "Gimp brushes".  There are also many collections of brushes for
      other programs with painting functionality.  Some can be converted
      easily into GIMP brushes, some require special conversion
      utilities, and some cannot be converted at all.  Most fancy
      procedural brush types fall into the last category.  If you need
      to know, look around on the web, and if you don't find anything,
      look for an expert to ask. 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      有大量含有能下载的 GIMP 画笔资源的网站。这里给您个列表可能其链接很快就会过时，因此我们建议最好是在 Google 上搜索“Gimp brushes”。还有大量其它有画图功能的软件的画笔。一些可以容易地转换为 GIMP 画笔，有些需要专门的转换工具，而有些则完全无法转换。大部分不成熟的过程画笔就属于最后一类。假如您需要知道能否转换，可以在网上寻找，如果您没有找到任何东西，可以寻求专家的帮助。
    </para>

  </simplesect>
  
</sect2>
