<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-fileformats'>
  <title lang="en">Files</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">文件</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Files</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">文件</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The GIMP is capable of reading and writing a large variety of
    graphics file formats.   With the exception of GIMP's native XCF
    file type, file handling is done by plug-ins.  Thus, it is
    relatively easy to extend GIMP to new file types when the need
    arises. 
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 有读写大量图像文件格式的能力。除了 GIMP 专用的 XCF 文件格式外，其它的处理其它的格式都靠插件。因此，当需要让 GIMP 支持新的文件格式时，就相对的比较容易。
  </para>
  
  <para lang="en">
    Not all file types are equally good for all purposes.  This part
    of the documentation should help you understand the advantages and
    disadvantages of each type.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    并不是所有的文件格式在各种情况下都一样。这部分将帮助您了解各种格式的优点和缺点。
  </para>  



  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Opening Files</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">打开文件</title>
    <para lang="en">
      There are several ways of opening an existing image in GIMP:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在 Gimp 中有多种方式打开一个现有图像：
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          The most obvious is to open it using a menu, by choosing
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          from either the Toolbox menu or an image menu.  This brings
          up a File Chooser dialog, allowing you to navigate to the
          file and click on its name.  This method works well if you
          know the name of the file you want to open, and where it is
          located. It is not so convenient if you want to find the
          file on the basis of a thumbnail.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          最明显地打开是使用菜单，选取
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>打开</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          在工具栏菜单或一个图像菜单中。将出现一个允许浏览文件并点击其名字的文件选择对话框。该方法适合于您知道要打开的图像的名字，和它所在的位置。而在您象通过一个缩略图来找对应的文件时就不是那么方便了。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          If instead of a file name, you have a URI (i.e., a web
          address) for the image, you can open it using the menu, by
          choosing 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Open Location</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          from either the Toolbox menu or an image menu.  This brings
          up a small dialog that allows you to enter the URI.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          假如是一个 URL (比如一个网络地址)的图像，您能通过使用菜单，选取
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>打开位置</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。 
          在工具栏菜单或一个图像菜单中。会出现一个允许输入URL的小的对话框。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          If the image is one that you previously created using GIMP,
          perhaps the easiest way to open it is from the menu, using
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Open Recent</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          This gives you a scrollable list of the images you
          have most recently worked on in, with icons beside them.
          You need only select the one you want, and it will be
            opened.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          如果是一个前面用 Gimp 创建的图像，也许打开它最简单的方式就是从菜单，选取
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>最近打开</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
          将出现一个您最近处理过的图像的可滚动的列表，您只需要点击一个图像旁的图标，就会将其打开。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          If you have associated the file type of the image with GIMP,
          either when you installed GIMP or later, then you can
          navigate to the file using a file manager (such as Nautilus
          in Linux, or Windows Explorer in Windows), and once you have
          found it, double-click on the icon.  If things are set up
          properly, this will cause the image to open in GIMP.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          如果您用 Gimp 关联了文件类型，不管是安装 Gimp 时还是以后，都可以通过一个文件管理器(比如 Linux 中的 Nautilus，或 Windows 中的 Windows Explorer)来浏览文件，一旦找到了，双击它的图标。如果一切设置正确，该图像将在 Gimp 中打开。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          Alternatively, once you have found the file, you can click
          on its icon and drag it into the GIMP Toolbox.  (If instead
          you drag it into an existing GIMP image, it will be added to
          that image as a new layer or set of layers.)
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          另外，一旦您找到该文件，能够点击图标并将它拖到 Gimp 的工具栏中。(如果拖到一个已打开的 Gimp 图像中，它将被添加为图像的一个或一系列图层。)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          For many applications, you can click on a displayed image (a
          full image, not just a thumbnail) and drag it into the GIMP
          toolbox. 
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          对大多数应用程序，您能点击一个显示的图像(一个完整图像，而不是缩略图)并拖动到 GIMP 的工具栏中。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          Also for many applications, if the application gives you a
          way of copying the image to the clipboard, you can then open
          the image in GIMP by choosing
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Acquire</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Paste as New</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          from the Toolbox menu.  Support for this is somewhat
          variable, however, so your best bet is to try it and see
          whether it works.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
           同样对大多数应用程序，如果程序让您拷贝图像到剪贴板中，您就能然后在 GIMP 中选取
           <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>获取</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>粘贴为新图像</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          在工具栏菜单中。对它的支持稍微有些差异，因此您最好尝试下并看看它是否肯工作。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          You might want to take a look at a program called
          <application>gthumb</application>, an image-management
          application that in several ways nicely complements GIMP.
          In <application>gthumb</application>, you can cause an image
          to open in GIMP either by right-clicking on the icon and
          selecting GIMP from among the list of options, or by
          dragging the icon into the GIMP Toolbox.  See the <ulink
          url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb home page</ulink>
          for more information.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
         您也许想要看一个叫 <application>gthumb</application> 的程序，一个图像管理程序在许多方面对 GIMP 是个很好的补充。在 <application>gthumb</application> 中，您可以通过右键点击图标并从选项列表中选取 GIMP，或拖动图标到 GIMP 工具栏中。请到<ulink url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb主页</ulink>获取更多信息。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para id="gimp-file-open-by-extension" lang="en">
      When you open a file, using the File menu or any other method,
      GIMP needs to determine what type of file it is.  Unless there
      is no alternative, GIMP does not simply rely on the extension
      (such as ".jpg") to determine the file type, because extensions
      are not reliable:  they vary from system to system; any file can
      be renamed to have any extension; and there are many reasons why
      a file name might lack an extension.  Instead, GIMP first tries
      to recognize a file by examining its contents:  most of the
      commonly used graphics file formats have "magic headers" that
      permit them to be recognized.  Only if the magic yields no
      result does GIMP resort to using the extension.
    </para>
    
    <para id="gimp-file-open-by-extension" lang="zh_CN">
      当您打开文件，使用文件菜单或其它方式，GIMP 需要知道这个文件是什么格式。除非实在没有选择，不然 GIMP 并不是简单的靠文件扩展名(如“.jpg”)来决定文件格式，因为扩展名并不可靠：它们在各个系统中不同来;任何文件都可以改为其它的扩展名;由于很多原因一个文件会没有扩展名。而 GIMP 首先尝试检查其内容来了解是什么文件：大部分常用的图形文件格式都可以通过“magic headers”来被识别。只有那些无法识别的才会用到扩展名。
    </para>  

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect id='gimp-export-dialog'>
    <title lang="en">Saving Files</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>
    <anchor id='gimp-export-confirm-dialog' />

    <informalfigure pgwide="0">
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/export-dialog-en.png'
        format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>The Export dialog</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/export-dialog-en.png'
	format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>导出对话框</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>  
    </informalfigure>
    <para lang='en'>
      There is no file format, with the exception of GIMP's native <link
      linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> format, that is capable of
      storing all the data in a GIMP image.  When you ask to save an
      image in a format that will not completely represent it, GIMP
      notifies you of this, tells you what kind of information will be
      lost, and asks you whether you would like to "export" the image in
      a form that the file type can handle.  Exporting an image does not
      modify the image itself, so you do not lose anything by doing
      this.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了 GIMP 专用的 <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> 格式，没有其它一种格式可以保存 GIMP 图像中的所有信息。当您要将图像保存为一种无法完全表现其内容的格式时，GIMP 就会提醒您，并告诉您那些信息会丢失，是否愿意“输出”图像到该文件格式能处理的形式。输出一个图像并不修改图像本身，所以您不会因为这么做而丢失什么。
    </para> 
    <note lang='en'>
      When you close an image (possibly by
      quitting GIMP), you are warned if the image is "dirty"; that is,
      if it has been changed without subsequently being saved.  Saving
      an image in any file format will cause the image to be
      considered "not dirty", even if the file format does not
      represent all of the information from the image.
    </note>

    <note lang="zh_CN">
      当您关闭一个图像时(也许时退出 GIMP),如果该图像被改动后而未保存，即所谓的“脏”文件,这时您将被警告。当您将图像保存为某种格式后，这个文件就是"干净"的,即使该文件格式不能无法显示图像中的所有信息。
    </note>  
  </simplesect>

</sect1>
