<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-14 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-11-25 added enhanced Korean translation by Dust
  2006-09-12 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-11 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-fileformats" lang="de;en;es;cs;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="de;fr;ko;nl;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2006-02-25</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="fr">2006-03-12</date>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="ko">2006-06-21</date>
        <authorinitials lang="ko">Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="nl">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="nl">2006-06-02</date>
        <authorinitials lang="nl">HansdeJ</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="no">2007-01-27</date>
        <authorinitials lang="no">KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-14</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>


  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Files</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Bilddateien</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Archivos</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Soubory</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fichiers</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">File</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">파일</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Bestanden</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Filer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">文件</phrase>
  </title>


  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Files</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Bilddateien</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Archivos</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Soubory</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Fichiers</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>File</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>파일</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Bestanden</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Filer</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>文件</secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <para lang="en">
    The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is capable of reading and writing a large
    variety of graphics file formats.  With the exception of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native XCF file type, file handling is done by
    plug-ins.  Thus, it is relatively easy to extend <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    to new file types when the need arises.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ist imstande, viele Dateiformate schreiben und
    lesen zu können. Die meisten Formate werden von Plug-ins gelesen und
    geschrieben; die einzige Ausnahme bildet hier das
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-eigene
    <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>. Nachfolgend soll kurz auf
    Vor- und Nachteile beim Anlegen, Öffnen und Speichern von Dateien
    eingegangen werden.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El <acronym>GIMP</acronym> capaz de leer y escribir una gran variedad de
    archivos en formatos gráficos.  Con la excepsión del tipo de archivo
    nativo XCF, la gestión de formatos se realiza mediante complementos
    (plug-ins).  Esto significa que es relativamente fácil extender al
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> para que admita otros formatos de archivo cuando
    surje la necesidad.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> umí pracovat s velkým množstvím různých grafických
    souborových formátů. S výjimkou nativního formátu XCF je práce se soubory
    zajišťována zásuvnými moduly. Díky tomu je poměrně snadné v případě
    potřeby doplnit možnost práce s dalšími grafickými souborovými formáty.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sait lire et écrire une palette importante de
    formats de fichiers graphiques.  Hormis pour le format XCF natif du
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, la gestion des fichiers est assurée par des
    greffons. Il est ainsi facile d'introduire un nouveau type de
    fichier dans GIMP quand le besoin s'en fait sentir.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è in grado di leggere e scrivere una grande
    varietà di formati di file grafici. Con l'eccezione del tipo di file XCF
    nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, la gestione dei file viene effettuata
    tramite l'ausilio di speciali plug-in. Per questa ragione, è relativamente
    facile estendere <acronym>GIMP</acronym>  a nuovi formati di file, se ne
    sorgesse la necessità, aggiungendo un plugin appositamente sviluppato.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    <acronym>김프</acronym>는 굉장히 많은 그래픽 파일 포맷들을 읽고 쓸 수
    있습니다. <acronym>김프</acronym>의 기본 포맷인 XCF 파일을 제외한 다른
    파일 타입의 관리는 플러그인을 이용합니다. 따라서 새로운 파일 포맷을
    지원하도록 확장하는 것이 쉽습니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    kan een behoorlijke verscheidenheid aan grafische beeldopformaten inlezen.
    Behalve het eigen <acronym>XCF</acronym>-bestandsformaat, worden deze door
    <quote>plug-ins</quote>
    afgehandeld. Daarom is het erg makkelijk om mogelijkheden voor nieuwe
    bestandsformaten in te bouwen als dat nodig is.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan lese frå og skrive til eit uttal av
    ulike grafiske filformat. Med unnatak av <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt
    eige filformat, <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>, blir
    filhandteringa gjort med hjelpeprogram. Difor er det relativt enkelt å
    legge til nye format dersom behovet skulle dukka opp.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 有读写大量图像文件格式的能力。除了
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 专用的 XCF 文件格式外，其它的处理其它的格式都靠
    插件。因此，当需要让 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 支持新的文件格式时，就相对
    的比较容易。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    Not all file types are equally good for all purposes. This part of the
    documentation should help you understand the advantages and disadvantages
    of each type.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Všechny typy souborů se ale nehodí ke všem účelům. Tato část manuálu proto
    vysvětluje výhody a nevýhody jednotlivých formátů.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    Ningún tipo de archivo es bueno para ser usado en todos los casos.  Esta
    parte de la documentación lo ayudará a entender las ventajas y desventajas
    de cada tipo.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    En fonction du but, tous les types de fichier ne sont pas équivalents.
    Cette partie de la documentation devrait vous aider à comprendre les
    avantages et les inconvénients de chacun.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    I tipi di file non sono tutti uguali e soprattutto non sono adatti per
    ogni scopo. Questa parte della documentazione dovrebbe aiutare a
    comprendere vantaggi e svantaggi per ogni tipo di file.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    각 파일 포맷은 용도에 따라 쓰임새가 다릅니다. 여기에서는 각 포맷의 장단점에 대해 이야기할 것입니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    Niet alle bestandsformaten zijn even geschikt voor alle doeleinden. In dit
    deel van de handleiding proberen we u uit te leggen wat de sterke en
    zwakke punten van de verschillende formaten zijn.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Ikkje alle filtypane er like gode for alle føremål. I dette kapitlet vil
    vi prøve å vise fordeler og ulemper med dei vanlegaste typane.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    并不是所有的文件格式在各种情况下都一样。这部分将帮助您了解各种格式的优点和缺点。
  </para>


  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Saving Images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ukládání obrázků</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bilder speichern</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Guardado de imágenes</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Enregistrer des images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">opslaan van afbeeldingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Salvataggio delle immagini</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">이미지 저장하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Lagra bilete</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Сохранение изображений</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">保存图像</phrase>
      <phrase lang="hr">Pohraniti sliku</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      When you are finished working with an image, you will want to save the
      results. (In fact, it is often a good idea to save at intermediate
      stages too: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is a pretty robust program, but we have heard rumors, possibly
      apocryphal, that it may have been known on rare and mysterious occasions
      to crash.) Most of the file formats that <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      can open, can also be used for saving. There is one file format that is
      special, though: XCF is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native format, and is
      useful because it stores <emphasis>everything</emphasis> about an image
      (well, almost everything; it does not store <quote>undo</quote>
      information). Thus, the XCF format is especially suitable for saving
      intermediate results, and for saving images to be re-opened later in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      XCF files are not readable by most other programs that display images,
      so once you have finished, you will probably also want to save the image
      in a more widely used format, such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Když skončíte s úpravou obrázku, obvykle si budete chtít výsledek svého
      snažení uložit. (Ve skutečnosti se vyplatí ukládat i během práce. GIMP
      je sice velmi stabilní program, ale program, který nemůže spadnout za
      žádných okolností, skutečně neexistuje. Ani GIMP není výjimka.) Většinu
      formátů, které umí GIMP otevřít, lze použít i k ukládání obrázků.
      Nicméně jeden z formátů je obzvláště významný. Je to XCF, nativní formát
      Gimpu, který ukládá <emphasis>všechny informace</emphasis>
      o obrázku (s výjimkou dat pro funkci zpět/znovu a historii). XCF se
      proto výborně hodí zejména pro ukládání během práce nebo pro obrázky,
      které budou v budoucnu v Gimpu dále upravovány. Většina ostatních
      programů ale neumí soubory XCF otevřít, proto je vhodné po dokončení
      práce obrázek uložit také v některém rozšířenějším formátu, např. JPEG,
      PNG, TIFF a podobně.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie mit der Arbeit an einem Bild fertig sind, werden Sie Ihre
      Änderungen in der Regel speichern wollen. (Genaugenommen ist es eine
      gute Idee, auch während der Arbeit an dem Bild gelegentlich die
      Zwischenergebnisse zu speichern.) Die meisten der Dateiformate, welche
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      lesen kann, können Sie auch zum Speichern Ihrer Bilder verwenden.
      Allerdings sollten Sie auf jeden Fall beachten, welche speziellen
      Eigenschaften und Effekte das von Ihnen gewählte Dateiformat speichern
      kann. Es gibt nur genau ein Format in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, welches
      alle Funktionen und Effekte, die <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      Ihnen zur Verfügung stellt, auch in einer Datei speichern kann:
      <emphasis>XCF</emphasis>. Allerdings hat auch XCF einen Nachteil: Es
      gibt nicht allzuviele Programme außer <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      die XCF-Dateien lesen können. Es ist also eine gute Idee, Dateien,
      welche Sie weitergeben möchten, zusätzlich in einem anderen Dateiformat
      wie JPEG oder TIFF zu speichern.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Cuando haya terminado de trabajar con una imagen, querrá guardar los
      resultados. (de hecho, es a menudo una buena idea guardar también en
      etapas intermedias: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      es un programa completo y robusto, pero hemos escuchado algunos rumores,
      posiblemente apócrifos, de que en raras y misteriosas ocasiones se lo ha
      visto fallar). La mayoría de los formatos de archivo que el
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      puede abrir, también pueden ser usados para guardar. Hay, sin embargo,
      un formato de archivo que es especial: XCF es el formato nativo del
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      y es útil porque guarda todo lo que hay en una imagen (bueno, casi
      todo, no guarda la información de <quote>deshacer</quote>
      ). Por eso, el formato XCF es especialmente útil para guardar resultados
      intermedios de trabajos que van a volver a ser abiertos en el
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      Los archivos XCF no pueden ser leídos por la mayoría de otros
      programas que muestran imágenes, así que una vez que haya terminado,
      probablemente también querrá guardar la imagen en un formato usado más
      ampliamente, como JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Quand vous aurez fini votre travail sur une image vous voudrez
      sauvegarder le résultat (en fait, c'est une bonne habitude de
      sauvegarder durant les étapes intermédiaires : GIMP est un programme
      plutôt robuste, mais nous avons entendu des rumeurs, sans doute
      apocryphes, qu'il lui serait arrivé, dans de rares et mystérieuses
      occasions, de planter). La plupart des formats de fichier que GIMP sait
      ouvrir peuvent être utilisés pour l'enregistrement. L'un d'eux est
      spécial : XCF est le format natif de GIMP, et il est très utile
      puisqu'il sauvegarde <emphasis>tout</emphasis>
      d'une image (enfin, presque tout, les informations d'annulation ne sont
      pas enregistrées). Ainsi, le format XCF est parfait pour enregistrer les
      résultats intermédiaires, et pour enregistrer des images destinées à
      être réouvertes par le GIMP. Le format XCF n'étant pas exploité par la
      plupart des autres programmes qui affichent des images, vous voudrez
      probablement enregistrer vos images dans un format plus répandu, comme
      JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="hr">
      Kad završite s radom na jednoj slici sigurno ćete poželjeti sačuvati
      rezultat (u stvari pohranjivanje u tijeku same obrade slike, između
      određenih faza rada, jedna je jako dobra navika: iako je GIMP jedan vrlo
      otporan program, načuli smo od, zasigurno nevjerodostojnih izvora, da mu
      se ponekad zna dogoditi, u rijetkim i čudnim okolnostima, da padne).
      Većina tipova formata slika koje GIMP otvora mogu biti korišteni i za
      njihovo pohranjivanje. Jedan od tih formata je međutim poseban : XCF je
      format Gimpa i neizmjerno je koristan jer čuva <emphasis>sve</emphasis>
      informacije koje nosi jedna slika (ili gotovo sve, informacije o
      poništavanju nisu pohranjene). Format XCF je idealan za pohranjivanje
      <quote>među-rezultata</quote>
      onih slika koje su predviđene za rad jedino u Gimpu. Budući de se format
      XCF ne koristi u većini drugih programa za obradu slike, trebali bi ste
      pohraniti vaše slike i u jenom drugom korištenijem, formatu kao što je
      JPEG, PNG, TIFF, itd.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Quando si ha finito di lavorare su di un'immagine, in genere si desidera
      salvarla. In effetti è sempre una buona idea fare molti salvataggi
      intermedi, dato che, non si sa mai, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      potrebbe anche andare in crash (raro ma non impossibile) o potrebbe
      mancare la corrente. La maggior parte dei formati di file che
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      può aprire, possono essere usati anche per salvare. C'è un formato file
      che è speciale: l'XCF, il formato nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      molto utile perché memorizza
      <emphasis>quasi ogni informazione</emphasis>
      relativa all'immagine (non memorizza le modifiche intermedie per gli
      <quote>annullamenti</quote>
      ). Perciò il formato XCF è particolarmente interessante per i salvataggi
      delle versioni intermedie di lavoro e per salvare immagini che devono
      successivamente essere riaperte in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      I file XCF non sono leggibili dalla gran parte dei programmi di
      visualizzazione delle immagini perciò, una volta finito il lavoro, è
      conveniente salvare l'immagine in un formato di uso più diffuso come
      JPEG, PNG, TIFF, ecc.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이미지 편집을 완료했으면, 이제 결과를 저장해야 한다(사실 작업
      중간중간에 저장을 해두는 것이 좋다. <acronym>김프</acronym>는
      상당히 안정적인 프로그램이지만, 떠도는 말에 따르면 간혹 충돌을
      일으킬 수도 있다고 한다). 저장가능한 파일 포맷은
      <acronym>김프</acronym>로 열 수 있는 모든 포맷이다. 이 중에서
      XCF 파일은 조금 특별한데, 이것은 <acronym>김프</acronym> 고유의
      포맷이다. 이 포맷을 이용하면 이미지에 대한
      <emphasis>모든 정보</emphasis>를 저장할 수 있어 굉장히 유용하다
      (단, <quote>되돌리기</quote> 정보는 저장할 수 없다). 따라서
      이 XCF 포맷은 작업 중간에 저장하기에 적당한 포맷이고,
      또 나중에 <acronym>김프</acronym>로 다시 열어보기에도 좋다.
      하지만 대부분의 그래픽 뷰어에서는 이 포맷을 읽을 수 없으므로
      최종적인 결과물은 널리 사용되는 JPEG, PNG, TIFF 등의 포맷으로
      저장하는 것이 좋다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Wanneer u klaar bent met het bewerken van een afbeelding zult u het
      resultaat ervan op willen slaan. (Het is sowieso een goed idee om
      tijdens het bewerken regelmatig de tussenresultaten op te slaan.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is een behoorlijk robuust programma, maar we hebben geruchten gehoord,
      mogelijk nog uit de pre-historie, dat het in zeldzame en mysterieuze
      omstandigheden wel eens is vastgelopen of afgestort.) De meeste
      bestandsformaten die <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      kan lezen zijn ook de formaten waarin iets opgeslagen kan worden. Het
      <quote>eXperimental Computing Facility</quote>-formaat (XCF) neemt
      echter een speciale plaats in: XCF is het eigen formaat van
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en erg nuttig omdat hier
      <emphasis>alles</emphasis>
      over de afbeelding in opgeslagen wordt (behalve de de lijst van recente
      wijzigingen helaas). Het XCF-formaat is daarom bij uitstek geschikt om
      tussentijdse resultaten op te slaan van plaatjes die later nog met
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      verder bewerkt moeten worden. Veel andere grafische programma's kunnen
      het XCF-bestanden echter niet lezen. Dus als u afbeeldingen buiten
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      wilt gebruiken kunt u ze beter ook volgens een algemener gebruikt
      formaat als JPEG, PNG, TIFF , enz. opslaan.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Når du er ferdig med eit bilete, ønskjer du til vanleg å lagre dette.
      (Det er forresten ein god idé å lagre bilete innimellom også.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      er eit nokså robust program, men vi har høyrt rykte om at det ved
      sjeldne og mystiske tilfelle har krasja.) Som regel vil du lagra bileta
      i same formatet som dei blei opna i. Det kan likevel vere ein god regel
      å lagra i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      sitt eige filformat XCF medan du arbeider med biletet. Dette fordi
      nesten alle opplysningane om biletet og arbeidsgangen blir lagra
      samstundes. Einaste viktige som ikkje blir lagra samstundes er
      angrehistoria. XCF-filene kan, etter det vi kjenner til, ikkje lesast av
      andre program, så når biletet er ferdig, bør du lagra det i eit meir
      vanleg format som t.d. JPEG, PNG, TIFF, osv.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      По окончании работы вам нужно будет сохранить результат. (Кроме того,
      неплохо было бы сохранять изображение и на промежуточных стадиях: GIMP,
      конечно, весьма устойчивая программа, но ходят слухи, возможно
      недостоверные, что и у него случаются фатальные сбои.) Большинство
      форматов файлов, которые открываются с помощью GIMP, можно использовать
      и для сохранения. Обратите внимание на формат XCF: это родной формат
      GIMP, он полезен тем, что сохраняет <emphasis>всю</emphasis>
      информацию о изображении (ну, почти всю; он не сохраняет информацию
      "истории отмен"). Поэтому формат XCF особенно удобен для сохранения
      промежуточных результатов, и для тех изображений, которые позднее будут
      открыты в GIMP вновь. Файлы формата XCF не поддерживаются большинством
      программ для просмотра изображений, поэтому после окончания работы вам
      понадобится сохранить изображение в более распространенном формате,
      таком, как JPEG, PNG, TIFF, и т.д.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当修改完图像时，您想要保存其结果。(实际上，保存一些中间步骤常常是个好
      主意：GIMP 是非常健壮的程序，不过我们听说，也许是不可信的：发生罕见和
      难以解释的崩溃。)大部分 GIMP 能打开的文件格式，也能够保存。不过有一个
      特殊个文件格式：XCF 是 GIMP 内建的文件格式， 它非常有用因为它保存一个
      图像的所有信息(实际是几乎所有信息，它不保存“撤销”信息)。因此 XCF 特别
      适合保存中间步骤，以后再在 GIMP 中打开。不过 XCF 不能被大多数其它显示
      图像的程序读取，所有完成后，最好保存为更广泛使用的格式如 JPEG，PNG，
      TIFF等。
    </para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-export-dialog">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Saving Files</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Speichern von Bilddateien</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ukládání souborů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Guardar archivos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Enregistrer les fichiers</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Salvataggio dei file</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">파일 저장</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Opslaan van de afbeeldingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å lagra filer</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">保存文件</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      There are several commands for saving images. A list, and information on
      how to use them, can be found in the section covering the
      <link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">File menu</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Hay varias maneras de guardar las imágenes.  Un listado de estas, y la
      información necesaria sobre las mismas, se encuentra en la sección sobre
      <link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">el menú Archivo</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono diversi comandi per salvare le immagini. Un elenco e le
      corrispondenti informazioni su come usarli li si può trovare alla
      sezione che riguarda il
      <!--link linkend='gimp-image-window-menus-file' FIXME: it -->Menu
      file<!--/link-->.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      이미지를 저장하는 명령어는 여러가지가 있습니다. 그 방법들을 사용하는
      법은
      <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">파일
      메뉴</link> -->
      파일 메뉴에 설명되어 있습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Er zijn veel opdrachten om afbeeldingen op te slaan. In het hoofdstuk
      <!-- nl FIXME: link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file"-->Bestand
      menu<!--/link--> zult u meer informatie kunnen vinden welke dat zijn en
      hoe u ze kunt gebruiken.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan lagra biletfiler på fleire måtar. Du finn meir om dette i
      <!-- PENDING: no (menus -> menus-file.xml)
      <link linkend='gimp-image-window-menus-file'-->Filmenyen<!--/link-->
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      有许多保存图像的命令。关于其列表和如何使用它们的信息请看<link
      linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">文件菜单</link>这一节。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to save the images you create in a
      wide variety of formats.  It is important to realize that the only
      format capable of saving <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the information in
      an image, including layers, transparency, etc., is GIMP's native XCF
      format.   Every other format preserves some image properties and loses
      others.  When you save an image, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tries to let
      you know about this, but basically it is up to you to understand the
      capabilities of the format you choose.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bietet eine ganze Reihe von Dateiformaten,
      in denen Sie je nach Verwendung Ihre Bilder speichern können.
      Wichtig ist zu wissen, dass nur das <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-eigene
      Format <link linkend="gimp-xcf-open">XCF</link> imstande ist,
      alle Informationen wie Ebenen, Pfade, Transparenz, ohne Verluste
      zu speichern. Das heißt, dass nach dem nächsten Öffnen der
      Bilddatei alle Ihre angelegten Ebenen, Pfade, etc. noch vorhanden
      sind.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> permette di salvare le immagini che abbiamo
      creato in una varietà di formati. È importante ricordare che l'unico
      formato in grado di mantenere <emphasis>tutte</emphasis> le
      informazioni sull'immagine, inclusi livelli, trasparenze, ecc. è il
      formato nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> xcf. Ogni altro formato
      mantiene solo alcune informazioni sull'immagine mentre altre vanno
      perse. Quando si salva un'immagine, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tenta di
      ricordarvi questo fatto, ma è comunque compito dell'utente
      comprendere le capacitza del formato immagine che si sceglie.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym>를 이용하면 이미지를 다양한 포맷으로 저장할
      수가 있습니다. 하지만 레이어, 투명도 등 이미지의
      <emphasis>모든</emphasis> 정보를 저장할 수 있는 것은 김프 전용 포맷인
      XCF 뿐입니다. 다른 모든 포맷들은 특정 속성만 보존할뿐 나머지는 모두
      잃어버립니다. 이미지를 저장할때 <acronym>김프</acronym>에서 이러한 사실을
      알려주긴 하지만, 기본적으로 선택한 포맷의 특성은 사용자 자신이 이해하고
      있어야 합니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan lagra eit bilete i svært mange ulike format. Dei ulike
      formata kan lagra ulike opplysningar om biletet, men bare
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt eige filformat (<filename>XCF</filename>)
      lagrar <emphasis>alle</emphasis> dei viktigaste opplysningane om
      biletet. Ønskjer du å lagra eit bilete i eit anna format, vil
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> seie frå om at du kjem til å misse data,
      men sjølvsagt er det opp til deg å kjenne eigenskapane til det
      formatet du vel.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 让您保存图像为多种不同的格式。有一点需要重视：
      只有<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 内建的 XCF 格式才能保存图像中包括图层，透
      明度等的<emphasis>全部</emphasis>信息。其它的各种格式都是保存一些图像
      属性丢失一些。当您保存图像时，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 会让您告诉您这些，
      不过在原则上您需要了解一下您所选择格式的基本特性。
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Example of an Export dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Exportní dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Ansicht des Exportieren-Dialogs.</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Exemple de dialogue d'export</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Un'esempio di finestra di esportazione immagine
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">내보내기 대화상자 예제</phrase>
        <phrase lang="nl">Voorbeeld van een exporteer dialoogvenster</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på ein eksportdialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">导出对话框范例</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;de;es;zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/export-dialog-en.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/it/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="ko">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/ko/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="nl">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/nl/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      As stated above, there is no file format, with the exception of GIMP's
      native <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>
      format, that is capable of storing all the data in a
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      image. When you ask to save an image in a format that will not
      completely represent it, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      notifies you of this, tells you what kind of information will be lost,
      and asks you whether you would like to <quote>export</quote> the image
      in a form that the file type can handle. Exporting an image does not
      modify the image itself, so you do not lose anything by doing this. See
      <link linkend="export-file-dialog">Export file</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Kromě XCF, nativního formátu GIMPu, neexistuje žádný jiný formát, který
      by dokázal uchovat kompletní informace o obrázku. Pokud požádáte
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, aby uložil obrázek ve formátu, který ho
      nedokáže plně popsat, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vás upozorní, oznámí vám,
      jaké informace budou ztraceny (protože je není možné ve zvoleném formátu
      zaznamenat) a zeptá se, zda chcete obrázek exportovat do podoby, kterou
      lze v daném formátu uložit (tedy do podoby bez informací, které formát
      neumí popsat). Exportování ale nezmění vlastní otevřený obrázek v Gimpu,
      takže ten bude stále obsahovat informace všechny a můžete ho později
      uložit v jiném formátu, např. XCF.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wie bereits beschrieben, kann nur das
      <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>-Dateiformat alle
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-eigenen
      Informationen speichern. Wenn Sie ein anderes Format
      benutzen, werden Sie darauf hingewiesen, welche Informationen nicht
      gespeichert werden können. Da es sich meist um Zusatzinformationen
      handelt, die das Bild in seinem <quote>Aussehen</quote>
      nicht verändern, verlieren Sie keine wichtigen Bildbestandteile beim
      speichern in ein anderes Dateiformat.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Aucun format de fichier, hormis le format natif du
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>, n'est
      capable de contenir toutes les données d'une image
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Lorsque vous demandez d'enregistrer une image
      dans un format qui ne la représentera pas intégralement,
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vous le signale, en vous informant des
      informations qui seront perdues et en vous demandant si vous voulez
      <quote>exporter</quote> l'image dans une structure que le format de
      fichier supportera. Exporter une image ne modifie pas l'image elle-même,
      aussi ne perdez-vous rien en faisant cela. Voyez
      <link linkend="export-file-dialog">Exporter un fichier</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Come detto sopra, non c'è formato file, con l'eccezione del formato
      nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> <!--link linkend="gimp-xcf-save" FIXME it
      -->XCF<!--/link-->, in grado di memorizzare tutti i dati di un'immagine
      di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Quando si richiede di salvare un'immagine in
      un formato che non la rappresenta completamente, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      lo segnala, elencando le informazioni che verranno perse, e chiede se si
      vuole "esportare" l'immagine in una forma che il formato di file possa
      gestire. L'esportazione di un'immagine non modifica l'immagine originale
      perciò non si perde nulla nell'operazione.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      앞서 말한 것과 같이, <acronym>김프</acronym> 이미지의 모든 정보를
      저장할 수 있는 것은 김프 전용 포맷인
      <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> 뿐입니다. 그 외의 포맷으로
      저장을 하려고 하면 <acronym>김프</acronym> 는 어떠한 정보가 손실될 것인지
      알려주며, 해당 파일 타입으로 이미지로 "내보내기" 를 할 것인지 묻습니다.
      내보내기 작업은 원본 이미지에는 아무런 변형을 가하지 않으므로, 이 작업
      자체만으로는 어떠한 정보도 손실되지 않습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Zoals we hierboven al opmerkten kan alleen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
      eigen <!-- XXX_NL link linkend="gimp-xcf-save"-->XCF<!--/link--> opmaak
      alle informatie van een <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-afbeelding opslaan. Als
      u deze dus in een andere opmaak opslaat, laat  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> u
      eerst weten dat, en welke informatie er verloren zal gaan en u vragen of
      u accoord gaat met de manier waarop er met dit informatieverlies
      omgegaan wordt. Het exporteren veranderd niets aan de afbeelding zelf,
      dus hierin gaat geen informatie verloren (tot u de afbeelding sluit en
      er op dat moment geen <acronym>XCF</acronym>-versie van opgeslagen heeft
      natuurlijk.)
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Som sagt ovanfor, er det bare filformatet
      <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> som tar vare på (nesten)
      alle data i eit bilete. Prøver du å lagra eit bilete i eit format som
      ikkje tar vare på informasjonen i biletet, vil <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      åtvara deg med ei melding om dette, og kva for data som går tapt
      dersom du likevel nyttar det valde formatet. Du får også eit spørsmål
      om du heller vil <quote>eksportera</quote> biletet. Når du eksporterar
      eit bilete, blir sjølve biletet ikkje forandra.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      正如上面所说的，除了 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 专用的 <link
      linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> 格式，没有其它一种格式可以保存
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 图像中的所有信息。当您要将图像保存为一种无法完
      全表现其内容的格式时，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 就会提醒您，并告诉您那些
      信息会丢失，是否愿意“输出”图像到该文件格式能处理的形式。输出一个图像并
      不修改图像本身，所以您不会因为这么做而丢失什么。
    </para>

    <note lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
      <para lang="en">
        When you close an image (possibly by
        quitting GIMP), you are warned if the image is "dirty"; that is,
        if it has been changed without subsequently being saved.  Saving
        an image in any file format will cause the image to be
        considered "not dirty", even if the file format does not
        represent all of the information from the image.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        Předtím, než zavřete obrázek (například ukončením Gimpu), vás GIMP
        varuje, pokud je obrázek tzv. nečistý., tj. byl od posledního uložení
        změněn. Uložení obrázku ho učiní čistým, a to i v případě, že zvolený
        formát neuchovává úplnou informaci o obrázku.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie ein Bild schließen (etwa, weil Sie GIMP beenden), erhalten
        Sie eine Warnung, dass das Bild verändert und nicht gesichert wurde.
        Ein Bild, das in irgendeinem Format gespeichert wurde, wird als
        unverändert angesehen, auch wenn das gewählte Dateiformat nicht
        alle Informationen zu diesem Bild enthält.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Lorsque vous fermez une image (par exemple en quittant GIMP), vous
        êtes prévenu si l'image a été modifiée sans être enregistrée. Une
        image n'est plus considérée comme modifiée dès qu'elle est
        enregistrée.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Quando si chiude un'immagine (probabilmente uscendo da GIMP), si
        viene avvertiti se l'immagine è "sporca"; cioè, se è stata
        modificata senza successivamente essere salvata. Salvando
        un'immagine in qualsiasi formato file, farà in modo di far
        considerare a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> l'immagine come "non sporca",
        anche se il formato file non garantisce il salvataggio di tutte le
        informazioni che compongono l'immagine.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        이미지를 닫을 때(혹은 김프를 종료할 때) 해당 이미지가 "변경된"
        것이라면(변경된 후에 저장이 되지 않은), 경고가 나타납니다.
        그리고 어떠한 형태의 파일 포맷이든 저장을 하게 되면, 이미지가 가지고 있는
        모든 정보를 보전하지 못하더라도 이미지는 "변경되지 않은" 이미지로
        간주되어집니다.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        Wanneer u een afbeelding afsluit en deze <quote>vuil</quote> is wordt
        u hiervoor gewaarschuwd. Een <quote>vuile</quote> afbeelding is een
        afbeelding waarop wijzigingen zijn aangebracht die nog niet opgeslagen
        zijn. Zodra u de afbeelding in een willekeurig formaat opslaat (dus
        ook formaten waarbij informatie verloren gaat) veranderd de status
        naar <quote>niet vuil</quote>.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Når du lukker eit bilete t.d. ved å avslutta <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
        vil du få opp ei melding dersom biletet er <quote>ureint</quote>,
        dvs. at biletet er endra utan å bli lagra etterpå. Lagrar du eit
        bilete, vil biletet etter lagringa bli sett på som
        <quote>reint</quote>, sjølv om filformatet du valde ikkje lagrar alle
        biletdata.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
      当您关闭一个图像时(也许时退出 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>),如果该图像被改
      动后而未保存，即所谓 的“脏”文件,这时您将被警告。当您将图像保存为某种格
      式后，这个文件就是"干 净"的,即使该文件格式不能无法显示图像中的所有信息。
      </para>

    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
