<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-fileformats'>
  <title lang="en">Files</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">文件</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Files</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">文件</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The Gimp is capable of reading and writing a large variety of
    graphics file formats.   With the exception of Gimp's native XCF
    file type, file handling is done by plug-ins.  Thus, it is
    relatively easy to extend Gimp to new file types when the need
    arises. 
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    Gimp有读写大量图像文件格式的能力。除了Gimp专用的XCF文件格式外，其它
    的处理其它的格式都靠插件。因此，当需要让Gimp支持新的文件格式时，就
    相对的比较容易。
  </para>
  
  <para lang="en">
    Not all file types are equally good for all purposes.  This part
    of the documentation should help you understand the advantages and
    disadvantages of each type.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    并不是所有的文件格式在各种情况下都一样。这部分将帮助你了解各种格式的
    优点和缺点。
  </para>  

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>
    <para id="gimp-file-open-by-extension" lang="en">
      When you open a file, using the File menu or any other method,
      Gimp needs to determine what type of file it is.  Unless there
      is no alternative, Gimp does not simply rely on the extension
      (such as ".jpg") to determine the file type, because extensions
      are not reliable:  they vary from system to system; any file can
      be renamed to have any extension; and there are many reasons why
      a file name might lack an extension.  Instead, Gimp first tries
      to recognize a file by examining its contents:  most of the
      commonly used graphics file formats have "magic headers" that
      permit them to be recognized.  Only if the magic yields no
      result does Gimp resort to using the extension.
    </para>
    
    <para id="gimp-file-open-by-extension" lang="zh_CN">
      当你打开文件，使用文件菜单或其它方式，Gimp需要知道这个文件是什么
      格式。除非实在没有选择，不然Gimp并不是简单的靠文件扩展名(如".jpg")
      来决定文件格式，因为扩展名并不可靠：它们在各个系统中不同来;任何文
      件都可以改为其它的扩展名;由于很多原因一个文件会没有扩展名。而Gimp
      首先尝试检查其内容来了解是什么文件：大部分常用的图形文件格式都可以
      通过"magic headers"来被识别。只有那些无法识别的才会用到扩展名。
    </para>  
    <informalfigure pgwide="0">
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/export-dialog-en.png'
        format='png'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>The Export dialog</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/export-dialog-en.png'
	format='png'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>导出对话框</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>  
    </informalfigure>
    <para lang='en'>
      There is no file format, with the exception of Gimp's native <link
      linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> format, that is capable of
      storing all the data in a Gimp image.  When you ask to save an
      image in a format that will not completely represent it, Gimp
      notifies you of this, tells you what kind of information will be
      lost, and asks you whether you would like to "export" the image in
      a form that the file type can handle.  Exporting an image does not
      modify the image itself, so you do not lose anything by doing
      this.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了Gimp专用的<link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>格式，没有其它一种
      格式可以保存Gimp图像中的所有信息。当你要将图像保存为一种无法完全表现其内
      容的格式时，Gimp就会提醒你，并告诉你那些信息会丢失，是否愿意"输出"图像到
      该文件格式能处理的形式。输出一个图像并不修改图像本身，所以你不会因为这么
      做而丢失什么。
    </para> 
    <note lang='en'>
      When you close an image (possibly by
      quitting Gimp), you are warned if the image is "dirty"; that is,
      if it has been changed without subsequently being saved.  Saving
      an image in any file format will cause the image to be
      considered "not dirty", even if the file format does not
      represent all of the information from the image.
    </note>

    <note lang="zh_CN">
      当你关闭一个图像时(也许时退出Gimp),如果该图像被改动后而未保存，即所谓的"脏"
      文件,这时你将被警告。当你将图像保存为某种格式后，这个文件就是"干净"的,即使
      该文件格式不能无法显示图像中的所有信息。
    </note>  
  </simplesect>

</sect1>
