<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2015-12-21 j.h: fixed bug #691579: save color values from transparent pixels (PNG)
  2007-10-06 ude: added description for "quality settings from original image"
  2007-07-15 lexa: added PackBits description
  2007-03-19 lexa: added description for save dialogs for jpeg gif png and tif

-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-fileformats">
  <title>Files</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Files</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is capable of reading and writing a large
    variety of graphics file formats. With the exception of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native XCF file format, file handling is done by
    plug-ins. This makes it relatively easy to extend <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    to support new file types when the need arises.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="save-export-image">
    <title>Save / Export Images</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Save/Export Images</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Images</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <note>
      <para>
        When you open an image, let's say in JPG or PNG file format, it is
        imported into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s own XCF format, as a new project.
      </para>
      <para>
        For example, a <quote>sunflower.png</quote> image will be loaded as
        <quote>*[sunflower] (imported)-1.0 (indexed color, 1 layer)</quote>.
        The leading asterisk indicates that this file has been changed. This
        image can be saved as <quote>sunflower.xcf</quote> by using the
        <command>Save</command> command. If you need your image in another
        format, you should use the <command>Export</command> command.
       </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      When you are finished working with an image, you will save the results.
      In fact, it is often a good idea to save at intermediate stages too.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a pretty robust program, but on rare occasions
      crashes have happened.
    </para>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native format XCF is special. It is the only
      format that can store <emphasis>everything</emphasis> about an image
      (with the exception of <quote>undo</quote> information).
      This is the reason that saving can only be done in this format.
      It makes the XCF format especially suited for storing intermediate
      results, and for saving images to be re-opened later in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para>
      XCF files are not readable by most other programs that display images.
      Once you have finished editing your image, you can export it to the
      format of your choice.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> supports a wide range of formats. Most file
      formats that can be imported, can also be used for exporting.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-export-dialog">
    <title>File Formats</title>
    <para>
      There are several commands for <emphasis>saving</emphasis> and <emphasis>
      exporting</emphasis> images. They are listed in the section covering
      the <link linkend="gimp-file-menu">File Menu</link>. More information on
      how to use them can be found there.
    </para>
    <para><acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to <emphasis>export</emphasis> the
      images you create in a wide variety of formats. It is important to
      realize that the only format capable of saving <emphasis>all</emphasis> of
      the information in an image, including layers, transparency, etc., is
      GIMP's native XCF format. Every other format preserves some image
      properties and loses others. It is up to you to understand the
      capabilities of the format you choose.
    </para>
    <para>
      Exporting an image does not modify the image itself, so you do not lose
      anything by exporting. See
      <link linkend="gimp-export-dialog">Export file</link>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        When you close an image (possibly by quitting GIMP), you are warned if
        the image has been changed without subsequently being saved (an asterisk
        is in front of the image name in the title bar of the main window).
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
