<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-04-03 Mr.Dust : added 'ko' for some missing part
  2007-10-06 ude: added description for "quality settings from original image"
  2007-07-15 lexa: added PackBits description
  2007-03-19 lexa: added description for save dialogs for jpeg gif png and tif
  2007-02-14 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-11-25 added enhanced Korean translation by Dust
  2006-09-12 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-11 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-fileformats">
  <sect1info>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-06</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>
  <title>
    <phrase>Files</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Files</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is capable of reading and writing a large
    variety of graphics file formats.  With the exception of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native XCF file type, file handling is done by
    Plugins.  Thus, it is relatively easy to extend <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    to new file types when the need arises.
  </para>
  <para>
    Not all file types are equally good for all purposes. This part of the
    documentation should help you understand the advantages and disadvantages
    of each type.
  </para>
  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase>Saving Images</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      When you are finished working with an image, you will want to save the
      results. (In fact, it is often a good idea to save at intermediate
      stages too: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is a pretty robust program, but we have heard rumors, possibly
      apocryphal, that it may have been known on rare and mysterious occasions
      to crash.) Most of the file formats that <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      can open, can also be used for saving. There is one file format that is
      special, though: XCF is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native format, and is
      useful because it stores <emphasis>everything</emphasis> about an image
      (well, almost everything; it does not store <quote>undo</quote>
      information). Thus, the XCF format is especially suitable for saving
      intermediate results, and for saving images to be re-opened later in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      XCF files are not readable by most other programs that display images,
      so once you have finished, you will probably also want to save the image
      in a more widely used format, such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-export-dialog">
    <title>
      <phrase>Saving Files</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      There are several commands for saving images. A list, and information on
      how to use them, can be found in the section covering the
      <link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">File Menu</link>.
    </para>
    <para><acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to save the images you create in a
      wide variety of formats.  It is important to realize that the only
      format capable of saving <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the information in
      an image, including layers, transparency, etc., is GIMP's native XCF
      format.   Every other format preserves some image properties and loses
      others.  When you save an image, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tries to let
      you know about this, but basically it is up to you to understand the
      capabilities of the format you choose.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>Example of an Export dialog</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/export-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      As stated above, there is no file format, with the exception of GIMP's
      native <link linkend="glossary-xcf">XCF</link> format, that is capable
      of storing all the data in a <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      image. When you ask to save an image in a format that will not
      completely represent it, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      notifies you of this, tells you what kind of information will be lost,
      and asks you whether you would like to <quote>export</quote> the image
      in a form that the file type can handle. Exporting an image does not
      modify the image itself, so you do not lose anything by doing this. See
      <link linkend="gimp-export-dialog">Export file</link>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        When you close an image (possibly by quitting GIMP), you are warned if
        the image is "dirty"; that is, if it has been changed without
        subsequently being saved. Saving an image in any file format will
        cause the image to be considered "not dirty", even if the file format
        does not represent all of the information from the image.
      </para>
    </note>
    <sect3 id="file-gif-save">
      <title>
        <phrase>Saving as GIF</phrase>
      </title>
      <anchor id="file-gif-load" xreflabel="GIF"/>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>GIF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>.gif</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Save as GIF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>GIF</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase>The GIF Save dialog</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/gif-save-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <warning>
        <para>
          Please note, that the GIF file format is incapable of storing some
          rather basic image informations like
          <emphasis>print resolution</emphasis>.
          If you care for these properties, you should consider a different
          file format like PNG.
        </para>
      </warning>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GIF Options</term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Interlace</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    When this option is checked, the image will be displayed
                    progressively on the Web page. It was interesting when
                    computers and modems were slow, as it allowed to stop
                    loading an image of no interest.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>GIF comment</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Beware of do not insert characters outside the ASCII
                    range, because of the GIF format supports 7-bits ASCII
                    texts only, that GIMP can't provide. If you insert
                    inadvertently a non-ASCII char, the option will be
                    automatically disabled.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Animated GIF Options</term>
          <listitem>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Animation</primary>
              <secondary>Animated GIF options</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Loop forever</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    When this option is checked the animation will start
                    playing again repeatedly until you stop it.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Delay between frames if unspecified</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    You can set the delay, in millisecondes, between frames
                    if it has not been set before. In this case, you can
                    modify every delay in the Layer Dialog.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Frame disposal when unspecified</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If this has not been set before, you can set how frames
                    will be superimposed. You can select among three options :
                  </para>
                  <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>I don't care</guilabel>
                        : you can use this option if all your layers are
                        opaque. Layers will overwrite what is beneath.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>Cumulative Layers (combine)</guilabel>
                        : previous frames will not be deleted when a new one
                        is displayed.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>One frame per layer (replace)</guilabel>
                        : previous frames will be deleted before displaying a
                        new frame.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="file-jpeg-save">
      <title>
        <phrase>Saving as JPEG</phrase>
      </title>
      <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" xreflabel="JPEG"/>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>JPEG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>.jpg</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>.jpeg</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Save as JPEG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>JPEG</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg. It is a
        very widely used format, because it compresses images very
        efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality. No other
        format comes close to achieving the same level of compression. It does
        not, however, support transparency or multiple layers. For this
        reason, saving images as JPEG often requires them to be exported from
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase>The JPEG Save dialog</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/save-jpeg-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering number
        of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this documentation.
        Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality parameter is probably the
        only one you will need to adjust.
      </para>
      <para>
        <caution>
          <para>
            After you save an image as a JPEG file, the image is no longer
            considered <quote>dirty</quote> by <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
            so unless you make further changes to it, you will not receive
            any warning if you close it. Because JPEG is lossy and does not
            support transparency or multiple layers, some of the information
            in the image might then be lost. If you want to save all of the
            information in an image, use <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native
            <link linkend="glossary-xcf">XCF format</link>.
          </para>
        </caution>
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Quality</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              When you save a file in JPEG format, a dialog is displayed
              that allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 0
              to 100. Values above 95 are generally not useful, though. The
              default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, but
              in many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
              lower without noticeably degrading the image. You can test the
              effect of different quality settings by checking
              <guilabel>Show Preview in image window</guilabel>
              in the JPEG dialog.
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                Please note, that the numbers for the JPEG quality level have
                a different meaning. Saving with a level of 80 in GIMP is not
                necessarily comparable with saving with a level of 80 in an
                different application.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Preview in image window</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Checking this option causes each change in quality (or any other
              JPEG parameter) to be shown in the image display. (This does not
              alter the image, though: it reverts back to its original state
              when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Advanced settings</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Some information about the advanced settings:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Optimize</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If you enable this option, the optimization of entropy
                    encoding parameters will be used.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Progressive</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    With this option enabled the chunks of the image will be
                    inserted in a certain order in the file. This is done with
                    the intent to give a progressive refinement of the image
                    appearance during a slow connection web download, similar
                    and with the same purpose of the corresponding option
                    present in the GIF format too. The downside of enabling
                    this option is, that you get slightly larger files.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save EXIF data</term>
                <listitem>
                  <indexterm>
                    <primary>EXIF</primary>
                  </indexterm>
                  <para>
                    JPEG files from many digital cameras contain extra
                    information, called EXIF data, which specifies camera
                    settings and other information concerning the
                    circumstances under which the image was created. GIMP's
                    ability to handle EXIF data depends on whether the
                    <quote>libexif</quote>
                    library is available on your system; it is not
                    automatically packaged with GIMP. If GIMP was built with
                    libexif support, then EXIF data is preserved if you open a
                    JPEG file, work with the resulting image, and then save it
                    as JPEG. The EXIF data is not altered in any way when you
                    do this (which means that some of its fields are no longer
                    valid). If GIMP was not built with EXIF support, this does
                    not prevent files with EXIF data from being opened, but it
                    does mean that the EXIF data will not be present when the
                    resulting image is later saved.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save Preview</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This option lets you save a thumbnail with the image.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save XMP data</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If you enable this option, the meta data of the image will
                    be saved as <acronym>XMP</acronym>-structure within the
                    file.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>
                  Use quality settings from original image
                </term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If a particular quality setting (or
                    <quote>quantization table</quote>
                    ) was attached to the image when it was loaded, then this
                    option allows you to use them instead of the standard
                    ones.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    If you have only made a few changes to the image, then
                    re-using the same quality setting will give you almost the
                    same quality and file size as the original image. This
                    will minimize the losses caused by the quantization step,
                    compared to what would happen if you used different
                    quality setting.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    If the quality setting found in the original file are not
                    better than your default quality settings, then the option
                    <quote>Use quality settings from original image</quote>
                    will be available but not enabled. This ensures that you
                    always get at least the minimum quality specified in your
                    defaults. If you did not make major changes to the image
                    and you want to save it using the same quality as the
                    original, then you can do it by enabling this option.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Smoothing</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Compression can create artefacts. By using this option,
                    you can smooth the image when saving, reducing them. But
                    your image becomes somewhat blurred.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Restart markers</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The image file can include some markers which allow to
                    segment it. If loading this image in a Web page is broken
                    off, loading can resume from the following marker.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Subsampling</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Human eye is not sensitive in the same way all over color
                    spectrum. Compression can use this to consider as
                    identical slightly different colors. Three methods are
                    available :
                  </para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>1x1,1x1,1x1 (best quality)</guilabel>
                        : preserves borders and contrasting colors, but
                        compression is less.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>2x1,1x1,1x1 (4:2:2)</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>1x2,1x1,1x1</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>2x2,1x1,1x1 (smallest file)</guilabel>
                        : important compression; suits images with weak
                        borders but tends to denature colors.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>DCT Method</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    DCT is <quote>discrete cosine transform</quote>,
                    and it is the first step in the JPEG algorithm going
                    from the spatial to the frequency domain. The choices are
                    <quote>float</quote>, <quote>integer</quote>
                    (the default), and <quote>fast integer</quote>.
                  </para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>float</guilabel>
                        : The float method is very slightly more accurate than
                        the integer method, but is much slower unless your
                        machine has very fast floating-point hardware. Also
                        note that the results of the floating-point method may
                        vary slightly across machines, while the integer
                        methods should give the same results everywhere.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>integer</guilabel>
                        (the default): This method is faster than
                        <quote>float</quote>, but not as accurate.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guilabel>fast integer</guilabel>
                        : The fast integer method is much less accurate than
                        the other two.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Image comments</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    In this text box, you can enter a comment which will be
                    saved with the image.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="file-png-save">
      <title>
        <phrase>Saving as PNG</phrase>
      </title>
      <anchor id="file-png-load" xreflabel="PNG"/>
      <anchor id="file-png-save-defaults" xreflabel="PNG"/>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Save as PNG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>PNG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>PNG</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase>
            The <quote>Save as PNG</quote> dialog
          </phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/save-png-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Interlacing</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              When this option is checked, the image is progressively
              displayed on a Web page. So, slow computer users can stop
              downloading if they are not interested.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save background color</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If your image has many transparency levels, the Internet
              browsers which recognize only two levels, will use the
              background color of your Toolbox instead. But Internet Explorer
              up to version 6 did not use these informations.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save gamma</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Informations about your monitor will be saved, so that the
              image will be displayed in the same way on other computers,
              provided that the display program supports these
              informations, what is rarely the case.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save layer offset</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
               No interest. Images with layers are flattened before saving
               to PNG and layer offset is taken in account.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save Resolution</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Save the image resolution, in dpi (dot per inch).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save creation time</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              That will be the date of last saving.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save comment</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can read this comment in the <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para><!-- modified 2007-05-01 -->
              With this option is checked, the color values are saved even if the
              pixels are completely transparent.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Compression level</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Since compression is not lossy, the only reason to use a
              compression level less than 9 would be a too long time to
              compress file on a slow computer. Nothing to fear from
              decompression: it is as quick whatever the compression level.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save defaults</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you click on this button, your settings will be saved and
              can be used by other savings by clicking on the
              <guibutton>Load defaults</guibutton>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <note>
        <para>
          Since PNG format supports indexed images, you have better reduce the
          number of colors before saving if you want to have the lightest file
          for the Web. See <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Computers work on 8 bits blocks named <quote>Byte</quote>.
          A byte allows 256 colors. Reducing the number of colors below 256
          is not useful: a byte will be used anyway and the file size will not
          be less. More, this <quote>PNG8</quote>
          format, like GIF, uses only one bit for transparency; only two
          transparency levels are possible, transparent or opaque.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you want PNG transparency to be fully displayed by Internet
          Explorer, you can use the AlphaImageLoader DirectX filter in the
          code of your Web page. See Microsoft Knowledge Base
          <xref linkend="bibliography-online-microsoft-kb294714"/>.
          Please note, that this should not be necessary for
          InternetExplorer 7 and above.
        </para>
      </note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="file-tiff-save">
      <title>
        <phrase>Saving as TIFF</phrase>
      </title>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase>The TIFF Save dialog</phrase>
        </title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Save as TIFF</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>TIFF</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Formats</primary>
          <secondary>TIFF</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/save-tiff-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Compression</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This option give you the opportunity to choose the compression
              method that is appropriate for your image:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>None</guilabel> : fast method, but resulting in
                  a big file.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>LZW</guilabel> : The image will be compressed
                  using the <quote>Lempel-Ziv-Welch</quote> algorithm, a
                  lossless compression technique. This is an old method,
                  still efficient and fast. More informations at
                  <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-lzw"/>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Pack Bits</guilabel> : is a fast, simple
                  compression scheme for run-length encoding of data. Apple
                  introduced the PackBits format with the release of
                  MacPaint on the Macintosh computer. A PackBits data
                  stream consists of packets of one byte of header followed
                  by data. (Source: <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-packbits"/>)
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Deflate</guilabel>: It is a lossless data
                  compression algorithm that uses a combination of the LZ77
                  algorithm and Huffman coding. It is also used in Zip, 
                  Gzip and PNG file formats. Source: <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deflate">Wikipedia</ulink>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>JPEG</guilabel>: this is a very good
                  compression algorithm but lossy.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>CCITT Group 3 fax</guilabel>;
                  <guilabel>CCITT Group 4 fax</guilabel></para>
                <note>
                  <para>
                    These options can only be selected, if the image is in
                    indexed mode and reduced to two colors.
                  </para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para><!-- added 2007-07-01 -->
              With this option the color values are saved even if the pixels
              are completely transparent.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Comment</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In this text box, you can enter a comment which will be
              associated with the image.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
