<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-fileformats'>
  <title lang="en">Files</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Files</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The Gimp is capable of reading and writing a large variety of
    graphics file formats.   With the exception of Gimp's native XCF
    file type, file handling is done by plug-ins.  Thus, it is
    relatively easy to extend Gimp to new file types when the need
    arises. 
  </para>
  <para>
    Not all file types are equally good for all purposes.  This part
    of the documentation should help you understand the advantages and
    disadvantages of each type.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <para lang="en">
      When you open a file, using the File menu or any other method,
      Gimp needs to determine what type of file it is.  Unless there
      is no alternative, Gimp does not simply rely on the extension
      (such as ".jpg") to determine the file type, because extensions
      are not reliable:  they vary from system to system; any file can
      be renamed to have any extension; and there are many reasons why
      a file name might lack an extension.  Instead, Gimp first tries
      to recognize a file by examining its contents:  most of the
      commonly used graphics file formats have "magic headers" that
      permit them to be recognized.  Only if the magic yields no
      result does Gimp resort to using the extension.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is no file format, with the exception of Gimp's native XCF
      format, that is capable of storing all the data in a Gimp
      image.  When you ask to save an image in a format that will not
      completely represent it, Gimp notifies you of this, tells you
      what kind of information will be lost, and asks you whether you
      would like to "export" the image in a form that the file type
      can handle.  Exporting an image does not modify the image
      itself, so you do not lose anything by doing this.
    </para>
    <tip>
      A caution, though:  when you close an image (possibly by
      quitting Gimp), you are warned if the image is "dirty"; that is,
      if it has been changed without subsequently being saved.  Saving
      an image in any file format will cause the image to be
      considered "not dirty", even if the file format does not
      represent all of the information from the image.
    </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-file-save-xcf">
    <title lang="en">XCF</title>
    <anchor id="gimp-file-open-xcf" />
    <para lang="en">
      The XCF file type is special because it is Gimp's native file
      type:  that is, it was designed specifically to store all of the
      data that goes to make up a Gimp image.  Because of this,
      XCF files may be quite complicated, and there are few programs
      other than Gimp that can read them.  
    </para>
    <para>
      When an image is stored as an XCF file, the file encodes nearly
      everything there is to know about the image:  the pixel data for
      each of the layers, the current selection, additional channels
      if there are any, paths if there are any, and guides.  The most
      important thing that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> saved in an XCF
      file is the undo history.
    </para>
    <para>
      The pixel data in an XCF file is represented in a raw,
      uncompressed form: each byte of image data equals one byte in
      the XCF file.  Thus, XCF files for even modestly sized images
      can be quite large:  for example, a 1000x1000 RGB image with 3
      layers will produce an XCF file of over 10 megabytes.  It is not
      at all difficult to get XCF files of over 100 megabytes.
      Fortunately, although XCF files do not intrinsically compress
      their data, Gimp allows you to compress the files themselves,
      using either the gzip or bzip2 compression methods, both of
      which are fast, efficient, and freely available.  Compressing an
      XCF file will often shrink it by a factor of 10 or more.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Gimp developers have made a great effort to keep the XCF
      file format compatible across versions.  If you create a file
      using Gimp 2.0, it ought to be possible to open the file in Gimp
      1.2.  However, some of the information in the file may not be
      usable:  for example, Gimp 2.0 has a much more sophisticated way
      of handling text than Gimp 1.2, so a text layer from a Gimp 2.0
      XCF file will appear as an ordinary image layer if the file is
      opened in Gimp 1.2.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-jpeg-save">
    <title lang="en">JPEG</title>
    <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-png-save">
    <title lang="en">PNG</title>
    <anchor id="file-png-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-tiff-save">
    <title lang="en">TIFF</title>
    <anchor id="file-tiff-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-gif-save">
    <title lang="en">GIF</title>
    <anchor id="file-gif-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-psd-save">
    <title lang="en">PSD</title>
    <anchor id="file-psd-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-ps-save">
    <title lang="en">Postscript</title>
    <anchor id="file-ps-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-pdf-save">
    <title lang="en">PDF</title>
    <anchor id="file-pdf-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-psp-save">
    <title lang="en">PSP</title>
    <anchor id="file-psp-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-tga-save">
    <title lang="en">TGA</title>
    <anchor id="file-tga-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="file-bmp-save">
    <title lang="en">BMP</title>
    <anchor id="file-bmp-load" />
    <para lang="en">
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
