<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-03-23 j.h: update to v2.8
  2007-10-06 ude: added description for "quality settings from original image"
  2007-07-15 lexa: added PackBits description
  2007-03-19 lexa: added description for save dialogs for jpeg gif png and tif
  2006-07-11 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-fileformats">
  <title>Files</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Files</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is capable of reading and writing a large
    variety of graphics file formats.  With the exception of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native XCF file type, file handling is done by
    Plugins.  Thus, it is relatively easy to extend <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    to support new file types when the need arises.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="save-export-image">
    <title>Save / Export Images</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Save/Export Images</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Export Images</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <note>
      <para>
        In former <acronym>GIMP</acronym> releases, when you loaded an image in
        some format, let us say JPG or PNG, the image kept its format and
        was saved in the same format by <command>Save</command>. With
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.8, images are loaded, imported, in the XCF
        format as a new project. For example, a <quote>sunflower.png</quote>
        image will be loaded as <quote>*[sunflower] (imported)-1.0 (indexed
        color, 1 layer)</quote>. The leading asterisk indicates that this file
        has been changed. This image will be saved as
        <quote>sunflower.xcf</quote> by <command>Save</command>. To save this
        image in a format other than XCF, you must use
        <command>Export</command>.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      When you are finished working with an image, you will want to save the
      results. (In fact, it is often a good idea to save at intermediate
      stages too: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is a pretty robust program, but we have heard rumors, possibly
      apocryphal, that it may have been known on rare and mysterious occasions
      to crash.) Most of the file formats that <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      can open, can also be used for saving. There is one file format that is
      special, though: XCF is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native format, and is
      useful because it stores <emphasis>everything</emphasis> about an image
      (well, almost everything; it does not store <quote>undo</quote>
      information). Thus, the XCF format is especially suitable for saving
      intermediate results, and for saving images to be re-opened later in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      XCF files are not readable by most other programs that display images,
      so once you have finished, you will probably also want to export the image
      in a more widely used format, such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-export-dialog">
    <title>File Formats</title>
    <para>
      There are several commands for <emphasis>saving</emphasis> images. A list,
      and information on how to use them, can be found in the section covering
      the <link linkend="gimp-file-menu">File Menu</link>.
    </para>
    <para><acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to <emphasis>export</emphasis> the
      images you create in a wide variety of formats.  It is important to
      realize that the only format capable of saving <emphasis>all</emphasis> of
      the information in an image, including layers, transparency, etc., is
      GIMP's native XCF format. Every other format preserves some image
      properties and loses others. It is up to you to understand the
      capabilities of the format you choose.
    </para>
    <para>
      Exporting an image does not modify the image itself, so you do not lose
      anything by exporting. See
      <link linkend="gimp-export-dialog">Export file</link>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        When you close an image (possibly by quitting GIMP), you are warned if
        the image is "dirty"; that is, if it has been changed without
        subsequently being saved (an asterisk is in front of the image name).
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Closing warning</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/close-warning.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Saving an image in any file format will cause the image to be considered
        "not dirty", even if the file format does not represent all of the
        information from the image.
      </para>
    </note>

    <sect3 id="file-gif-save">
      <title>Export Image as GIF</title>
      <anchor id="file-gif-load" xreflabel="GIF"/>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>GIF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>.gif</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Export Image as GIF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>GIF</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <figure>
        <title>The GIF Export dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/export-gif-dialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <warning>
        <para>
          The GIF file format does not support some basic image        
          properties such as <emphasis>print resolution</emphasis>.
          If you care for these properties, use a different file
          format like PNG.
        </para>
      </warning>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GIF Options</term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Interlace</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Checking interlace allows an image on a web page to be
                    progressively displayed as it is downloaded.
                    Progressive image display is useful with slow connection
                    speeds, because you can stop an image that is of no
                    interest; interlace is of less use today with our faster
                    connection speeds.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>GIF comment</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    GIF comments support only 7-bit ASCII characters.
                    If you use a character outside the 7-bit ASCII set,
                    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will export the image without
                    a comment, and then inform you that the comment was not
                    saved.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Animated GIF Options</term>
          <listitem>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Animation</primary>
              <secondary>Animated GIF options</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Loop forever</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    When this option is checked, the animation will
                    play repeatedly until you stop it.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Delay between frames where unspecified</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    You can set the delay, in milliseconds, between frames
                    if it has not been set before. In this case, you can
                    modify every delay in the Layer Dialog.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Frame disposal where unspecified</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If this has not been set before, you can set how frames
                    will be superimposed. You can select among three options :
                  </para>
                  <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>I don't care</guilabel>:
                        you can use this option if all your layers are
                        opaque. Layers will overwrite what is beneath.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>Cumulative Layers (combine)</guilabel>:
                        previous frames will not be deleted when a new one
                        is displayed.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>One frame per layer (replace)</guilabel>:
                        previous frames will be deleted before displaying a
                        new frame.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Use delay entered above for all frames</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Self-explanatory.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Use disposal entered above for all frames</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Self-explanatory.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="file-jpeg-save">
      <title>Export Image as JPEG</title>
      <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" xreflabel="JPEG"/>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>JPEG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>.jpg</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>.jpeg</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Export Image as JPEG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>JPEG</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg. It is a
        very widely used format, because it compresses images very
        efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality. No other
        format comes close to achieving the same level of compression. It does
        not, however, support transparency or multiple layers.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>The JPEG Export dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/export-jpeg-dialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering number
        of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this documentation.
        Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality parameter is probably the
        only one you will need to adjust.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Quality</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              When you save a file in JPEG format, a dialog is displayed
              that allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 0
              to 100. Values above 95 are generally not useful, though. The
              default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, but
              in many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
              lower without noticeably degrading the image. You can test the
              effect of different quality settings by checking
              <guilabel>Show Preview in image window</guilabel>
              in the JPEG dialog.
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                Please note, that the numbers for the JPEG quality level have
                a different meaning in different applications.
                Saving with a quality level of 80 in GIMP is not
                necessarily comparable with saving with a quality level of
                80 in a different application.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Preview in image window</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Checking this option causes each change in quality (or any other
              JPEG parameter) to be shown in the image display. (This does not
              alter the image: the image reverts back to its original state
              when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Advanced settings</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Some information about the advanced settings:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Optimize</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If you enable this option, the optimization of entropy
                    encoding parameters will be used. The result is typically
                    a smaller file, but it takes more time to generate.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Progressive</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    With this option enabled, the image chunks are
                    stored in the file in an order that allows
                    progressive image refinement
                    during a slow connection web download.
                    The progressive option for JPG has the same
                    purpose as the interlace option for GIF.
                    Unfortunately, the progressive option produces
                    slightly larger JPG files (than without the
                    progressive option).
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save EXIF data</term>
                <listitem>
                  <indexterm>
                    <primary>EXIF</primary>
                  </indexterm>
                  <para>
                    JPEG files from many digital cameras contain extra
                    information, called EXIF data.
                    EXIF data provides information about the image such as
                    camera make and model, image size, image date, etc.
                    Although GIMP uses the <quote>libexif</quote> library to
                    read and write EXIF data, the library is not
                    automatically packaged with GIMP. If GIMP was built with
                    libexif support, then EXIF data is preserved if you open a
                    JPEG file, work with the resulting image, and then export 
                    it as JPEG. The EXIF data is not altered in any way when 
                    you do this. The EXIF data may indicate things such as 
                    image creation time and file name, which may no longer be
                    correct.
                    If GIMP was not built with EXIF support, you can still
                    open JPG files containing EXIF data, but the EXIF data
                    is ignored, and will not be saved when the resulting image
                    is later exported.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save thumbnail</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This option lets you save a thumbnail with the image.
                    Many applications use the small thumbnail image as
                    a quickly available small preview image.
                  </para>
                  <note>
                    <para>
                      This option is present only if <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                      was built with EXIF support.
                    </para>
                  </note>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save XMP data</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    XMP data is <quote>meta</quote> data about the image;
                    it is a competing format with EXIF.
                    If you enable this option, the meta data of the image is
                    saved in an <acronym>XMP</acronym>-structure within the
                    file.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>
                  Use quality settings from original image
                </term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If a particular quality setting (or <quote>quantization
                    table</quote>) was attached to the image when it was
                    loaded, then this option allows you to use them instead of
                    the standard ones.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    If you have only made a few changes to the image, then
                    re-using the same quality setting will give you almost the
                    same quality and file size as the original image. This
                    will minimize the losses caused by the quantization step,
                    compared to what would happen if you used different
                    quality setting.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    If the quality setting found in the original file are not
                    better than your default quality settings, then the option
                    <quote>Use quality settings from original image</quote>
                    will be available but not enabled. This ensures that you
                    always get at least the minimum quality specified in your
                    defaults. If you did not make major changes to the image
                    and you want to save it using the same quality as the
                    original, then you can do it by enabling this option.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Smoothing</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    JPG compression creates artifacts. By using this option,
                    you can smooth the image when saving, reducing them. But
                    your image becomes somewhat blurred.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Restart markers</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The image file can include markers which allow the image
                    to be loaded as segments. If a connection is broken while
                    loading the image in a web page,
                    loading can resume from the next marker.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Subsampling</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The human eye is not sensitive in the same way over
                    the entire color spectrum. The compression
                    can use this to treat slightly different colors
                    that the eye perceives as very close, as identical
                    colors. Three methods are available :
                  </para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>1x1,1x1,1x1 (best quality)</guilabel>:
                        Commonly referred to as (4:4:4), this produces
                        the best quality,
                        preserving borders and contrasting colors, but
                        compression is less.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>2x1,1x1,1x1 (4:2:2)</guilabel>:
                        This is the standard subsampling, which usually
                        provides a good ratio between image quality and file
                        size. There are situations, however, in which using no
                        subsampling (4:4:4) provides a noticeable increase in
                        the image quality; for example, when the image
                        contains fine details such as text over a uniform
                        background, or images with almost-flat colors.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>1x2,1x1,1x1</guilabel>
                        This is similar to
                        (2x1,1x1,1x1), but the chroma sampling is in the
                        horizontal direction rather than the vertical
                        direction; as if someone rotated an image.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>2x2,1x1,1x1 (smallest file)</guilabel>:
                        Commonly referred to as (4:1:1), this produces
                        the smallest files. This suits images with weak
                        borders but tends to denature colors.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>DCT Method</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    DCT is <quote>discrete cosine transform</quote>,
                    and it is the first step in the JPEG algorithm going
                    from the spatial to the frequency domain. The choices are
                    <quote>float</quote>, <quote>integer</quote>
                    (the default), and <quote>fast integer</quote>.
                  </para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>float</guilabel>:
                        The float method is very slightly more accurate than
                        the integer method, but is much slower unless your
                        machine has very fast floating-point hardware. Also
                        note that the results of the floating-point method may
                        vary slightly across machines, while the integer
                        methods should give the same results everywhere.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>integer</guilabel>
                        (the default): This method is faster than
                        <quote>float</quote>, but not as accurate.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <guilabel>fast integer</guilabel>:
                        The fast integer method is much less accurate than
                        the other two.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Image comments</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    In this text box, you can enter a comment which is
                    saved with the image.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
       
    <sect3 id="file-png-save">
      <title>Export Image as PNG</title>
      <anchor id="file-png-load" xreflabel="PNG"/>
      <anchor id="file-png-save-defaults" xreflabel="PNG"/>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Export Image as PNG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>PNG</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>PNG</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <figure>
        <title>The <quote>Export Image as PNG</quote> dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/export-png-dialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Interlacing</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Checking interlace allows an image on a web page to be
              progressively displayed as it is downloaded.
              Progressive image display is useful with slow connection
              speeds, because you can stop an image that is of no
              interest; interlace is of less use today with our faster
              connection speeds.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save background color</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If your image has many transparency levels, the Internet
              browsers that recognize only two levels, will use the
              background color of your Toolbox instead. Internet Explorer
              up to version 6 did not use this information.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save gamma</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Gamma correction is the ability to correct for
              differences in how computers interpret color values.
              This saves gamma information in the PNG that reflects
              the current Gamma factor for your display. Viewers on
              other computers can then compensate to ensure that the image
              is not too dark or too bright.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save layer offset</term>
          <listitem>
            <!-- Andrew Pitonyak (andrew@pitonyak.org)
            verified this with Alexia Death (alexiadeath@gmail.com)
            on August 17, 2009. -->
            <para>
              PNG supports an offset value called the
              <quote>oFFs chunk</quote>, which provides position data.
              Unfortunately, PNG offset support in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
              is broken, or at least is not compatible with other
              applications,
              and has been for a long time. Do not enable offsets,
              let <acronym>GIMP</acronym> flatten the layers before
              saving, and you will have no problems.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save Resolution</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Save the image resolution, in ppi (pixels per inch).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save creation time</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Date the file was saved.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save comment</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can read this comment in the
              <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              With this option is checked, the color values are saved even if
              the pixels are completely transparent.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Compression level</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Since compression is not lossy, the only reason to use a
              compression level less than 9, is if it takes too long to
              compress a file on a slow computer.
              Nothing to fear from
              decompression: it is as quick whatever the compression level.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save Defaults</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Click to save the current settings. Latter, you can use
              <guibutton>Load Defaults</guibutton> to load the saved
              settings.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <note>
        <para>
          The PNG format supports indexed images. Using fewer colors,
          therefore, results in a smaller file; this is especially useful
          for creating web images;
          see <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Computers work on 8 bits blocks named <quote>Byte</quote>.
          A byte allows 256 colors. Reducing the number of colors below 256
          is not useful: a byte will be used anyway and the file size will not
          be less. More, this <quote>PNG8</quote>
          format, like GIF, uses only one bit for transparency; only two
          transparency levels are possible, transparent or opaque.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you want PNG transparency to be fully displayed by Internet
          Explorer, you can use the AlphaImageLoader DirectX filter in the
          code of your Web page. See Microsoft Knowledge Base
          <xref linkend="bibliography-online-microsoft-kb294714"/>.
          Please note, that this is not necessary for
          InternetExplorer 7 and above.
        </para>
      </note>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="file-tiff-save">
      <title>Export Image as TIFF</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Export Image as TIFF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>TIFF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Formats</primary>
        <secondary>TIFF</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <figure>
        <title>The TIFF Export dialog</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/export-tiff-dialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Compression</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This option allows you to specify the algorithm used to
              compress the image.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>None</guilabel>: is fast, and lossless, but the
                  resulting file is very large.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>LZW</guilabel>: The image is compressed
                  using the <quote>Lempel-Ziv-Welch</quote> algorithm, a
                  lossless compression technique. This is old, but
                  efficient and fast. More information at
                  <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-lzw"/>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Pack Bits</guilabel>: is a fast, simple
                  compression scheme for run-length encoding of data. Apple
                  introduced the PackBits format with the release of
                  MacPaint on the Macintosh computer. A PackBits data
                  stream consists of packets of one byte of header followed
                  by data. (Source:
                  <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-packbits"/>)
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Deflate</guilabel>: is a lossless data
                  compression algorithm that uses a combination of the LZ77
                  algorithm and Huffman coding. It is also used in Zip,
                  Gzip and PNG file formats. Source:
                  <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-deflate"/>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>JPEG</guilabel>: is a very good
                  compression algorithm but lossy.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>CCITT Group 3 fax</guilabel>;
                  <guilabel>CCITT Group 4 fax</guilabel> is a
                  black and white format developed to transfer images by FAX.
                </para>
                <note>
                  <para>
                    These options can only be selected, if the image is in
                    indexed mode and reduced to two colors. Use
                    <menuchoice>
                      <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                      <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu>
                      <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>
                    to convert the image to indexed. Be certain to check
                    <quote>Use black and white (1-bit) palette</quote>.
                  </para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Save color values from transparent pixels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              With this option the color values are saved even if the pixels
              are completely transparent.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Comment</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In this text box, you can enter a comment that is
              associated with the image.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    
      <sect3 id="file-mng-export">
        <title>Export Image as MNG</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Export Image as MNG</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>MNG</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Formats</primary>
          <secondary>MNG</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <figure>
          <title>Export MNG File Dialog</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                          fileref="images/using/export-mng-dialog.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          MNG is acronym for <quote>Multiple-Image Network Graphics</quote>. 
        </para>
        <para>
          The main problem is that Konqueror is the only Web navigator that 
          recognizes the MNG animation format. Please see 
          <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple-image_Network_Graphics"/>.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
  </sect2>
</sect1>
