<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-11-25 added enhanced Korean translation by Dust
  2006-09-12 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-11 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-fileformats" lang="de;en;cs;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="de;fr;ko;nl;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2006-02-25</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="fr">2006-03-12</date>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="ko">2006-06-21</date>
        <authorinitials lang="ko">Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="nl">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="nl">2006-06-02</date>
        <authorinitials lang="nl">HansdeJ</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="no">2007-01-27</date>
        <authorinitials lang="no">KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>


  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Files</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Bilddateien</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Soubory</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fichiers</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">File</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">파일</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Bestanden</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Filer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">文件</phrase>
  </title>


  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Files</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Bilddateien</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Soubory</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Fichiers</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>File</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>파일</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Bestanden</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Filer</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>文件</secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <para lang="en">
    The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is capable of reading and writing a large
    variety of graphics file formats.  With the exception of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native XCF file type, file handling is done by
    plug-ins.  Thus, it is relatively easy to extend <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    to new file types when the need arises.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ist imstande, viele Grafikformate schreiben und
    lesen zu können. Die meisten Formate werden von Plug-ins gelesen und
    geschrieben; die einzige Ausnahme bildet hier das
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-eigene
    <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>. Nachfolgend soll kurz auf
    Vor- und Nachteile beim Anlegen, Öffnen und Speichern von Dateien
    eingegangen werden.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> umí pracovat s velkým množstvím různých grafických
    souborových formátů. S výjimkou nativního formátu XCF je práce se soubory
    zajišťována zásuvnými moduly. Díky tomu je poměrně snadné v případě
    potřeby doplnit možnost práce s dalšími grafickými souborovými formáty.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sait lire et écrire une palette importante de
    formats de fichiers graphiques.  Hormis pour le format XCF natif du
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, la gestion des fichiers est un nouveau type de
    fichier quand le besoin s'en fait sentir.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è in grado di leggere e scrivere una grande
    varietà di formati di file grafici. Con l'eccezione del tipo di file XCF
    nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, la gestione dei file viene effettuata
    tramite l'ausilio di speciali plug-in. Per questa ragione, è relativamente
    facile estendere <acronym>GIMP</acronym>  a nuovi formati di file, se ne
    sorgesse la necessità, aggiungendo un plugin appositamente sviluppato.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    <acronym>김프</acronym>는 굉장히 많은 그래픽 파일 포맷들을 읽고 쓸 수 
    있습니다. <acronym>김프</acronym>의 기본 포맷인 XCF 파일을 제외한 다른 
    파일 타입의 관리는 플러그인을 이용합니다. 따라서 새로운 파일 포맷을 
    지원하도록 확장하는 것이 쉽습니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    kan een behoorlijke verscheidenheid aan grafische beeldopformaten inlezen.
    Behalve het eigen <acronym>XCF</acronym>-bestandsformaat, worden deze door
    <quote>plug-ins</quote>
    afgehandeld. Daarom is het erg makkelijk om mogelijkheden voor nieuwe
    bestandsformaten in te bouwen als dat nodig is.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan lese frå og skrive til eit uttal av
    ulike grafiske filformat. Med unnatak av <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt
    eige filformat, <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>, blir
    filhandteringa gjort med hjelpeprogram. Difor er det relativt enkelt å
    legge til nye format dersom behovet skulle dukka opp.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 有读写大量图像文件格式的能力。除了
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 专用的 XCF 文件格式外，其它的处理其它的格式都靠
    插件。因此，当需要让 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 支持新的文件格式时，就相对
    的比较容易。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    Not all file types are equally good for all purposes. This part of the
    documentation should help you understand the advantages and disadvantages
    of each type.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Všechny typy souborů se ale nehodí ke všem účelům. Tato část manuálu proto
    vysvětluje výhody a nevýhody jednotlivých formátů.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    En fonction du but, tous les types de fichier ne sont pas équivalents.
    Cette partie de la documentation devrait vous aider à comprendre les
    avantages et les inconvénients de chacun.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    I tipi di file non sono tutti uguali e soprattutto non sono adatti per
    ogni scopo. Questa parte della documentazione dovrebbe aiutare a
    comprendere vantaggi e svantaggi per ogni tipo di file.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    각 파일 포맷은 용도에 따라 쓰임새가 다릅니다. 여기에서는 각 포맷의 
    장단점에 대해 이야기할 것입니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    Niet alle bestandsformaten zijn even geschikt voor alle doeleinden. In dit
    deel van de handleiding proberen we u uit te leggen wat de sterke en
    zwakke punten van de verschillende formaten zijn.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Ikkje alle filtypane er like gode for alle føremål. I dette kapitlet vil
    vi prøve å vise fordeler og ulemper med dei vanlegaste typane.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    并不是所有的文件格式在各种情况下都一样。这部分将帮助您了解各种格式的优点和缺点。
  </para>


  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-creating" lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Creating new Files</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Erstellen von Bildateien</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Création d'un nouveau fichier d'image</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Creazione di nuovi file</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">새 파일 만들기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Nieuwe bestanden aanmaken</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å lage nye filer</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Files</primary>
      <secondary>Create</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Bildateien</primary>
      <secondary>Erstellen</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Fichiers</primary>
      <secondary>Création</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it">
      <primary>File</primary>
      <secondary>Creazione</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>파일</primary>
      <secondary>만들기</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="nl">
      <primary>Afbeeldingsbestanden</primary>
      <secondary>Aanmaken</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Filer</primary>
      <secondary>Oppretta nye</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      You can create new files in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> by using the
      following menuitem:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      This opens the <guilabel>Create a new image</guilabel> dialog,
      where you can modify the initial width and height of the file or
      using the standard values. More information about this dialog can
      be found in <xref linkend="gimp-file-new" />.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Sie können neue Dateien in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> über das Bildmenü
      anlegen:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Datei</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Neu</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Dadurch wird der Dialog mit dem Titel <guilabel>Ein neues Bild
      erstellen</guilabel> aufgerufen, in dem Sie entweder neue Werte für
      Höhe und Breite des neuen Bildes eingeben oder die Standardwerte
      belassen. Mehr Informationen über diesen Dialog gibt es in <xref
      linkend="gimp-file-new" />.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez créer un nouveau fichier d'image en suivant:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Nouveau</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      dans le menu de la Boîte à outils.
      Cela ouvre la fenêtre <guilabel>Création d'une nouvelle image
      </guilabel>, où vous pouvez garder les dimensions proposées ou en
      adopter de nouvelles. Voyez <xref linkend="gimp-file-new" />.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Une autre façon de créer une nouvelle image est de coller une image en
      tant que nouveau fichier. Voyez
      <xref linkend="gimp-edit-paste-as-new" />.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      La creazione di nuovi file con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> viene
      effettuata tramite la seguente voce di menu:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Nuovo</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Questo comando apre la finestra di dialogo <guilabel>Crea una nuova
      immagine</guilabel>, nella quale sarà possibile modificare la
      larghezza e l'altezza iniziali dell'immagine o usare per questi
      dei valori standard. Ulteriori informazioni circa questa finestra si
      trovano in <!-- xref FIXME linkend=" -->gimp-file-new<!-- " / -->.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym> 에서 새로운 파일을 만들려면
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>파일</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>새로</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> 메뉴를 이용합니다.
      그러면 <guilabel>새 이미지 만들기</guilabel> 대화상자가 나오고,
      여기서 파일의 기본 너비, 높이 등을 고치거나 표준값을 이용할 수 
      있습니다. 이 대화상자에 대한 자세한 사항은
      <!-- PENDING: ko <xref linkend="gimp-file-new" /> -->
      Section 5.2, “ 새로 ” 에 있습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Met de menukeuzes <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>B</accel>estand</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>ieuw</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> kunt u in  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>  nieuwe bestanden
      aanmaken.
      Hiermee opent u het <guilabel>Nieuwe afbeelding
      maken</guilabel>-dialoogvenster waar u de breedte en hoogte van het
      nieuwe bestand kunt veranderen als u niet de standaardwaardes wilt.
      Meer informatie hierover vind u in <!--XXX_NL xref linkend="gimp-file-new" /-->
      een ander hoofdstuk.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan oppretta nye filer med kommandoen
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Nytt bilete</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> frå hovudmenyen eller biletmenyen.
      Dialogen <guilabel>Lage eit nytt bilete</guilabel> dukkar fram. Her
      kan du anten bruke standardverdiane for breidde og høgde på biletet
      eller du kan skrive inn nye verdiar. <!-- PENDING:no Du finn meir om denne
      dialogen under <xref linkend="gimp-file-new" />.(menus -> file.new.xml)-->
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-opening">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Opening Files</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Öffnen von Bildateien</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Otevírání souborů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Ouvrir des fichiers existants</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Aprire file esistenti</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">파일 열기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Bestanden openen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å opna filer</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">打开文件</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en" >
      <primary>Files</primary>
      <secondary>Open</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it" >
      <primary>File</primary>
      <secondary>Apri</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko" >
      <primary>파일</primary>
      <secondary>열기</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="nl" >
      <primary>Bestanden</primary>
      <secondary>Openen</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no" >
      <primary>Filer</primary>
      <secondary>Opna</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      There are several ways of opening an existing image in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>:
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Es gibt verschiedene Möglichkeiten, Bilder im
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zu öffnen:
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Možností, jak v Gimpu otevřít soubor s obrázkem, je několik:
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Il y a plusieurs façons d'ouvrir des fichiers avec
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> :
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono diversi modi per aprire un'immagine esistente in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>:
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym>로 이미지를 여는 방법에는 여러 가지가 
      있습니다. :
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Er zijn verschillende manieren om een bestaande afbeelding met
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> te openen.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Det er fleire måtar å opna eksisterande bilete i
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>:
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 中有多种方式打开一个现有图像：
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">Open File</term>
        <term lang="de">Bild öffnen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Ouvrir un fichier</term>
        <term lang="it">File apri</term>
        <term lang="ko">파일 열기</term>
        <term lang="nl">Een bestand openen</term>
        <term lang="no">Opna frå menylinja</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">打开文件</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The most obvious is to open it using a menu, by choosing
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            from either the Toolbox menu or an image menu.  This brings
            up a File Chooser dialog, allowing you to navigate to the
            file and click on its name.  This method works well if you
            know the name of the file you want to open, and where it is
            located. It is not so convenient if you want to find the
            file on the basis of a thumbnail.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Der naheliegende Weg, eine Bilddatei zu öffnen, ist, den
            Dialog <guilabel>Bild öffnen</guilabel> zu verwenden. Das
            setzt natürlich voraus, dass Sie wissen, wo sich das Bild
            befindet und wie es heißt. Sie erreichen ihn entweder über
            das Bild- oder das Werkzeugfenstermenü: <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Datei</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Öffnen</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            la façon la plus évidente d'ouvrir un fichier est de choisir
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Ouvrir</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            dans le menu de la Boîte à outils ou de l'image. La fenêtre du
            navigateur de fichiers apparaît qui vous permet de retrouver le
            fichier voulu. Cette méthode est efficace si vous connaissez le
            nom du fichier et sa localisation. C'est moins simple si vous
            voulez retrouver un fichier sur la base d'une vignette.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
          La più ovvia è di aprire l'immagine tramite un menu, scegliendo
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Apri</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            sia dal menu degli strumenti che un menu immagine. Quest'azione
            porta in primo piano una finestra di scelta file che permette
            di navigare alla ricerca del file su cui fare clic per
            caricarlo. Questo metodo funziona bene se si conosce la
            posizione e il nome del file da aprire, non è molto conveniente
            se invece si vuole aprirlo in base ad una miniatura.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            가장 일반적인 방법은 도구상자 메뉴나 이미지 메뉴의
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>파일</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>열기</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            메뉴를 이용해 이미지를 여는 것입니다. 메뉴를 선택하면 열리는 
            파일 선택 대화상자에서 열 파일을 선택합니다. 이 방법은 열려고 
            하는 파일 이름과 그 위치를 알고 있을 때 유용하지만 미리보기를 
            통해 찾기에는 다소 불편하다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            De eenvoudigste manier om een bestand te openen is met het menu
            door:
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu><accel>B</accel>estand</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>penen</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            in het gereedschapsvenster te gebruiken. Hierdoor opent u het
            `Afbeelding openen' venster en kunt u naar de bestanden, waar u
            toestemming voor heeft, bladeren. Het gewenste bestand kunt u
            aanklikken. Als u weet waar het bestand staat en wat de naam ervan
            is, is dit een hele makkelijke manier. Als u dit niet precies weet
            en een klein icoonweergave nodig heeft om de goede afbeelding te
            selecteren is het niet zo handig.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Den mest nærliggande måten er å opna fila med kommandoen
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Opna</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            anten frå hovudmenyen eller frå biletmenyen. Begge fører til ein
            filvaldialog der du kan leite deg fram til, og klikke på namnet
            til, den fila du ønskjer å opna. Dette er vel og bra så lenge du
            veit namnet på fila og kvar ho er å finna. Ikkje fullt så enkelt
            dersom du treng å finna biletet på grunnlag av ein miniatyr.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            最明显地打开方式是使用菜单，在工具箱菜单或图像菜单中选取
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>打开</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            。将出现一个允许浏览文件并点击其名字的文件选择对话框。该方法适合
            于您知道要打开的图像的名字，和它所在的位置。而在您想通过一个缩略
            图来找对应的文件时就不是那么方便了。
          </para>

        <figure lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
          <title>
            <phrase lang="en">
              The <quote>File Open</quote> dialog.
            </phrase>
            <phrase lang="de">
              Der Dialog <guilabel>Bild öffnen</guilabel>.
            </phrase>
            <phrase lang="fr">Le dialogue Ouvrir une image</phrase>
            <phrase lang="it">
              La finestra di dialogo <quote>Apri immagine</quote>.
            </phrase>
            <phrase lang="ko">
              <quote>이미지 열기</quote> 대화상자
            </phrase>
            <phrase lang="nl">
              Het <quote>Bestand openen</quote> dialoogvenster.
            </phrase>
            <phrase lang="no">
              Dialogen <guilabel>Opna biletet</guilabel>
            </phrase>
            <phrase lang="zh_CN">“打开文件”对话框</phrase>
          </title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject lang="en;de">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="fr">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="it">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/it/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="ko">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/ko/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="nl">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/nl/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
             <imageobject lang="no">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
              <imagedata fileref="../images/using/zh_CN/file-open-dialog.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang="en">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          2.2 introduced a new File Chooser that provides several features to
          help you navigate quickly to the file you are looking for. Perhaps
          the most important is the ability to create <quote>bookmarks</quote>
          for folders that you use often. Your list of bookmarks appears on
          the left side of the dialog. The ones at the top (
          <quote>Home</quote>, <quote>Desktop</quote>,
          etc) come automatically; the others you create using the
          <quote>Add</quote>
          button at the bottom of the list. Double-clicking on a bookmark
          takes you straight to that directory.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 wurde ein neuer Dateiauswahl-Dialog
          eingeführt, der Ihnen mehrere Möglichkeiten bietet, schnell zur
          gesuchten Datei zu navigieren. Die vielleicht wichtigste davon
          ist die Fähigkeit, <quote>Lesezeichen</quote> für oft benutzte
          Verzeichnisse anlegen zu können. Die Liste Ihrer Lesezeichen
          sehen Sie auf der linken Seite des Dialogs. Die oberen
          (<quote>Heimatverzeichnis</quote>, <quote>Desktop</quote> etc.)
          werden automatisch erstellt. Andere legen Sie mit der
          <guibutton>Hinzufügen</guibutton>-Schaltfläche unterhalb der Liste
          an. Mit einem Doppelklick auf ein Lesezeichen gelangen Sie
          unverzüglich in dieses Verzeichnis.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 a introduit un nouveau Sélecteur de
          Fichiers qui apporte plusieures caractéristiques vous permettant de
          naviguer plus rapidement vers le fichier voulu. La plus importante
          est peut-être la possibilité de créer des <quote>Marque
          pages</quote> pour les dossiers que vous utilisez souvent. Votre
          liste de marque-pages apparaît à la gauche de la boîte de dialogue.
          Ceux du haut, (<quote>Home</quote>, <quote>Bureau</quote>, etc)
          viennent automatiquement; ceux que vous créez grâce au bouton
          <quote>Ajouter</quote> en bas de la liste. Un double clic sur un des
          marque-pages vous envoie directement dans le dossier.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 introduce una nuova finestra di
          selezione file che fornisce diverse nuove caratteristiche che
          vengono in aiuto a chi vuole navigare velocemente alla ricerca del
          file che si sta cercando. Forse l'abilità più importante consiste
          nel poter creare <quote>segnalibri</quote> per le cartelle che si
          usano più spesso. L'elenco dei segnalibri è posizionato nella parte
          sinistra della finestra. Quelli in cima (<quote>Home</quote>,
          <quote>Desktop</quote>, sono predefiniti; gli altri vengono creati
          usando il pulsante <quote>Aggiungi</quote> presente in fondo
          all'elenco. Facendo doppio clic su un segnalibro si finisce
          direttamente nella cartella corrispondente.
        </para>

        <para lang="ko">
          김프 2.2 에서는 새로운 파일 선택기가 추가되었는데, 여기서 
          제공하는 몇 가지 기능들을 이용하면 찾고자 하는 파일을 빠르게 찾을
          수 있습니다. 그 중 가장 주요한 기능은 자주 사용하는 폴더의 
          <quote>북마크</quote> 를 만들 수 있는 기능입니다. 북마크 리스트는
          대화상자의 왼쪽에 위치하게 됩니다. 북마크의 상단에 있는 것들
          (<quote>바탕화면</quote>,<quote>A:\</quote>,<quote>C:\</quote>,
          <quote>D:\</quote>...)은 자동적으로 생성되는 것이며, 그 아래에
          있는 것들은 <quote>더하기</quote> 버튼을 이용해 추가한 
          것들입니다. 북마크를 더블클릭하면 해당 디렉토리로 바로 
          이동합니다.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          Met de komst van versie 2.2 van <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is de opbouw
          van het bestandsselectievenster vernieuwd. Er zijn enkele functies
          toegevoegd waardoor u sneller het bestand dat u wilt kunt vinden.
          Een van de belangrijkste toegevoegde mogelijkheden zijn de
          <quote>bladwijzers</quote> naar mappen die u regelmatig gebruikt.
          Deze lijst staat aan de linkerkant van het dialoogvenster.  De
          bovenste bladwijzers (<quote>Thuis</quote>,
          <quote>Bureaublad</quote> etc. ) verschijnen automatisch; De anderen
          kunt u zelf maken door op de
          <guibutton><accel>T</accel>oevoegen</guibutton> te klikken. U word
          direkt naar de folder van de bladwijzer geleid door er op te
          dubbelklikken.
        </para>


        <para lang="no">
          I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 blei det tatt i bruk ein ny dialog
          for å opne filer. Det skulle nå vere nokså enkelt å navigera deg
          fram til den ønskte fila dersom katalogoppsettet i maskinen din er
          nokolunde systematisk. Etter kvart som du klikkar deg fram, vil
          mappene bli viste øvst i dialogvindauget. (<quote>Heim</quote>,
          <quote>Mine dokument</quote> osv på figuren). Aktiv mappe blir
          vist med utheva skrift. Du kan også lage <quote>bokmerke</quote>
          for mapper du ofte bruker. Mappa <quote>diverse</quote> til
          venstre på figuren er eit slikt bokmerke. Når du dobbeltklikkar på
          bokmerket, kjem du rett fram til ønskt mappe eller fil. Dersom du
          klikkar på knappen <guibutton>Legg til</guibutton>, vil den
          aktive mappa bli lagt inn som bokmerke. Du fjernar eit markert
          bokmerke med knappen <guibutton>Fjern</guibutton>.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 中引入新的文件选择器，它提供许多帮助您
          快速寻找所需要文件的新特性。可能其中最重要的就是为您经常使用的目录
          创建“书签”的能力。书签的列表在对话框的左边。那些在最上面的(“主目录
          ”，“桌面”等)是自动添加的;用列表下部的“添加”按钮添加其它目录。双击
          一个书签项则把您直接带到那个目录。
        </para>


        <para lang="en">
          At the center of the dialog appears a listing of the contents of the
          selected directory. Subdirectories are shown at the top of the list,
          files below them. By default all files in the directory are listed,
          but you can restrict the listing to image files of a specific type
          using the File Type selection menu that appears beneath the
          directory listing.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          In der Mitte des Dialoges wird der Inhalt des ausgewählten
          Verzeichnisses aufgelistet. Unterverzeichnisse befinden sich oben
          in der Liste, darunter die Dateien. Per Voreinstellung werden
          alle Dateien des Verzeichnisses angezeigt, aber mit Hilfe des
          Dateiauswahlmenüs direkt unter der Liste können Sie die Auswahl
          auf Dateien eines bestimmten Typs einschränken.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Au centre du dialogue se trouve une liste du contenu du répertoire
          sélectionné. Les sous-répertoires sont en-haut de la liste et les
          fichiers en-dessous. Par défaut, tous les fichiers du répertoire sont
          affichés, mais vous pouvez vous limiter aux fichiers d'image d'un
          certain type en utilisant le menu de sélection du Type de Fichier situé
          sous la liste.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Al centro della finestra di dialogo appare l'elenco dei contenuti della
          cartella selezionata. Le sottocartelle vengono mostrate in cima
          all'elenco, mentre i file sono sotto di esse. Il comportamento
          predefinito è di mostrare tutti i file contenuti nella cartella ma è
          possibile restringere la visualizzazione ai soli file immagine di un
          tipo specifica usando il menu di selezione del tipo di file che appare
          sotto l'elenco delle cartelle.
        </para>

        <para lang="ko">
          대화상자의 가운데에는 선택된 디렉토리의 내용이 표시됩니다. 하위
          디렉토리가 리스트의 상단에 위치하고, 그 아래로 파일들이 
          보여집니다. 기본값으로 디렉토리 내의 모든 파일이 표시되지만, 
          리스트 아래쪽의 파일 타입 선택 메뉴를 이용하면, 특정 파일 형태의 
          이미지 파일만 표시되게 할 수도 있습니다.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          In het midden van het dialoogvenster staat de inhoud van de
          geselecteerde map afgebeeld. De mappen die weer onder deze hangen komen
          als eerste, bovenaan de lijst te staan waarna de bestandsnamen afgebeeld
          worden. Standaard worden alle bestanden in de geselecteerde map getoond
          maar met behulp van de bestandstype selectie die onder de bestandelijst
          staat, kunt u de weergave tot bestanden van een enkel type beperken.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          I midten av dialogvindauget finn du ei liste over innhaldet i den
          valde mappa. Eventuelle underkatalogar blir lista øvst, og deretter
          filene. Normalt blir alle filene i mappa lista ut, men du kan
          avgrensa listinga til bestemte filtypar ved hjelp av utvalsmenyen
          <quote>Vel filtype</quote>.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          对话框的中间是选中目录中的内容列表。其列表上方是子目录，下方是文件。
          默认是显示目录中所有文件，您可以使用目录内容列表下方的文件类型选择
          菜单使它只显示某个特定类型的图像文件的列表。
        </para>


        <para lang="en">
          When you click on a file entry in the listing, if it is an image
          file, a preview will appear on the right side of the dialog, along
          with some basic information about the properties of the image. Note
          that previews are cached when they are generated, and there are some
          things you can do that may cause a preview to be incorrect. If you
          suspect that this may be happening, you can force a new preview to
          be generated by holding down the Ctrl key and clicking in the
          Preview area.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Wenn Sie eine Datei in der Liste anklicken und es sich um eine Bilddatei
          handelt, erscheint rechts vom Dialog eine Vorschau sowie einige
          Informationen zu den Eigenschaften des Bildes. Beachten Sie bitte, dass
          Vorschauen zwischengespeichert werden und Sie durch einige Aktionen
          bewirken können, dass die Vorschau nicht mehr korrekt ist. Wenn Sie das
          Gefühl haben, dass so etwas passiert sein könnte, können Sie eine neue
          Vorschau erzwingen, indem Sie die Ctlr-Taste (bzw. Strg-Taste) gedrückt
          halten und dann auf das Vorschaufenster klicken.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Quand vous cliquez sur une des entrées de la liste et s'il s'agit
          d'un fichier d'image, un Aperçu apparaît à la droite du dialogue,
          accompagné de quelques informations de base sur les propriétés de
          l'image. Il peut arriver que l'aperçu soit incorrect; dans ce cas,
          vous pouvez régénérer l'aperçu en maintenant la touche Ctrl enfoncée
          et en cliquant sur l'aire de l'aperçu.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Quando si fa clic su di una voce di file presente nell'elenco, se è
          un file immagine, appare un'anteprima nella parte destra della

          finestra insieme ad un sommario di informazioni sull'immagine.
          Notare che le anteprime, quando vengono create, vengono inserite in
          una memoria cache, e può capitare che non corrispondano più
          all'immagine originale. Se si ha questo sospetto è possibile forzare
          la rigenerazione dell'anteprima premendo il tasto Ctrl mentre si fa
          clic sull'area dell'anteprima.
        </para>

        <para lang="ko">
          리스트에서 파일을 클릭했을 때, 해당 파일이 이미지 파일이라면
          대화상자의 오른쪽에 미리보기와 간략한 속성 정보가 나타납니다. 이
          미리보기는 파일을 처음 만들었을 때 생성된 것이므로 간혹 잘못된
          것이 있을 수 있습니다. 만약 미리보기가 잘못되었다고 생각된다면,
          Ctrl 키를 누르고 미리보기 영역을 클릭함으로써 새 미리보기를 만들
          수 있습니다.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          Als u op een van de ingangen in de lijst van bestandsnamen klikt en
          het bestand een bekend afbeeldingsbestand is, zal er een vooruitblik
          van het bestand zichtbaar worden gemaakt aan de rechterkant van het
          dialoogvenster, samen met enlkele globale eigenschappen van de
          afbeeling. Deze vooruitblikken worden ergens tijdelijk aangemaakt en
          er kunnen dus vreemde dingen gebeuren die de afbeelding ervan
          verstoren. Als u inderdaad iets vreemds ziet gebeuren kunt u de
          vooruitblik verversen door de <keycap>CTRL</keycap>-toets in te
          drukken en dan in het vak van de vooruitblik te klikken.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          Dersom fila du klikkar på er ei biletfil, vil biletet bli vist til
          høgre i dialogvindauget. Det hender at førehandsvisinga ikkje er
          heilt korrekt. Dersom du har mistanke om at dette er tilfelle, kan
          du laste ho inn på nytt ved å halde nede
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten medan du klikkar på biletet.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          当您点击列表中一个文件时，假如它是图像文件，它的预览和一些基本信息
          就会显示在对话框右边。需要注意的是生成预览时是将它们缓存的，有些操
          作会导致预览出错。如果您发现了这种情况，请按下 Ctrl 键并同时点击预
          览区域来强行生成新的预览。
        </para>


        <para lang="en">
          One thing that strikes many people when they first see the
          File Open dialog is that there is no way to enter the name
          of the file using the keyboard.  Actually this can be done,
          but the feature is a bit hidden:  if you type
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          with the dialog focused, an "Open Location" dialog pops up,
          with a space to type the file name.  This dialog is
          described in more detail below.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Etwas irritiert viele Leute, wenn sie das erste Mal den

          Dateiauswahl-Dialog sehen: es gibt keine Möglichkeit, den
          Dateinamen über die Tastatur einzugeben. Tatsächlich gibt es
          doch eine, allerdings ist sie versteckt. Wenn Sie
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          eingeben (und der Dialog den Fokus besitzt), erscheint ein
          Dialog <quote>Ort öffnen</quote>, wo Sie den Dateinamen
          eingeben können. Dieser Dialog wird später detailliert
          beschrieben.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Une chose qui frappe le nouvel utilisateur quand il voit le
          dialogue Ouvrir une Image est l'absence de possibilité d'entrer
          le nom d'un fichier en utilisant le clavier. En fait, c'est
          possible, mais cette caractéristique est cachée: si vous tapez
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>,
          vous verrez apparaître la boîte de dialogue Ouvrir un
          emplacement où vous pourrez inscrire le chemin et le nom du
          fichier d'image recherché. Ce dialogue est décrit plus en détail
          plus loin.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Una cosa che colpisce molta gente la prima volta che vedono la
          finestra di selezione e apertura file è che non c'è modo di
          inserire il nome del file con la tastiera. In realtà è comunque
          possibile farlo ma la funzione è un po' nascosta: se si preme la
          combinazione di tasti
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          quando la finestra di dialogo è selezionata, appare in primo
          piano una finestra di dialogo "Apri posizione", con lo spazio
          necessario ad inserire il nome del file. Questa finestra di
          dialogo è descritta in maggiore dettaglio più avanti.
        </para>

        <para lang="ko">
          많은 사람들이 파일 열기 대화상자를 처음 보았을 때 부딪히는 문제는
          키보드를 이용해 파일 이름을 입력할 수 있는 방법이 없다라는 
          것입니다. 하지만 이는 없는 것이 아니라 감추어져 있을 뿐입니다.
          대화상자에서
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          키를 누르면 "위치 열기" 대화상자가 뜨며 파일 이름을 입력할 수
          있는 공간이 나옵니다. 이 대화상자에 대해서는 차후에 자세히 설명할
          것입니다.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          Een van de dingen die de meeste mensen opvalt in het Bestand openen
          dialoogvenster is dat er geen invoerveld in beeld is om de
          bestandsnaam rechtstreeks met het toetsenbord in te voeren. Deze
          mogelijkheid bestaat nog wel maar is enigszins verborgen: Als het
          dialoogvenster actief is, kunt u de toetsencombinatie
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          gebruiken om het <quote>Lokatie openen</quote> dialoogvenster te
          activeren. Dt venster wordt hieronder uitgebreider behandeld.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          Høyrer du til dei som saknar ein stad å kunne skrive inn namnet
          på fila du vil opna? Fortvil ikkje. Linja finst, men er noe
          skjult. Med fildialogen aktiv, bruker du tastekombinasjonen
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> for
          å kalle fram dialogvindauget <quote>Opna adresse</quote>. Her
          kan du skrive inn ønskt filnamn. Meir om denne dialogen seinare.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          另外一个可能是用户迷惑的是，发现在打开文件对话框中无法用键盘输入文
          件名。实际上是有该功能的，只是它是隐藏的：同时按下
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>就会出
          现一个“打开位置”对话框，其中可以输入文件名。关于该对话框下面有详细
          解释。
        </para>


        <note lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
          <para lang="en">
            In the great majority of cases, if you select a file name from the
            list, and click the <quote>Open</quote> button in the lower right
            corner or the dialog, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will automatically
            determine the file type for you.  On rare occasions, mainly if the
            file type is unusual and the name lacks a meaningful extension,
            this may fail. If this happens, you can tell
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> specifically what type of file it is by
            expanding the <quote>Select File Typ</quote> option at the bottom
            of the dialog, and choosing an entry from the list that appears.
            More commonly, though, if <acronym>GIMP</acronym> fails to open an
            image file, it is either corrupt or not in a supported format.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Das Öffnen von Bildern geschieht in den meisten Fällen durch
            die Auswahl des Bildes und den Mausklick auf die
            <guibutton>Öffnen</guibutton>-Schaltfläche.
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bestimmt
            den Dateityp beim Öffnen automatisch. In wenigen Fällen
            jedoch kann der Dateityp nicht automatisch bestimmt werden.
            Wenn dieser Fall eintritt, können Sie den Dateityp mit einem
            Mausklick auf <guilabel>Dateityp: Automatisch
            bestimmt</guilabel> und eine zusätzliche Auswahl explizit
            angeben.  Sollte sich auch dann die Bilddatei nicht öffnen
            lassen, kann die Datei kaputt sein.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Dans la grande majorité des cas, si vous sélectionnez un fichier
            dans la liste et que vous cliquiez sur le bouton Ouvrir dans le
            coin en bas à droite de la fenêtre, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> déterminera
            automatiquement le type du fichier. En cas d'échec, s'il s'agit
            d'un type de fichier inhabituel ou avec une extension malformée,
            vous pouvez choisir manuellement le type de fichier en cliquant
            sur la case <quote>Sélectionner le type de fichier</quote> en
            bas de la fenêtre, ce qui déroulera une liste des types de
            fichiers. Mais le plus souvent, néanmoins, c'est que le fichier
            est détérioré ou non reconnu par <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Nella gran parte dei casi, se si seleziona il nome del file
            dall'elenco facendo clic sul pulsante "Apri" nell'angolo in basso
            a destra della finestra, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> determinerà
            automaticamente il tipo di file. In rare occasioni, principalmente
            se il tipo di file è inusuale e il nome manca di un'estensione
            significativa, questo meccanismo può fallire. Se accade
            quest'evenienza è possibile specificare manualmente il tipo di
            file a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allargando il pulsante di opzione
            "Seleziona tipo di file" presente in fondo alla finestra,
            scegliendo la voce corretta dall'elenco che apparirà. Più spesso,
            se <acronym>GIMP</acronym> fallisce il caricamento dell'immagine è
            perché questa è corrotta o di un formato non supportato.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            일반적으로 리스트에서 파일을 선택하고 대화상자의 우측 하단에 
            있는 <quote>열기</quote> 버튼을 누르면, 
            <acronym>김프</acronym>가 자동으로 파일 타입을 판단합니다. 
            하지만 아주 가끔 일반적인 파일 타입이 아니거나, 확장자가 
            정확하지 않은 경우 실패할 수도 있습니다. 이런 경우 대화상자 
            아래쪽에 있는 <quote>파일 타입 선택</quote> 옵션에서 파일 
            타입을 지정해 줄 수도 있습니다. 하지만 보통 이런 경우는 이미지
            파일이 망가진 경우거나 김프에서 지원하지 못하는 포맷입니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Meestal is het voldoende om de naam van het bestand te selecteren
            en op de <guibutton><accel>O</accel>penen</guibutton>-knop aan de
            rechteronderkant van het dialoogventer te klikken.
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan dan vaak zelf wel bepalen om wat voor
            type bestand het gaat. In zeldzame gevallen, meestal als het om
            een ongewoon bestandtype gaat en de extensie van het bestand ook
            geen duidelijkheid geeft, kan dit misgaan. Indien dit gebeurd kunt
            u de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> expliciet vertellen wat het type is
            door het <guibutton>Selecteer
            bestands<accel>t</accel>ype</guibutton>-menu uit te rollen en zelf
            het het correcte type uit de lijst te selecteren. Het komt echter
            vaker voor dat het bestand niet gelezen kan worden omdat het
            beschadigd is geraakt of de opmaak niet door
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ondersteund word.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            I dei aller fleste tilfella vil <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bestemma
            filtypen automatisk når du opnar ei fil. I noen sjeldne tilfelle,
            særleg dersom filtypen er uvanleg eller dersom filnamnet er
            ufullstendig, kan det hende automatikken ikkje verkar. Du kan då
            opna <quote>Vel filtype</quote> og klikka på ønskt format.
            Den vanlegaste årsaka til at <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ikkje greier
            å opna ei biletfil, er likevel at fila er øydelagt eller at
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ikkje har støtte for dette formatet.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            在大多数情况下，从列表中选择一个文件，然后点击对话框右下角的“打
            开”按钮，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 会自动判断文件格式。在一些罕见
            的情况下，主要是文件类型不常见或文件名没有一个有意义的扩展名时就
            会判断失败。如果发生了这种情况，您可以使用对话框底部的“选择文件
            类型”选项告诉 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>该文件是何类型。更常见的是
            由于文件损坏或是不被支持的格式使 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>无法打开
            该图像文件。
          </para>
        </note>

        <para lang="cs">
          Zřejmá je možnost otevřít obrázek pomocí menu panelu nástrojů
          nebo menu obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Otevřít</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Tím se otevře dialog pro výběr souborů, ve kterém lze nalézt
          a vybrat požadovaný soubor. To je výhodné, když znáte jméno
          a umístění požadovaného souboru.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">Open Location</term>
        <term lang="de">Von Ort öffnen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Ouvrir un emplacement</term>
        <term lang="it">Apri posizione</term>
        <term lang="ko">위치 열기</term>
        <term lang="nl">Locatie openen</term>
        <term lang="no">Opna frå ei nettadresse</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">打开位置</term>

        <listitem>
          <para  lang="en">
            If instead of a file name, you have a <acronym>URI</acronym>
            (i.e., a web address) for the image, you can open it using the
            menu, by choosing
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Open Location</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            from either the Toolbox menu or an image menu.  This brings up a
            small dialog that allows you to enter (or paste) the
            <acronym>URI</acronym>.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud místo jména souboru znáte jeho URI (tj. internetovou
            adresu), můžete ho otevřít volbou
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Otevřít umístění</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            z menu panelu nástrojů nebo z menu obrázku. Objeví se malé
            dialogové okno, do kterého je třeba zadat příslušnou adresu (URI).
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie Bilder aus dem Internet (z.B. von Internetseiten)
            öffnen möchten, können Sie das über den Dialog
            <guilabel>Bild von Ort öffnen</guilabel> tun. Der
            Dialog besteht aus einer Eingabezeile, in der Sie die Adresse
            (URI) zum Bild angeben können. Wenn <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            das Bild nicht öffnen kann (durch eine fehlerhafte Adresse
            z.B.), bricht der Dialog mit einer entsprechenden
            Fehlermeldung ab.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous avez une URI (adresse Web) au lieu d'un nom de
            fichier pour l'image, vous pouvez l'ouvrir via le
            menu
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Ouvrir suivant l'emplacement</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            de la boîte d'outils ou d'une fenêtre d'image. Un dialogue
            est ouvert vous permettant d'indiquer l'URI.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
          Se invece di un nome file su ha una URI (cioè un'indirizzo web)
            dell'immagine, è possibile aprirla usando il menù scegliendo
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Apri posizione</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          sia dal menu degli strumenti che da un menu immagine. Ciò porta
            in primo piano una piccola finestra di dialogo entro la quale è
            possibile battere l'URI dell'immagine che si intende aprire.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            파일 이름대신 이미지의 <acronym>URI</acronym>(예:웹 주소)를 
            알고 있다면, 도구상자 메뉴나 이미지 메뉴의
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>파일</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>위치 열기</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            를 이용해 이미지를 열 수 있습니다. 이 메뉴를 선택하면 
            <acronym>URI</acronym> 를 입력할 수 있는 작은 대화상자가 뜹니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Als u een bestand vanaf een <acronym>URI</acronym> inplaats van
            een lokaal bestand wilt openen, kunt u dit ook doen met behulp van
            de menukeuzes:
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu><accel>B</accel>estand</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem><accel>L</accel>ocatie openen</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            in het gereedschapsvenster of het afbeeldingsmenu. Hierdoor wordt
            er een klein dialoogvenster ge-opend waar u de
            <acronym>URI</acronym> kunt invoeren (of plakken).
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Dersom biletet du ønskjer å opna ligg på ei nettadresse, anten
            det nå er Internett eller lokalnett,
            kan du bruke
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Opna ei nettadresse</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            anten frå verktøyskrinet eller frå ein biletmeny.
            Det vil då dukka opp eit dialogvindauge der du kan skriva inn
            nettadressa.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            假如不是一个文件名而是一个 URL (比如一个网络地址)的图像，您能通
            过使用菜单，在工具箱菜单或图像菜单中选取
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>打开位置</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>。
            会出现一个允许输入URL的小的对话框。
          </para>

          <figure lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                The <quote>Open Location</quote> dialog.
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Der Dialog, um ein Bild aus dem Internet (URI) zu öffnen.
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Le dialogue Ouvrir un emplacement.</phrase>
              <phrase lang="it">
                La finestra di dialogo <quote>Apri posizione</quote>.
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="ko">
                <quote>위치 열기</quote> 대화상자.
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="nl">
                Het <quote>Locatie Openen</quote> dialoogvenster.
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">
                Dialogvindauget for <quote>Opna ei nettadresse</quote>.
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="zh_CN">“打开位置”对话框</phrase>
            </title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en;de">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/fr/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="it">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/it/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="ko">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/ko/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="nl">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/nl/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="no">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/no/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/using/zh_CN/file-open-dialog-location.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>

              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  The <quote>Open Location</quote> dialog.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Der Dialog um ein Bild aus dem Internet (URL) zu öffnen.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">Le dialogue Ouvrir un emplacement.</para>
                <para lang="it">
                  La finestra di dialogo <quote>Apri posizione</quote>.
                </para>
                <para lang="ko">
                  <quote>위치 열기</quote> 대화상자.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Het <quote>Locatie openen</quote> dialoogvenster.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Dialogvindauget for å opna eit bilete frå ei nettadresse (URL).
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">“打开位置”对话框</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;it;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">Open Recent</term>
        <term lang="de">Zuletzt geöffnet</term>
        <term lang="fr">Récemment ouverts</term>
        <term lang="it">Apri recenti</term>
        <term lang="ko">최근 파일 열기</term>
        <term lang="nl">Recent geopend</term>
        <term lang="no">Opna tidlegare brukte filer</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">最近打开</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If the image is one that you previously created using
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
            perhaps the easiest way to open it is from the menu, using
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Open Recent</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            This gives you a scrollable list of the images you
            have most recently worked on in, with icons beside them.
            You need only select the one you want, and it will be
            opened.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud chcete otevřít obrázek, se kterým jste v Gimpu nedávno
            pracovali, je nejjednodušší zvolit z menu panelu nástrojů nebo z
            menu obrázku
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Otevřít nedávný</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            Dostanete se tak k seznamu nedávno otevřených souborů. Názvy
            souborů jsou doplněny malými ikonkami zobrazujícími jejich obsah,
            což vám může usnadnit orientaci. Ze seznamu si vyberte požadovaný
            soubor.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Gehört das Bild, welches sie öffnen wollen, zu einem früher mit
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> erstellten Bild, ist der einfachste Weg,
            es über den Menüpunkt <guilabel>Zuletzt geöffnet</guilabel> zu
            öffnen.  Sie finden ihn über das Bild- oder das
            Werkzeugfenstermenü:
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Datei</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Zuletzt geöffnet</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            Die Liste, die Sie beim Aufruf des Menüpunktes erhalten, besteht
            aus Bildern, die Sie zuletzt mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> erstellt
            oder bearbeitet haben.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Si l'image est l'une de celles que vous avez récemment
            travaillée en utilisant <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, le plus simple
            est est de l'ouvrir avec le menu
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Récemment ouverts</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            Ceci vous donne une liste déroulante des images sur lesquelles
            vous avez travaillé récemment, accompagnées d'une miniature.
            Il vous suffit de sélectionner celle que vous voulez, ou
            d'utiliser le raccourci clavier indiqué.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
          Se l'immagine in questione è una tra quelle che si è aperte
          recentemente con <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, il metodo più immediato
          per aprirla è usando il menu
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Apri recenti</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
          Si ottiene un'elenco scorrevole di immagini sulle
          quali si è lavorato recentemente con le corrispondnti miniature
          accanto. Basta selezionare quella desiderata ed essa verrà
          aperta.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            최근에 <acronym>김프</acronym>로 열었던 파일은
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>파일</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>최근 파일 열기</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            메뉴를 이용하면 쉽게 다시 열 수 있습니다. 여기에 가장 최근에 
            작업한 이미지의 리스트가 아이콘과 함께 보여집니다. 이 
            리스트에서 필요한 파일을 선택하면 해당 파일이 열립니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Indien u een afbeelding wilt bewerken die u kortgeleden al eens
            eerder met <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gemaakt of bewerkt heeft, is
            het waarschijnlijk het eenvoudigste via het menu met behulp van de
            keuzen
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Bestand</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>ecent geopend</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
           Hiermee komt u in een uitrolbare lijst met afbeeldingen die u de
           laatste tijd bewerkt heeft, met kleine iconen ernaast. Na het
           selecteren van het gewenste bestand wordt dit automatisch geopend.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du tidlegare har opna eit bilete i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
            kan du gjenopna det med menyvalet
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Sist opna filer</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            Det vil då dukka opp ei liste over dei bileta du har opna
            tidlegare, med ein miniatyr ved sida av namnet. Du kan nå klikka
            på eit bilete for å opna det igjen. Er lista lang, vil dei
            eldste bileta bli pressa ut av lista.
          </para>

          <para  lang="zh_CN">
            如果是一个前面用 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 创建的图像，也许打开它
            最简单的方式就是从菜单，选取
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>最近打开</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>。将出现一个您最近处理过的图像的可滚动的列表，您只
            需要点击一个图像旁的图标，就会将其打开。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">File Browser</term>
        <term lang="de">Dateimanager</term>
        <term lang="fr">Explorateur de fichiers</term>
        <term lang="it">Navigatore dei file</term>
        <term lang="ko">파일 탐색기</term>
        <term lang="nl">Bestanden bekijken</term>
        <term lang="no">Filutforskaren</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">文件浏览器</term>

        <listitem>
          <para  lang="en">
            If you have associated the file type of the image with
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
            either when you installed <acronym>GIMP</acronym> or later, then you can
            navigate to the file using a file manager (such as Nautilus
            in Linux, or Windows Explorer in Windows), and once you have
            found it, double-click on the icon.  If things are set up
            properly, this will cause the image to open in
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud jsou obrazové soubory s Gimpem na vašem systému asociovány,
            můžete nalézt požadovaný soubor ve správci souborů (např. Nautilus
            na Linuxu nebo Windows Explorer ve Windows) a poklepat na jeho
            ikonu myší. Při vhodném nastavení se tak obrázek otevře v Gimpu.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Sobald Dateiformate mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> im
            Betriebssystem verknüpft sind, bieten Dateimanager immer
            eine Möglichkeit, mit einem Mausklick das gewünschte Bild zu
            öffnen.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous avez associé le type de fichier de l'image avec
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, quand vous avez installé
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ou plus tard, vous pouvez alors naviguer
            en utilisant un gestionnaire de fichier tel que Nautilus ou
            Konqueror sous Linux ou Explorateur sous Windows. Une fois le
            fichier trouvé double-cliquez dessus pour l'ouvrir.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Se si ha associato il tipo di immagine con <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            sia durante l'installazione di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> che in
            seguito, allora sarà possibile scorrere i file usando un gestore
            di file (come Nautilus in Linux, o Windows Explorer in Windows), e
            una volta che si è trovata l'immagine che interessa basterà fare
            doppio clic sulla sua icona. Se le cose sono impostate
            correttamente ciò provocherà l'apertura dell'immagine con
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            <acronym>김프</acronym>가 설치되어 있고 파일 타입을 
            <acronym>김프</acronym>와 연동시켜 놓았다면, 파일 
            관리자(리눅스의 노틸러스(Nautilus), 윈도우즈의 윈도우즈 
            탐색기)로 파일을 찾아 더블 클릭합니다. 파일 연결이 제대로 되어 
            있다면 파일 아이콘을 더블 클릭할 경우 
            <acronym>김프</acronym>로 이미지가 열릴 것입니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Als u het bestandstype van een bestand in een bestandsbeheer
            programma (zoals <acronym>Nautilus</acronym> in
            <acronym>Linux</acronym> of de <acronym>Windows
            Verkenner</acronym> in <acronym>Windows</acronym>) met
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> verbonden heeft, kunt u afbeeldingen van
            dat type eenvoudig met <acronym>GIMP</acronym> openen door er
            eenvoudigweg op te dubbelklikken.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du har tilordna filtypen til <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
            anten då du installerte <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eller seinare,
            kan du bruke filbehandlingsprogrammet til maskinen din, som
            t.d. <quote>Nautilus</quote> i Linux eller <quote>Windows
            utforsker</quote> i Windows, for å finne biletet ditt. Når du
            har funne det, kan du dobbeltklikka på filnamnet eller ikonet for
            å opna biletet i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. (Sjå hjelp for
            maskinen din om korleis du kan tilordna [eng.:
            <quote>associate</quote>] filtypar til bestemte program).
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            如果您用 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 关联了文件类型，不管是安装
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 时还是以后，都可以通过一个文件管理器(比
            如 Linux 中的 Nautilus，或 Windows 中的 Windows Explorer)来浏览
            文件，一旦找到了，双击它的图标。如果一切设置正确，该图像将在
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>中打开。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Drag and Drop</term>
        <term lang="cs">Drag and Drop</term>
        <term lang="de">Drag and Drop</term>
        <term lang="fr">Glisser-Poser</term>
        <term lang="it">Trascinamento</term>
        <term lang="ko">끌어놓기(드래그 앤 드랍)</term>
        <term lang="nl">Bestanden slepen</term>
        <term lang="no">Dra og slepp</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">拖放</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Alternatively, once you have found the file, you can click on its icon
            and drag it into the  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolbox.  (If instead you
            drag it into an existing  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image, it will be added
            to that image as a new layer or set of layers.)
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Jinou možností je ikonu obrazového souboru ze správce souborů
            přetáhnout myší na panel nástrojů Gimpu. (Pokud ji přetáhnete
            na již existující obrázek, bude soubor přidán k obrázku jako
            nová vrstva nebo sada vrstev.)
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Mittels <quote>Drag and Drop</quote> können Sie gewünschte
            Bilder von vielen Orten (z.B. Dateimanager,
            Bildverwaltungs-Software) auf das Werkzeugfenster oder
            Bildfenster des <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ziehen.  Ziehen Sie
            das Bild auf das Bildfenster, wird es als neue Ebene eingefügt.
            Ziehen Sie das Bild hingegen auf das Werkzeugfenster, wird es
            als neues Bild im <acronym>GIMP</acronym> geöffnet.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Alternativement, une fois que vous avez trouvé le fichier, vous pouvez le
            glisser/déposer dans la boite à outils de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Si
            vous le glisser/déposer dans une fenêtre d'images alors il sera intégré
            dans l'image en tant que calque.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            In alternativa, una volta trovato il file, è possibile fare clic e
            trascinarlo sulla barra degli strumenti di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            (se lo si fa su di un'immagine esistente di
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, verrà aggiunta a quell'immagine un nuovo
            insieme di livelli).
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            또는 파일 아이콘을 클릭한 후에 <acronym>김프</acronym> 
            도구상자로 드래그해서 열 수도 있습니다.(이미 열려있는 김프 
            이미지 위로 드래그할 경우, 기존 이미지의 새 레이어로 추가되어 
            열리게 됩니다.)
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Een andere manier om bestanden te openen, is door op het pictogram te
            klikken en het in het <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gereedschapsvenster te
            slepen. Als u het naar het afbeeldingsvenster sleept, wordt het als een
            nieuwe verzameling lagen aan deze afbeelding toegevoegd.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Du kan også klikke på biletikonet eller filnamnet og dra
            biletet og sleppa det i verktøyskrinet for å opna biletet.
            Slepp du biletet i eit eksisterande bilete, vil det bli lagt
            til originalbiletet som eit nytt lag eller eit sett med lag.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            另外，一旦您找到该文件，能够点击图标并将它拖到
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 的工具箱中。(如果拖到一个已打开的
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 图像中，它将被添加为图像的一个或一系列图
            层。)
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            For many applications, you can click on a displayed image (a
            full image, not just a thumbnail) and drag it into the
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            toolbox.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            V některých aplikacích lze rovněž kliknout na obrázek a přetáhnout
            jej na panel nástrojů Gimpu.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Pour beaucoup d'applications vous pouvez cliquer sur
            l'image affichée (une image complète pas une simple vignette)
            et la glisser dans la boite à outils de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Per molte applicazioni, basta fare clic su un'immagine mostrata
            (un'immagine piena, non una miniatura) e trascinarla sulla barra
            degli strumenti di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            다른 응용 프로그램에서 열려진 이미지(미리보기가 아닌 전체
            이미지)를 <acronym>김프</acronym>의 도구상자로 끌어놓기(드래그
            앤 드랍)할 수도 있습니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            In veel toepassingen kunt u een afbeelding aanklikken (de volledige
            afbeelding dus, niet de iconografische weergave) om het te openen door het
            naar hetgereedschapsvenster van <acronym>GIMP</acronym> te verslepen.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            I noen oppsett kan du gjere dette også med det viste biletet.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            对大多数应用程序，您能点击一个显示的图像(一个完整图像，而不是缩
            略图)并拖动到 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 的工具箱中。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">Copy and Paste</term>
        <term lang="de">Kopieren und Einfügen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Copier-Coller</term>
        <term lang="it">Copia e incolla</term>
        <term lang="ko">복사와 붙여넣기</term>
        <term lang="nl">Kopieëren en plakken</term>
        <term lang="no">Kopier og Lim inn</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">粘贴和拷贝</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            For some applications, if the application gives you a
            way of copying the image to the clipboard, you can then open
            the image in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> by choosing
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Acquire</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Paste as New</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            from the Toolbox menu.  Support for this is somewhat
            variable, however, so your best bet is to try it and see
            whether it works.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            V mnoha aplikacích lze také zkopírovat obrázek do schránky. Je-li obrázek
            ve schránce, je možné ho otevřít v Gimpu volbou
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Získat</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Vložit jako nové</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            z menu panelu nástrojů. Tato funkce však nemusí fungovat na všech
            systémech.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            In verschiedenen Programmen und abhängig vom verwendeten Betriebssystem
            ist es möglich, Bilddaten in die Zwischenablage zu kopieren. Sie können
            diese Bilddaten dann als neues Bild aus der Zwischenablage einfügen
            mittels
            <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>Datei</guimenu>
             <guisubmenu>Holen</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>Als neues Bild einfügen</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>.
         </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Pour beaucoup d'applications, si elle vous permet de copier vers le
            presse-papiers alors vous pourrez l'ouvrir dans GIMP par le menu
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fichier</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Acquisition</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Coller en tant que nouveau</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            de la Boîte à outils. Le support de cette fonction est un peu arbitraire
            toutefois il ne coûte rien d'essayer.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
          Per alcune applicazioni, se l'applicazione permette la copia
            dell'immagine negli appunti, è possibile aprire l'immagine in
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> scegliendo
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>File</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Acquisizione</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Incolla come nuovo</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            dal menu degli strumenti. Il supporto a questa funzione non è
            sempre presente ma basta provare per verificarne il
            funzionamento.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            클립보드로 이미지를 복사할 수 있는 프로그램에서는 이미지를 
            클립보드로 복사한 다음, 김프 도구상자의
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>파일</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>얻기</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>새로 붙여넣기</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            메뉴를 통해 이미지를 열 수 있습니다. 이상으로 소개한 방법들을
            직접 해보면서 어떻게 동작하는지 확인하시기 바랍니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Sommige toepassingen bieden de mogelijkheid een afbeelding naar het
            klembord te kopieëren. In dat geval kunt u deze afbeelding met
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> openen door
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu><accel>B</accel>estand</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu><accel>I</accel>mporteren</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Plakken als <accel>n</accel>ieuw beeld</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            in het gereedschapsvenster. Deze methode werkt soms wel en soms niet,
            maar u kunt altijd proberen of het werkt.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Desse operasjonane er nokså avhengige av kva plattform
            (operativsystem) du bruker. I noen oppsett kan du importera
            biletfila via utklippstavla med kommandoen
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Importer</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Lim inn som ny</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> i hovudmenyen.
            Dersom dette ikkje verker i oppsettet ditt, kan du prøva om
            kommandoen
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Importer</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>From Clipboard</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            verkar betre, dersom du har denne i hovudmenyen.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            同样对大多数应用程序，如果程序让您拷贝图像到剪贴板中，您就能然后在
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>中选取
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>文件</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>获取</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>粘贴为新图像</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            在工具箱菜单中。对它的支持稍微有些差异，因此您最好尝试下并看看它是否正常工作。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">Image Browser</term>
        <term lang="cs">Image Browser</term>
        <term lang="de">Bildbetrachter</term>
        <term lang="fr">Explorateur d'image</term>
        <term lang="it">Navigatore immagini</term>
        <term lang="ko">이미지 브라우저</term>
        <term lang="nl">Afbeeldingen bladeren</term>
        <term lang="no">Biletutforskaren</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">图像浏览器</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            In Linux, you might want to take a look at a program called
            <application>gthumb</application>, an image-management
            application that in several ways nicely complements
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  In <application>gthumb</application>,
            you can cause an image to open in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            either by right-clicking on the icon and selecting
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> from among the list of options, or by
            dragging the icon into the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolbox.
            See the <ulink url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb home
            page</ulink> for more information. Other similar applications :
            <ulink url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink>,
            <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Můžete si také vyzkoušet <application>gthumb</application>,
            program pro správu a prohlížení obrázků, který velmi dobře
            doplňuje <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Můžete z něj ikonu obrázku
            přetáhnout na panel nástrojů Gimpu, a tak obrázek
            otevřít. Můžete také kliknout pravým tlačítkem myši na obrázek
            či jeho ikonu, zvolit z menu položku <guimenuitem>Otevřít
            pomocí</guimenuitem>, a z nabídky, která se objeví, vybrat
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Více informací o prohlížeči obrázků
            <application>gthumb</application> získáte na jeho <ulink
            url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">domovské stránce</ulink>.
            Existuje i mnoho dalších podobných aplikací pro prohlížení
            obrázků, např.  <ulink
            url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink> nebo <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Unter Linux sollten Sie vielleicht einen Blick auf ein Programm
            namens <application>gthumb</application> werfen, ein
            Bildbetrachter, der <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in vielerlei
            Hinsicht ergänzt.  In <application>gthumb</application> können
            Sie ein Bild mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> öffnen, indem Sie
            entweder nach einem Rechtsklick auf das Bild in der Liste der
            Optionen <acronym>GIMP</acronym> auswählen oder das Icon in das
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Fenster ziehen. unter <ulink
            url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb home page</ulink>
            finden Sie weitere Informationen. Andere, ähnliche Anwendungen:
            <ulink url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink>,
            <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Sous Linux, Vous pourriez être aussi intéressé par un
            gestionnaire d'image appelé <application>gthumb</application>
            qui complémente agréablement <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. On peut
            ouvrir une image par un clic droit sur l'icône et sélectionner
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> dans une liste d'options ou en déposant
            la vignette dans la Boîte à outils de
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Voyez <ulink
            url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb</ulink> pour plus
            d'informations.  Autres programmes similaires ; <ulink
            url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink>, <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            In Linux, è utile dare un'occhiata al programma
            <application>gthumb</application>, un'appicazione di gestione
            immagini che in vari modi è complementare a
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  In <application>gthumb</application>,
            è possibile aprire un'immagine in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sia
            facendo clic con il tasto destro del mouse sull'icona e
            successivamente selezionando <acronym>GIMP</acronym> da
            un'elenco di opzioni che trascinando l'icona sulla barra degli
            strumenti di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Per ulteriori
            informazioni visitare il <ulink
            url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">sito di gthumb</ulink>.
            Altre applicazioni simili a gthumb: <ulink
            url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink>, <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            리눅스에서는 <acronym>김프</acronym>와 호환성이 좋은 이미지 
            관리 프로그램인 <application>gthumb</application> 를 사용할 수 
            있습니다. <application>gthumb</application> 에서
            이미지 아이콘을 마우스 우클릭한 후 나오는 메뉴에서
            <acronym>김프</acronym>를 선택하거나 이미지를
            <acronym>김프</acronym> 도구상자로 드래그해서 이미지를
            <acronym>김프</acronym>로 열 수 있습니다. 더 자세한 내용은 
            <ulink url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb 
            홈페이지</ulink> 를 참조하십시오. 다른 응용 프로그램들 :
            <ulink url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink>, 
            <ulink 
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Onder linux bestaat het afbeeldingsbeheer programma
            <application>gthumb</application> dat erg handig met
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> samenwerkt; Dit programma laat een
            verzameling afbeeldingen die in een map aanwezig zijn, in
            kleine diaraampjes. U kunt zo'n afbeelding snel met
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> openen door er met de rechtermuisknop
            op te klikken en via de keuze
            <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>penen met</guimenuitem>
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uit de lijst van beschikbare
            toepassingen te kiezen. Een tweede manier is het slepen van het
            afbeeldingsicoon naar
            het<acronym>GIMP</acronym>-gereedschapsvenster. Meer informatie
            vindt u op de <ulink url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb
            webstek</ulink>. Andere soortgelijke toepassingen zijn: <ulink
            url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink> en <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du arbeider i Linux kan du sjå på programmet
            <application>gthumb</application>. Dette er eit
            biletbehandlingsprogram som på mange måtar utfyller
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Når du arbeider i
            <application>gthumb</application> kan du opna eit bilete i
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> anten ved å høgreklikka på ikonet
            og velje <acronym>GIMP</acronym> frå lista som dukkar opp,
            eller du kan dra ikonet over i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Sjå
            meir om dette på nettsida <ulink
            url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb home page</ulink>.
            Du finn liknande program på nettsidene
            <ulink url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink> og
            <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview
            </ulink>
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            在 Linux 中，您也许想要看一下一个 叫
            <application>gthumb</application> 的程序，一个图像管理程序在 许
            多方面对 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 是个很好的补充。 在
            <application>gthumb</application> 中，您可以通过右键点击图标 并
            从选项列表中选取 GIMP，或拖动图标到 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 工具
            箱中。请 到<ulink url="http://gthumb.sourceforge.net">gthumb主页
            </ulink> 获取更多信息。其它相似的程序有：<ulink
            url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net">gqview</ulink>, <ulink
            url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pierre.g/xnview/enhome.html">xnview</ulink>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para lang="en">
      When you open a file, using the File menu or any other method,
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      needs to determine what type of file it is. Unless there is no
      alternative, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      does not simply rely on the extension (such as ".jpg") to determine the
      file type, because extensions are not reliable: they vary from system to
      system; any file can be renamed to have any extension; and there are
      many reasons why a file name might lack an extension. Instead,
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      first tries to recognize a file by examining its contents: most of the
      commonly used graphics file formats have "magic headers" that permit
      them to be recognized. Only if the magic yields no result does
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> resort to using the extension.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      Bilddateien öffnen, versucht das Programm automatisch, das Dateiformat
      herauszufinden. Dies geschieht zunächst nicht über den Namen, sondern
      über den Inhalt der Datei. In vielen Dateiformaten für Bilder sind
      Zusatzinformationen versteckt, die helfen, den Dateityp zu bestimmen.
      Nur wenn die Erkennung des Dateityps mittels der Zusatzinformation
      mißlingt, wird versucht, das Format anhand der Dateinamenserweiterung zu
      erkennen und zu öffnen.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Když chcete otevřít soubor, ať už jakoukoliv z výše uvedených metod,
      musí <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zjistit, o jaký typ obrázku se jedná. Pokud
      má <acronym>GIMP</acronym> jinou možnost, nespoléhá se na přípony
      souborů (např. <filename>.jpg</filename>
      ), protože ty nejsou spolehlivé. Přípony se totiž liší systém od
      systému, soubory mohou mít nesprávné přípony, protože je lze libovolně
      přepsat, a soubor dokonce nemusí mít vůbec žádnou příponu. Proto se
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      snaží rozpoznat typ souboru podle jeho obsahu, většina grafických
      formátů má totiž v hlavičkách speciální údaje, podle kterých mohou být
      rozpoznány. Pouze pokud <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      nerozpozná typ souboru podle obsahu, uchýlí se k použití přípon.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Lorsque vous ouvrez un fichier, en utilisant le menu fichier ou par
      une autre méthode, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> a besoin de savoir de quel
      type de fichier il s'agit. A moins qu'il n'y ait pas d'alternative,
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ne se contente pas de l'extension (comme
      ".jpg") pour déterminer ce type.  En effet, les extensions ne sont
      pas dignes de confiance : elles varient selon les systèmes ; un
      fichier peut-être renommé avec une fausse extension ; et il y a plein
      de raisons pour qu'un fichier n'ait pas d'extension du
      tout. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> essaye d'abord de reconnaître le type
      en examinant le contenu du fichier : la plupart des formats de
      fichiers graphiques couramment utilisés ont un <quote>en-tête
      magique</quote> qui leur permet d'être reconnu. C'est seulement si
      cet en-tête n'est d'aucun secours que <acronym>GIMP</acronym> se
      contentera d'utiliser l'extension.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Quando si apre un file, usando il menu file o un'altro metodo, GIMP
      necessita di determinare il tipo di file in questione. A meno che non
      ci siano alternative, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> non si affida completamente alle
      estensioni (come ".jpg") per determinare il tipo di file, dato che le
      estensioni non sono affidabili: esse infatti variano da sistema a
      sistema, ogni file può essere rinominato in modo da avere
      qualsiasi estensione e spesso succede che un file manchi totalmente
      di estensione. Percò <acronym>GIMP</acronym> prima prova a riconoscere il file
      esaminando il suo contenuto: molti dei formati file grafici più usati
      possiedono delle "intestazioni magiche" che consentono loro di essere
      riconosciuti. Solo se questa "magia" non dà nessun risultato che
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, come ultima risorsa, usa le estensioni dei file.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      파일 메뉴나 다른 방법을 통해 파일을 열때 <acronym>김프</acronym>는
      해당 파일의 타입 정보를 필요로 합니다. 특별한 경우가 아니면
      <acronym>김프</acronym>는 .jpg 과 같은 확장자로 파일 타입을 판별하지
      않습니다. 그것은 파일이 다양한 시스템으로 옮겨다닐 경우, 확장자가
      바뀌는 경우도 있기 때문에 신뢰도가 떨어지기 때문입니다. 따라서 
      <acronym>김프</acronym>는 먼저 파일의 내용을 보고 파일 형태를
      확인합니다. 대부분의 그래픽 파일 포맷은 "magic headers" 를 가지고 
      있어 자신이 그래픽 파일임을 알리기 때문에 "magic headers" 가 없는 
      경우에만 확장자로 파일을 판별합니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Wanneer u een bestand met het
      <guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>estand</guimenuitem> opent, moet de
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eerst bepalen in welke opmaak het bestand de
      afbeelding beschrijft; het besandstype. Tenzij het niet anders mogelijk
      is zal dit niet eenvoudigweg uit de uitgang van het bestand (de <quote>
      extensie</quote>zoals <acronym>jpg</acronym> o.i.d.) afgeleid worden
      omdat extensies niet betrouwbaar zijn; ze kunnen van computersysteem tot
      computersysteem varieëren. Bovendien kan ieder bestand met een
      willekeurige andere uitgang benoemd worden. Verder zijn er ook nog veel
      redenen waarom een uitgang kan ontbreken. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kijkt
      eerst in het bestand om aan de hand hiervan te bepalen om wat voor
      opmaak het gaat: de inhoud is een betrouwbaardere maatstaf voor het
      bestandstype. De meest gebruikte bestandsopmaken maken gebruik van de
      zogenaamde <quote>magic headers</quote> oftewijl Magische koppen waaraan
      ze herkend kunnen worden. Alleen als deze koppen geen uitsluitsel geven,
      zal <acronym>GIMP</acronym> de indeling volgens de uitgang proberen te
      gebruiken.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Når du opnar ei fil, må <acronym>GIMP</acronym> finna ut kva filtype
      dette er. Det er diverre ikkje nok bare å sjå på filutvidinga, som
      t.d. <quote>.jpg</quote>. Måten dei ulike filtypane blir laga på i dei
      ulike programma varierer nokså mykje. Dessutan er det fritt fram for å
      gi ei fil den utvidinga, det <quote>etternamnet</quote>, ein ønskjer,
      eller å sløyfa det heilt. Så i staden for å sjå på utvidinga, prøver
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> å sjå på innhaldet. Dei fleste biletformata
      har filer med <quote>magisk heading</quote> som identifiserer filtypen.
      Bare når denne headingen ikkje gir noe brukbart resultat, nyttar
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> filutvidinga som kjennemerke på filtypen.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当您打开文件，使用文件菜单或其它方式，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 需要知道
      这个文件是什么格式。 除非实在没有选择，不然 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 并
      不是简单的靠文件扩展名(如“.jpg”)来决定文 件格式，因为扩展名并不可靠：
      它们在各个系统中不同来;任何文件都可以改为 其它的扩展名;由于很多原因一
      个文件会没有扩展名。而<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 首先尝试检查其 内容来了
      解是什么文件：大部分常用的图形文件格式都可以通过“magic headers”来被识
      别。只有那些无法识别的才会用到扩展名。
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fileformats-export-dialog">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Saving Files</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Speichern von Bilddateien</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ukládání souborů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Enregistrer les fichiers</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Salvataggio dei file</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">파일 저장</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Opslaan van de afbeeldingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å lagra filer</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">保存文件</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      There are several commands for saving images. A list, and information on
      how to use them, can be found in the section covering the
      <link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">File menu</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono diversi comandi per salvare le immagini. Un elenco e le
      corrispondenti informazioni su come usarli li si può trovare alla
      sezione che riguarda il
      <!--link linkend='gimp-image-window-menus-file' FIXME: it -->Menu
      file<!--/link-->.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      이미지를 저장하는 명령어는 여러가지가 있습니다. 그 방법들을 사용하는
      법은
      <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">파일
      메뉴</link> -->
      파일 메뉴에 설명되어 있습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Er zijn veel opdrachten om afbeeldingen op te slaan. In het hoofdstuk
      <!-- nl FIXME: link linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file"-->Bestand
      menu<!--/link--> zult u meer informatie kunnen vinden welke dat zijn en
      hoe u ze kunt gebruiken.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan lagra biletfiler på fleire måtar. Du finn meir om dette i
      <!-- PENDING: no (menus -> menus-file.xml)
      <link linkend='gimp-image-window-menus-file'-->Filmenyen<!--/link-->
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      有许多保存图像的命令。关于其列表和如何使用它们的信息请看<link
      linkend="gimp-image-window-menus-file">文件菜单</link>这一节。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to save the images you create in a
      wide variety of formats.  It is important to realize that the only
      format capable of saving <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the information in
      an image, including layers, transparency, etc., is GIMP's native XCF
      format.   Every other format preserves some image properties and loses
      others.  When you save an image, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tries to let
      you know about this, but basically it is up to you to understand the
      capabilities of the format you choose.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bietet eine ganze Reihe von Dateiformaten,
      in denen Sie je nach Verwendung Ihre Bilder abspeichern können.
      Wichtig ist zu wissen, dass nur das <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-eigene
      Format <link linkend="gimp-xcf-open">XCF</link> imstande ist,
      alle Informationen wie Ebenen, Pfade, Transparenz, ohne Verluste
      abzuspeichern. Das heißt, dass nach dem nächsten Öffnen der
      Bilddatei alle Ihre angelegten Ebenen, Pfade, etc. noch vorhanden
      sind.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> permette di salvare le immagini che abbiamo
      creato in una varietà di formati. È importante ricordare che l'unico
      formato in grado di mantenere <emphasis>tutte</emphasis> le
      informazioni sull'immagine, inclusi livelli, trasparenze, ecc. è il
      formato nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> xcf. Ogni altro formato
      mantiene solo alcune informazioni sull'immagine mentre altre vanno
      perse. Quando si salva un'immagine, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tenta di
      ricordarvi questo fatto, ma è comunque compito dell'utente
      comprendere le capacitza del formato immagine che si sceglie.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym>를 이용하면 이미지를 다양한 포맷으로 저장할
      수가 있습니다. 하지만 레이어, 투명도 등 이미지의 
      <emphasis>모든</emphasis> 정보를 저장할 수 있는 것은 김프 전용 포맷인
      XCF 뿐입니다. 다른 모든 포맷들은 특정 속성만 보존할뿐 나머지는 모두
      잃어버립니다. 이미지를 저장할때 <acronym>김프</acronym>에서 이러한 사실을
      알려주긴 하지만, 기본적으로 선택한 포맷의 특성은 사용자 자신이 이해하고 
      있어야 합니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan lagra eit bilete i svært mange ulike format. Dei ulike
      formata kan lagra ulike opplysningar om biletet, men bare
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt eige filformat (<filename>XCF</filename>)
      lagrar <emphasis>alle</emphasis> dei viktigaste opplysningane om
      biletet. Ønskjer du å lagra eit bilete i eit anna format, vil
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> seie frå om at du kjem til å misse data,
      men sjølvsagt er det opp til deg å kjenne eigenskapane til det
      formatet du vel.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 让您保存图像为多种不同的格式。有一点需要重视：
      只有<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 内建的 XCF 格式才能保存图像中包括图层，透
      明度等的<emphasis>全部</emphasis>信息。其它的各种格式都是保存一些图像
      属性丢失一些。当您保存图像时，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 会让您告诉您这些，
      不过在原则上您需要了解一下您所选择格式的基本特性。
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Example of an Export dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Exportní dialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Ansicht des Exportieren-Dialogs.</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Le dialogue d'export</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Un'esempio di finestra di esportazione immagine
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">내보내기 대화상자 예제</phrase>
        <phrase lang="nl">Voorbeeld van een exporteer dialoogvenster</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på ein eksportdialog</phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">导出对话框范例</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs;de;en;zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/export-dialog-en.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/it/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="ko">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/ko/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="nl">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/nl/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/export-dialog.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      As stated above, there is no file format, with the exception of GIMP's
      native <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>
      format, that is capable of storing all the data in a
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      image. When you ask to save an image in a format that will not
      completely represent it, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      notifies you of this, tells you what kind of information will be lost,
      and asks you whether you would like to "export" the image in a form that
      the file type can handle. Exporting an image does not modify the image
      itself, so you do not lose anything by doing this.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Kromě XCF, nativního formátu GIMPu, neexistuje žádný jiný formát, který
      by dokázal uchovat kompletní informace o obrázku. Pokud požádáte
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, aby uložil obrázek ve formátu, který ho
      nedokáže plně popsat, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vás upozorní, oznámí vám,
      jaké informace budou ztraceny (protože je není možné ve zvoleném formátu
      zaznamenat) a zeptá se, zda chcete obrázek exportovat do podoby, kterou
      lze v daném formátu uložit (tedy do podoby bez informací, které formát
      neumí popsat). Exportování ale nezmění vlastní otevřený obrázek v Gimpu,
      takže ten bude stále obsahovat informace všechny a můžete ho později
      uložit v jiném formátu, např. XCF.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wie bereits beschrieben, kann nur das
      <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>-Dateiformat alle
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-eigenen
      Informationen speichern. Wenn Sie ein anderes Format
      benutzen, werden Sie darauf hingewiesen, welche Informationen nicht
      gespeichert werden können. Da es sich meist um Zusatzinformationen
      handelt, die das Bild in seinem <quote>Aussehen</quote>
      nicht verändern, verlieren Sie keine wichtigen Bildbestandteile beim
      Abspeichern in ein anderes Dateiformat.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Aucun format de fichier, hormis le format natif du
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>, n'est
      capable de contenir toutes les données d'une image
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Lorsque vous demandez d'enregistrer une image
      dans un format qui ne la représentera pas intégralement,
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vous le signale, en vous informant des
      informations qui seront perdues et en vous demandant si vous voulez
      <quote>exporter</quote> l'image dans une structure que le format de
      fichier supportera. Exporter une image ne modifie pas l'image elle-même,
      aussi ne perdez-vous rien en faisant cela.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Come detto sopra, non c'è formato file, con l'eccezione del formato
      nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> <!--link linkend="gimp-xcf-save" FIXME it
      -->XCF<!--/link-->, in grado di memorizzare tutti i dati di un'immagine
      di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Quando si richiede di salvare un'immagine in
      un formato che non la rappresenta completamente, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      lo segnala, elencando le informazioni che verranno perse, e chiede se si
      vuole "esportare" l'immagine in una forma che il formato di file possa
      gestire. L'esportazione di un'immagine non modifica l'immagine originale
      perciò non si perde nulla nell'operazione.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      앞서 말한 것과 같이, <acronym>김프</acronym> 이미지의 모든 정보를
      저장할 수 있는 것은 김프 전용 포맷인
      <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> 뿐입니다. 그 외의 포맷으로 
      저장을 하려고 하면 <acronym>김프</acronym> 는 어떠한 정보가 손실될 것인지
      알려주며, 해당 파일 타입으로 이미지로 "내보내기" 를 할 것인지 묻습니다. 
      내보내기 작업은 원본 이미지에는 아무런 변형을 가하지 않으므로, 이 작업 
      자체만으로는 어떠한 정보도 손실되지 않습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Zoals we hierboven al opmerkten kan alleen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
      eigen <!-- XXX_NL link linkend="gimp-xcf-save"-->XCF<!--/link--> opmaak
      alle informatie van een <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-afbeelding opslaan. Als
      u deze dus in een andere opmaak opslaat, laat  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> u
      eerst weten dat, en welke informatie er verloren zal gaan en u vragen of
      u accoord gaat met de manier waarop er met dit informatieverlies
      omgegaan wordt. Het exporteren veranderd niets aan de afbeelding zelf,
      dus hierin gaat geen informatie verloren (tot u de afbeelding sluit en
      er op dat moment geen <acronym>XCF</acronym>-versie van opgeslagen heeft
      natuurlijk.)
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Som sagt ovanfor, er det bare filformatet
      <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> som tar vare på (nesten)
      alle data i eit bilete. Prøver du å lagra eit bilete i eit format som
      ikkje tar vare på informasjonen i biletet, vil <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      åtvara deg med ei melding om dette, og kva for data som går tapt
      dersom du likevel nyttar det valde formatet. Du får også eit spørsmål
      om du heller vil <quote>eksportera</quote> biletet. Når du eksporterar
      eit bilete, blir sjølve biletet ikkje forandra.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      正如上面所说的，除了 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 专用的 <link
      linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> 格式，没有其它一种格式可以保存
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 图像中的所有信息。当您要将图像保存为一种无法完
      全表现其内容的格式时，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 就会提醒您，并告诉您那些
      信息会丢失，是否愿意“输出”图像到该文件格式能处理的形式。输出一个图像并
      不修改图像本身，所以您不会因为这么做而丢失什么。
    </para>

    <note lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;zh_CN">
      <para lang="en">
        When you close an image (possibly by
        quitting GIMP), you are warned if the image is "dirty"; that is,
        if it has been changed without subsequently being saved.  Saving
        an image in any file format will cause the image to be
        considered "not dirty", even if the file format does not
        represent all of the information from the image.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        Předtím, než zavřete obrázek (například ukončením Gimpu), vás GIMP
        varuje, pokud je obrázek tzv. nečistý., tj. byl od posledního uložení
        změněn. Uložení obrázku ho učiní čistým, a to i v případě, že zvolený
        formát neuchovává úplnou informaci o obrázku.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie ein Bild schließen (etwa, weil Sie GIMP beenden), erhalten
        Sie eine Warnung, dass das Bild verändert und nicht gesichert wurde.
        Ein Bild, das in irgendeinem Format gespeichert wurde, wird als
        unverändert angesehen, auch wenn das gewählte Dateiformat nicht
        alle Informationen zu diesem Bild enthält.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Lorsque vous fermez une image (par exemple en quittant GIMP), vous
        êtes prévenu si l'image a été modifiée sans être enregistrée. Une
        image n'est plus considérée comme modifiée dès qu'elle est
        enregistrée.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Quando si chiude un'immagine (probabilmente uscendo da GIMP), si
        viene avvertiti se l'immagine è "sporca"; cioè, se è stata
        modificata senza successivamente essere salvata. Salvando
        un'immagine in qualsiasi formato file, farà in modo di far
        considerare a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> l'immagine come "non sporca",
        anche se il formato file non garantisce il salvataggio di tutte le
        informazioni che compongono l'immagine.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        이미지를 닫을 때(혹은 김프를 종료할 때) 해당 이미지가 "변경된"
        것이라면(변경된 후에 저장이 되지 않은), 경고가 나타납니다.
        그리고 어떠한 형태의 파일 포맷이든 저장을 하게 되면, 이미지가 가지고 있는
        모든 정보를 보전하지 못하더라도 이미지는 "변경되지 않은" 이미지로
        간주되어집니다.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        Wanneer u een afbeelding afsluit en deze <quote>vuil</quote> is wordt
        u hiervoor gewaarschuwd. Een <quote>vuile</quote> afbeelding is een
        afbeelding waarop wijzigingen zijn aangebracht die nog niet opgeslagen
        zijn. Zodra u de afbeelding in een willekeurig formaat opslaat (dus
        ook formaten waarbij informatie verloren gaat) veranderd de status
        naar <quote>niet vuil</quote>.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Når du lukker eit bilete t.d. ved å avslutta <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
        vil du få opp ei melding dersom biletet er <quote>ureint</quote>,
        dvs. at biletet er endra utan å bli lagra etterpå. Lagrar du eit
        bilete, vil biletet etter lagringa bli sett på som
        <quote>reint</quote>, sjølv om filformatet du valde ikkje lagrar alle
        biletdata.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
      当您关闭一个图像时(也许时退出 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>),如果该图像被改
      动后而未保存，即所谓 的“脏”文件,这时您将被警告。当您将图像保存为某种格
      式后，这个文件就是"干 净"的,即使该文件格式不能无法显示图像中的所有信息。
      </para>

    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
