<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-04-13 added Spanish translation by AntI
  2006-09-12 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-29 added Korean translation by Mr.Dust
  2006-05-03 added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-text">
  <title>Text</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Text</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title>Embellishing Text</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Embellishing text</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <figure>
      <title>Fancy text</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/logo-examples.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Four fancy text items created using logo scripts: <quote>alien
            neon</quote>, <quote>bovination</quote>, <quote>frosty</quote>,
            and <quote>chalk</quote>. Default settings were used for
            everything except font size.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      There are many things you can do to vary the appearance of text beyond
      just rendering it with different fonts or different colors. By
      converting a text item to a selection or a path, you can fill it, stroke
      the outlines, transform it, or generally apply the whole panoply of
      GIMP tools to get interesting effects. As a demonstration of some of the
      possibilities, try out the "logo" scripts at
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Create</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Logos</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>.
      Each of these scripts allows you to enter some text, and then creates
      a new image showing a logo constructed out of that text. If you would
      like to modify one of these scripts, or construct a logo script of your
      own, the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-script-fu">Using Script-Fu</link>
      and
      <link linkend="gimp-using-script-fu-tutorial">Script-Fu Tutorial</link>
      sections should help you get started. Of course, you don't need
      Script-Fu to create these sorts of effects, only to automate them.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fonts">
    <title>Adding Fonts</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Fonts</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fonts</primary>
      <secondary>Add</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      For the most authoritative and up-to-date information on fonts
      in GIMP, consult the <quote>Fonts in GIMP 2.0</quote> page
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-fonts"/>
      at the GIMP web site. This section attempts to give you a
      helpful overview.
    </para>
    <para>
      GIMP uses the FreeType 2 font engine to render fonts, and a system
      called Fontconfig to manage them. GIMP will let you use any font in
      Fontconfig's font path; it will also let you use any font it finds in
      GIMP's font search path, which is set on the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Font Folders</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog. By default, the font search path
      includes a system GIMP-fonts folder (which you should not alter, even
      though it is actually empty), and a <filename>fonts</filename>
      folder inside your personal GIMP directory. You can add new folders to
      the font search path if it is more convenient for you.
    </para>
    <para>
      FreeType 2 is a very powerful and flexible system. By default, it
      supports the following font file formats:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>TrueType fonts (and collections)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Type 1 fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CID-keyed Type 1 fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CFF fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>OpenType fonts (both TrueType and CFF variants)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>SFNT-based bitmap fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>X11 PCF fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Windows FNT fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>BDF fonts (including anti-aliased ones)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>PFR fonts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Type42 fonts (limited support)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      You can also add modules to support other types of font files. See
      FREETYPE 2 <xref linkend="bibliography-online-freetype"/> for more
      information.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Linux</title>
      <para>
        On a Linux system, if the Fontconfig utility is set up as usual, all
        you need to do to add a new font is to place the file in the directory
        <filename>~/.fonts</filename>.
        This will make the font available not only to GIMP, but to any other
        program that uses Fontconfig. If for some reason you want the font to
        be available to GIMP only, you can place it in the
        <filename>fonts</filename>
        sub-directory of your personal GIMP directory, or some other location
        in your font search path. Doing either will cause the font to show up
        the next time you start GIMP. If you want to use it in an already
        running GIMP, press the <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis>
        <guiicon>
          <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-reload-16.png"/>
        </guiicon>
        button in the <link linkend="gimp-font-dialog">Fonts dialog</link>.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Windows</title>
      <para>
        The easiest way to install a font is to drag the file onto the
        Fonts directory and let the shell do its magic.  Unless you've done
        something creative, it's probably in its default location of
        <filename role="html">C:\windows\fonts</filename>
        <filename role="tex">C:\\windows\\fonts</filename>
        or
        <filename role="html">C:\winnt\fonts</filename><filename
        role="tex">C:\\winnt\\fonts</filename>.
        Sometimes double-clicking on
        a font will install it as well as display it; sometimes it only
        displays it.  This method will make the font available not only to
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but also to other Windows applications.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Mac OS X</title>
  <!--http://docs.info.apple.com/article.html?path=FontBook/2.0/en/fb680.html-->
      <para>
        There are several ways to install fonts on your system.  You can
        drag-and-drop them to the <quote>Fonts</quote> folder in
        <quote>Libraries</quote> folder of your <quote>Home Folder</quote>.  Or
        you may use <application>Font Book</application>, invoked by
        double-clicking the font file icon in the Finder.  You can see what the
        font looks like, and click your favorite fonts so that their files are
        to be installed on the system.  These methods will make the fonts
        available for all applications, not only <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  If
        you want all users can use the fonts, drag-and-drop the fonts to the
        <quote>Fonts</quote> folder in <quote>Libraries</quote> folder of the
        <productname>Mac OS X</productname> Disk, or to the
        <quote>Computer</quote> folder in the <guilabel>Collection</guilabel>
        column of <application>Font Book</application>.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
      To install a Type 1 file, you need both the
      <filename>.pfb</filename> and <filename>.pfm</filename>
      files. Drag the one that gets an icon into the fonts folder.
      The other one doesn't strictly need to be in the same directory
      when you drag the file, since it uses some kind of search
      algorithm to find it if it's not, but in any case putting it in
      the same directory does no harm.
    </para>
    <para>
      In principle, GIMP can use any type of font on Windows that FreeType can
      handle; however, for fonts that Windows can't handle natively, you
      should install them by placing the font files in the
      <filename>fonts</filename>
      folder of your personal GIMP directory, or some other location in your
      font search path. The support Windows has varies by version. All that
      GIMP runs on support at least TrueType, Windows FON, and Windows FNT.
      Windows 2000 and later support Type 1 and OpenType. Windows ME supports
      OpenType and possibly Type 1 (but the most widely used Windows GIMP
      installer does not officially support Windows ME, although it may work
      anyway).
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        GIMP uses Fontconfig to manage fonts on Windows as well as Linux. The
        instructions above work because Fontconfig by default uses the Windows
        fonts directory, i. e., the same fonts that Windows uses itself. If
        for some reason your Fontconfig is set up differently, you will have
        to figure out where to put fonts so that GIMP can find them: in any
        case, the <filename>fonts</filename>
        folder of your personal GIMP directory should work.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="font-problems">
    <title>Font Problems</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fonts</primary>
      <secondary>Problems</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Problems with fonts have probably been responsible for more GIMP 2 bug
      reports than any other single cause, although they have become much less
      frequent in the most recent releases in the 2.0 series. In most cases
      they have been caused by malformed font files giving trouble to
      Fontconfig. If you experience crashes at start-up when GIMP scans your
      font directories, the best solution is to upgrade to a version of
      Fontconfig newer than 2.2.0. As a quick workaround you can start gimp
      with the <filename>--no-fonts</filename>
      command-line option, but then you will not be able to use the text tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      Another known problem is that Pango 1.2 cannot load fonts that don't
      provide an Unicode character mapping. (Pango is the text layout library
      used by GIMP.) A lot of symbol fonts fall into this category. On some
      systems, using such a font can cause GIMP to crash. Updating to Pango
      1.4 will fix this problem and makes symbol fonts available in GIMP.
    </para>
    <para>
      A frequent source of confusion occurs on Windows systems, when GIMP
      encounters a malformed font file and generates an error message: this
      causes a console window to pop up so that you can see the message.
      <emphasis>
        Do not close that console window. It is harmless, and closing it will
        shut down GIMP.
      </emphasis>
      When this happens, it often seems to users that GIMP has crashed. It
      hasn't: closing the console window causes Windows to shut GIMP down.
      Unfortunately, this annoying situation is caused by an interaction
      between Windows and the libraries that GIMP links to: it cannot be fixed
      within GIMP. All you need to do, though, if this happens, is minimize
      the console window and ignore it.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
