<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-04-13 added Spanish translation by AntI
  2006-09-12 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-29 added Korean translation by Mr.Dust
  2006-05-03 added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-text">
  <title>Text</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Text</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fonts">
    <title>Adding Fonts</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Fonts</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fonts</primary>
      <secondary>Add</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      GIMP uses the FreeType 2 font engine to render fonts, and a system
      called Fontconfig to manage them.
      FreeType 2 supports many common font file formats.
      You can also add modules to support other types of font files. See
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-freetype"/> for more information.
    </para>
    <para>
      Any font in Fontconfig's font path is available in GIMP. In addition,
      any font which is located in GIMP's <guilabel>Font Folders</guilabel>
      is available in GIMP. Font Folders are set on the
      <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> page in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Folders</link> preferences.
      By default, there are two <guilabel>Font Folders</guilabel>: The system
      GIMP fonts folder (which you should not alter), and a
      <filename>fonts</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP directory.
      You can also add additional font folders if wanted.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Linux:</para>
        <para>There are several ways to install a font:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Use an application like <application>GNOME Fonts</application> or
            <application>KFontView</application> to install the font.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Place the font file in the directory
            <filename>~/.local/share/fonts/</filename>. This will make the font
            available to you only.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            If you have administrator rights, place the font file in the
            directory <filename>/usr/local/share/fonts/</filename>.
            This will make the font available to all users.
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          In all cases, the font will become available to all programs that use
          Fontconfig.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Microsoft Windows:</para>
        <para>There are several ways to install a font system-wide:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Drag the font file into the Fonts directory
            <filename role="html">C:\Windows\Fonts</filename>
            <filename role="tex">C:\\Windows\\Fonts</filename>.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            Install the font via the Windows <application>Control Panel</application>.
            In Windows 7 and Windows 10, go to <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Control Panel</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Fonts</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. In Windows 8.1, go to
            <menuchoice><guimenu>Control Panel</guimenu><guisubmenu>Appearance and
            Personalization</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Fonts</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          Windows support for different font file formats varies by Windows version.
          Please ask in a Windows support forum in case of problems.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X</para>
  <!--https://support.apple.com/guide/font-book/welcome/mac-->
        <para>
          Install the font via the <application>Font Book</application> application.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The installed font will show up the next time you start GIMP. If you
        want to use it in an already running GIMP instance, press the
        <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis>
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/view-refresh.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        button in the <link linkend="gimp-font-dialog">Fonts dialog</link>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        If for some reason you run into problems trying to install a font
        system-wide, try to install the font in the <filename>fonts</filename>
        folder of your personal GIMP directory instead (see above).
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      For the most authoritative and up-to-date information on fonts
      in GIMP, consult the <quote>Fonts in GIMP 2.0</quote> page
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-fonts"/>
      at the GIMP web site.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="font-problems">
    <title>Font Problems</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fonts</primary>
      <secondary>Problems</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      In most cases, problems with fonts 
      have been caused by malformed font files giving trouble to
      Fontconfig. If you experience crashes at start-up when GIMP scans your
      font directories, as a quick workaround you can start GIMP
      with the <filename>--no-fonts</filename>
      <link linkend="gimp-concepts-running-command-line">command line
      argument</link>, but then you will not be able to use the text tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      A frequent source of confusion occurs on Windows systems, when GIMP
      encounters a malformed font file and generates an error message: this
      causes a console window to pop up so that you can see the message.
      <emphasis>
        Do not close that console window. It is harmless, and closing it will
        shut down GIMP.
      </emphasis>
      When this happens, it often seems to users that GIMP has crashed. It
      hasn't: closing the console window causes Windows to shut GIMP down.
      Unfortunately, this annoying situation is caused by an interaction
      between Windows and the libraries that GIMP links to: it cannot be fixed
      within GIMP. All you need to do, though, if this happens, is minimize
      the console window and ignore it.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
