<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-04-13 added Spanish translation by AntI
  2006-09-12 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-29 added Korean translation by Mr.Dust
  2006-05-03 added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-text">
  <title>Text</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Text</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-fonts">
    <title>Adding Fonts</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Fonts</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fonts</primary>
      <secondary>Add</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      For the most authoritative and up-to-date information on fonts
      in GIMP, consult the <quote>Fonts in GIMP 2.0</quote> page
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-fonts"/>
      at the GIMP web site. This section attempts to give you a
      helpful overview.
    </para>
    <para>
      GIMP uses the FreeType 2 font engine to render fonts, and a system
      called Fontconfig to manage them. Any font in Fontconfig's font path
      is available in GIMP. In addition, any font which is located in GIMP's
      <guilabel>Font Folders</guilabel> is available in GIMP. Font Folders are
      set on the <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> page in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Folders</link> preferences.
      By default, there are two <guilabel>Font Folders</guilabel>: The system
      GIMP fonts folder (which you should not alter), and a
      <filename>fonts</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP directory.
      You can also add additional font folders if wanted.
    </para>
    <para>
      FreeType 2 supports many common font file formats.
      You can also add modules to support other types of font files. See
      FREETYPE 2 <xref linkend="bibliography-online-freetype"/> for more
      information.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Linux</title>
      <para>
        On a Linux system, if the Fontconfig utility is set up as usual, all
        you need to do to add a new font is to place the file in the directory
        <filename>~/.fonts</filename>.
        This will make the font available not only to GIMP, but to any other
        program that uses Fontconfig. If for some reason you want the font to
        be available to GIMP only, you can place it in the
        <filename>fonts</filename>
        sub-directory of your personal GIMP directory, or some other location
        in your font search path. Doing either will cause the font to show up
        the next time you start GIMP. If you want to use it in an already
        running GIMP, press the <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis>
        <guiicon>
          <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-reload-16.png"/>
        </guiicon>
        button in the <link linkend="gimp-font-dialog">Fonts dialog</link>.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Windows</title>
      <para>
        The easiest way to install a font is to drag the file onto the
        Fonts directory and let the shell do its magic.  Unless you've done
        something creative, it's probably in its default location of
        <filename role="html">C:\windows\fonts</filename>
        <filename role="tex">C:\\windows\\fonts</filename>
        or
        <filename role="html">C:\winnt\fonts</filename><filename
        role="tex">C:\\winnt\\fonts</filename>.
        Sometimes double-clicking on
        a font will install it as well as display it; sometimes it only
        displays it.  This method will make the font available not only to
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but also to other Windows applications.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Mac OS X</title>
  <!--https://support.apple.com/guide/font-book/welcome/mac-->
      <para>
        There are several ways to install fonts on your system.  You can
        drag-and-drop them to the <quote>Fonts</quote> folder in
        <quote>Libraries</quote> folder of your <quote>Home Folder</quote>.  Or
        you may use <application>Font Book</application>, invoked by
        double-clicking the font file icon in the Finder.  You can see what the
        font looks like, and click your favorite fonts so that their files are
        to be installed on the system.  These methods will make the fonts
        available for all applications, not only <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  If
        you want all users can use the fonts, drag-and-drop the fonts to the
        <quote>Fonts</quote> folder in <quote>Libraries</quote> folder of the
        <productname>Mac OS X</productname> Disk, or to the
        <quote>Computer</quote> folder in the <guilabel>Collection</guilabel>
        column of <application>Font Book</application>.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
      In principle, GIMP can use any type of font on Windows that FreeType can
      handle; however, for fonts that Windows can't handle natively, you
      should install these fonts by placing the font files in the
      <filename>fonts</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP directory (see
      above). Windows support for different font file formats varies by the
      Windows version. Please ask in a Windows support forum in case of problems.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        GIMP uses Fontconfig to manage fonts on Windows as well as Linux. The
        instructions above work because Fontconfig by default uses the Windows
        fonts directory, i. e., the same fonts that Windows uses itself. If
        for some reason your Fontconfig is set up differently, you will have
        to figure out where to put fonts so that GIMP can find them: in any
        case, the <filename>fonts</filename>
        folder of your personal GIMP directory should work.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="font-problems">
    <title>Font Problems</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Fonts</primary>
      <secondary>Problems</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      In most cases, problems with fonts 
      have been caused by malformed font files giving trouble to
      Fontconfig. If you experience crashes at start-up when GIMP scans your
      font directories, as a quick workaround you can start GIMP
      with the <filename>--no-fonts</filename>
      command-line option, but then you will not be able to use the text tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      A frequent source of confusion occurs on Windows systems, when GIMP
      encounters a malformed font file and generates an error message: this
      causes a console window to pop up so that you can see the message.
      <emphasis>
        Do not close that console window. It is harmless, and closing it will
        shut down GIMP.
      </emphasis>
      When this happens, it often seems to users that GIMP has crashed. It
      hasn't: closing the console window causes Windows to shut GIMP down.
      Unfortunately, this annoying situation is caused by an interaction
      between Windows and the libraries that GIMP links to: it cannot be fixed
      within GIMP. All you need to do, though, if this happens, is minimize
      the console window and ignore it.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
