<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-08-27 lexa: replaced list by sect3
  2007-04-24 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-02-21 lexa: changed top level from chapter to sect1
  2006-08-18 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-06-19 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-15 HdJ: Added dutch translation.
  2006-05-13 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-10 changed structure
  2006-02-20 fixed #322305
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">
  <title>Getting Unstuck</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Getting Unstuck</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck-general">
    <title>Stuck!</title>
    <para>
      All right, okay: you're stuck. You're trying to use one of the tools on
      an image, and nothing is happening, and nothing you try makes any
      difference. Your fists are starting to clench, and your face is starting
      to feel warm. Are you going to have to kill the program, and lose all
      your work? This sucks!
    </para>
    <para>
      Well, hold on a second. This happens pretty frequently, even to people
      who've used <acronym>GIMP</acronym> for a long time, but generally the
      cause is not so hard
      to figure out (and fix) if you know where to look. Lets be calm, and
      go through a checklist that will probably get you GIMPing happily again.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck-common-causes">
    <title>Common Causes of GIMP Non-Responsiveness</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>There is a floating selection</title>
      <figure>
        <title>
          Layers dialog showing a floating selection.
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-floating-sel.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        If there is a floating selection, many actions are impossible
        until the floating section is anchored.
        To check, look at the Layers dialog (making
        sure it's set to the image you're working on) and see whether the
        top layer is called <quote>Floating Selection</quote>.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to solve:</emphasis>
        Either anchor the floating selection, or convert it into an
        ordinary (non-floating) layer. If you need help on how to do this,
        see <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection">
          Floating Selections
        </link>.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>The selection is hidden</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Unstuck show selection menu</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-show-selection-menu.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              In the View menu, make sure that "Show Selection" is checked.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        If this is the problem, merely reading this will already have made
        you realize it, probably, but to explain in any case: sometimes
        the flickering line that outlines the selection is annoying
        because it makes it hard to see important details of the image, so
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gives you the option of hiding the selection,
        by unchecking
        <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem>
        in the <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        menu. It is easy to forget that you have done this, though.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> If this
        hasn't rung any bells, it isn't the problem, and if it has,
        you probably know how to fix it, because it doesn't happen
        unless you explicitly tell it to; but anyway:  just go to
        the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu for the image and, if
        <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem> is
        unchecked, click on it..
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>You are acting outside of the selection</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Unstuck select all</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-select-all.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Click <quote>All</quote>
              in the Select menu to make sure that everything is selected.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
        If doing this has destroyed a selection that you wanted to keep, hit
        <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>
        (undo) a couple of times to restore it, and then we'll figure
        out what the problem is. There are a couple of possibilities. If you
        couldn't see any selection, there may have been a very tiny one, or
        even one that contained no pixels. If this was the case, it surely is
        not a selection that you wanted to keep, so why have you gotten this
        far in the first place? If you can see a selection but thought you
        were inside it, it might be inverted from what you think. The easiest
        way to tell is to hit the Quick Mask button: the selected area will be
        clear and the unselected area will be masked. If this was the problem,
        then you can solve it by toggling Quick Mask off and choosing Invert
        in the <guimenu>Select</guimenu> menu.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>The active drawable is not visible</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Unstuck layer invisibility</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-invislayer.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Layers dialog with visibility off for the active layer.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        The Layers dialog gives you ability to toggle the visibility of
        each layer on or off. Look at the Layers dialog, and see if
        the layer you are trying to act on is active (i.e., darkened) and
        has an eye symbol to the left of it. If not, this is your problem.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
        If your intended target layer is not active, click on it in the Layers
        dialog to activate it. (If none of the layers are active, the
        active drawable might be a channel -- you can look at the Channels tab
        in the Layers dialog to see. This does not change the solution,
        though.) If the eye symbol does not appear, click in the Layers dialog
        at the left edge to toggle it: this should make the layer visible. See
        the Help section for the
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>
        if you need more help.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>The active drawable is transparent</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Unstuck layer transparency</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-transparentlayer.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Layers dialog with opacity set to zero for the active layer.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        When the opacity is set 0 on the layer, you cannot see anything which
        you draw on it. Look the <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> slider,
        and see which side the slider placed at.  If it is at the leftmost side,
        that is your problem.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Move the slider.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>You are trying to act outside the layer</title>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, layers don't need to have the same
        dimensions as the
        image: they can be larger or smaller. If you try to paint outside
        the borders of a layer, nothing happens. To see if this is
        happening, look for a black-and-yellow dashed rectangle that does
        not enclose the area you're trying to draw at.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
        You need to enlarge the layer. There are two commands at the bottom of
        the Layer menu that will let you do this: Layer to Image Size, which
        sets the layer bounds to match the image borders; and Layer Boundary
        Size, which brings up a dialog that allows you to set the layer
        dimensions to whatever you please.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>The image is in indexed color mode.</title>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis><acronym>GIMP</acronym> can handle
        three different color modes:
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">RGB(A), Indexed and Grayscale</link>.
        The indexed colormode uses a colormap,
        where all used colors on the image are indexed. The
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">color picker</link> in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> however, let you choose RGB colors.
        That means, if you try to paint with a different color than
        it is indexed in the colormap, you end up in very
        undetermined results (e.g. it paints with the wrong color or
        you can't paint).
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Always use the
        RGB Color mode to paint on images. You can verify and select
        another color mode from the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">Mode</link> menuitem in the
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu> menu.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
