<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-getting-unstuck' lang="cs;en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Řešení problémů</title>
  <title lang="en">Getting Unstuck</title>
  <title lang="de">Problemhilfe für GIMP</title>
  <title lang="fr">Débloquer la situation</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">不要抓狂</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="de">GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">řešení problémů</secondary>
    <secondary lang="en">Getting Unstuck</secondary>
    <secondary lang="de">Problemhilfe</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Débloquer la situation</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">不要抓狂</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title lang='cs'><emphasis>Nevím jak dál!</emphasis></title>
    <title lang='en'><emphasis>Stuck!</emphasis></title>
    <title lang="de"><emphasis>Hängen geblieben!</emphasis></title>
    <title lang='fr'><emphasis>Bloqué!</emphasis></title>
    <title lang='zh_CN'><emphasis>抓狂！</emphasis></title>

  <para lang="cs">
    Dobře, dobře, nevíte jak dál. Zkoušíte na obrázek použít nějaký nástroj,
    a ono se nic neděje a nic, co vás napadá, problém neřeší. Svírají se vám
    pěsti a rudnete ve tváři. Ukončíte program a ztratíte všechnu svou práci?
    Takhle ne!
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    All right, okay: you're stuck.  You're trying to use one of the
    tools on an image, and nothing is happening, and nothing you try
    makes any difference.  Your fists are starting to clench, and your
    face is starting to feel warm.  Are you going to have to kill the
    program, and lose all your work?  This sucks!
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Okey, sie sind bei Ihrer ganzen Arbeit vollkommen verwirrt und
    hängen fest; wissen ein noch aus wie Sie weiterkommen könnten. Am
    liebsten würden Sie GIMP schließen, jedoch hängt die Arbeit einiger
    Minuten wenn nicht schon Stunden an Ihrer Geduld und an diesem
    Programm.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Eh bien voilà, vous êtes bloqué. Vous essayez d'utiliser un outil sur 
    une image, et rien ne se passe, quoi que vous fassiez. Vos poings se 
    serrent, vous transpirez. Allez-vous perdre tout votre travail? Ca 
    craint!
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    是的，您正在抓狂。您正在尝试使用图像上的一个工具，可是什么也没发生，您的任何尝试都没有作用。您的拳头开始握紧，脸也逐渐涨红。您是否想杀掉这个程序，丢弃您所做的一切？这就是抓狂！
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Vydržte chvíli. Takové věci se stávají poměrně často i zkušeným
    uživatelům. Příčinu ale není obvykle těžké najít a odstranit, pokud víte,
    kam se koukat. Uklidněte se a zkontrolujte položky na seznamu, který z vás
    pravděpodobně udělá opět spokojeného uživatele Gimpu.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Well, hold on a second.  This happens pretty frequently, even to
    people who've used the GIMP for a long time, but generally the
    cause is not so hard to figure out (and fix) if you know what to
    look at. Lets be calm, and go through a checklist that will
    probably get you GIMPing happily again.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Bevor Sie jedoch das Programm <quote>killen</quote>, geben wir Ihnen
    eine kleine Checkliste mit auf dem Weg, um aus Sie aus dieser
    misslichen Lage zu befreien. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Attendez un peu! Cela arrive, pas si rarement que ça, même à ceux qui 
    utilisent Gimp depuis longtemps, mais généralement la cause n'est pas 
    dure à déterminer (ni à régler) si vous savez ce qu'il faut vérifier. 
    Restez calme et suivez la liste des mesures qui vous permettront de vous 
    tirer d'embarras.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    不过，请等下。这种事常常发生，即使是对使用 GIMP 很长时间的人，但是一般来说，并不难发现(和修正)其原因，如果您知道该看什么的话。先冷静下来，让我们来一个个地检查，也许其后会使您的 GIMP 之旅再次快乐起来。
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title lang='cs'>Obvyklé případy nekomunikativnosti GIMPu</title>
    <title lang='en'>Common causes of GIMP non-responsiveness</title>
    <title lang="de"> Die Hauptgründe, weshalb GIMP scheinbar
      <quote>einfriert</quote></title>
    <title lang='fr'>Causes communes de non-réponse de Gimp</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">GIMP 没有反应的主要原因</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Existuje plovoucí výběr</term>
        <term lang='en'>There is a floating selection</term>
        <term lang="de">Es existiert eine schwebende Auswahl</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Il y a une sélection flottante</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">这儿有个浮动选区</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="cs;en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/unstuck-floating-sel.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/fr/unstuck-floating-sel.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/zh_CN/unstuck-floating-sel.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang='en'>
                  Layers dialog showing a floating selection.
                </para>
                <para lang='cs'>
                  Dialog Vrstvy s plovoucím výběrem
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Der Ebenendialog mit einer schwebenden Auswahl.
                </para>
                <para lang='fr'>
                  Le dialogue des calques montrant une sélection flottante.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  有一个浮动选区的对话框。
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Rozpoznání problému:</emphasis>
            Pokud existuje plovoucí výběr, je mnoho operací nemožných, dokud
            není výběr ukotven. Podívejte se proto do dialogu Vrstvy (a
            ujistěte se, že se vztahuje k problematickému obrázku), zda se
            nejhořejší vrstva nejmenuje „Plovoucí výběr“.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to tell:</emphasis>  If there is a
            floating selection, many actions are impossible until it is
            anchored. To check, look at the Layers dialog (making sure
            it's set to the image you're working on) and see whether the
            top layer is called "Floating Selection". 
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Falls eine schwebende Auswahl existiert, sind nur die
            Funktionen aktiviert, mit der sich schwebende Auswahlen
            manipulieren lassen. Entweder die schwebende Auswahl wird
            aufgelößt oder <link
            linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">verankert</link>. Schauen Sie in
            den Ebenendialog (vergewissern Sie sich, dass er Ihnen die
            Ebenen des aktuellen Bildes anzeigt) und prüfen Sie, ob die
            oberste Ebene <guilabel>schwebende Auswahl</guilabel> heißt.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Où est le problème?</emphasis> s'il y a une 
            sélection flottante, beaucoup d'actions restent impossibles 
            jusqu'à ce qu'elle soit ancrée. Pour vérifier, regardez le 
            dialogue des calques (assurez-vous qu'il correspond bien à 
            l'image sur laquelle vous travaillez), et voyez si le calque du 
            haut est bien appelé «sélection flottante».
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何发现：</emphasis>如果这儿有个浮动选区，许多动作都无法进行除非它被固定。您可以检查图层对话栏(确保是您正在操作的图像)，然后看看最顶上的图层是不是叫“浮动选区”。
          </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Řešení:</emphasis>
            Buď plovoucí výběr ukotvěte nebo ji převeďte na běžnou neplovoucí
            vrstvu. Pokud nevíte jak na to, podívejte se do části
            Plovoucí výběr.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to solve:</emphasis> Either anchor
            the floating selection, or convert it into an ordinary
            (non-floating) layer.  If you need help on how to do this,
            see Floating Selections.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Solution:</emphasis> Soit vous ancrez la 
            sélection, soit vous la convertissez en un calque ordinaire, non 
            flottant. Voyez <!--FIXME<link
            linkend='gimp-using-floating-selection'>-->sélection
            flottante<!--</link>-->.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何解决：</emphasis>要么固定浮动选区，要么把它转化为普通(非浮动)的图层。如果您要如何做这些的帮助,请看浮动选区。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Výběr je skrytý</term>
        <term lang='en'>The selection is hidden</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Auswahl ist nicht sichtbar</term>
        <term lang='fr'>La sélection est cachée</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">选区被隐藏</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure lang="cs;de;en;fr;zh_CN">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="cs;de;en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/unstuck-show-selection-menu.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/fr/unstuck-show-selection-menu.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/zh_CN/unstuck-show-selection-menu.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="de">
                  Vergewissern Sie sich, dass im
                  <guimenu>Ansicht</guimenu> Menü
                  <guimenuitem>Auswahl anzeigen</guimenuitem> aktiviert
                  ist.
                </para>
                <para lang='cs'>
                  Ujistěte se, že je v nabídce <guimenu>Zobrazení</guimenu>
                  aktivní volba <guimenuitem>Zobrazovat výběr</guimenuitem>.
                </para>
                <para lang='en'>
                  In the View menu, make sure that "Show Selection" is
                  checked. 
                </para>
                <para lang='fr'>
                  Dans le menu Affichage soyez certain que l'option
                  <guimenuitem>Afficher la sélection</guimenuitem>
                  est bien cochée.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  确认勾选了查看菜单中的“显示选区”。
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Rozpoznání problému:</emphasis>
            Občas jsou „pochodující mravenci“ ohraničující vybranou oblast
            otížní, protože zakrývají důležité detaily. Proto je lze skrýt
            zakázáním volby <guimenuitem>Zobrazovat výběr</guimenuitem>
            v nabídce <guimenu>Zobrazení</guimenu>. Pak na to lze snadno
            zapomenout.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to tell:</emphasis>  If this is
            the problem, merely reading this will already have made
            you realize it, probably, but to explain in any case:
            sometimes the flickering line that outlines the selection
            is annoying because it makes it hard to see important
            details of the image, so Gimp gives you the option of
            hiding the selection, by unchecking <guimenuitem>Show
            Selection</guimenuitem> in the
            <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.  It is easy to forget that
            you have done this, though. 
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sollten Sie keine Auswahl sehen, überprüfen Sie die
            <guimenuitem>Auswahl anzeigen</guimenuitem> Option im
            <guimenu>Ansicht</guimenu> Menü. Manchmal ist es nützlich
            die <quote>laufenden Ameisen</quote>, die eine Auswahl
            markieren nicht anzuzeigen, vor allem wenn diese wichtige
            Bestandteile des Bildes verdecken.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Où est le problème?</emphasis> La ligne 
            pointillée qui entoure les sélections peut, dans certains cas, 
            être gênante. Gimp vous offre donc la possibilité de la 
            supprimer en décochant l'option <guimenuitem> Montrer la 
            sélection</guimenuitem> dans le menu <guimenu>Affichage</guimenu>.
            Il est facile de l'oublier. 
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何发现：</emphasis>如果是这个原因，可能只需读到这已经让您认识到了，但是无论如何还是解释下：有时选区闪动的外缘线使人烦恼，因为它让图像的重要细节很难看清，所以提供隐藏选区的选项，不要选取<guimenuitem>显示选区</guimenuitem>在<guimenu>查看</guimenu> 菜单上。不过很容易忘记这样做过。
          </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Řešení:</emphasis>
            Aktivujte volbu <guimenuitem>Zobrazovat výběr</guimenuitem>
            v nabídce <guimenu>Zobrazení</guimenu> v okně obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to fix:</emphasis> If this
            hasn't rung any bells, it isn't the problem, and if it has,
            you probably know how to fix it, because it doesn't happen
            unless you explicitly tell it to; but anyway:  just go to
            the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu for the image and, if
            <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem> is 
            unchecked, click on it..
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Solution:</emphasis> Vous avez compris:
            cochez l'option <guimenuitem>Montrer la sélection</guimenuitem>.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何解决：</emphasis> 如果您不知道我说什么，这就不是个问题，如果知道，您可能知道如何解决，因为它不会发生，除非明白地告诉您有这个。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Pracujete mimo výběr</term>
        <term lang='en'>You are acting outside of the selection</term>
        <term lang="de">Sie arbeiten ausserhalb einer Auswahl</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Vous agissez en dehors de la sélection</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">您在选区外进行操作</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure lang="cs;de;en;fr;zh_CN">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="cs;de;en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/unstuck-select-all.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/fr/unstuck-select-all.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/zh_CN/unstuck-select-all.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang='cs'>
                  Zvolte <guimenuitem>Vše</guimenuitem> z nabídky
                  <guimenu>Vybrat</guimenu> v okně obrázku.
                </para>
                <para lang='en'>
                  Click "All" in the Select menu to make sure that
                  everything is selected.
                </para>
                <para lang='de'>
                  Klicken Sie auf
                  <guimenu>Auswahl</guimenu>/<guimenuitem>Alles</guimenuitem>
                  im Bildmenü um sicherzugehen, dass Sie in der Auswahl
                  arbeiten.
                </para>
                <para lang='fr'>
                  Sélectionnez Tout dans le menu de Sélection pour
                  être sûr que tout le canevas soit sélectionné.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  点击选择菜单中“全部”以确保选中了所有像素。
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Où est le problème?</emphasis> dans le menu
            <guimenu>Sélection</guimenu> de l'image, choisissez
            <guimenuitem>Tout sélectionner</guimenuitem> et recommencer 
            votre action. Si ça marche, c'était le problème.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何发现：</emphasis> 在图像的 <guimenu>选择</guimenu> 菜单，选<guimenuitem>全部</guimenuitem>(最上面的选项)，再进行您的操作，如果成功了，就是这个问题。
          </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Rozpoznání problému:</emphasis>
            Pokud volba<guimenuitem>Vše</guimenuitem> z nabídky
            <guimenu>Vybrat</guimenu> v okně obrázku zničila výběr,
            který chcete zachovat, vraťte se zpět příkazem Zpět
            (Ctrl-Z). V čem může být problém? Pokud výběr nevidíte,
            může být velmi malý, dokonce tak malý, že neobsahuje žádné
            pixely. Takový výběr ale určitě nechcete zachovat, proč
            jste se tedy vraceli? Pokud výběr vidíte, může být invertovaný
            a se můžete marně pokoušet pracovat mimo něj, i když si myslíte,
            že pracujete uvnitř. Nejsnáze to lze zjistit zapnutím rychlé
            masky: vybraná oblast zůstane čistá, nevybraná se překryje barvou.
            Pokud bylo problémem toto, zle ho snadno vyřešit vypnutím rychlé
            masky a volbou Inverovat v nabídce <guimenu>Vybrat</guimenu>
            v okně obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to fix:</emphasis> If doing this
            has destroyed a selection that you wanted to keep, hit
            Ctrl-Z (undo) a couple of times to restore it, and then
            we'll figure out what the problem is.  There are a couple
            of possibilities.  If you couldn't see any selection,
            there may have been a very tiny one, or even one that
            contained no pixels.  If this was the case, it surely is
            not a selection that you wanted to keep, so why have you
            gotten this far in the first place?  If you can see a
            selection but thought you were inside it, it might be
            inverted from what you think.  The easiest way to tell is
            to hit the Quick Mask button:  the selected area will be
            clear and the unselected area will be masked.  If this was
            the problem, then you can solve it by toggling Quick Mask
            off and choosing Invert in the <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
            menu.   
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Probleme mit Auswahlen können vielseitiger Natur sein.
            Wenn Sie nicht sicher sind, was mit der Auswahl passiert
            ist, oder wie groß die Auswahl ist entfernen Sie sie und
            fangen nochmal neu an.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Solution:</emphasis> Si, en faisant cela, 
            la sélection que vous vouliez garder a été détruite, tapez 
            Ctrl-Z (Annuler) plusieurs fois jusqu'à récupérer votre 
            sélection. Si vous ne voyez pas de sélection, c'est peut-être 
            qu'elle était très petite, voire ne contenait qu'un seul pixel. 
            pourquoi alors vouloir la garder? Si vous voyez une sélection et 
            pensiez être à l'intérieur, peut-être en fait la sélection 
            était-elle inversée. Le plus simple pour s'en assurer est de 
            cliquer sur le bouton Masque Rapide: la zone non sélectionnée 
            sera masquée. Il suffit alors de basculer le bouton Masque 
            rapide et de choisir <guilabel>Inverser</guilabel> dans le menu 
            Sélection.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何解决：</emphasis> 如果上面的作法破坏了您想保留的选区，敲 Ctrl-Z (撤销)几次来恢复，然后我们再来指出问题所在。这儿有多种可能性。假如您看不到选区，可能它非常小，或是没有包含任何像素。如果是这样，这就确实不是您想要保留的选区，那么起初为什么退这么多步呢？假如您能看到选去，却在其中，这就和您的想的所相反。最简单的方法发现这个问题就是单击快速蒙板按钮：选区是清楚的，而非选区将被遮罩。要是是这个问题，您能通过关闭快速模板并在<guimenu>选择</guimenu>菜单中选"反转"来解决。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Aktivní kreslící plocha není viditelná</term>
        <term lang='en'>The active drawable is not visible</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Zeichfläche ist nicht sichtbar</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Le dessin actif n'est pas visible</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">活动可画不能见</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure lang="cs;de;en;fr;zh_CN">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="cs;de;en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-invislayer.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/fr/unstuck-layers-dialog-invislayer.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/zh_CN/unstuck-layers-dialog-invislayer.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang='cs'>
                  Dialog Vrstvy s vypnutou viditelností aktivní vrstvy
                </para>
                <para lang='en'>
                  Layers dialog with visibility off for the active layer.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Der Ebenendialog mit ausgeschalteter Sichtbarkeit
                  der aktiven Ebene.
                </para>
                <para lang='fr'>
                  Le dialogue des calques avec la visibilité enlevée
                  au calque actif.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  活动图层在图层对话框中不可见。
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Rozpoznání problému:</emphasis>
            V dialogu Vrstvy lze vypínat a zapínat viditelnost jednotlivých
            vsrtev. Podívejte se proto do tohoto dialogu a ověřte, že je
            vrstva, se kterou se snažíte pracovat aktivní (je zvýrazněna)
            a její viditelnost je zapnutá (vlevo je zobrazena ikona oka).
            Pokud nikoliv, našli jste příčinu problému.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to tell:</emphasis>  The Layers
            dialog gives you ability to toggle the visibility of each
            layer on or off.  Look at the Layers dialog, and see
            whether the layer you are trying to act on is active
            (i.e., darkened) and has an eye symbol to the left of it.
            If not, this is your problem. 
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wie im Ebenendialog <link linkend="gimp-dialogs-icon-eye">
            beschrieben</link>,
            müssen Sie in den Bereich der Sichtbarkeit klicken um die
            Ebene wieder sichtbar zu machen. 
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Où est le problème?</emphasis>  Le 
            dialogue Calques vous donne la possibilité de basculer la 
            visibilité de chaque calque. Vérifiez que le calque représentant 
            le dessin manquant est bien «visible», avec un symbole œil 
            présent à sa gauche, et qu'il est actif (surligné). Si ces 
            conditions ne sont pas remplies, là est le problème.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何发现：</emphasis>图层对话框给您决定各图层是否可见的能力。看下图层对话框，看准备操作的图层是否是活动的(比其它图层颜色深)和是不是在其左边有个眼睛标志。如果没有，就是这个问题。
          </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Řešení problému:</emphasis>
            Pokud není požadovaná vrstva aktivní, aktivujte ji kliknutím na
            její pložku v dialogu Vrstvy. (Pokud není aktivní žádná vrstva,
            může být aktivní kreslící plochou kanál – podívejte se do dialogu
            Kanály. Na řešení to nicméně nic nemění.) Pokud u vrstvy není
            zobrazen symbol oka, klikněte na levý okraj položky vrstvy v
            dialogu. Vrstva se tak zviditelní. Více se dozvíte v části
            <link linkend='gimp-layer-dialog'>Dialog vrstvy</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to fix:</emphasis> If your
            intended target layer is not active, click on it in the
            Layers dialog to activate it.  (If none of the layers
            there is active, the active drawable might be a channel --
            you can look at the Channels tab in the Layers dialog to
            see.  This does not change the solution, though.)  If the
            eye symbol does not appear, click in the Layers dialog at
            the left edge to toggle it: this should make the layer
            visible.  See the Help section for the <link
            linkend='gimp-layer-dialog'>Layers Dialog</link> if you
            need more help. 
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Solution:</emphasis> Si votre calque n'est 
            pas actif, cliquer une fois sur sa miniature dans la boîte de 
            dialogue des calques pour l'activer (Si aucun calque n'est 
            actif, c'est que le dessin actif est peut-être un canal: 
            regardez dans l'onglet Canaux du Dialogue des calques pour 
            voir). Si le symbole œil n'est pas apparent, cliquez dans la 
            partie gauche du bandeau du calque pour le faire apparaître (ou 
            disparaître). Voyez <link linkend='gimp-layer-dialog'>Dialogue  
            des calques</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何解决：</emphasis>如果您目标图层不是活动的，在图层对话框中单击它使其活动。(如果没有图层是活动的，活动画区可能是通道--您可通过图层对话框的通道标签看到。虽然这并不改变现在考虑的情况。) 如果没有眼睛标志，点击图层对话框左边边缘来开启它：这样就能让图层可见。如果您需要更多帮助，可以看<link linkend='gimp-layer-dialog'>图层对话框</link>这部分。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Aktivní kreslící plocha je průhledná</term>
        <term lang='en'>The active drawable is transparent</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Zeichfläche ist transparent</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Le dessin actif est transparent</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">活动画区是透明的</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure lang="cs;de;en;fr;zh_CN">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="cs;de;en">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-transparentlayer.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/fr/unstuck-layers-dialog-transparentlayer.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
                <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/zh_CN/unstuck-layers-dialog-transparentlayer.png'
                format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang='cs'>
                  Dialog Vrstvy s průhledností aktivní vrstvy nastavenou na
                  minimum
                </para>
                <para lang='en'>
                  Layers dialog with opacity set to zero for the active layer.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Der Ebenendialog, die eine Ebene ohne Deckkraft zeigt. 
                </para>
                <para lang='fr'>
                  Le dialogue des calques avec l'opacité du calque actif
                  réglée à zéro. 
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  活动图层在图层对话框中不透明度为零。
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>

          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Où est le problème?:</emphasis> Si vous 
            travaillez sur un calque dont l'opacité est à zéro, vous ne 
            verrez aucun résultat. Vérifiez, dans la boîte de dialogue des 
            calques, la position du curseur d'Opacité. S'il est complètement 
            à gauche, là est le problème.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何发现：</emphasis>如果您操作的图层的不透明度为零，您将不会看到任何结果。看下图层对话框的不透明度滑条。要是全滑到最右边，即值为零，那就是问题。
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to fix:</emphasis> Move the
            slider.
          </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Řešení:</emphasis> Nastavte posuvníkem vyšší
            krytí.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Deckkraft der Ebene wurde auf 0 gestellt. Damit ist die
            Ebene vollkommen transparent und nicht mehr sichtbar.  Wie
            im Ebenendialog <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog-opacity-scale">
            beschrieben</link>, können Sie den Schieberegler nach
            rechts bewegen um die Deckkraft zu erhöhen.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Solution:</emphasis> Déplacez le curseur.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何解决：</emphasis>移动滑条。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Snažíte se pracovat mimo vrstvu</term>
        <term lang='en'>You are trying to act outside the layer</term>
        <term lang="de">Sie können nicht außerhalb der Ebene zeichnen</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Vous essayez d'agir en dehors du calque</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">您尝试在图层外操作</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Rozpoznání problému:</emphasis>
            V Gimpu nemusí mít vrstvy stejné rozměry jako obrázek, mohou být
            větší i menší. Pokud se snažíte malovat mimo hranice vsrtvy,
            nestane se vůbec nic. POznáte to podle toho, že se snažíte
            pracovat mimo černožlutě orámovanou oblast.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to tell:</emphasis> In Gimp,
            layers don't need to have the same dimensions as the
            image: they can be larger or smaller.  If you try to paint
            outside the borders of a layer, nothing happens.  To see
            if this is happening, look for a black-and-yellow dashed
            rectangle that does not enclose the area you're trying to
            draw at.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Ebenen im GIMP müssen haben nicht die gleichen Dimensionen
            wie das eigentliche Bild haben. Sie können kleiner oder auch
            größer sein. Gekennzeichnet werden Ebenen mit einer
            Gelb/Schwarzen Umrandung. Daher können Sie auch nicht
            außerhalb der Ebene zeichnen oder Filter anwenden.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Où est le problème?:</emphasis> Dans Gimp, 
            les calques n'ont pas forcément la même dimension que l'image: 
            ils peuvent être plus grands ou plus petits. Si vous essayez de 
            peindre en dehors des limites du calque actif, rien ne se passe. 
            Pour voir si c'est bien ça, cherchez un rectangle en pointillés 
            noirs et jaunes qui n'englobe pas la zone où vous essayez de 
            dessiner. 
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何发现：</emphasis>在 GIMP 中，图层并不需要和图像有相同的尺寸：它们可以更大或更小。如果您尝试在图层边界外画图，什么也不会发生。要知道是否发生，寻找一个包括您要绘画区域的封闭由黄黑虚线构成的矩形。
          </para>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Řešení problému:</emphasis> Je potřeba
            zvětšit vrstvu. V nabídce Vrstvy v okně obrázku jsou dole dva
            příkazy: Velikost vrstvy dle obrázku, který nastaví hranice
            vrstvy podle hranic obrázku, a Rozměry hranic vrstvy, který
            otevře dialog umožňující libovolné nastavení velikosti vrstvy.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>How to fix:</emphasis> You need to
            enlarge the layer.  There are two commands at the bottom
            of the Layer menu that will let you do this:  Layer to
            Image Size, which sets the layer bounds to match the image
            borders; and Layer Boundary Size, which brings up a dialog
            that allows you to set the layer dimensions to whatever
            you please. 
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn die Ebene zu klein ist, muss sie vergrößert werden. Die
            Funktionen dafür befinden sich am unteren Ende des
            Ebenenmenüs: Ebenengröße, Ebene auf Bildgröße, Ebene
            skalieren.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            <emphasis role='bold'>Solution:</emphasis> Vous devez agrandir 
            le calque. Vous disposez pour cela de deux commandes en haut du 
            menu Calque: <guimenuitem>Calque aux dimensions de l'image
            </guimenuitem> et <guimenuitem>Echelle et taille du calque
            </guimenuitem> qui ouvre une boîte de dialogue vous permettant 
            de préciser les dimensions du calque.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis role='bold'>如何解决：</emphasis>您需要拉伸图层，可以使用在图层菜单底部两个的命令：“图层到图像大小”，它让图层边界和图像边界重合;和“图层边界大小”，它会出现一个允许您把图层的尺寸变为您想要的对话框。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
