<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2015-08-30 j.h: fix bug #742256
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-08-27 lexa: replaced list by sect3
  2007-02-21 lexa: changed top level from chapter to sect1
  2006-03-10 changed structure
  2006-02-20 fixed #322305
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">
  <title>Common Causes of GIMP Non-Responsiveness</title>
  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-floating-selection">
    <title>There is a floating selection</title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        Layers dialog showing a floating selection.
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/unstuck-floating-sel.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Showing a floating selection that can be anchored (
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>) or
            turned into a new layer (
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>).
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      If there is a floating selection, many actions are impossible
      until the floating section is anchored.
      To check, look at the
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>, shortcut
      <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> (making sure
      it's set to the image you're working on) and see whether the top layer
      is called <quote>Floating Selection</quote>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to solve:</emphasis>
      Right click on the floating selection to open the Layer menu and
      select either <guimenuitem>Anchor Layer</guimenuitem>
      (shortcut <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>)
      to anchor the floating selection to the layer below it, or convert it
      into an ordinary layer by selecting <guimenuitem>To New Layer
      </guimenuitem> (shortcut <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>).
      If you need more help on how to do this, see
      <link linkend="anchor-floating-selection">Floating Selections</link>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-hidden-selection">
    <title>The selection is hidden</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      If this is the problem, merely reading this will already have made
      you realize it, probably, but to explain in any case: sometimes
      the flickering line that outlines the selection is annoying
      because it makes it hard to see important details of the image, so
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gives you the option of hiding the selection,
      by unchecking
      <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem>
      in the <guimenu>View</guimenu>
      menu. It is easy to forget that you have done this, though.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Go to
      the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu for the image and, if
      <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem> is
      unchecked, click on it.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-outside-selection">
    <title>You are acting outside the selection</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Fix selection using the "Select" menu</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/select.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            From the Select menu choose <quote>All</quote> to make sure that
            everything is selected, choose <quote>None</quote> to remove
            the selection, or <quote>Invert</quote> to invert the selected
            area.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      You may have previously selected a part of your image, but now you are
      trying to work on another part that is not inside the selection. Look
      for the selection outline and check if it is where you want it to be.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
      There are a couple of possibilities.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you can't see any selection, there may be a very small one, or
          it is outside the visible area on your screen, or it can even be one
          that contains no pixels. If this is the case, either display the
          selection via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>View</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Zoom</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Zoom to Selection</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
          or remove the selection via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>None</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          or the shortcut <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
          <keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you can see a selection and thought you were inside it, it might
          be inverted from what you think. The easiest way to tell is to hit the
          <link linkend="gimp-image-window-quick-mask-button">Quick Mask</link> button:
          the selected area will be clear and the unselected area will be masked.
          If this is the problem, you can solve it by choosing
          <quote>Invert</quote> in the <guimenu>Select</guimenu> menu (after
          turning the <quote>Quick Mask</quote> off if you still have that
          enabled).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
      <para>
        If doing this has destroyed a selection that you wanted to keep, use
        <quote>Undo</quote> (<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>)
        to restore it, and then we can continue to figure out what the problem is.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-drawable-invisible">
    <title>The active drawable is not visible</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Layer is invisible</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-invislayer.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Layers dialog with visibility off for the active layer.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      The Layers dialog gives you ability to toggle the visibility of
      each layer on or off. Look at the
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>, and see if
      the layer you are trying to work on is active (i.e., darkened) and
      has an eye symbol to the left of it. If not, this is your problem.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
      If your intended target layer is not active, click on it in the Layers
      dialog to activate it. If none of the layers are active, the
      active drawable might be a channel&mdash;you can look at the
      <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">Channels Dialog</link> to see.
      This does not change the solution, though.
      If the eye symbol is not visible, click in the Layers dialog at the left
      edge to toggle it: this should make the layer visible. See the Help
      section for the
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link> if you need more
      help.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-drawable-transparent">
    <title>The active drawable is transparent</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Layer opacity set to zero</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-transparentlayer.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Layers dialog with opacity set to zero for the active layer.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      When the opacity of a layer is 0, you cannot see anything you draw on it.
      Look at the <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> slider at the top of the
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link> and check the
      value next to it. If it is 0 or another very low value, that is your
      problem.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Move or click on the slider to change
      it to the desired value.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-outside-layer">
    <title>You are trying to act outside the layer</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, layers don't need to have the same
      dimensions as the image: they can be larger or smaller. If you try to
      paint outside the borders of a layer, nothing happens. To see if this is
      the case, look for a black-and-yellow dashed rectangle that does
      not enclose the area you're trying to draw at.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
      You need to enlarge the layer. There are two commands near the bottom of
      the <guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu that will let you do this:
      <guimenuitem>Layers to Image Size</guimenuitem>, which sets the layer
      bounds to match the image borders; and
      <guimenuitem>Layer Boundary Size</guimenuitem>, which brings up a dialog
      that allows you to set the layer dimensions to whatever you please.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-layer-group">
    <title>You are trying to act on a layer group</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Layer group selected</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Layers dialog where a layer group is selected.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
      Check the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link> to
      see if the active layer is actually a
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-groups">Layer group</link>.
      When a layer group is not empty, a small icon 
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/pan-end-symbolic.svg"
              contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> or
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/pan-down-symbolic.svg"
              contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> appears in front of the layer group's thumbnail and name.
      Most actions don't work on a layer group, in which case an error message
      will show up: <quote>Cannot paint on layer groups.</quote>
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
      You need to make a layer active that is not a layer group. Select a layer
      by clicking it in the Layers Dialog. If the active layer group has a
      <guibutton>+</guibutton> sign in front of it, it is collapsed. You can
      click it to expand and show the individual layers inside that group.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-indexed-mode">
    <title>The image is in indexed color mode.</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can handle
      three different color modes:
      <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">RGB(A), Grayscale and Indexed</link>.
      The indexed color mode uses a colormap, where all colors used in the
      image are indexed. The
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">color picker</link> in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> however, lets you choose RGB colors.
      That means, if you try to paint with a different color than is indexed
      in the colormap, you can end up with the wrong color.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> If possible, use the RGB color mode to
      paint on images. You can verify and select another color mode from the
      <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">Mode</link> menuitem in the
      <guimenu>Image</guimenu> menu. If you need to use indexed mode you can
      pick the color you want to use from the
      <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Colormap Dialog</link>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-tool-opacity">
    <title>No visible effect when trying to use a brush, eraser or other tool</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> You are trying to use the brush or eraser
      but you are not seeing anything changing.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Check the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-options-dialog">Tool Options</link> and make sure
      that <guimenuitem>Opacity</guimenuitem> is not set to 0.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-tool-transform">
    <title>No visible effect when trying to use the move tool, rotate or other
    transform tool</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> You are trying to move (or perform a
      transformation) on a layer but you do not see anything changing.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Check the
      <link linkend="gimp-image-window-status-bar">status bar</link> to see
      if there is a message telling you what is happening, next check
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-options-dialog">Tool Options</link> and make sure
      that the tool you are using is not set to work on a
      <guibutton>Selection</guibutton> or <guibutton>Path</guibutton>. These
      little buttons are at the top of the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-transform-options">Tool Options for Transform
      Tools</link>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-empty-clipboard"><!--Bug #742256 2015-08-30-->
    <title>Eraser and brushes no longer work</title>
    <para>
      You have selected the clipboard brush and the clipboard is empty.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Empty Clipboard Brush</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/brushes-dialog-empty-clipboard.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> You are trying to use a brush or the
      eraser and nothing is happening.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Check the
      <link linkend="gimp-brush-dialog">Brush Dialog</link> to see which
      brush is currently in use. If it is the Clipboard Brush and it shows
      an empty rectangle then select a different brush to use.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-no-alpha-channel"><!--Bug #742256 2015-08-30-->
    <title>Eraser does not make area transparent</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> You are trying to use the eraser to
      remove all color but instead of a transparent area appearing it turns
      into the background color (usually white).
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Check the active layer in the
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>: right click on it
      to open a menu and see if <guimenuitem>Add Alpha Channel</guimenuitem> is
      enabled. If it is, then your layer has no alpha channel: click that
      menu item to add an alpha channel. With that fixed, you will be able
      to erase to transparency.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-layer-mask">
    <title>Unexpected colors when trying to use a brush or eraser</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> You are trying to use the brush or
      eraser but the outcome is not as you expected.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Check whether the layer you are painting
      on has a <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask">Layer Mask</link>. If there is,
      you may be painting on the Layer Mask instead of the Layer itself. In that
      case click the Layer to make that the active painting area.
    </para>
    <para>
      Another similar possibility is that a Channel is active instead of a
      Layer. In that case click a layer in the Layers Dialog to make a layer
      active.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-delete-cropped-pixels">
    <title>The crop tool leaves an empty area after cropping</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> After cropping using the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-crop">Crop Tool</link> the image canvas is still
      using the old size and only the visible part was cropped.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Go to the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-options-dialog">Tool Options</link> and make
      sure that <guilabel>Delete cropped pixels</guilabel> is checked.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-not-responding">
    <title>I've been waiting for a long time and GIMP is not responding</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis> your mouse cursor is spinning or the
      window is saying it is not responding and you can't do anything in GIMP.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> some filters and other operations can
      take a long time, especially on large images or if your computer does not
      have a lot of free memory. In these cases, you may just need more
      patience. It can sometimes help to reduce the part you are working on by
      making a selection around a specific area.
    </para>
    <para>
      GIMP, just like any other software, is not perfect. You may have found a
      bug. The best thing to do is report it, since you may be the first to
      encounter it. Not reporting it may mean it won't get fixed until someone
      else reports it.
    </para>
    <para>
      First check to make sure that you are using the latest version of GIMP; if
      not update and check if the problem is still there. If it is, check if
      the issue is already known by searching our
      <ulink url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp/-/issues">list of
      issues</ulink> (also check the closed issues, fixed issues get closed even
      if there is no new version available yet). If you don't see it there,
      please open a new issue, making sure to give us all details like your
      Operating System, GIMP version, what tool or filter you were using and
      what exactly happened. Adding a screenshot, or uploading the image
      you are using can also be helpful in certain cases.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-stuck-general-guidelines">
    <title>General guidelines on what to check if you are stuck</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Check the <link linkend="gimp-image-window-status-bar">status
          bar</link> to see if there is a message telling you what is happening.
        </para>
        <tip>
          <para>
            If you add the <link linkend="gimp-errors-dialog">Error
            Console</link> to one of your docks most of the warnings will
            appear there. This can make it easier to spot any problems.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Check the
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-options-dialog">Tool Options</link> and make
          sure that all settings there have expected values, or else try to
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-options-reset">reset to default values</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Check which <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">Image Mode</link> your
          image is using. Some operations have limitations when using Indexed
          mode.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Check if a selection is active and if needed
          <link linkend="gimp-selection-none">remove the selection</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Check the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link> and make sure
          the correct layer is active, that the opacity, blending mode and
          layer attributes are set as expected.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
