<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-gradients' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Gradients</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Gradients</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         Some examples of GIMP gradients.
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>gradient</emphasis> is a set of colors arranged in a
    linear order.  The most basic use of gradients is by the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Blend tool</link>, sometimes known as
    the "gradient tool" or "gradient fill tool":  it works by filling
    the selection with colors from a gradient.  You have many options
    to choose from for controlling the way the gradient colors are
    arranged within the selection.   There are also other
    important ways to use gradients, including:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Painting with a gradient</title>
        Each of GIMP's basic painting tools allows you the option of
        using colors from a gradient.
        This enables you to create brushstrokes that change color from
        one end to the other.
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>The Gradient Map filter</title>
        This filter allows you to "colorize" a grayscale image, by replacing
        each shade of gray with the corresponding color from a
        gradient. See the <link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>Gradient
        Map</link> section for more information.
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a large number of
    interesting gradients, and you can add new ones that you create or
    download from other sources.  You can access the full set of
    available gradients using the <link
    linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>Gradients dialog</link>, a dockable
    dialog that you can either activate when you need it, or keep
    around as a tab in a dock.  The "current gradient", used in most
    gradient-related operations, is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the
    gradient symbol in the Toolbox is an alternative way of bringing
    up the Gradients dialog.
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-usage.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         Four ways of using the Tropical Colors gradient:  a linear
         gradient fill, a 
         shaped gradient fill, a stroke painted using colors from
         a gradient, and a stroke painted with a fuzzy brush then
         colored using the Gradient Map filter.
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A few useful things to know about GIMP's gradients:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        The top four gradients shown in the Gradients dialog are
        special, because they 
        make use of GIMP's current foreground and background colors,
        substituting the foreground color for black, and the
        background color for white.  Thus, by altering the foreground
        and background colors, you can make these gradients transition
        smoothly between any two colors you want.  The other gradients
        in the list, and any custom gradients you may create, have
        fixed colors.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        Gradients can involve not just color changes, but also changes
        in opacity.  Some of the gradients are completely opaque;
        others include transparent or translucent parts.  When you
        fill or paint with a non-opaque gradient, the existing
        contents of the layer will show through behind it.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        You can create new <emphasis>custom</emphasis> gradients,
        using the <link linkend='dialogs-gradient-editor'>Gradient
        Editor</link>.  You cannot modify the gradients that are
        supplied with GIMP, but you can duplicate them or create new
        ones, and then edit those.
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    The gradients that are supplied with GIMP are stored in a system
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder.  By default, gradients that
    you create are stored in a folder called
    <filename>gradients</filename> in your personal GIMP directory.
    Any gradient files (ending with the extension
    <filename>.ggr</filename>) will automatically be loaded when you
    start GIMP.  You can add more directories to the gradient search
    path, if you want to, in the Gradients tab of the <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Data Folders</link> pages of the
    Preferences dialog.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    New in GIMP 2.2 is the ability to load gradient files in SVG
    format, used by many vector graphics programs.  To make GIMP load
    an SVG gradient file, all you need to do is place it in the
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your personal GIMP
    directory, or any other folder in your gradient search path.
  </para>

</sect2>
