<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-gradients' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Gradients</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">渐变</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Gradients</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">渐变</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         Some examples of GIMP gradients.
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang="zh_CN">
         一些 GIMP 渐变的范例。
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>gradient</emphasis> is a set of colors arranged in a
    linear order.  The most basic use of gradients is by the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Blend tool</link>, sometimes known as
    the "gradient tool" or "gradient fill tool":  it works by filling
    the selection with colors from a gradient.  You have many options
    to choose from for controlling the way the gradient colors are
    arranged within the selection.   There are also other
    important ways to use gradients, including:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一个<emphasis>渐变</emphasis>就是一系列线性排列的颜色。渐变最基本的使用是<link linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>渐变工具</link>，也被叫作“渐变填充工具”：它将一个渐变中的颜色填充的选区，有很多控制渐变颜色与选区排列方式的很多选项。还有其它多种使用渐变的方式，包括：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>Painting with a gradient</title>

	<para>
	  Each of GIMP's basic painting tools allows you the option of
	  using colors from a gradient.  This enables you to create
	  brushstrokes that change color from one end to the other.
	</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>用渐变涂画</title>
	<para>
	  GIMP 中每个基本的涂画工具提供使用一个渐变中颜色的选项。这使您可以画出从一端到另一端改变颜色的笔划。
	</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>The Gradient Map filter</title>

	<para>
	  This filter allows you to "colorize" a grayscale image, by
	  replacing each shade of gray with the corresponding color from a
	  gradient. See the <link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>Gradient
	  Map</link> section for more information.
	</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>渐变映射滤镜</title>
	<para>
	  该插件通过一个渐变中相应的颜色来替代每个灰色色度，允许您“单色化”一个灰度图像，请看<link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>渐变映射</link>以便获取更多信息。
	</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a large number of
    interesting gradients, and you can add new ones that you create or
    download from other sources.  You can access the full set of
    available gradients using the <link
    linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>Gradients dialog</link>, a dockable
    dialog that you can either activate when you need it, or keep
    around as a tab in a dock.  The "current gradient", used in most
    gradient-related operations, is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the
    gradient symbol in the Toolbox is an alternative way of bringing
    up the Gradients dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当您安装 Gimp 时，它已经自带了大量有趣的渐变，并且您可以自己创建或从其它地方下载来添加新的。可以用<link linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>渐变对话框</link>来显示所有可用的渐变，它是一个可停靠的对话框，您可以需要它是来打开它或放置它为一个停靠栏上的页签。显示在工具箱的画笔/图案/渐变区域的“当前渐变”在大多数有关渐变的操作中使用。点击工具箱的渐变标志则是另外一种唤出渐变对话框的方法。
  </para>   

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-usage.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-usage.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         Four ways of using the Tropical Colors gradient:  a linear
         gradient fill, a 
         shaped gradient fill, a stroke painted using colors from
         a gradient, and a stroke painted with a fuzzy brush then
         colored using the Gradient Map filter.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
         四种使用 Tropical Colors 渐变的方法：线性渐变填充，形状渐变填充，用模糊画笔涂画和使用渐变映射滤镜着色。
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A few useful things to know about GIMP's gradients:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一些对了解 GIMP 渐变有用的东西：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        The top four gradients shown in the Gradients dialog are
        special, because they 
        make use of GIMP's current foreground and background colors,
        substituting the foreground color for black, and the
        background color for white.  Thus, by altering the foreground
        and background colors, you can make these gradients transition
        smoothly between any two colors you want.  The other gradients
        in the list, and any custom gradients you may create, have
        fixed colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        渐变对话框顶部四个渐变比较特别，因为它们使用 GIMP 当前的前景和背景色，将前景色置换为黑色和将背景色置换为白色。这样通过交换前景和背景色，您能使这些渐变在想要的任何两种颜色间平滑地过渡。其它渐变在列表中，任何您自建的渐变有其固定的颜色。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        Gradients can involve not just color changes, but also changes
        in opacity.  Some of the gradients are completely opaque;
        others include transparent or translucent parts.  When you
        fill or paint with a non-opaque gradient, the existing
        contents of the layer will show through behind it.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        渐变并不仅仅导致颜色改变，而且改变不透明度。一些渐变完全不透明；而一些包括透明或半透明部分。当您用一个非不透明的渐变填充或涂画时，图层的已存在内容会从下面透出来。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        You can create new <emphasis>custom</emphasis> gradients,
        using the <link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>Gradient
        Editor</link>.  You cannot modify the gradients that are
        supplied with GIMP, but you can duplicate them or create new
        ones, and then edit those.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您能使用<link linkend='dialogs-gradient-editor'>渐变编辑器</link>来创建<emphasis>自定义</emphasis>渐变。您不能修改 GIMP 自带的渐变，但可以复制或创建一个新的，然后再编辑它们。
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    The gradients that are supplied with GIMP are stored in a system
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder.  By default, gradients that
    you create are stored in a folder called
    <filename>gradients</filename> in your personal GIMP directory.
    Any gradient files (ending with the extension
    <filename>.ggr</filename>) will automatically be loaded when you
    start GIMP.  You can add more directories to the gradient search
    path, if you want to, in the Gradients tab of the <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Data Folders</link> pages of the
    Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 自带的渐变放在系统的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹。而您创建的渐变默认保存在个人 GIMP 文件夹的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹中。任何渐变文件(扩展名为 <filename>.ggr</filename>) 将在每次启动 GIMP 时自动加载。您可以根据需要添加更多的文件夹到渐变搜索路径，在首选项对话框的<link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>文件夹</link>页的渐变标签中。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    New in GIMP 2.2 is the ability to load gradient files in SVG
    format, used by many vector graphics programs.  To make GIMP load
    an SVG gradient file, all you need to do is place it in the
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your personal GIMP
    directory, or any other folder in your gradient search path.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 2.2 中允许读取在许多矢量图形程序中使用的 SVG 格式的渐变文件。要使 GIMP 读取一个 SVG 渐变文件，需要做的就是将它放在您个人 GIMP 目录的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹中，或任何渐变搜索路径的其它文件夹中。
  </para> 

  <!-- added 9/21/04 -->
  <para lang='en'>
    You can find a large number of interesting SVG gradients on the
    web, in particular at <ulink
    url='http://openclipart.org/cgi-bin/navigate/Gradients'>OpenClipArt
    Gradients</ulink>.  You won't be able to see what these gradients
    look like unless your browser supports SVG, but that won't prevent
    you from downloading them.
  </para>

</sect2>
