<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-imagewindow' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Image Window</title>
  <title lang="fr">Fenêtre d'image</title>
  <title lang="sv">Bildfönstret</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="sv">Bild</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Introduction</title>
    <title lang="fr">Introduction</title>
    <title lang="sv">Introduktion</title>
    <para lang="en">
      In Gimp, each image that you have open is displayed in its own
      separate window.  (In some cases, multiple windows may all
      display the same image, but this is unusual.)  We will begin
      with a brief description of the components that are present by
      default in an ordinary image window.  Most of these, in fact,
      can be made to disappear using commands in the <link
	linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>View</link> menu; but
      you will probably find that you don't want to do that.  You may
      find this section easier to follow if you have an image
      open in front of you to look and experiment with as you read
      it. 
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Title Bar</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    At the top of the image window you will probably see a title
	    bar, showing the name of the image and some basic information
	    about it.  The title bar is actually provided by the
	    windowing system, not by Gimp itself, so its appearance may
	    vary with different operating systems, window managers,
	    and/or themes.  In the <link
	    linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>Preferences dialog</link> you can customize
	    the information that appears here, if you so desire.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Menu Bar</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    Directly below the title bar appears the Image Menu
	    (unless it has been suppressed).  This menu gives you
	    access to virtually every operation you can perform on an
	    image.   (There are some "global" actions
	    that can only be accessed via the Toolbox menu, not via the
	    image menu.)  You can also get the image menu by right-clicking
	    inside the image, or by left-clicking on the little
	    "arrow" symbol in the upper left corner, if for some
	    reason you find one of these more convenient.  More: most 
	    menu operations can also be activated from the keyboard,
	    using Alt plus an "accelerator" key underlined in the menu
	    title.  More: you can define your own custom shortcuts for
	    menu actions, if you enable <link
	    linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Use Dynamic Keyboard
	    Shortcuts</link> in the 
	    Preferences dialog. 
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Rulers</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the
	    left of the image, indicating coordinates within the
	    image.  You can control what type of coordinates are shown
	    if you want to.  By default, pixels are used, but you can
	    change to other units if you need to.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Image Display</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    The most important part of the image window is, of course,
	    the image display.  It occupies the central area of the window,
	    surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image
	    boundary, against a neutral gray background.  You can
	    change the zoom level of the image display in a variety of
	    ways. 
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Scrollbars</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    Below and to the right of the image display are scrollbars
	    that you can use to pan the image display.  You can also
	    pan the display by holding down the middle mouse button
	    while inside it, and dragging, or by using the navigation
	    control, described below.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">QuickMask Toggle</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    At the lower left corner of the image display is a small
	    button that toggles on or off the Quick Mask, which is an
	    alternate, and often extremely useful, way of viewing the
	    selected area within the image. For more details see <link
	    linkend='gimp-image-window-qmask-button'>QuickMask</link>.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Navigation Button</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right
	    corner of the image display.  Clicking on it, and holding
	    the left mouse button down, brings up a window showing a
	    miniature view of the image, with the displayed area
	    outlined.  You can pan to a different part of the image by
	    moving the mouse while keeping the button depressed.  For
	    large images of which only a small part is displayed, the
	    navigation window is often the most convenient way of
	    getting to the part of the image you are looking for.
	    (See  <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigation
	    Dialog</link> for other ways to access the Navigation Window).
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Cursor Location</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    In the lower left corner of the window is a rectangular
	    area used to show the current pointer coordinates,
	    whenever the pointer is within the image boundaries.  The
	    units used are the same as for the rulers.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Status Area </term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    The Status Area appears below the image display.  You can
	    customize the information that appears here:  by default
	    it shows the name of the active layer of the image, and
	    the amount of memory the image is currently using.  When
	    you perform possibly time-consuming operations, the status
	    area changes temporarily to show what operation is being
	    performed, and its state of progress.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Cancel Button</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    At the lower right corner of the window appears the Cancel
	    button.  If you start a complex, time-consuming operation
	    (most commonly a plug-in), and then decide, while it is
	    being computed, that you didn't really want to do it after
	    all, this button will cancel it immediately.  (Note,
	    though, that there are a few plug-ins that respond badly
	    to being canceled, possibly leaving corrupted pieces of
	    images behind.)
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para lang="fr">
      À écrire.
    </para>
    <para lang="sv">
      KOMMER SNART
    </para>
  </sect2>
    
  <xi:include href="imagewindow/qmask.xml" />

</sect1>
