<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-image-window' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
lang="cs;de;en;fr;sv;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Okno obrázku</title>
  <title lang="en">Image Window</title>
  <title lang='de'>Bildfenster</title>
  <title lang="fr">Fenêtre d'image</title>
  <title lang="sv">Bildfönstret</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">图像窗口</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">okno obrázku</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Image Window</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Fenêtre d'image</primary>
    <primary lang="sv">Bildfönstret</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像窗口</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <mediaobjectco>
    <imageobjectco>
      <areaspec units="calspair">
        <!-- make the id's unique, to not clash with others -->
        <area id='co-imagewindow-titlebar' coords='73,17 385,1' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-menu' coords='52,41 401,19' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-menu-button' coords='54,65 73,46' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-ruler' coords='54,210 73,69' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-quickmask' coords='55,225 67,213' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-coordinates' coords='53,259 95,232' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-units' coords='99,257 152,233' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-zoom' coords='160,259 224,231' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-statusbar' coords='229,259 354,231' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-cancel' coords='356,260 403,232' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-navigation' coords='385,228 402,212' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-inactive' coords='77,210 385,68' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-display' coords='180,176 281,102' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-resize' coords='386,59 80,38' />
      </areaspec>

      <imageobject lang='cs;en;de'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/imagewindow-description.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fr/imagewindow-description.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='zh_CN'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/using/zh_CN/imagewindow-description.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </imageobjectco>
  </mediaobjectco>

  <para lang="cs">
    V Gimpu je každý otevřený obrázek zobrazen v samostatném okně (v některých
    případxech může být jeden obrázek zobrazován i ve více oknech, ale není
    to, zejména u začátečníků obvyklé). Zde popíšeme všechny části okna
    obrázku, které jsou viditelné ve výchozím nastavení. Některé z nich lze
    skrýt pomocí příkazů z nabídky <link
    linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>Zobrazení</link>, ale pravděpodobně
    to nebudete potřebovat.
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    In Gimp, each image that you have open is displayed in its own
    separate window.  (In some cases, multiple windows may all
    display the same image, but this is unusual.)  We will begin
    with a brief description of the components that are present by
    default in an ordinary image window.  Some of these, in fact,
    can be made to disappear using commands in the <link
    linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>View</link> menu; but
    you will probably find that you don't want to do that.  
  </para>

  <para lang='de'>
    In <acronym>Gimp</acronym> wird jedes Bild in seinem eigenen Fenster
    geöffnet. Folgende eine Beschreibung der Elemente die per
    Voreinstellung sichtbar sind. Einige dieser Elemente können per
    <link linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>Ansicht</link> Menü
    ausgeblendet werden.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Dans Gimp, chaque image ouverte est affichée dans sa propre fenêtre 
    (dans certain cas la même image peut être affichée dans plusieurs 
    fenêtres mais c'est inhabituel). Nous commencerons par une brève 
    description des composants présents dans une fenêtre image 
    ordinaire. En fait, certains peuvent disparaître lors de 
    l'utilisation de commandes dans le menu  
    <link linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>Affichage</link> ; mais 
    sans doute n'est-ce pas ce que vous voulez faire.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    在 <acronym>Gimp</acronym> 中，打开的各个图像都在自己独立的窗口显示。(有时多个窗口都显示同一个图像，但这不常见。)我们在这将对默认普通图像窗口的组件一个简单的介绍。事实上，您可以用<link linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>查看</link>菜单使其中的一些不显示;但是可能会发现您并不想这么干。
  </para>

  <calloutlist>
    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-titlebar'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Lišta s titulkem</title>
        <para>
          V nejhořejší čáasti okna obrázku pravděpodobně je lišta s titulkem,
          která zobrazuje jméno obrázku a další informace o něm. Titulkovou
          lištu ve skutečnosti nevytváří Gimp, ale okenní systém, takže její
          zobrazování a vzhled závisí na používaném operačnímk systému,
          správci oken, případně používaném tématu vzhledu. V <link
          linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>dialogu předvoleb</link> lze nastavit,
          jaké informace se v liště mají zobrazovat.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Title Bar:</title>
        <para>
          At the top of the image window you will probably see a title bar,
          showing the name of the image and some basic information about
          it. The title bar is actually provided by the windowing system,
          not by Gimp itself, so its appearance may vary with different
          operating systems, window managers, and/or themes.  In the <link
          linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>Preferences dialog</link> you can
          customize the information that appears here, if you want to.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Titelzeile:</title>
        <para>
          Im oberen Bereich des Fensters befindet sich die Titelzeile indem
          verschiedene Informationen angezeigt werden. Die Titelbar wird
          von GIMP selber nicht beeinflußt, sondern sieht von
          Fenstersystem zu Fenstersystem verschieden aus; die Informationen
          bleiben jedoch gleich. Sie können in den Einstellungen unter
          <link linkend='gimp-prefs-image-window'>Bildfenster</link> die
          angezeigten Informationen beeinflussen.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Barre de titre</title>
        <para>
          En haut de la fenêtre image se trouve probablement la barre de 
          titre dans laquelle s'affiche le nom de l'image et quelques 
          informations de base. La barre de titre est actuellement 
          générée par le gestionnaire de fenêtre et non par Gimp, aussi 
          son apparence peut changer selon le système d'exploitation, le 
          gestionnaire de fenêtre et/ou le thème. Dans le 
          <link linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>Dialogue des préférences</link> 
          vous pouvez personnaliser les informations qui y apparaîssent.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>标题栏： </title>
        <para>
  在图像窗口最上面是标题栏，显示图像的名字和一些基本信息。标题栏其实是由窗口系统而不是 Gimp 自身提供的，因此在不同操作系统，窗口管理器和主题中表现也不尽相同。如果您愿意，可以在<link linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>首选项对话框</link>中定制您想显示的信息。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-menu'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Nabídka obrázku</title>
        <para>
          Přímo pod titulkovou lištou se nachází (pokud nebyla potlačena)
          lišta s nabídkou okna obrázku. Poskytuje přístup k téměř všem
          operacím, které lze s obrázkem provádět. (Některé globální operace
          jsou přístupné jen z nabídky Panelu nástrojů). Stejná nabídka je
          přístupná i kliknutím pravým tlačítkem myši do obrázku
          <footnote><para>Uživatelé počítačů Macintosh mohou stisknout klávesu
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> a levé tlačítko myši.</para></footnote> nebo
          kliknutím na šipku v levém horním rohu okna obrázku mezi pravítky,
          pokud to považujete za pohodlnější. Navíc lze většinu operací z
          nabídky vyvolat i pomocí klávesnice stisknutím klávesy
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> a tzv. <emphasis>akcelerační
          klávesy</emphasis>, tj. klávesy odpovídající podtrženému znaku
          v názvu požadované nabídky a položky. Lze také používat klávesové
          zkratky, a to i vlastní, uživatelsky definované, pokud je
          v předvolbách povolena volba <link
          linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Používat dynamické klávesové
          zkratky</link>.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Image Menu:</title>
        <para>
          Directly below the title bar appears the Image Menu (unless it
          has been suppressed).  This menu gives you access to nearly every
          operation you can perform on an image.   (There are some "global"
          actions that can only be accessed via the Toolbox menu.)  You can
          also get the Image Menu by right-clicking inside the
          image<footnote><para> Users with an Apple Macintosh can use
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+left mousebutton.</para></footnote>, or by
          left-clicking on the little "arrow" symbol in the upper left
          corner, if for some reason you find one of these more convenient.
          More: most menu operations can also be activated from the
          keyboard, using Alt plus an "accelerator" key underlined in the
          menu title. More: you can define your own custom shortcuts for
          menu actions, if you enable <link
          linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Use Dynamic Keyboard
          Shortcuts</link> in the Preferences dialog.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Bildmenü:</title>
        <para>
          Genau unter der Titelzeile befindet sich die Menüzeile mit dem
          Bildmenü. Das Bildmenü gibt Zugriff zu fast jeder Operation und
          Werkzeug, die in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> zur Verfügung steht.
          Das Bildmenü ist ausserdem mit einem rechten Mausklick
          <footnote><para> Benutzer eines Apple Macintosh benutzten
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+linke Maustaste.</para></footnote> auf das
          <link linkend='co-imagewindow-inactive'>Bild</link> zu erreichen.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Barre des Menus :</title>
        <para>
          Juste en dessous de la barre de titre se trouve le menu image 
          (à moins qu'il n'ait été désactivé). Ce menu vous permet 
          d'accéder à presque toutes les opérations réalisables sur une 
          image (Il y a des actions "globales" qui ne sont accessibles 
          que par le menu de la boîte à outil). Vous pouvez aussi 
          dérouler le menu image en cliquant avec le bouton droit sur 
          l'image
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Les utilisateurs de Mac peuvent utiliser
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+bouton.
            </para>
          </footnote>, ou bien en cliquant sur la flèche dans le coin 
          supérieur gauche, si l'une de ces méthodes vous convient 
          mieux. De plus, la plupart des opérations du menu peuvent 
          aussi être activées depuis le clavier, en utilisant Alt et 
          une touche "accélératrice" soulignée dans le texte du menu. 
          Enfin, vous pouvez définir vos propres raccourcis clavier 
          pour les actions du menu, si vous avez autorisé 
          <link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Utiliser les raccourcis 
          clavier dynamiques</link> dans le dialogue des préférences.
        </para>
      </formalpara>


      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>图像菜单： </title>
        <para>
  标题栏正下方是图像菜单(除非它被挤压了)。该菜单提供几乎所有的可以在图像上操作的功能。(一些“全局”操作只能通过工具箱菜单实现。)您也能在图像菜单中点右键或在左上角左键点“箭头”标志来打开图像菜单，选择您觉得最方便的办法。另外：大部分操作也能通过键盘，用 Alt+ 菜单标题旁带下划线的字母。如果您在首选项对话框勾选<link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>使用动态快捷键</link>，就可以自定义自己菜单动作的快捷键。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-menu-button'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Tlačítko nabídky:</title>
        <para>
          Stisknutím tohoto tlačítka se otevře nabídka obrázku ve vertikální,
          nikoliv horizontální podobě. Z kláv esnice lze tato nabídka otevřít
          zkratkou <keycap>Shift F10</keycap>.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en"> <!-- changed 10/10/2004 -->
        <title>Menu Button:</title>
        <para>
          Clicking on this little button gives you the Image Menu, except
          in a column instead of a row.  Mnemonics users who don't want the
          menu bar visible can acces to this menu by pressing the
          <keycap>Shift F10</keycap> key.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'> <!-- fuzzy 10/10/2004 -->
        <title>Menüschaltfläche:</title>
        <para>
          Durch klicken auf die Menüschaltfläche erreichen Sie das
          Bildmenü als Kontextmenü.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Bouton Menu :</title>
        <para>
          Cliquer sur ce petit bouton déroule le menu Image sur une 
          colonne. Ceux qui utilisent les accélérateurs claviers 
          et qui et qui n'ont pas la barre des menus visible peuvent 
          accéder au menu d'image par la touche <keycap>Maj F10</keycap>.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN"> <!-- fuzzy 10/10/2004 -->
        <title>菜单按钮： </title>
        <para>
          点击这个小按钮就出现竖向的图像菜单。这个按钮并不是特别有用。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-ruler' id='gimp-image-window-ruler'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Pravítko:</title>
        <para>
          Ve výchozím nastavení jsou vlevo a nahoře od obrázku zobrazena
          pravítka ukazující souřadnice obrázku. Jednotky souřadnic lze
          nastavit dle libosti. Ve výchozím nastavení se používají pixely,
          ale to lze snadno změnit, jak bude popsáno dále.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <para lang='cs'>
        Jedním z nejdůležitějších využití pravítek je vytváření
        <emphasis>vodítek</emphasis>. Pokud kliknete na pravítko a se stále
        stisknutým tlačítkem myši táhnete do obrázku, vytvoří se vodící linka,
        vodítko, která usnadňuje přesné umisťování objektů a grafických prvků
        v obrázku. Vodítka lze přesouvat kliknutím a tažením na jiné místo,
        přesunutím mimo obrázek je lze zcela smazat.
      </para>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Ruler:</title>
        <para>
          In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the left of
          the image, indicating coordinates within the image.  You can
          control what type of coordinates are shown if you want to.  By
          default, pixels are used, but you can change to other units,
          using the Units setting described below.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <para lang='en'>
        One of the most important uses of rulers is to create
        <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.  If you click on a ruler and drag into
        the image display, a guideline will be created, which you can use
        to help you position things accurately.  Guides can be moved by
        clicking on them and dragging, or deleted by dragging them out of
        the image display.
      </para>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Lineal:</title>
        <para>
          In einer voreingestellten Anzeige des Bildfensters erscheinen
          Lineale an der oberen und linken Kante. Diese Lineale beschreiben
          die aktuellen Koordinaten des Bildes.  Voreingestellt wird als
          Maßeinheit Pixel benutzt, jedoch kann dies durch die
          Einheitenschaltfläche geändert werden.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Les règles :</title>
        <para>
          Dans la configuration par défaut, les règles sont affichées 
          en haut et à gauche de l'image, elles indiquent les 
          coordonnées dans l'image. Vous pouvez choisir le type de 
          coordonnées affiché. Par défaut, l'unité de mesure est le 
          pixel, mais vous pouvez choisir une autre unité en utilisant 
          les paramètres d'unité décrits plus loin.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <para lang='fr'>
        Un des usages majeur des règles est de créer des <emphasis>guides
        </emphasis>. Si vous cliquez sur une règle et que vous la
        glissez dans l'image affichée un guide va être créé que vous
        pouvez dès lors utiliser pour vous positionner précisement
        dans l'image. Les guides sont déplacables en cliquant dessus,
        ramenez les vers leur règle d'origine pour les ôter de l'image.
      </para>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>标尺：</title>
        <para>
  在默认布局中，标尺在图像的左边和上面，显示图像的坐标。您可以控制想显示何种类型的坐标。默认使用像素，但能够用下面提到的单位设置更换为其它单位。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-quickmask'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Přepínač rychlé masky:</title>
        <para>
          V levém dolním rohu okna obrázku je malé tlačítko, které přepíná
          mezi běžným režimem a režimem rychlé masky. Rychlá maska je
          alternativní a často velmi užitečný způsob zobrazování výběrů v
          obrázku. Více viz část <link linkend='gimp-qmask'>Rychlá
          maska</link>.
        </para>
     </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>QuickMask Toggle:</title>
        <para>
          At the lower left corner of the image display is a small button
          that toggles on or off the Quick Mask, which is an alternate, and
          often extremely useful, way of viewing the selected area within
          the image. For more details see <link
          linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMask</link>.
        </para>
     </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>QuickMask Schaltfläche:</title>
        <para>
          Mit der QuickMask Schaltfläche können Sie die QuickMask
          aktivieren und deaktivieren. Die Maske selber ist eine
          alternative Ansicht um Auswahlen zu bearbeiten. Für mehr
          Informationen lesen Sie im Abschnitt <link
          linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMask benutzen</link> nach.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>(Dés)activer le masquage rapide :</title>
        <para>
          En bas à gauche de la fenêtre image se trouve un petit bouton 
          qui permet d'activer ou de désactiver le masquage rapide qui 
          est une manière alternative, et souvent très utile, de voir 
          la partie sélectionnée d'une image. Pour plus d'information 
          voyez la section 
  <link linkend='gimp-image-window-qmask-button'>Masquage rapide</link>.
        </para>
     </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>快速蒙板开关：</title>
        <para>
  在图像显示的左下角有一个控制快速蒙板开启关闭的小按钮，这是非常有用的一种查看图像选区的方法。要了解更多，请看<link linkend='gimp-image-window-qmask-button'>快速蒙板</link>。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-coordinates'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Souřadnice kurzoru:</title>
        <para>
          V levém dolním rohu okna obrázku je oblast zobrazující aktuální
          souřadnice kurzoru (tedy polohu myši, používáte-li myš), je-li
          nad obrázkem. Jednotky jsou tytéž, jaké používají pravítka (ve
          výchozím nastavení pixely).
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Pointer coordinates:</title>
        <para>
          In the lower left corner of the window is a rectangular area used
          to show the current pointer coordinates (that is, the mouse
          location, if you are using a mouse), whenever the pointer is
          within the image boundaries.  The units are the same as for the
          rulers.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Mauszeigerkoordinaten:</title>
        <para>
          Die Koordinaten des Mauszeiger im aktuellen Bild werden in diesem
          Bereich eingeblendet. Die Einheiten der Koordinaten (x, y im
          Koordinatensystem des Bildes) können mit der angrenzenden
          Schaltfläche verändert werden.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Coordonnées du pointeur :</title>
        <para>
          Dans le coin inférieur gauche de la fenêtre image s'affiche 
          les coordonnées du pointeur (c-à-d la position de la souris, 
          si vous utilisez une souris), tant que le pointeur se trouve 
          sur l'image. L'unité est la même que pour les règles.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>指针坐标：</title>
        <para>
  当您的指针在图像内部时，左下角的矩形窗口就会显示当前的指针坐标。(假如您使用鼠标，就是指鼠标指针所在位置。)改单位和标尺单位一样。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-units'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Nabídka jednotek:</title>
        <para>
          (Tato vlastnost je nová v Gimpu 2.2; nebyla přítomná v Gimpu 2.0.)
          Ve výchozímk nastavení se pro pravítka a řadu dalších účelů
          používají pixely. Pomocí této nabídky lze používané jednotky
          přepnout na palce, milimetry nebo některou z řady dalších možností.
          <!-- dot dot fix - en? -->
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Units menu:</title>
        <para>
          (This feature is new in Gimp 2.2; it does not appear in Gimp
          2.0).  By default, the units used for the rulers and several
          other purposes are pixels.  You can change to inches, cm, or
          several other possibilities using this menu.  (If you do, note
          that the setting of "Dot for dot" in the View menu affects how
          the display is scaled:  see <link
          linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>Dot for Dot</link> for more
          information.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Einheitenmenü:</title>
        <para>
          Die voreingestellte Maßeinheit in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> ist
          Pixel. Diese Maßeinheit wird von Werkzeugen, Linealen und
          vielen anderen Dingen in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> benutzt. Durch
          klicken auf die Schaltfläche können Sie die Maßeinheit auf
          cm, inch oder andere, verändern.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='fr'>
        <title>Menu des unités</title>
        <para>
          (fonctionnalité apparue dans Gimp 2.2)
          Par défaut, l'unité utilisée pour les règles et d'autres 
          fonctions est le pixel. Vous pouvez la changer pour le 
          centimètre, le pouce ou bien d'autre possibilités en 
          utilisant ce menu (Si vous le faites, sachez que le 
          paramètre "Point pour point" du menu Affichage modifiera 
          la mise à l'échelle de l'écran :
          Voyez <link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>Point pour point</link>
          pour plus d'informations.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>单位菜单：</title>
        <para>
  (这是 Gimp 2.2 的新特性,在 Gimp 2.0 中没有)。在标尺和许多其它操作中默认的单位是像素。您能在该菜单中将其单位变为英尺，厘米或其它可用的单位。(如果您要这么做，要注意在“查看”菜单中“点对点”的设置对显示刻度的影响：更详细的信息可以看<link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>点对点</link>。)
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-zoom' id='gimp-image-window-zoom'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Nabídka přiblížení:</title>
        <para>
          (Tato vlastnost je nová v Gimpu 2.2.) Existuje řada metod pro
          přibližování a oddalování obrázku, ale použití této nabídky je
          zřejmě nejjednodušší.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Zoom button:</title>
        <para>
          (This feature is new in Gimp 2.2; it does not appear in Gimp
          2.0).  There are a number of ways to zoom the image in or out,
          but this menu is perhaps the simplest.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Zoom Schaltfläche:</title>
        <para>
          Sie können die Zoom-Stufe durch Klicken auf diese Schaltfläche
          beliebig verändern.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Bouton Zoom :</title>
        <para>
          (fonctionnalité apparue dans Gimp 2.2)
          Il y a plusieurs manières de zoomer plus ou moins dans l'image,
          mais ce menu est rapide d'accès et affiche la valeur courante
          du zoom.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>缩放按钮：</title>
        <para>
          (这是 Gimp 2.2 的新特性,在 Gimp 2.0 中没有)。有许多方法放大缩小图像，但使用这个菜单可能是最简单的。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-statusbar' id='gimp-image-window-status-bar'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Stavová oblast:</title>
        <para>
          Pod obrázkem je stavová oblast, která většinou, ve výchozím
          nastavení, zobrazuje informace o právě aktivní části obrázku
          a o množství systémové paměti, které obrázek zabírá. Informace
          zobrazované ve stavové oblasti lze v předvolbách nastavit podle
          potřeb uživatele. Během časově nároičných operací se ve stavové
          oblasti zobraují informace o průběhu operace.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Status Area:</title>
        <para>
          The Status Area appears below the image display.  Most of the
          time, by default, it shows which part of the image is currently
          active, and the amount of system memory that the image is
          consuming.  You can customize the information that appears here,
          by changing your Preferences.  When you perform time-consuming
          operations, the status area changes temporarily to show what
          operation is being performed, and its state of progress.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Statuszeile:</title>
        <para>
          Die Statuszeile zeigt die aktuelle Ebene auf der gezeichnet wird,
          sowie die Größe des derzeit vom Bild benutzten Speichers. Bei
          Zeitintensiven Operationen verändert sich die Statuszeile zu
          einer Fortschrittsanzeige.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Bandeau de statut :</title>
        <para>
          Le bandeau de statut se trouve en bas de la fenêtre image. 
          La plupart du temps, par défaut, il affiche la partie de 
          l'image actuellement active, et l'espace mémoire que 
          l'image occupe. Vous pouvez personnaliser ces informations 
          en changeant vos Préférences. Lorsque vous lancez des 
          opérations consommatrice de temps, le bandeau de statut 
          affiche quelle est l'opération en cours et son état 
          d'avancement.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>状态区：</title>
        <para>
  状态区在图像显示下方。大部分时间，它默认显示图像当前活动部分和图像消耗的系统内存量。您可以改变首选项来定制择里显示的信息。当您运行很耗时的操作时，状态区就零时地显示当前进行地操作及其进程。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-cancel'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Tlačítko Zrušit:</title>
        <para>
          V pravém dolním rohu okna obrázku je tlačítko
          <guibutton>Zrušit</guibutton>, které umožňuje přerušit běh
          složitých, dlouhotrvajících operací (obvykle zásuvných modulů).
          Hodí se v případech, kdy si uživatel uvědomí, že prováděnou operaci
          nepotřebuje, a nechce čekat na její dokončení.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <note lang='cs'>
        <para>
          Některé zásuvné moduly ale na přerušení reagují nepěkně a mohou po
          sobě zanechat poškozené části obrázku.
        </para>
      </note>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Cancel Button:</title>
        <para>
          At the lower right corner of the window appears the Cancel
          button. If you start a complex, time-consuming operation (most
          commonly a plug-in), and then decide, while it is being computed,
          that you didn't really want to do it after all, this button will
          cancel it immediately.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <note lang='en'>
        <para>
          There are a few plug-ins that respond badly to being canceled,
          possibly leaving corrupted pieces of images behind.
        </para>
      </note>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Abbrechen Schaltfläche:</title>
        <para>
          Mit der Abbrechen Schaltfläche können zeitintensive Operationen
          abgebrochen werden.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <note lang='de'>
        <para>
          Einige Plugins reagieren sehr langsam auf die Abbrechen
          Schaltfläche, welches zu unerwünschten Resultaten führt.
        </para>
      </note>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Bouton Annuler :</title>
        <para>
          Dans le coin en bas à droite de la fenêtre image se trouve 
          le bouton Annuler. Si vous commencez une opération complexe 
          et consommatrice de temps (la plupart du temps un greffon), 
          et décidez, alors qu'elle est en cours, que vous ne voulez 
          plus vraiment l'effectuer, ce bouton l'arrêtera immédiatement.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <note lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Il y a quelques greffons qui répondent mal à l'arrêt et 
          peuvent altérer des parties de l'image.
        </para>
      </note>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>取消按钮：</title>
        <para>
  取消按钮在窗口的右下角。假如您启动一个复杂，耗时的操作(主要是插件)，当它正在计算时，您决定不这么干了，该按键就使其马上停止下来。
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <note lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
  有些插件对被取消无法及时响应，可能在图像上留下未完成部分。
        </para>
      </note>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-navigation' id='gimp-image-window-nav-button'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Navigátor:</title>
        <para>
          Toto malé tlačítko tvaru zkřížených šipek v pravém dolním rohu okna
          obrázku slouží k navigaci v obrázku. Kliknutím na něj a podržením
          levého tlačítka myši se objeví okno se zmenšeným náhledem celého
          brázku. V náhledu je zvýrazněna oblast právě zobrazená v okně.
          Posunem myši se stále stlačeným levým tlačítkem lze tuto oblast
          přesunovat, a tak měnit část obrázku zobrazovanou v okně. V případě
          velmi velkých obrázků, ze kterých je v okně vidět jen malá část, je
          to nejpohodlnější způsob navigace. (Další způsoby navigace v obrázku
          jsou popsány v části <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Dialog
          Navigace</link>. Oblíbenou metodou je například kliknutí prostředním
          tlačítkem myši přímo do obrázku a tažení.)
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Navigation control:</title>
        <para>
          This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right corner of
          the image display.  Clicking on it, and holding the left mouse
          button down, brings up a window showing a miniature view of the
          image, with the displayed area outlined.  You can pan to a
          different part of the image by moving the mouse while keeping the
          button depressed.  For large images of which only a small part is
          displayed, the navigation window is often the most convenient way
          of getting to the part of the image you are looking for.  (See
          <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigation Dialog</link>
          for other ways to access the Navigation Window).
          (If your mouse has a middle-button, click-drag with it to span 
          across the image).
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Navigationsschaltfläche:</title>
        <para>
          Diese kleine Schaltfläche blendet durch Klicken eine
          Miniaturansicht des aktuellen Bildes ein, in dem navigiert werden
          kann. So können Sie die aktuelle Ansicht des Bildabschnitts
          beliebig verschieben. Für sehr große Bilder kann auch der
          <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigationsdialog</link>
          hilfreich sein.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Bouton Navigation :</title>
        <para>
          C'est un petit bouton avec une croix dont les bras sont des 
          flèches en bas à droite de la fenêtre image. Cliquer dessus et 
          maintenir le bouton gauche de la souris enfoncé fait 
          apparaître une fenêtre montrant une vue miniature de l'image 
          et la partie actuellement affichée encadrée. Vous pouvez vous 
          déplacer dans l'image en bougeant la souris tout en maintenant 
          le bouton pressé. Pour les images de grande taille, dont une 
          petite partie seulement est affichée, la fenêtre de navigation 
          est souvent la manière la plus simple d'afficher la partie qui 
          vous intéresse (voir
       <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>dialogue de Navigation</link>
          pour les autres manières d'accèder à la fenêtre de navigation).
          (Si votre souris possède un bouton-roue du milieu, le fait de 
          cliquer avec dans l'image vous permet de vous déplacer dans 
          l'image).
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>导航控制：</title>

        <para>
          这是一个在右下角地十字形按钮。点击它，然后按住右键不放，将出现图像的缩略图，轮廓线内表示显示区域。您可以按住按键移动鼠标让它在图像不同的区域上移动。对于只能显示一小部分的大图像来说，导航窗口常常是最方便地在图像上搜寻的方法。(要了解其它打开导航窗口的方法，请看<link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>导航对话框</link>。)
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-inactive'>
      <formalpara lang='cs'>
        <title>Neaktivní výplň:</title>
        <para>
          Tato oblast odděluje obrázek od ostatních částí okna. <!-- FIXME-->
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>inactive padding area:</title>
        <para><!-- FIXME -->
          This padding area seperates the active image display and the
          inactive padding area, so you're able to distinguish between
          them. You cannot apply any Filters or Operations in generall on
          the inactive area.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>inaktiver Bildrahmen:</title>
        <para>
          Der inaktive Bildrahmen grenzt das eigentlich aktive Bild vom
          inaktiven Rahmen ab. Der Rahmen selber kann nur in seiner
          Rahmenfarbe verändert werden, wird aber von Operationen oder
          Werkzeugen die auf das Bild angewandt werden nicht beeinflußt.
          Wenn Ebenen größer als das eigentliche Bild sind, sieht man
          den Ebenenrahmen im inaktiven Bildrahmen.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='fr'>
        <title>Partie inactive de la fenêtre image :</title>
        <para>
          Ce remplissage sépare, dans la fenêtre image, la partie 
          active de l'image de la partie inactive, ainsi vous pouvez 
          faire la distinction entre elles. Vous ne pouvez pas 
          appliquer de filtres ni, plus généralement, faire 
          d'opération sur la partie inactive.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>非活动填充区域：</title>
        <para>
          该填充区域将活动图像的显示和非活动填充区域区分开。您无法在非活动区域上进行任何滤镜和一般操作。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-display'>
      <formalpara lang="cs">
        <title>Oblast zobrazující obrázek:</title>
        <para>
          Nejdůležitější část okna obrázku je samosřejmě obrázek samotný.
          Zabírá porstřední část okna. <!-- FIXME -->
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="en">
        <title>Image Display:</title>
        <para>
          The most important part of the image window is, of course, the
          image display.  It occupies the central area of the window,
          surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image boundary,
          against a neutral gray background.  You can change the zoom level
          of the image display in a variety of ways, including the Zoom
          setting described below.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Bildanzeige:</title>
        <para>
          Der wohl wichtigste Teil des Bildfensters ist die Anzeige des
          Bildes. Um dem Bild herum befindet sich eine gelblich, schwarz
          gestrichelte Linie, welche die Grenzen einer Ebene kennzeichnet.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="fr">
        <title>Affichage de l'image :</title>
        <para>
          La partie la plus importante de la fenêtre image est, bien entendu,
          l'image elle-même. Elle occupe la partie centrale de la fenêtre,
          entourée d'un tireté jaune et noir montrant les limites de l'image, sur un fond
          gris neutre. Vous pouvez changer le niveau de zoom de la fenêtre image
          de diverses manières, y compris avec le paramètre du comportement
          du zoom décrit plus bas.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>图像显示：</title>
        <para>
          图像窗口中最重要的部分当然是图像显示。它由表示图像边界的黄色点划线围住，外围是中性灰色的背景，占据窗口的中间地带。由多种方式改变图像显示的大小，包括下面要提到的缩放设置。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>

    <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-resize'>
      <formalpara lang='cs'>
        <title>Přepínač přibližování obrázku:</title>
        <para>
          Pokud je toto tlačítko stisknuto, mění se se změnou velikosti okna i
          stupeň přiblížení obrázku.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>image window resize toggle:</title>
        <para>
          If this button is pressed, the image itself will be resized if
          the image window is resized.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='de'>
        <title>Schaltfläche zur Vergrößerung des Bildfensters:</title>
        <para>
          Durch klicken der Schaltfläche wird bei Vergrößerung oder
          Verkleinerung des Bildfensters ebenso das Bild vergrößert oder
          verkleinert.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang='fr'>
        <title>(Dés)activer le redimensionnement de la fenêtre image :</title>
        <para>
          Si ce bouton est pressé, l'image est redimensionnée si la 
          fenêtre image l'est aussi.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
        <title>图像窗口大小控制开关：</title>
        <para>
          如果按下该按钮，图像将随着图像窗口一起改变大小。
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </callout>
  </calloutlist>
</sect2>
