<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-using-imagewindow' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Image Window</title>
  <title lang="fr">Fenêtre d'image</title>
  <title lang="sv">Bildfönstret</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image Window</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Fenêtre d'imageImage</primary>
    <primary lang="sv">Bildfönstret</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/imagewindow-description-en.png' format='png'/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para lang="en">
    In Gimp, each image that you have open is displayed in its own
    separate window.  (In some cases, multiple windows may all
    display the same image, but this is unusual.)  We will begin
    with a brief description of the components that are present by
    default in an ordinary image window.  Some of these, in fact,
    can be made to disappear using commands in the <link
    linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>View</link> menu; but
    you will probably find that you don't want to do that.  
  </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Title Bar</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    At the top of the image window you will probably see a title
	    bar, showing the name of the image and some basic information
	    about it.  The title bar is actually provided by the
	    windowing system, not by Gimp itself, so its appearance may
	    vary with different operating systems, window managers,
	    and/or themes.  In the <link
	    linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>Preferences dialog</link> you can customize
	    the information that appears here, if you want to.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Image Menu</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    Directly below the title bar appears the Image Menu
	    (unless it has been suppressed).  This menu gives you
	    access to nearly every operation you can perform on an
	    image.   (There are some "global" actions
	    that can only be accessed via the Toolbox menu.)  
            You can also get the Image Menu by right-clicking
	    inside the image, or by left-clicking on the little
	    "arrow" symbol in the upper left corner, if for some
	    reason you find one of these more convenient.  More: most 
	    menu operations can also be activated from the keyboard,
	    using Alt plus an "accelerator" key underlined in the menu
	    title.  More: you can define your own custom shortcuts for
	    menu actions, if you enable <link
	    linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Use Dynamic Keyboard
	    Shortcuts</link> in the 
	    Preferences dialog. 
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Menu Button</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    Clicking on this little button gives you the Image Menu,
	    except in a column instead of a row.  It is not especially
	    useful. 
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Ruler</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the
	    left of the image, indicating coordinates within the
	    image.  You can control what type of coordinates are shown
	    if you want to.  By default, pixels are used, but you can
	    change to other units, using the Units setting described
	    below. 
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Image Display</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    The most important part of the image window is, of course,
	    the image display.  It occupies the central area of the window,
	    surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image
	    boundary, against a neutral gray background.  You can
	    change the zoom level of the image display in a variety of
	    ways, including the Zoom setting described below.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">QuickMask Toggle</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    At the lower left corner of the image display is a small
	    button that toggles on or off the Quick Mask, which is an
	    alternate, and often extremely useful, way of viewing the
	    selected area within the image. For more details see <link
	    linkend='gimp-image-window-qmask-button'>QuickMask</link>.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Pointer coordinates</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    In the lower left corner of the window is a rectangular
	    area used to show the current pointer coordinates (that
	    is, the mouse location, if you are using a mouse),
	    whenever the pointer is within the image boundaries.  The
	    units are the same as for the rulers.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Units menu</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    (This feature is new in Gimp 2.2; it does not appear in
	    Gimp 2.0).  By default, the units used for the rulers and
	    several other purposes are pixels.  You can change to
	    inches, cm, or several other possibilities using this
	    menu.  (If you do, note that the setting of "Dot for dot"
	    inthe View menu affects how the display is scaled:  see
	    <link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>Dot for Dot</link>
	    for more information.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Zoom menu</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    (This feature is new in Gimp 2.2; it does not appear in
	    Gimp 2.0).  There are a number of ways to zoom the image
	    in or out, but this menu is perhaps the simplest.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Status Area </term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    The Status Area appears below the image display.  Most of
	    the time, by default, it shows which part of the image is
	    currently active, and the amount of system memory that the
	    image is consuming.  You can
	    customize the information that appears here, by changing
	    your Preferences.  When
	    you perform time-consuming operations, the status
	    area changes temporarily to show what operation is being
	    performed, and its state of progress.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Navigation control</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right
	    corner of the image display.  Clicking on it, and holding
	    the left mouse button down, brings up a window showing a
	    miniature view of the image, with the displayed area
	    outlined.  You can pan to a different part of the image by
	    moving the mouse while keeping the button depressed.  For
	    large images of which only a small part is displayed, the
	    navigation window is often the most convenient way of
	    getting to the part of the image you are looking for.
	    (See  <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigation
	    Dialog</link> for other ways to access the Navigation Window).
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term lang="en">Cancel Button</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para lang="en">
	    At the lower right corner of the window appears the Cancel
	    button.  If you start a complex, time-consuming operation
	    (most commonly a plug-in), and then decide, while it is
	    being computed, that you didn't really want to do it after
	    all, this button will cancel it immediately.  (Note,
	    though, that there are a few plug-ins that respond badly
	    to being canceled, possibly leaving corrupted pieces of
	    images behind.)
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
    
</sect2>
