<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-image-window' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Image Window</title>
  <title lang='de'>Bildfenster</title>
  <title lang="fr">Fenêtre d'image</title>
  <title lang="sv">Bildfönstret</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">图像窗口</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image Window</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Fenêtre d'imageImage</primary>
    <primary lang="sv">Bildfönstret</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像窗口</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <mediaobjectco>
    <imageobjectco>
      <areaspec units="calspair">
        <!-- make the id's unique, to not clash with others -->
        <area id='co-imagewindow-titlebar' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-menu' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-menu-button' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-ruler' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-quickmask' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-coordinates' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-units' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-zoom' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-statusbar' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-cancel' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-navigation' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-inactive' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-display' coords='' />
        <area id='co-imagewindow-resize' coords='' />
      </areaspec>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/imagewindow-description.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
    </imageobjectco>
  </mediaobjectco>

  <para lang="en">
    In Gimp, each image that you have open is displayed in its own
    separate window.  (In some cases, multiple windows may all
    display the same image, but this is unusual.)  We will begin
    with a brief description of the components that are present by
    default in an ordinary image window.  Some of these, in fact,
    can be made to disappear using commands in the <link
    linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>View</link> menu; but
    you will probably find that you don't want to do that.  
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    In <acronym>Gimp</acronym> wird jedes Bild in seinem eigenen Fenster
    geöffnet. Folgende eine Beschreibung der Elemente die per
    Voreinstellung sichtbar sind. Einige dieser Elemente können per
    <link linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>Ansicht</link> Menü
    ausgeblendet werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    在 <acronym>Gimp</acronym> 中，打开的各个图像都在自己独立的窗口显示。(有时多个窗口都显示同一个图像，但这不常见。)我们在这将对默认普通图像窗口的组件一个简单的介绍。事实上，您可以用<link linkend='gimp-imagewindow-menus-view'>查看</link>菜单使其中的一些不显示;但是可能会发现您并不想这么干。
 </para>

    <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-titlebar'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
            <title>
              Title Bar:
            </title>
            At the top of the image window you will probably see a title 
            bar, showing the name of the image and some basic
            information about it.  The title bar is actually provided by
            the windowing system, not by Gimp itself, so its appearance
            may vary with different operating systems, window managers,
            and/or themes.  In the <link
            linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>Preferences dialog</link> you
            can customize the information that appears here, if you want
            to.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
            <title>
              Titelzeile:
            </title>
            Im oberen Bereich des Fensters befindet sich die Titelzeile
            indem verschiedene Informationen angezeigt
            werden. Die Titelbar wird von GIMP selber nicht beeinflußt,
            sondern sieht von Fenstersystem zu Fenstersystem verschieden
            aus; die Informationen bleiben jedoch gleich. Sie können in
            den Einstellungen unter <link
            linkend='gimp-prefs-image-window'>Bildfenster</link> die
            angezeigten Informationen beeinflussen.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>
              标题栏：
            </title>
            在图像窗口最上面是标题栏，显示图像的名字和一些基本信息。标题栏其实是由窗口系统而不是 Gimp 自身提供的，因此在不同操作系统，窗口管理器和主题中表现也不尽相同。如果您愿意，可以在<link linkend='gimp-prefs-dialog'>首选项对话框</link>中定制您想显示的信息。
          </formalpara>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-menu'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
            <title>
              Image Menu:
            </title>
            Directly below the title bar appears the Image Menu (unless
            it has been suppressed).  This menu gives you access to
            nearly every operation you can perform on an image.   (There
            are some "global" actions that can only be accessed via the
            Toolbox menu.)  You can also get the Image Menu by
            right-clicking inside the image 
            <footnote>
              <para>
                Users with an Apple Macintosh can use
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+left mousebutton.
              </para>
            </footnote>, or by left-clicking on the
            little "arrow" symbol in the upper left corner, if for some
            reason you find one of these more convenient.  More: most
            menu operations can also be activated from the keyboard,
            using Alt plus an "accelerator" key underlined in the menu
            title.  More: you can define your own custom shortcuts for
            menu actions, if you enable <link
            linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>Use Dynamic Keyboard
            Shortcuts</link> in the Preferences dialog. 
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
            <title>
              Bildmenü:
            </title>
            Genau unter der Titelzeile befindet sich die Menüzeile mit
            dem Bildmenü. Das Bildmenü gibt Zugriff zu fast jeder
            Operation und Werkzeug, die in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> zur
            Verfügung steht. Das Bildmenü ist ausserdem mit einem
            rechten Mausklick 
            <footnote>
              <para>
                Benutzer eines Apple Macintosh benutzten
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+linke Maustaste.
              </para>
            </footnote>
            auf das <link linkend='co-imagewindow-inactive'>Bild</link> zu erreichen.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
            <title>
              图像菜单：
            </title>
              标题栏正下方是图像菜单(除非它被挤压了)。该菜单提供几乎所有的可以在图像上操作的功能。(一些“全局”操作只能通过工具栏菜单实现。)您也能在图像菜单中点右键或在左上角左键点“箭头”标志来打开图像菜单，选择您觉得最方便的办法。另外：大部分操作也能通过键盘，用 Alt+ 菜单标题旁带下划线的字母。如果您在首选项对话框勾选<link linkend='gimp-prefs-interface'>使用动态快捷键</link>，就可以自定义自己菜单动作的快捷键。
	  </formalpara> 
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-menu-button'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>
            Menu Button:
          </title>
            Clicking on this little button gives you the Image Menu,
            except in a column instead of a row.  It is not especially
            useful. 
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>
            Menüschaltfläche:
          </title>
            Durch klicken auf die Menüschaltfläche erreichen sie das
            Bildmenü als Kontextmenü.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>
            菜单按钮：
          </title>
            点击这个小按钮就出现竖向的图像菜单。这个按钮并不是特别有用。
          </formalpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-ruler' id='gimp-image-window-ruler'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Ruler:</title>
            In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the
            left of the image, indicating coordinates within the
            image.  You can control what type of coordinates are shown
            if you want to.  By default, pixels are used, but you can
            change to other units, using the Units setting described
            below.
          </formalpara>
          <para lang='en'>
            One of the most important uses of rulers is to create
            <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.  If you click on a ruler and
            drag into the image display, a guideline will be created,
            which you can use to help you position things accurately.
            Guides can be moved by clicking on them and dragging, or
            deleted by dragging them out of the image display.
          </para>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Lineal:</title>
            In einer voreingestellten Anzeige des Bildfensters
            erscheinen Lineale an der oberen und linken Kante. Diese
            Lineale beschreiben die aktuellen Koordinaten des Bildes.
            Voreingestellt wird als Maßeinheit Pixel benutzt, jedoch
            kann dies durch die Einheitenschaltfläche geändert werden.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>标尺：</title>
            在默认布局中，标尺在图像的左边和上面，显示图像的坐标。您可以控制想显示何种类型的坐标。默认使用像素，但能够用下面提到的单位设置更换为其它单位。
          </formalpara>
        </callout>


        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-quickmask'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>QuickMask Toggle:</title>
            At the lower left corner of the image display is a small
            button that toggles on or off the Quick Mask, which is an
            alternate, and often extremely useful, way of viewing the
            selected area within the image. For more details see <link
            linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMask</link>.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>QuickMask Schaltfläche:</title>
            Mit der QuickMask Schaltfläche können Sie die QuickMask
            aktivieren und deaktivieren. Die Maske selber ist eine
            alternative Ansicht um Auswahlen zu bearbeiten. Für mehr
            Informationen lesen Sie im Abschnitt <link
            linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMask
            benutzen</link> nach.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>快速蒙板开关：</title>
             在图像显示的左下角有一个控制快速蒙板开启关闭的小按钮，这是非常有用的一种查看图像选区的方法。要了解更多，请看<link linkend='gimp-image-window-qmask-button'>快速蒙板</link>。
          </formalpara>
          </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-coordinates'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Pointer coordinates:</title>
            In the lower left corner of the window is a rectangular
            area used to show the current pointer coordinates (that
            is, the mouse location, if you are using a mouse),
            whenever the pointer is within the image boundaries.  The
            units are the same as for the rulers.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Mauszeigerkoordinaten:</title>
            Die Koordinaten des Mauszeiger im aktuellen Bild werden in
            diesem Bereich eingeblendet. Die Einheiten der Koordinaten
            (x, y im Koordinatensystem des Bildes) können mit der
            angrenzenden Schaltfläche verändert werden.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>指针坐标：</title>
            当您的指针在图像内部时，左下角的矩形窗口就会显示当前的指针坐标。(假如您使用鼠标，就是指鼠标指针所在位置。)改单位和标尺单位一样。
          </formalpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-units'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Units menu:</title>
            (This feature is new in Gimp 2.2; it does not appear in
            Gimp 2.0).  By default, the units used for the rulers and
            several other purposes are pixels.  You can change to
            inches, cm, or several other possibilities using this
            menu.  (If you do, note that the setting of "Dot for dot"
            in the View menu affects how the display is scaled:  see
            <link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>Dot for Dot</link>
            for more information.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Einheitenmenü:</title>
            Die voreingestellte Maßeinheit in <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
            ist Pixel. Diese Maßeinheit wird von Werkzeugen, Linealen
            und vielen anderen Dingen in <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
            benutzt. Durch klicken auf die Schaltfläche können Sie die
            Maßeinheit auf cm, inch oder andere, verändern.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>单位菜单：</title>
            (这是 Gimp 2.2 的新特性,在 Gimp 2.0 中没有)。在标尺和许多其它操作中默认的单位是像素。您能在该菜单中将其单位变为英尺，厘米或其它可用的单位。(如果您要这么做，要注意在“查看”菜单中“点对点”的设置对显示刻度的影响：更详细的信息可以看<link linkend='gimp-view-dot-for-dot'>点对点</link>。)
	  </formalpara>
          </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-zoom' id='gimp-image-window-zoom'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Zoom button:</title>
            (This feature is new in Gimp 2.2; it does not appear in
            Gimp 2.0).  There are a number of ways to zoom the image
            in or out, but this menu is perhaps the simplest.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Zoom Schaltfläche:</title>
            Sie können die Zoom-Stufe durch Klicken auf diese
            Schaltfläche beliebig verändern.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>缩放按钮：</title>
            (这是 Gimp 2.2 的新特性,在 Gimp 2.0 中没有)。有许多方法放大缩小图像，但使用这个菜单可能是最简单的。
          </formalpara>
	  </callout>
        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-statusbar' id='gimp-image-window-status-bar'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Status Area:</title>
            The Status Area appears below the image display.  Most of
            the time, by default, it shows which part of the image is
            currently active, and the amount of system memory that the
            image is consuming.  You can customize the information that
            appears here, by changing your Preferences.  When you
            perform time-consuming operations, the status area changes
            temporarily to show what operation is being performed, and
            its state of progress.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Statuszeile:</title>
            Die Statuszeile zeigt die aktuelle Ebene auf der gezeichnet
            wird, sowie die Größe des derzeit vom Bild benutzten
	Speichers. Bei Zeitintensiven Operationen verändert sich die
            Statuszeile zu einer Fortschrittsanzeige.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>状态区：</title>
            状态区在图像显示下方。大部分时间，它默认显示图像当前活动部分和图像消耗的系统内存量。您可以改变首选项来定制择里显示的信息。当您运行很耗时的操作时，状态区就零时地显示当前进行地操作及其进程。
          </formalpara>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-cancel'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Cancel Button:</title>
             At the lower right corner of the window appears the
	     Cancel button. If you start a complex, time-consuming
	     operation (most commonly a plug-in), and then decide,
	     while it is being computed, that you didn't really
	     want to do it after all, this button will cancel it
	     immediately.
          </formalpara>
          <note lang='en'>
            There are a few plug-ins that respond badly to being
            canceled, possibly leaving corrupted pieces of images
            behind.
          </note>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Abbrechen Schaltfläche:</title>
            Mit der Abbrechen Schaltfläche können zeitintensive
            Operationen abgebrochen werden.
          </formalpara>
          <note lang='de'>
            Einige Plugins reagieren sehr langsam auf die Abbrechen
            Schaltfläche, welches zu unerwünschten Resultaten führt.
          </note>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>取消按钮：</title>
             取消按钮在窗口的右下角。假如您启动一个复杂，耗时的操作(主要是插件)，当它正在计算时，您决定不这么干了，该按键就使其马上停止下来。
          </formalpara>
          <note lang="zh_CN">
            有些插件对被取消无法及时响应，可能在图像上留下未完成部分。
          </note>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-navigation' id='gimp-image-window-nav-button'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Navigation control:</title>
            This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right
            corner of the image display.  Clicking on it, and holding
            the left mouse button down, brings up a window showing a
            miniature view of the image, with the displayed area
            outlined.  You can pan to a different part of the image by
            moving the mouse while keeping the button depressed.  For
            large images of which only a small part is displayed, the
            navigation window is often the most convenient way of
            getting to the part of the image you are looking for.
            (See  <link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigation
            Dialog</link> for other ways to access the Navigation Window).
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Navigationsschaltfläche:</title>
            Diese kleine Schaltfläche blendet durch Klicken eine
            Miniaturansicht des aktuellen Bildes ein, in dem navigiert
            werden kann. So können Sie die aktuelle Ansicht des
            Bildabschnitts
            beliebig verschieben. Für sehr große Bilder kann auch der
            <link
            linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>Navigationsdialog</link>
            hilfreich sein.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>导航控制：</title>
            这是一个在右下角地十字形按钮。点击它，然后按住右键不放，将出现图像的缩略图，轮廓线内表示显示区域。您可以按住按键移动鼠标让它在图像不同的区域上移动。对于只能显示一小部分的大图像来说，导航窗口常常是最方便地在图像上搜寻的方法。(要了解其它打开导航窗口的方法，请看<link linkend='gimp-navigation-dialog'>导航对话框</link>。)
          </formalpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-inactive'>
          <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>inactive padding area:</title>
            This padding area seperates the active image display and the
            inactive padding area, so you're able to distinguish between
            them. You cannot apply any Filters or Operations in generall
            on the inactive area.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>inaktiver Bildrahmen:</title>
            Der inaktive Bildrahmen grenzt das eigentlich aktive Bild
            vom inaktiven Rahmen ab. Der Rahmen selber kann nur in
            seiner Rahmenfarbe verändert werden, wird aber von
            Operationen oder Werkzeugen die auf das Bild angewandt
            werden nicht beeinflußt. Wenn Ebenen größer als das
            eigentliche Bild sind, sieht man den Ebenenrahmen im
            inaktiven Bildrahmen.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>非活动填充区域：</title>
            该填充区域将活动图像的显示和非活动填充区域区分开。您无法在非活动区域上进行任何滤镜和一般操作。
          </formalpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-display'>
          <formalpara lang="en">
          <title>Image Display:</title>
            The most important part of the image window is, of course,
            the image display.  It occupies the central area of the window,
            surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image
            boundary, against a neutral gray background.  You can
            change the zoom level of the image display in a variety of
            ways, including the Zoom setting described below.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Bildanzeige:</title>
            Der wohl wichtigste Teil des Bildfensters ist die Anzeige
            des Bildes. Um dem Bild herum befindet sich eine gelblich,
            schwarz gestrichelte Linie, welche die Grenzen einer Ebene
            kennzeichnet.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>图像显示：</title>
            图像窗口中最重要的部分当然是图像显示。它由表示图像边界的黄色点划线围住，外围是中性灰色的背景，占据窗口的中间地带。由多种方式改变图像显示的大小，包括下面要提到的缩放设置。
          </formalpara>
          </callout>

        <callout arearefs='co-imagewindow-resize'>
          <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>image window resize toggle:</title>
            If this button is pressed, the image itself will be resized
            if the image window is resized.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang='de'>
          <title>Schaltfläche zur Vergrößerung des Bildfensters:</title>
            Durch klicken der Schaltfläche wird bei Vergrößerung oder
            Verkleinerung des Bildfensters ebenso das Bild vergrößert
            oder verkleinert.
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>图像窗口大小控制开关：</title>
            如果按下该按钮，图像将随着图像窗口一起改变大小。
          </formalpara>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

</sect2>
