<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-running' lang="en;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Running Gimp</title>
  <title lang='de'>Gimp benutzen</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">运行 Gimp</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang='de'>GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Using</secondary>
    <secondary lang='de'>Benutzen</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">使用</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Most often, you start Gimp either by clicking on an icon (if your
    system is set up to provide you with one), or by typing
    <userinput>gimp</userinput> on a command line.  If you have multiple
    versions of the Gimp installed, you may need to type
    <userinput>gimp-2.2</userinput> to get the latest version. You can,
    if you want, give a list of image files on the command line after
    the program name, and they will automatically be opened by Gimp as
    it starts.  It is also possible, though, to open files from within
    Gimp once it is running. 
  </para>

  <para lang='de'>
    Meistens werden Sie <acronym>Gimp</acronym> mit einem Icon (sofern
    Ihr System eins zur Verfügung stellt) oder per Kommandozeile mit der
    Eingabe von <userinput>gimp</userinput> starten.  Sollten Sie jedoch
    mehrere <acronym>Gimp</acronym> Versionen installiert haben, wird es
    nötig sein <acronym>Gimp</acronym> explizit mit dem Kommando
    <userinput>gimp-2.2</userinput> zu starten. Optional können Sie
    zusätzlich auch mehrere Bilder angeben, die dann beim starten
    geöffnet werden.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一般，要启动 Gimp 您可以点击其图标(如果您的系统提供给您)，或再命令行下输入“gimp”。如果安装了多个版本的 Gimp,您要输入“gimp-2.0”来运行最新的版本。如果您原意，您可以再在命令行中程序后面输入一串图像文件名，这些文件将在 Gimp 启动时自动打开。当然，您也可以在 Gimp 运行后一个个打开。
  </para>  

  <para lang='en'>
    In most operating systems, you can set things up so that various
    types of image files are "associated" with Gimp, and cause it to
    start automatically when icons for them are double-clicked.  
  </para>

  <para lang='de'>
    In den meisten Betriebssystemen können Sie <acronym>Gimp</acronym>
    mit Bildformaten assoziieren, so dass das Programm automatisch
    gestartet wird, wenn Sie das Bild bearbeiten möchten.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    在大多数操作系统中，您可以让各种图像文件和 Gimp 相关联，这样当您双击这些图像图标时，Gimp 就自动启动了。
  </para>

  <tip lang='en;de'>
    <para>
      Wenn Sie möchten, dass <acronym>Gimp</acronym> automatisch beim
      Bearbeiten ihrer Bilder geöffnet wird, sollten Sie lieber
      <userinput>gimp-remote</userinput> mit den Bildern assoziieren,
      anstatt <userinput>gimp</userinput>. Sollte
      <acronym>Gimp</acronym> schon im Hintergrund laufen, werden mit
      Hilfe von <userinput>gimp-remote</userinput> die Bilder im
      laufenden Programm gestartet, anstatt fuer jedes Bild eine neue
      <acronym>Gimp</acronym> Instanz zu starten.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you want to cause a certain file type to automatically open in
      Gimp, you should associate it with "gimp-remote" rather than with
      "gimp".  The gimp-remote program is an auxiliary that comes with
      gimp.  If gimp is not already running on the system when
      gimp-remote is executed, it is started and the image given as
      argument to gimp-remote is loaded.  If gimp is already running,
      though, the image is simply loaded into the already-running
      program. 
    </para>
  </tip>

  <tip lang="zh_CN">
    <para>
      如果您像让特定的文件类型在 Gimp 中自动打开，您应当关联到程序“gimp-remote”而不是“gimp”。gimp-remote 是 gimp 所附带的程序。当 gimp 在系统中还没被启动，此时运行 gimp-remote 的话，gimp 就将把 gimp-remote 载入的图像作为参数而启动。如果 gimp 已经在运行中，该图像就仅仅是简单地载入到程序中。
    </para>
  </tip>  

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Command Line Arguments</title>
    <title lang='de'>Kommandozeilenargumente</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">命令行参数</title>

    <para lang="en">
      Ordinarily you don't need to give any arguments when starting
      Gimp, but here is a list of some that may at one time or anther be
      useful.  This is not a complete list; on Unix systems you can get
      a complete list by running <userinput>man gimp</userinput> in a
      terminal window.
    </para>

    <para lang='de'>
      Kommandozeilenargumente können sehr nützlich sein, sind aber
      optional. Die folgende Liste ist nicht komplett, da Argumente auch
      Betriebsystemabhängig sind. Unter Posix kompatiblen
      Betriebssystemen können Sie eine komplette Liste in der Manpage
      (<userinput>man gimp</userinput>) erfragen.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      一般情况下，启动 Gimp 并不需要参数，这儿是一些列表，它们可能在一些情况下有用。下面列的并不完全;在 Unix 系统中通过在终端窗口中输入“man gimp”来获得完全的列表。
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-h, --help</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
               Display a list of all commandline options.
          </para>
          <para lnag='de'>
            Zeigt eine Liste von Kommandozeilenargumenten.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-v, --version</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Print the version of Gimp being used, and exit.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Zeigt die <acronym>Gimp</acronym> Version.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--verbose</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
               Show detailed startup messages.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Zeigt detailierte Startmeldungen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-d, --no-data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
              Do  not  load  patterns, gradients, palettes, or brushes.
              Often useful in non-interactive situations where startup
              time  is  to be minimized.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--display <emphasis>display</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
               Use the designated X display (does not apply to
               Gimp on Microsoft Windows).
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Benutze die angegebene X Anzeige (gilt nicht für die Windows
            Version von <acronym>Gimp</acronym>)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-s, --no-splash</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Do not show the splash screen while starting.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Zeige kein Startfenster.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--session name</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
             Use a different sessionrc for this GIMP session. The
             given session name is appended to the default sessionrc
             filename. 
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Ein alternatives session-Profil verwenden.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-g, --gimprc <emphasis>gimprc</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
             Use an alternative gimprc instead of the default one. The
             "gimprc" file contains a record of your preferences.
             Useful in cases where plugins paths or machine specs may be
             different.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Ein alternatives gimprc-Profil verwenden.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-c, --console-messages</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
               Do not popup dialog boxes on errors or warnings. Print
               the messages on the console instead. 
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Warnungen im Terminal statt in einem Dialog ausgeben.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-b, --batch <emphasis>commands</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
             Execute the set of commands> non-interactively.  The  set
             of commands  is  typically  in  the form of a script that
             can be executed by one of the GIMP scripting  extensions.
             When  commands is <userinput>-</userinput>, the commands
             are read from standard input. 
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Befehle im Stapelmodus ausführen. Die Befehle werden
            normalerweise in Form eines Scriptes angegeben. Sollte
            <userinput>-</userinput> angegeben sein, werden die
            Kommandos von der Standardeingabe gelesen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
