<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-04-04 alex falappa: fixed missing italian part
  2007-03-24 lexa: merged path concept and path usage
  2007-02-17 no rewritten by KoSt
  2007-02-12 de translation of re-written part by ude
  2007-01-11 fr modified by Pierre ; 1rst part re-written
  2006-09-10 added norwegian translation by KoSt
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-paths">
  <title>
    <anchor id="gimp-concepts-paths" xreflabel="Paths"/>
    <phrase condition="tag-is-required">Paths</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Paths</primary>
    <secondary>Using</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Paths</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Paths are curves (known as Bézier-curves). To understand their concepts
    and mechanism, look at the glossary
    <link linkend="glossary-bezier-curve">Bézier-curve</link> or Wikipedia
    <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-bezier"/>.
    The Paths tool allows you to design complex shapes.
    When designing a shape, you first use the
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Paths</link> tool in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    to create a path. After that you usually stroke or fill the path.
  </para>
  <para>
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, the term <quote>Stroke path</quote> means to
    apply a specific style to the path (color, width, pattern, etc).
  </para>
  <para>
    A path can be used in several ways:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>You can convert a closed path to a selection.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Any path, open or closed, can be <emphasis>stroked</emphasis>;
        that is, painted on the image in a variety of ways.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A path can be <emphasis>filled</emphasis> with a color or pattern.
        If the path is not closed, it will try to figure out the shape and then
        fill it. However, this will not work if the path is a straight line.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <figure>
    <title>Illustration of four different paths</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/path-examples.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Four examples of GIMP paths: one closed and polygonal; one open and
          polygonal; one closed and curved; one with a mixture of straight and
          curved segments.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-creating">
    <title>Path Creation</title>
    <para>
      Start by drawing the outline for your path; the outline
      can be modified later (see the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Paths</link> tool).
      To start, select the Paths tool using one of the following methods:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Use
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Paths</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          from the menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Use the relevant icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-path.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon> in toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use the <keycap>B</keycap> keyboard shortcut.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      When the Paths tool is selected, the mouse cursor changes into a
      crosshair with a curve by default. The actual shape depends on your
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-input-devices">mouse pointer mode setting</link>.
      Make sure that the Paths <guilabel>Edit Mode</guilabel> in
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Tool Options</link> is set to
      <guilabel>Design</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Left click in the image to create the first point of the path. Move
      the mouse to a new point and left click to create another
      point linked to the previous point. Although you can create as many
      points as you desire, you only need two points to learn about Paths.
    </para>
    <para>
      While adding points, the mouse cursor has a little <quote>+</quote>
      next to the curve, which indicates that clicking will add a new
      point.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the mouse cursor is close to one of the path points, the
      <quote>+</quote> changes into a cross with arrows; like the move tool.
      You can then move the existing path point.
    </para>
    <para>
      To close your path, go with the mouse on top of the point you want to
      connect to, and then click that point. When you are done designing
      your path, you can press <keycode>Enter</keycode>. This will turn the
      path into a Selection. You can also keep adding more points, or start
      changing the curves of the path.
    </para>
    <para>
      To edit the curves of your path, move the mouse cursor close to a line
      segment, left-click and drag the line segment. Two events occur.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The line segment bends and curves as it is pulled.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Each line segment has two start points and end points marked by
          little square rectangles, these are called handles.
          A <quote>direction line</quote> now projects from each start point
          for the line segment that was moved. This direction line usually has
          a different color than the lines of the path.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The curved line segment leaves an end point in the same direction that
      the <quote>direction line</quote> leaves the start point. The length of
      this line controls how far the line segment projects along the
      <quote>direction line</quote> before curving towards the other path point.
    </para>
    <para>
      The handle at the end of each <quote>direction line</quote> can be
      dragged to change the direction and length of the curve. The handles
      on the other end, where they connect to the path, can be used to move
      the position of that path point.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Appearance of a path while it is manipulated</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/path-with-anchors.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Appearance of a path while it is manipulated using the Paths tool.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The path is comprised of two components with both straight and curved
      segments. Black squares are anchor points, the open circle indicates
      the selected anchor, and the two open squares are the handles associated
      with the selected anchor.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-properties">
    <title>Path Properties</title>
    <para>
      Paths, like layers and channels, are components of an image. When an
      image is saved in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native XCF file format, any
      paths it has are saved with it. The list of paths in an image can be
      viewed and operated on using the
      <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths Dialog</link>.
      You can move a path from one image to another by copying and pasting
      using the pop-up menu in the Paths dialog, or by dragging an icon from
      the Paths dialog into the destination image window.
    </para>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> paths belong to a mathematical type called
      <quote>Bezier paths</quote>. What this means in practical terms is that
      they are defined by <emphasis>anchors</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>handles</emphasis>. <quote>Anchors</quote> are points the path
      goes through. <quote>Handles</quote> define the direction of a path when
      it enters or leaves an anchor point: each anchor point has two handles
      attached to it.
    </para>
    <para>
      Paths can be very complex. If you create them by hand using the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Paths</link> tool, they probably won't
      contain more than a few dozen anchor points and usually a lot less than
      that. However, if you create them by transforming a selection into a
      path, or by transforming text into a path, the result can easily contain
      hundreds or even thousands of anchor points.
    </para>
    <para>
      A path may contain multiple <emphasis>components</emphasis>. A
      <quote>component</quote> is a part of a path whose anchor points are all
      connected to each other by path segments. The ability to have multiple
      components in paths allows you to convert them into selections having
      multiple disconnected parts.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each component of a path can be either <emphasis>open</emphasis> or
      <emphasis>closed</emphasis>: <quote>closed</quote> means that the last
      anchor point is connected to the first anchor point.
      If you transform a path into a selection, any open components are
      automatically converted into closed components by connecting the last
      anchor point to the first anchor point with a straight line.
    </para>
    <para>
      Path segments can be either straight or curved. A path is called
      <quote>polygonal</quote> if all of its segments are straight.
      A new path segment is always created straight; the handles for the
      anchor points are directly on top of the anchor points, yielding
      handles of zero length, which produces straight-line segments.
      Drag a handle away from an anchor point to cause a segment
      to curve.
    </para>
    <para>
      One nice thing about paths is that they use very few resources,
      especially in comparison with images. Representing
      a path in RAM requires storing only the coordinates of its anchors and
      handles. Therefore, it is possible to have literally hundreds of paths in
      an image without causing any significant stress to your system. Even a
      path with thousands of segments consumes minimal resources in comparison
      to a typical layer or channel.
    </para>
    <para>
      Paths can be created and manipulated using the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Paths tool</link>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-and-selections">
    <title>Paths and Selections</title>
    <para>
      GIMP lets you transform the selection of an image into a path. It also
      lets you transform paths into selections. For information about the
      selection and how it works, see the
      <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Selection</link> section.
    </para>
    <para>
      When you transform a selection into a path, the path closely follows the
      <link linkend="glossary-marching-ants"><quote>marching ants</quote></link>.
      Now, the selection is a two-dimensional entity, but a path is a
      one-dimensional entity, so there is no way to transform the selection
      into a path without losing information. In fact, any information about
      partially selected areas (i.e., feathering) are lost when a
      selection is turned into a path. If the path is transformed back into a
      selection, the result is an all-or-none selection, similar to what is
      obtained by executing <link linkend="gimp-selection-sharpen">Sharpen</link>
      from the Select menu.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-transforming">
    <title>Transforming Paths</title>
    <para>
      Each of the <link linkend="gimp-tools-transform">Transform tools</link>
      (Rotate, Scale, Perspective, etc) can be set
      to act on a layer, selection, or path. Select the transform tool in the
      toolbox, then select
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-layer.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      layer,
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      selection, or
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-path.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      path for the
      <guilabel>Transform</guilabel> option in the tool's Tool Options
      dialog. This gives you a powerful set of
      methods for altering the shapes of paths without affecting other
      elements of the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      By default a Transform tool, when it is set to affect paths, acts only on
      the <emphasis>active path</emphasis> which is shown highlighted in the
      <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths Dialog</link>. You can make a
      transformation affect more than one path by selecting additional paths.
      Selecting multiple paths is done by using the mouse and
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> key, for adding a range of paths, or
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key, for adding or removing the clicked path.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-stroking">
    <title>Stroking a Path</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Stroking paths</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/path-stroking-examples.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The four paths from the top illustration, each stroked in a
            different way.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Paths do not alter the appearance of the image pixel data unless
      they are <emphasis>stroked</emphasis>, using
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Stroke Paths…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      from the main menu or the
      <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths Dialog</link> right-click menu,
      or the <quote>Stroke Path</quote> button in the Tool Options dialog for
      the <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Paths</link> tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      Choosing <quote>Stroke Path</quote> by any of these means brings up a
      dialog that allows you to control the way the stroking is done. You
      can choose from a wide variety of line styles, or you can stroke with
      any of the Paint tools, including unusual ones such as the Clone tool,
      Smudge tool, Eraser, etc.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The <guilabel>Stroke Path</guilabel> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <!--changed 2009-08-28: don't use 2 screenshots for the same dialog
              (OLD: images/dialogs/gimp-path-stroke.png)-->
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/edit/stroke-path.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
        <para>See <xref linkend="gimp-path-stroke"/> for more information.</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      You can further increase the range of stroking effects by stroking a
      path multiple times, or by using lines or brushes of different widths.
      The possibilities for getting interesting effects in this way are almost
      unlimited.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-and-text">
    <title>Paths and Text</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Text converted to a path</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/path-from-text.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Text converted to a path and then transformed using the
            Perspective tool.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/path-text-stroked.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The path shown above, stroked with a fuzzy brush and then
            gradient-mapped using the Gradient Map filter with the
            <quote>Yellow Contrast</quote> gradient.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      A text item created using the <link linkend="gimp-tool-text">Text</link>
      tool can be transformed into a path using the
      <link linkend="gimp-text-tool-text-to-path">Text to Path</link> command
      in the context menu of the Text tool. This can be useful for several
      purposes, including:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Stroking the path, which gives you many possibilities for fancy
          text.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          More importantly, transforming the text. Converting text into a
          path, then transforming the path, and finally either stroking the
          path or converting it to a selection and filling it, often leads to
          much higher-quality results than rendering the text as a layer and
          transforming the pixel data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      You can also wrap text along an existing path using the
      <link linkend="gimp-text-tool-text-along-path">Text along Path</link>
      command.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-paths-and-svg">
    <title>Paths and <acronym>SVG</acronym> files</title>
    <para>
      <acronym>SVG</acronym>, standing for <quote>Scalable Vector
      Graphics</quote>, is a popular file format for
      <emphasis>vector graphics</emphasis>, in which graphical elements are
      represented in a resolution-independent format, in contrast to
      <emphasis>raster graphics</emphasis>; in which graphical elements are
      represented as arrays of pixels. GIMP is mainly a raster graphics
      program, but paths are vector entities.
    </para>
    <para>
      Fortunately, paths are represented in <acronym>SVG</acronym> files in
      almost exactly the same way they are represented in GIMP. This
      compatibility makes it possible to store GIMP paths as
      <acronym>SVG</acronym> files without losing any information. You can
      access this capability in the
      <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths Dialog</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It also means that GIMP can create paths from
      <acronym>SVG</acronym> files saved in other programs, such as
      <application>Inkscape</application>,
      a popular open-source vector graphics application. This is nice
      because dedicated vector editing programs have much more powerful
      path-manipulation tools than GIMP does. You can import a path from an
      <acronym>SVG</acronym> file using the Paths dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <acronym>SVG</acronym>
      format handles many other graphical elements than just paths: among
      other things, it handles figures such as squares, rectangles, circles,
      ellipses, regular polygons, etc. GIMP cannot do anything with these
      entities, but it can load them as paths.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Creating paths is not the only thing GIMP can do with
        <acronym>SVG</acronym> files. It can also open
        <acronym>SVG</acronym> files as GIMP images, in the usual way.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
