<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-paths' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Paths</title>
  <title lang="cs">Cesty</title>
  <title lang='de'>Pfade</title>
  <title lang="fr">Chemins</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">路径</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="cs">obrázek</primary>
    <primary lang='de'>Bild</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Paths</secondary>
    <secondary lang="cs">cesty</secondary>
    <secondary lang='de'>Pfade</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Chemins</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">路径</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title lang='en'>Stroking a Path</title>
    <title lang='cs'>Vykreslení cesty</title>
    <title lang='de'>Pfade nachziehen</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Tracer un chemin</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">勾画路径</title>

    <figure>
      <title lang='en'>
         The four paths from the top illustration, each stroked in a
         different way.
      </title>
      <title lang='cs'>
         Čtyři cesty z horního obrázku, každá vykreslená jiným způsobem.
      </title>
      <title lang='de'>
        Vier Pfade mit unterschiedlichen Mustern und
        Strichkombinationen nachgezogen.
      </title>
      <title lang="fr">
        Les quatre chemins de l'illustration du haut, chacun «tracé» 
        différemment.
      </title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">
         用不同方式勾画的最上面图中四个路径。
      </title>
      <mediaobject lang="en;cs;de;fr;zh_CN">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/using/path-stroking-examples.png'
            format="PNG"/>
         </imageobject>

      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang='en'>
      Paths do not alter the appearance of the image pixel data unless
      they are <emphasis>stroked</emphasis>, using
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Stroke Path</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      from the image menu or the Paths dialog right-click menu, or the
      "Stroke Path" button in the Tool Options dialog for the Path
      tool.  
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Cesty neovlivňují vlastní pixely obrázku, pokud ovšem nejsou
      <emphasis>vykresleny</emphasis> volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Upravit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Vykreslit cestu</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      z nabídky obrázku nebo volbou <guimenuitem>Vykreslit cestu</guimenuitem>
      z kontextové nabídky dialogu Cesty nebo tlačítkem Vykreslit cestu
      v dialogu Volby nástrojů nástroje Cesty.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Pfade stellen, solang Sie nicht nachgezogen sind, Hilfslinien dar,
      die die Bilddaten selber nicht verändern. Pfade geben Sie mit
      folgendem Kommando ein Aussehen:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Pfad nachziehen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      Alternativ können Sie auch die <guilabel>Pfad
      nachziehen</guilabel> Schaltfläche in den Pfad Werkzeugdialog
      benutzen. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les chemins ne modifient pas les pixels de l'image jusqu'à ce 
      qu'ils soient «tracés» en choisissant
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Éditer</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tracer le chemin</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      dans le menu image, ou le menu local du Dialogue des chemins 
      obtenu par clic droit, ou le bouton «Tracer le chemin» dans le 
      dialogue d'options de l'outil de l'outil Chemin. 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      路径并不改变图像像素数据的显示，除非它们被<emphasis>勾画</emphasis>，在图像菜单或路径对话框的右键菜单中
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>编辑</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>勾画路径</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
     ，或路径工具的工具选项对话框中的“勾画路径”按钮。
    </para>
    
    <figure lang="en;de">
      <title lang='en'>
        The <guilabel>Stroke Path</guilabel> dialog.
      </title>
      <title lang='de'>
        Der Dialog um Pfade nachzuziehen.
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/gimp-path-stroke.png'
            format="PNG" 
            lang="en;de"
            />
         </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="tex">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/dialogs/gimp-path-stroke.png'
            format="PNG"
            width="10cm"
            scalefit="1"
            lang="en;de"
            />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para lang='en'>
      Choosing "Stroke Path" by any of these means brings up a dialog
      that allows you to control the way the stroking is done.  You
      can choose from a wide variety of line styles, or you can stroke
      with any of the Paint tools, including unusual ones such as the
      Clone tool, Smudge tool, Eraser, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Mit dem <guilabel>Pfad nachziehen</guilabel> Dialog können Sie das
      Aussehen des nachgezogenen Pfades bestimmen. Er bietet eine breite
      Auswahl an Stilen, Mustern sowie Werkzeugen um jegliche Art von
      Linieneffekten abzubilden.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Volba Vykreslit cestu, ať už provedená jakýmkoliv způsobem, otevře
      dialog, ve kterém je možno nastavit detailní parametry vykreslení.
      Lze vybírat z různých stylů čar, můžete cestu vykreslit kterýmkoliv
      kreslícím nástrojem, včetně neobvyklých, například Razítka, Gumy
      a dalších.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le fait de choisir «Tracer le chemin» d'une façon ou d'une autre 
      ouvre une fenêtre de dialogue qui vous permet de préciser la 
      manière dont le chemin est tracé. Vous avez le choix entre une 
      de styles de ligne, et vous pouvez tracer avec n'importe lequel 
      des outils de peinture, y compris ceux aussi sophistiqués que 
      les outils Cloner, Barbouiller, Gommer...
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      通过上面这些方式选择“勾画路径”都将开启一个可以控制勾画完成方式的对话框。您可以从大量的线形中选择，或使用任何涂画工具勾画，甚至包括那些不常用的如克隆工具，涂抹工具或橡皮等。
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      You can further increase the range of stroking effects by
      stroking a path multiple times, or by using lines or brushes of different
      widths.  The possibilities for getting interesting effects in
      this way are almost unlimited.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die nachgezogene Linie läßt sich verstärken, wenn Sie verschiedene
      Pinselgrößen benutzen oder den Pfad mehrmals nachziehen. Ihren
      Möglichkeiten um jedwede Art von Effekt zu erziehlen sind keine
      Grenzen gesetzt. Probieren Sie es selber aus.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Dalších efektů při vykreslování cest můžete dosáhnout několikanásobným
      vykreslením cesty různým typem čar či různě širokými štětci. Možnosti
      jsou v tomto směru v podstatě neomezené.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez augmenter encore plus la variété des effets de tracé 
      en repassant plusieurs fois, ou en utilisant des lignes ou des 
      brosses de taille différente. De cette façon, il est possible 
      d'obtenir de nombreux effets intéressants.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      您可以通过多次勾画路径，或使用不同宽度的线或画笔来增加勾画效果的范围，通过这些方式来增强效果的可能性几乎是无限的。
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title lang='en'>Transforming Paths</title>
    <title lang='cs'>Transformace cest</title>
    <title lang='de'>Pfade transformieren</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Transformer les chemins</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">转换路径</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      Each of the Transform tools (Rotate, Scale, Perspective, etc)
      can be set to act specifically on paths, using the "Affect:"
      option in the tool's Tool Options dialog.  This gives you a
      powerful set of methods for altering the shapes of paths without
      affecting other elements of the image.
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Každý transformační nástroj (Rotace, Škálování, Perspektiva atd.)
      lze nastavit, aby ovlivňoval cesty a jen cesty. Dosáhne se toho
      pomocí volby Ovlivnit v dialogu Volby nástrojů. Uživatel má tak
      široké možnosti úpravovat tvar cest, aniž by ovlivnil samotný obrázek.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Mit den <link
      linkend='gimp-tool-flip'>Transformationswerkzeugen</link> lassen
      sich nicht nur Ebenen oder Auswahlen transformieren, sondern auch
      Pfade. Gehen Sie in die Werkzeugeinstellungen einer der
      Transformationswerkzeuge und klicken Sie auf die <guilabel>Pfad
      transformieren</guilabel> Schaltfläche rechts neben
      <guilabel>Wirkt auf:</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Chaque outil de Transformation (Rotation, Changement d'échelle,
      Perspective, etc) peut être réglé pour agir spécifiquement sur 
      les chemins, grâce à l'option «Affecte:» dans le dialogue 
      d'Options de l'outil. Cela vous donne un puissant moyen d'action 
      sur la forme des chemins sans affecter les autres éléments de 
      l'image.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      每个变换工具(旋转，缩放和透视等)可以设置为对特别针对路径操作，使用其工具选项对话框的“影响：”选项，它提供许多改变路径形状的有效方法而不会影响图像的其它元素。
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      By default a Transform tool, when it is set to affect paths,
      only acts on a single path:  the <emphasis>active
      path</emphasis> for the image, which is shown highlighted in the
      Paths dialog.  You can make a transformation affect more than
      one path, and possibly other things as well, using the
      "transform lock" buttons in the Paths dialog.  Not only paths,
      but also layers and channels, can be transform-locked.  If you
      transform one element that is transform-locked, all others will
      be transformed in the same way.  So, for example, if you want to
      scale a layer and a path by the same amount, click the
      transform-lock buttons so that "chain" symbols appear next to
      the layer in the Layers dialog, and the path in the Paths
      dialog; then use the Scale tool on either the layer or the path,
      and the other will automatically follow.  
    </para>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Ve výchozím nastavení transformační nástroj, je-li nastaven pro
      transformaci cest, působí pouze na jednu jedinou cestu –
      <emphasis>aktivní cestu</emphasis> obrázku. Je to ta, která je
      v dialogu Cesty zvýrazněna. Pokud chcete, aby 
      for the image, which is shown highlighted in the
      Paths dialog.  You can make a transformation affect more than
      one path, and possibly other things as well, using the
      "transform lock" buttons in the Paths dialog.  Not only paths,
      but also layers and channels, can be transform-locked.  If you
      transform one element that is transform-locked, all others will
      be transformed in the same way.  So, for example, if you want to
      scale a layer and a path by the same amount, click the
      transform-lock buttons so that "chain" symbols appear next to
      the layer in the Layers dialog, and the path in the Paths
      dialog; then use the Scale tool on either the layer or the path,
      and the other will automatically follow.  
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Transformationswerkzeuge wirken standardmäßig nur auf einem Pfad,
      nämlich den <emphasis>aktiven</emphasis>. Transformationseffekte
      lassen sich aber nicht nur auf einen Pfad erziehlen. Um eine
      Transformation auf mehrere <link
      linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Pfade</link> anzuwenden, verketten Sie
      mehrere Pfade miteinander (symbolisiert durch eine Kette).
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Par défaut, quand un outil de transformation est réglé pour 
      affecter les chemins, il n'agit que sur un seul chemin, le 
      <emphasis>chemin actif</emphasis> de l'image, qui apparaît 
      surligné dans le Dialogue des Chemins. Vous pouvez faire qu'une 
      transformation affecte plus d'un chemin en utilisant les boutons 
      chaîne sur le bandeau de chaque chemin du Dialogue des Chemins.
      Ce ne sont pas seulement les chemins, mais aussi les calques et 
      les canaux qui peuvent être enchaînés et ainsi transformés de la 
      même façon. Vous pouvez ainsi, par exemple, changer la taille 
      dans les mêmes proportions pour un chemin et un calque en faisant 
      apparaître la chaîne pour le calque dans le Dialogue des Calques 
      et pour le chemin dans le Dialogue des Chemins.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当变换工具设置为影响路径时，其默认只对单个路径操作：即<emphasis>当前路径</emphasis>(在路径对话框中显示为高亮)，不过您可以使用路径对话框的“变换锁定”按钮让一个变换影响多个路径。不光是路径，图层和通道也能被变换锁定。如果对变换锁定中的一个元素变换，其它所有元素也会使用同样的方式变换。比如您想让一个图层和一个路径放大同样的倍数，可以点击变换锁定按钮，这样，“锁链”标志就会显示在图层对话框中的该图层旁边，也显示在路径对话框中的该路径旁边，然后对图层或路径中的一个使用缩放工具，另一个将自动被放大。
    </para>
 
  </sect2>


</sect1>
