<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-patterns' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">Patterns</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Patterns</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>pattern</emphasis> is an image, usually small, used
    for filling regions by <emphasis>tiling</emphasis>, that is, by
    placing copies of the pattern side by side like ceramic tiles.  A
    pattern is said to be <emphasis>tileable</emphasis> if copies of
    it can be adjoined left-edge-to-right-edge and
    top-edge-to-bottom-edge without creating obvious seams.  Not all
    useful patterns are tileable, but tileable patterns are nicest for
    many purposes.  (A <emphasis>texture</emphasis>, by the way, is
    the same thing as a pattern.)
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/patterns-usage.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
     <caption>
       <para lang='en'>
         Three ways of using the "Leopard" pattern:  bucket-filling a
         selection, painting with the Clone tool, and stroking an
         elliptical selection with the pattern.
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    In GIMP there are three main uses for patterns:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        With the <link linkend='gimp-tool-bucket-fill'>Bucket
        Fill</link> tool, you can choose to fill a region with a
        pattern instead of a solid color.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        With the <link linkend='gimp-tool-clone'>Clone</link> tool,
        you can paint using a pattern, with a wide variety of
        paintbrush shapes.  
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>
        When you <emphasis>stroke</emphasis> a path or selection, you
        can do it with a pattern instead of a solid color.  You can
        also use the Clone tool as your choice if you stroke the
        selection using a painting tool.
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    Note: Patterns do not need to be opaque.  If you fill or paint using a
    pattern with translucent or transparent areas, then the previous
    contents of the area will show through from behind it.  This is
    one of many ways of doing "overlays" in GIMP.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a few dozen
    patterns, which seem to have been chosen more or less randomly.
    You can also add new patterns, either ones you create yourself, or
    ones you download from the vast number available online.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP's <emphasis>current pattern</emphasis>, used in most
    pattern-related operations, is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the
    pattern symbol brings up the <link
    linkend='gimp-pattern-dialog'>Patterns dialog</link>, which allows
    you to select a different pattern.  You can also access the
    Patterns dialog by menu, or dock it so that it is present
    continuously. 
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    To add a new pattern to the collection, so that it shows up in the
    Patterns dialog, you 
    need to save it in a format GIMP can use, in a folder included in
    GIMP's pattern search path.  There are two file formats you can
    use for patterns:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>PAT</title>
        The <filename>.pat</filename> format is used only by GIMP, so
        you will not find patterns in this format unless they were
        created specifically for GIMP.  You can, however, convert any
        image into a <filename>.pat</filename> file by opening it in
        GIMP and then saving it using a file name ending in
        <filename>.pat</filename>. 
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <formalpara lang='en'>
        <title>PNG</title>
        New in GIMP 2.2 is the ability to use
        <filename>.png</filename> files as patterns.
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    To make a pattern available, you place it in one of the folders in
    GIMP's pattern search path. By default, the pattern search path
    includes two folders, the system <filename>patterns</filename>
    folder, which you should not use or alter, and the
    <filename>patterns</filename> folder inside your personal GIMP
    directory.  You can add new folders to the pattern search path
    using the <link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Pattern
    Folders</link> page of the Preferences dialog.  Any PAT or PNG
    file included in a folder in the pattern search path will show up
    in the Patterns dialog the next time you start GIMP.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    There are countless ways of creating interesting patterns in GIMP,
    using the wide variety of available tools and filters --
    particularly the rendering filters.  You can find tutorials for
    this in mny locations, including the <ulink
    url='www.gimp.org'>Gimp home page</ulink>.  Some of the filters
    have options that allow you to make their results tileable.  Also,
    the <link linkend='script-fu-tile-blur'>Tileable Blur</link>
    filter allows you to blend the edges of an image in order to make
    it more smoothly tileable.
  </para> 

</sect2>
