<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-04-06 Mr.Dust : reviewed and added 'ko'
  2007-02-25 ude: de translation of "printing your photos"
  2007-02-10 Pierre : fr modified &  ; para "printing your photos"  added in fr & en
  2006-12-10 lexa: added de translation provided by ude
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-photography">
  <title>Working with Digital Camera Photos</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Photography</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-photography-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      One of the most common uses of GIMP is to fix digital camera images
      that for some reason are less than perfect. Maybe the image is
      overexposed or underexposed; maybe rotated a bit; maybe out of focus:
      these are all common problems for which GIMP has good tools. The purpose
      of this chapter is to give you an overview of those tools and the
      situations in which they are useful. You will not find detailed
      tutorials here: in most cases it is easier to learn how to use the tools
      by experimenting with them than by reading about them. (Also, each tool
      is described more thoroughly in the Help section devoted to it.) You
      will also not find anything in this chapter about the multitude of
      "special effects" that you can apply to an image using GIMP. You should
      be familiar with basic GIMP concepts before reading this chapter, but
      you certainly don't need to be an expert–if you are, you probably know
      most of this anyway. And don't hesitate to experiment: GIMP's powerful
      "undo" system allows you to recover from almost any mistake with a
      simple <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most commonly the things that you want to do to clean up an imperfect
      photo are of four types: improving the composition; improving the
      colors; improving the sharpness; and removing artifacts or other
      undesirable elements of the image.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-photography-improving">
    <title>Improving Composition</title>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-rotating">
      <title>Rotating an Image</title>
      <para>
        It is easy, when taking a picture, to hold the camera not quite
        perfectly vertical, resulting in a picture where things are
        tilted at an angle.  In GIMP, the way to fix this is to use the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-rotate">Rotate</link> tool.
        Activate this by clicking its icon
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-rotate.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        in the Toolbox, or by pressing the
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> while
        inside the image. Make sure the Tool Options are visible, and at
        the top, make sure for <quote>Transform:</quote> that the left
        button (<quote>Transform Layer</quote>) is selected.  If you then
        click the mouse inside the image and drag it, you will see the image
        rotate as you drag. When the image looks right, click
        <guibutton>Rotate</guibutton> or press <keycap>Enter</keycap>, and
        the image will be rotated.
      </para>
      <para>
        Now as a matter of fact, it isn't so easy to get things right by this
        method: you often find that things are better but not quite perfect.
        One solution is to rotate a bit more, but there is a disadvantage to
        that approach. Each time you rotate an image, because the rotated
        pixels don't line up precisely with the original pixels, the image
        inevitably gets blurred a little bit. For a single rotation, the
        amount of blurring is quite small, but two rotations cause twice as
        much blurring as one, and there is no reason to blur things more than
        you have to. A better alternative is to undo the rotation and then do
        another, adjusting the angle.
      </para>
      <para>
        Fortunately, GIMP provides another way of doing it that is
        considerably easier to use: in the Rotate Tool Options, for the
        Transform Direction you can select "Corrective (Backward)". When you
        do this, instead of rotating the image to compensate for the error, you
        can rotate its frame to <emphasis>line up</emphasis>
        with the error. If this seems confusing, try it and you will see that
        it is quite straightforward.
      </para>
      <para>
        After you have rotated an image, there will be unpleasant triangular
        "holes" at the corners. One way to fix them is to create a background
        that fills the holes with some unobtrusive or neutral color, but
        usually a better solution is to crop the image. The greater the
        rotation, the more cropping is required, so it is best to get the
        camera aligned as well as possible when you take the picture in the
        first place.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-cropping">
      <title>Cropping</title>
      <para>
        When you take a picture with a digital camera, you have some control
        over what gets included in the image but often not as much as you
        would like: the result is images that could benefit from trimming.
        Beyond this, it is often possible to enhance the impact of an image by
        trimming it so that the most important elements are placed at key
        points. A rule of thumb, not always to be followed but good to keep in
        mind, is the <quote>rule of thirds</quote>,
        which says that maximum impact is obtained by placing the center of
        interest one-third of the way across the image, both widthwise and
        heightwise.
      </para>
      <para>
        To crop an image, activate the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-crop">Crop</link>
        tool in the Toolbox, or by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
        <keycap>C</keycap></keycombo> while inside the image. With the tool active,
        clicking and dragging in the image will sweep out a crop rectangle.
        When everything is perfect, hit <keycap>Enter</keycap>. Note: if
        <guibutton>Delete cropped pixels</guibutton> in Crop Tool Options is
        disabled, the cropped part will not be removed from the image, only
        the visible image area will be adjusted.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-photography-colors">
    <title>Improving Colors</title>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-automatic">
      <title>Automated Tools</title>
      <para>
        In spite of sophisticated exposure-control systems, pictures taken
        with digital cameras often come out over- or under-exposed, or with
        color casts due to imperfections in lighting. GIMP gives you a variety
        of tools to correct colors in an image, ranging to automated tools
        that run with a simple button-click to highly sophisticated tools that
        give you many parameters of control. We will start with the simplest
        first.
      </para>
      <para>
        GIMP gives you several automated color correction
        tools. Unfortunately they don't usually give you quite the results
        you are looking for, but they only take a moment to try out, and if
        nothing else they often give you an idea of some of the
        possibilities inherent in the image.  Except for "Auto Levels", you
        can find these tools by following the menu path
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        </menuchoice>
        in the main menu.
      </para>
      <para>Here they are, with a few words about each:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guimenuitem>Equalize</guimenuitem>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is a very powerful adjustment that tries to spread the
              colors in the image evenly across the range of possible
              intensities. In some cases the effect is amazing, bringing out
              contrasts that are very difficult to get in any other way; but
              more commonly, it just makes the image look weird. Oh well, it
              only takes a moment to try.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guimenuitem>White balance</guimenuitem>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This may enhance images with poor white or black by
              removing little used colors and stretch the remaining
              range as much as possible.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guimenuitem>Stretch Contrast</guimenuitem>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is useful for underexposed images: it adjusts the whole image
              until the brightest point is right at the saturation limit, and
              the darkest point is black. The downside is that the amount of
              brightening is determined entirely by the lightest and darkest
              points in the image, so even one single white pixel and/or one
              single black pixel will make normalization ineffective.
              It operates on the red, green, and blue channels independently.
              It often has the useful effect of reducing color casts.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guimenuitem>Stretch Contrast HSV</guimenuitem>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Does the same as Stretch Contrast but works in HSV color
              space, rather than RGB color space. It preserves the Hue.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guimenuitem>Color Enhance</guimenuitem>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para><!--changed 2008-01-29-->
              This command increases the saturation range of the colors in the
              layer, without altering brightness or hue. So this command does
              not work on grayscale images.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guimenuitem>Auto Levels</guimenuitem>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is done by selecting
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Levels…</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>
              in the main menu,
              and then pressing the <guibutton>Auto Input Levels</guibutton> button near
              the center of the dialog. You will see a preview of the result;
              you must press <guibutton>Okay</guibutton> for it to take
              effect. Pressing <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> instead will
              cause your image to revert to its previous state.
            </para>
            <para>
              If you can find a point in the image that ought to be perfect
              white, and a second point that ought to be perfect black, then
              you can use the Levels tool to do a semi-automatic adjustment
              that will often do a good job of fixing both brightness and
              colors throughout the image. First, bring up the Levels tool as
              previously described. Now, look down near the bottom of the
              Levels dialog for three buttons with symbols on them that look
              like eye-droppers (at least, that is what they are supposed to
              look like). The one on the left, if you mouse over it, shows its
              function to be <quote>Pick Black Point</quote>.
              Click on this, then click on a point in the image that ought
              to be black–really truly perfectly black, not just sort of
              dark–and watch the image change. Next, click on the rightmost of
              the three buttons ( <quote>Pick White Point</quote>
              ), and then click a point in the image that ought to be white,
              and once more watch the image change. If you are happy with the
              result, click the <guibutton>Okay</guibutton> button otherwise
              <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        Those are the automated color adjustments: if you find that none of
        them quite does the job for you, it is time to try one of the
        interactive color tools. All of these, except one, can be accessed via
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Colors</guimenu><guimenuitem>Auto</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> in the main menu.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-exposure">
      <title>Exposure Problems</title>
      <para>
        The simplest tool to use is the <link linkend="gimp-tool-brightness-contrast">Brightness/Contrast</link>
        tool.  It is also the least powerful, but in many cases it does
        everything you need. This tool is often useful for images that are
        overexposed or underexposed; it is not useful for correcting color
        casts.  The tool gives you two sliders to adjust, for
        <quote>Brightness</quote> and <quote>Contrast</quote>.  If you have
        the option <quote>Preview</quote> checked (and almost certainly you
        should), you will see any adjustments you make reflected in the
        image. When you are happy with the results, press
        <guibutton>Okay</guibutton> and they will take effect.  If you
        can't get results that you are happy with, press
        <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> and the image will revert to its
        previous state.
      </para>
      <para>
        A more sophisticated, and only slightly more difficult, way of
        correcting exposure problems is to use the Levels tool.  The
        dialog for this tool looks very complicated, but for the basic
        usage we have in mind here, the only part you need to deal
        with is the <quote>Input Levels</quote> area, specifically the three
        triangular sliders that appear below the histogram.  We refer
        you to the <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels Tool Help</link>
        for instructions;
        but actually the easiest way to learn how to use it is to
        experiment by moving the three sliders around, and watching
        how the image is affected.  (Make sure that <quote>Preview</quote> is
        checked at the bottom of the dialog.)
      </para>
      <para>
        A very powerful way of correcting exposure problems is to use the
        <emphasis>Curves</emphasis>
        tool. This tool allows you to click and drag control points on a
        curve, in order to create a function mapping input brightness levels
        to output brightness levels. The Curves tool can replicate any effect
        you can achieve with Brightness/Contrast or the Levels tool, so it is
        more powerful than either of them. Once again, we refer you to the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-curves">Curves Tool Help</link>
        for detailed instructions, but the easiest way to learn how to use it
        is by experimenting.
      </para>
      <para>
        The most powerful approach to adjusting brightness and contrast across
        an image, for more expert GIMP users, is to create a new layer above
        the one you are working on, and then in the Layers dialog set the Mode
        for the upper layer to <quote>Multiply</quote>.
        The new layer then serves as a <quote>gain control</quote>
        layer for the layer below it, with white yielding maximum gain and
        black yielding a gain of zero. Thus, by painting on the new layer, you
        can selectively adjust the gain for each area of the image, giving you
        very fine control. You should try to paint only with smooth gradients,
        because sudden changes in gain will give rise to spurious edges in the
        result. Paint only using shades of gray, not colors, unless you want
        to produce color shifts in the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        Actually, <quote>Multiply</quote> is not the only mode that is useful
        for gain control.  In fact, <quote>Multiply</quote> mode can only
        darken parts of an image, never lighten them, so it is only useful
        where some parts of an image are overexposed.  Using
        <quote>Divide</quote> mode has the opposite effect:  it can brighten
        areas of an image but not darken them.  Here is a trick that is often
        useful for bringing out the maximum amount of detail across all areas
        of an image:
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Duplicate the layer (producing a new layer above it).
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Desaturate the new layer.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Apply a Gaussian blur to the result, with a large radius (100 or
            more).
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Set Mode in the Layers dialog to Divide.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Control the amount of correction by adjusting opacity in the
            Layers dialog, or by using Brightness/Contrast, Levels, or Curves
            tools on the new layer.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            When you are happy with the result, you can use
            <guibutton>Merge Down</guibutton>
            to combine the control layer and the original layer into a single
            layer.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <para>
        In addition to <quote>Multiply</quote> and <quote>Divide</quote>, you
        may every so often get useful effects with other layer combination
        modes, such as <quote>Dodge</quote>, <quote>Burn</quote>, or
        <quote>Soft Light</quote>.  It is all too easy, though,
        once you start playing with these things, to look away from
        the computer for a moment and suddenly find that you have just
        spent an hour twiddling parameters.  Be warned: the more
        options you have, the harder it is to make a decision.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-hue-saturation">
      <title>Adjusting Hue and Saturation</title>
      <para>
        In our experience, if your image has a color cast—too much red, too
        much blue, etc—the easiest way to correct it is to use the Levels
        tool, adjusting levels individually on the red, green, and blue
        channels. If this doesn't work for you, it might be worth your while
        to try the Color Balance tool or the Curves tool, but these are much
        more difficult to use effectively. (They are very good for creating
        certain types of special effects, though.)
      </para>
      <para>
        Sometimes it is hard to tell whether you have adjusted colors
        adequately. A good, objective technique is to find a point in the
        image that you know should be either white or a shade of gray.
        Activate the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link>
        tool (the eyedropper symbol in the Toolbox), and
        <keycap>Shift</keycap>-click on the aforesaid point: this brings up
        the Color Picker dialog. If the colors are correctly adjusted, then the
        red, green, and blue components of the reported color should all be
        equal; if not, then you should see what sort of adjustment you need to
        make. This technique, when well used, allows even color-blind people
        to color-correct an image.
      </para>
      <para>
        If your image is washed out—which can easily happen when you take
        pictures in bright light—try the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-hue-saturation">Hue/Saturation</link>
        tool, which gives you three sliders to manipulate, for Hue, Lightness,
        and Saturation. Raising the saturation will probably make the image
        look better. In some cases it is useful to adjust the lightness at the
        same time. ( <quote>Lightness</quote> here is similar to
        <quote>Brightness</quote>
        in the Brightness/Contrast tool, except that they are formed from
        different combinations of the red, green, and blue channels.) The
        Hue/Saturation tool gives you the option of adjusting restricted
        subranges of colors (using the buttons at the top of the dialog), but
        if you want to get natural-looking colors, in most cases you should
        avoid doing this.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <para>
          Even if an image does not seemed washed out, often you can increase
          its impact by pushing up the saturation a bit. Veterans of the film
          era sometimes call this trick <quote>Fujifying</quote>,
          after Fujichrome film, which is notorious for producing highly
          saturated prints.
        </para>
      </tip>
      <para>
        When you take pictures in low light conditions, in some cases you have
        the opposite problem: too much saturation. In this case too the
        Hue/Saturation tool is a good one to use, only by reducing the
        saturation instead of increasing it.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-photography-sharpness">
    <title>Adjusting Sharpness</title>
    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-unblurring">
      <title>Unblurring</title>
      <para>
        If the focus on the camera is not set perfectly, or the camera is
        moving when the picture is taken, the result is a blurred image. If
        there is a lot of blurring, you probably won't be able to do much
        about it with any technique, but if there is only a moderate amount,
        you should be able to improve the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        The most generally useful technique for sharpening a fuzzy image is
        called the <link linkend="gimp-filter-unsharp-mask">Sharpen (Unsharp
        Mask)</link>.
        In spite of the rather confusing name, which derives from its
        origins as a technique used by film developers, its result is to make
        the image sharper, not <quote>unsharp</quote>.
        It is a plug-in, and you can access it via <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Enhance</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sharpen (Unsharp Mask)…</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> in the main menu. There are two parameters,
        <quote>Radius</quote> and <quote>Amount</quote>.
        The default values often work pretty well, so you should try them
        first. Increasing either the radius or the amount increases the
        strength of the effect. Don't get carried away, though: if you make
        the unsharp mask too strong, it will amplify noise in the image and
        also give rise to visible artifacts where there are sharp edges.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <para>
          Sometimes using Sharpen (Unsharp Mask) can cause color distortion
          where there
          are strong contrasts in an image. When this happens, you can often
          get better results by decomposing the image into separate
          Hue-Saturation-Value (HSV) layers, and running Sharpen (Unsharp Mask)
          on the Value layer only, then recomposing. This works because the
          human eye has much finer resolution for brightness than for color. See
          the sections on
          <link linkend="plug-in-decompose">Decompose</link> and
          <link linkend="plug-in-compose">Compose</link> for more information.
        </para>
      </tip>

      <para>
        In some situations, you may be able to get useful results by
        selectively sharpening specific parts of an image using the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-convolve">Blur/Sharpen</link>
        tool from the Toolbox, in "Sharpen" mode. This allows you to increase
        the sharpness in areas by painting over them with any paintbrush. You
        should be restrained about this, though, or the results will not look
        very natural: sharpening increases the apparent sharpness of edges in
        the image, but also amplifies noise.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-graininess">
      <title>Reducing Graininess</title>
      <para>
        When you take pictures in low-light conditions or with a very fast
        exposure time, the camera does not get enough data to make good
        estimates of the true color at each pixel, and consequently the
        resulting image looks grainy. You can <quote>smooth out</quote>
        the graininess by blurring the image, but then you will also lose
        sharpness. There are a couple of approaches that may give better
        results. Probably the best, if the graininess is not too bad, is to
        use the filter called
        <link linkend="gimp-filter-gaussian-blur-selective">Selective
        Gaussian Blur</link>, setting the blurring radius to 1 or 2 pixels.
        The other approach is to use the
        <link linkend="plug-in-despeckle">Despeckle</link> filter. This
        has a nice preview, so you can play with the settings and try to
        find some that give good results. When graininess is really bad,
        though, it is often very difficult to fix by anything except
        heroic measures (i.e., retouching with paint tools).
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-softening">
      <title>Softening</title>
      <para>
        Every so often you have the opposite problem: an image is
        <emphasis>too</emphasis>
        crisp. The solution is to blur it a bit: fortunately blurring an image
        is much easier than sharpening it. Since you probably don't want to
        blur it very much, the simplest method is to use one of the
        <quote>Blur</quote> filters, accessed via <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu><guisubmenu>Blur</guisubmenu>
        </menuchoice> from the main menu. This
        will soften the focus of the image a little bit. If you want more
        softening, just repeat until you get the result you desire.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-photography-retouching">
    <title>Removing Unwanted Objects from an Image</title>
    <para>
      There are two kinds of objects you might want to remove from an image:
      first, artifacts caused by junk such as dust or hair on the lens;
      second, things that were really present but impair the quality of the
      image, such as a telephone wire running across the edge of a beautiful
      mountain landscape.
    </para>
    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-despeckling">
      <title>Despeckling</title>
      <para>
        A good tool for removing dust and other types of lens grunge is the
        <link linkend="plug-in-despeckle">Despeckle</link>
        filter, accessed via <menuchoice><guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Enhance</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Despeckle…</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the main menu.
        Very important: to use this filter effectively, you must begin by
        making a small selection containing the artifact and a small area
        around it. The selection must be small enough so that the artifact
        pixels are statistically distinguishable from the other pixels inside
        the selection. If you try to run despeckle on the whole image, you
        will hardly ever get anything useful. Once you have created a
        reasonable selection, activate Despeckle, and watch the preview as you
        adjust the parameters. If you are lucky, you will be able to find a
        setting that removes the junk while minimally affecting the area
        around it. The more the junk stands out from the area around it, the
        better your results are likely to be. If it isn't working for you, it
        might be worthwhile to cancel the filter, create a different
        selection, and then try again.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you have more than one artifact in the image, it is necessary to
        use Despeckle on each individually.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-garbage">
      <title>Garbage Removal</title>
      <para>
        The most useful method for removing unwanted <quote>clutter</quote>
        from an image is the <link linkend="gimp-tool-clone">Clone</link>
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-clone.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        tool, which allows you to paint over one part of an image using pixel
        data taken from another part (or even from a different image). The
        trick to using the clone tool effectively is to be able to find a
        different part of the image that can be used to
        <quote>copy over</quote>
        the unwanted part: if the area surrounding the unwanted object is very
        different from the rest of the image, you won't have much luck. For
        example, if you have a lovely beach scene, with a nasty human walking
        across the beach who you would like to teleport away, you will
        probably be able to find an empty part of the beach that looks similar
        to the part he is walking across, and use it to clone over him. It is
        quite astonishing how natural the results can look when this technique
        works well.
      </para>
      <para>
        Consult the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-clone">Clone Tool Help</link>
        for more detailed instructions. Cloning is as much an art as a
        science, and the more you practice at it, the better you will get. At
        first it may seem impossible to produce anything except ugly blotches,
        but persistence will pay off.
      </para>
      <para>
        Another tool looking very much as the clone tool, but smarter, is the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-heal">healing tool</link> which also takes
        the area around the destination into account when cloning. A typical
        usage is removal of wrinkles and other minor errors in images.
      </para>
      <para>
        In some cases you may be able to get good results by simply cutting
        out the offending object from the image, and then using a plug-in
        called <quote>Resynthesizer</quote>
        to fill in the void. This plug-in is not included with the main GIMP
        distribution, but it can be obtained from the author's web site
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-plugin-resynthesizer"/>.
        As with many things, your mileage may vary.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-red-eye">
      <title>Removing Red-eye</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Red-eyes</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        When you take a flash picture of somebody who is looking directly
        toward the camera, the iris of the eye can bounce the light of the
        flash back toward the camera in such a way as to make the eye appear
        bright red: this effect is called <quote>red eye</quote>,
        and looks very bizarre. Many modern cameras have special flash modes
        that minimize red-eye, but they only work if you use them, and even
        then they don't always work perfectly. Interestingly, the same effect
        occurs with animals, but the eyes may show up as other colors, such as
        green.
      </para>
      <para>
        GIMP provides a special <link linkend="gimp-filter-red-eye-removal">remove red eye</link> filter.
        Make a selection with one of the selection tools of the red part of
        the eye and then choose the <quote>Red Eye Removal</quote> filter.
        You may have to fiddle around a bit with the threshold slider to
        get the right color.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-photography-saving">
    <title>Saving Your Results</title>
    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-files">
      <title>Files</title>
      <para>
        What file format should you use to save the results of your work, and
        should you resize it? The answers depend on what you intend to use the
        image for.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you intend to open the image in GIMP again for further work,
            you should save it in GIMP's native XCF format (i. e., name it
            something.xcf), because this is the only format that guarantees
            that none of the information in the image is lost.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you intend to print the image on paper, you should avoid
            shrinking the image, except by cropping it. The reason is that
            printers are capable of achieving much higher resolutions than
            video monitors &mdash; 600 to 1400 dpi (<quote>dots per
            inch</quote>, the physical density) for typical printers, as
            compared to 72 to 100 pixels per inch for monitors. A
            3000×5000-pixel image looks huge on a monitor, but it
            only comes to about 5 inches by 8 inches on paper at 600 ppi.
            There is usually no good reason to <emphasis>expand</emphasis> the
            image either: you can't increase the true resolution that way, and
            it can always be scaled up at the time it is printed. As for the
            file format, it will usually be fine to use JPEG at a quality
            level of 75 to 85. In rare cases, where there are large swaths of
            nearly uniform color, you may need to set the quality level even
            higher or use a lossless format such as TIFF instead.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you intend to display the image on screen or project it with a
            video projector, bear in mind the highest screen resolutions for
            most commonly available systems. There is nothing to gain by
            keeping the image much larger than these resolutions. For this
            purpose, the JPEG format is almost always a good choice.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you want to put the image on a web page or send it by email, it
            is a good idea to make every effort to keep the file size as small
            as possible. First, scale the image down to the smallest size that
            makes it possible to see the relevant details (bear in mind that
            other people may be using different sized monitors and/or
            different monitor resolution settings). Second, export the image as
            a JPEG file. In the JPEG export dialog, check the option to
            <quote>Preview in image window</quote>,
            and then adjust the Quality slider to the lowest level that
            gives you acceptable image quality. (You will see in the image the
            effects of each change.) Make sure that the image is zoomed at 1:1
            while you do this, so you are not misled by the effects of
            zooming.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        See the <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">File Formats</link>
        section for more information.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-printing">
      <title>Printing Your Photos</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Printing</primary>
        <secondary>Printing your photos</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        You print photos from the main menu through
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Print…</guisubmenu>
        </menuchoice>.
        However it is very useful to keep in mind some elementary concepts
        to prevent some unpleasant surprises when looking at the result, or
        to fix them if they occur. You must always remember:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            that image displayed on the screen is in RGB mode and printing
            will be in CMYK mode; consequently color feature you'll get on
            printed sheet will not be exactly what you was waiting for. That
            depends on the used corresponding chart. For the curious ones some
            adding explanations can be got through a click on these useful
            Wikipedia links:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                ICC-Profile <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-icc"/>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                CMYK <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-cmyk"/>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Gamut <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gamut"/>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            that a screen resolution is roughly within a range from 75 up to
            100 dpi; a printer resolution is about 10x higher (or more) than a
            screen one; printed image size depends on available pixels and
            resolution; so actual printed size doesn't correspond inevitably
            to what is displayed on screen nor available sheet size.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Consequently, before any printing, go to
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Print Size…</guisubmenu>
        </menuchoice>
        and choose a convenient output size in the
        <quote>Print Size</quote> box adjusting either sizes or resolution.
        The
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-vchain.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        symbol shows that the both values are linked. You can dissociate x
        and y resolution by clicking on that symbol, but it is risky. Only
        some printers support different X vs. Y resolutions.
      </para>
      <para>
        Last recommendation: think of checking your margins as well as
        centering. It would be a pity if a too large margin cuts off some
        part of your image or if an inappropriate centering damages your work
        especially if you use a special photo paper.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-using-photography-exif">
      <title>EXIF Data</title>
      <para>
        Digital cameras, when you take a picture, add information to your
        image about the camera settings and the circumstances under
        which the picture was taken. This so-called metadata is included in
        most image files in a structured format called EXIF.
      </para>
      <para>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> stores all metadata it can handle when loading
        an image. When exporting your image, you can select which types of
        metadata you want included. Not all file formats support all types of
        metadata.
        For JPEG files, EXIF metadata will be included if enabled in the
        export dialog. Besides values that directly depend on changes you
        made to your image (e.g. dimensions) most values will be saved
        unchanged from when the image was loaded.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can view the contents of the EXIF, XMP and IPTC metadata, by
        using the <link linkend="plug-in-metadata-viewer">metadata-viewer</link>
        plug-in. You can access it via <menuchoice><guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Metadata</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>View Metadata</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the main menu.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
