<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--section history
  2006-09-10: added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-22: added Korean Translation by Dust
  2006-06-22: changes in en;fr by j.h
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-quickmask" lang="en;cs;de;fr;sv;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="fr;ko;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-22</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-22</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-10</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Using the Quickmask</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Používání rychlé masky</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Die Schnellmaske verwenden</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Utilisation du masque rapide</phrase>
    <phrase lang="sv">Hantering</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Uso della maschera veloce</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">퀵마스크 사용하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Å bruke snarmaske</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">用法</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Quickmask</primary>
    <secondary>Using the Quickmask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Schnellmaske</primary>
    <secondary>Die Schnellmaske verwenden</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Masque rapide</primary>
    <secondary>Utilisation du masque rapide</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Maschera veloce</primary>
    <secondary>Uso della maschera veloce</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>퀵마스크</primary>
    <secondary>퀵마스크 사용하기</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Snarmaske</primary>
    <secondary>Bruk</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para lang="en">Open an image or begin a new document;</para>
      <para lang="cs">Otevřete existující obrázek nebo nový dokument.</para>
      <para lang="de">
        Öffnen Sie ein Bild oder erstellen Sie ein neues Bild.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Ouvrir une image ou commencer un nouveau document;
      </para>
      <para lang="it">Aprire un'immagine o crearne una nuova;</para>
      <para lang="ko">이미지를 열거나 새 이미지를 만든다;</para>
      <para lang="no">Opna eit bilete eller begynn på eit nytt</para>
      <para lang="sv">Öppna en bild eller skapa en ny;</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">打开一个图像或新建图像；</para>
    </step>

    <step>
      <para lang="en">
        Activate the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the image
        window. If a selection is present the mask is initialized with the
        content of the selection;
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pomocí tlačítka v levém dolním rohu okna obrázku aktivujte rychlou
        masku. Pokud existuje výběr, maska bude vytvořena podle něj.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Aktivieren Sie die Schnellmaske mit dem Schalter links unten im
        Bildfenster. Wenn bereits eine Auswahl existiert, wird die Maske mit
        dem Inhalt dieser Auswahl initialisiert.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Activer le Masque Rapide en utilisant le bouton Masque rapide en bas à
        gauche de la fenêtre d'image. Si une sélection est présente, le masque
        est initialisé avec le contenu de la sélection;
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Attivare la maschera veloce usando il pulsante presente nella parte in
        basso a sinistra della finestra immagine. Se è presente una selezione,
        la maschera viene inizializzata con il contenuto della selezione;
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이미지창의 좌하단에 있는 버튼을 이용해 퀵마스크를 활성화시킨다. 기존의 마스크에 이미 선택이 있다면 그것역시 선택의 일부로
        초기화된다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Aktiver snarmaska ved å klikke på knappen nede til venstre i
        biletvindauget. Dersom det finst ei markering i biletet, vil maska
        bli avgrensa av denne markeringa.
      </para>
      <para lang="sv">
        Aktivera snabbmask genom att klicka på ikonen för snabbmask i
        bildfönstret. Om det redan finns en markering kommer snabbmask att
        följa denna och inte lägga någon mask i markeringen;
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        点击图像窗口中左下角有红色外框的按钮来开启快速蒙板。如果已经有选区， 蒙板将初始化为选区内容。
      </para>
    </step>

    <step>
      <para lang="en">
        Choose any drawing tool. Paint on the Quick Mask using black color to
        remove selected areas and white color to add selected areas. You can
        use grey colors to get partially selected areas.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can also use selection tools and fill these selections with the
        Bucket Fill tool. This does not destroy the Qmask selections!
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        Pomocí libovolného kreslícího nástroje a odstínů šedi můžete rychlou
        masku upravovat.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Wählen Sie ein Malwerkzeug. Malen Sie auf der Schnellmaske mit
        schwarzer Farbe, um ausgewählte Bereiche zu entfernen, mit weißer
        Farbe, um Bereiche auszuwählen. Mit grauen Farben können Sie
        teilweise ausgewählte Bereiche erstellen.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Sie können auch Auswahlwerkzeuge verwenden und diese Auswahlen mit
        dem <quote>Fülleimer</quote> füllen. Dadurch werden die Auswahlen
        der Schnellmaske nicht zerstört.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Choisissez et paramétrez un outil de dessin dans la boîte à outils
        puis utilisez cet outil pour dessiner sur le masque avec la peinture
        noire pour supprimer des plages sélectionnées, et la peinture blanche
        pour ajouter des plages sélectionnées. Vous pouvez utiliser des
        niveaux de gris pour créer des aires partiellement sélectionnées.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Scegliere uno strumento di disegno e usarlo con colori in scala di
        grigi sulla maschera veloce;
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        아무 그리기 도구나 선택해서 그린다. 검정색은 선택을 제거하고, 흰색은 선택을 추가하며, 회색 계열은 부분적으로 선택된 영역을
        만든다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        선택 도구를 사용해 선택을 하고, 채우기 도구로 칠을 할 수도 있는데, 이때의 선택은 퀵마스크의 선택에 영향을 주지 않는다.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Vel eitt av teiknereiskapa og mal med svart der du ønskjer å fjerna
        eit område og med kvitt for å legge til eit område. Bruk gråfarge
        for å markera eit område delvis.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Du kan også lage ei markering med eitt av markeringsverktøya og
        fylle denne med svart, kvitt eller grått med fyllverktøyet. Dette
        øydelegg ikkje snarmaskemarkeringane.
      </para>

      <para lang="sv">
        Välj ett verktyg för att måla och använd gråskaliga färger för
        snabbmask;
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">选取任何涂画工具，使用灰度色在快速蒙板上涂画。</para>
    </step>

    <step>
      <para lang="en">
        Toggle off the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the image
        window: the selection will be displayed with its marching ants.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pomocí tlačítka v levém dolním rohu okna obrázku masku opět vypněte.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Schalten Sie die Schnellmaske mit dem Schalter links unten aus. Die
        Auswahl wird nun mit ihren <quote>laufenden Ameisen</quote>
        dargestellt.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Désactiver le Masque Rapide en utilisant le bouton Masque rapide en
        bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image: la sélection apparaîtra avec ses
        pointillés mobiles
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Disabilitare la maschera veloce con il pulsante usato in precedenza
        per attivarla;
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이미지창의 왼쪽 아래 버튼을 눌러 퀵마스크를 해제하면 선택은 움직이는 점선으로 표시될 것이다.
      </para>
      <para lang="sv">
        Inaktivera snabbmask genom att klicka på samma ikon i bildfönstret.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Slå snarmaska av og på ved å bruke Snarmaskeknappen i nedre,
        venstre hjørnet i biletvindauget.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">用图像窗口左下角的按钮来关闭快速蒙板。</para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
</sect1>
