<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-script-fu'>
  <title lang="en">Using Script-Fu Scripts</title>
  <title lang="fr">Utiliser Gimp</title>
  <title lang="sv">Använda GIMP</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">使用 Script-Fu 脚本</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="sv">GIMP</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Script-fu</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">Script-Fu</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Script-Fu?</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">Script-Fu？</title>
    <para lang="en">
      Script-Fu is what the Windows world would call "macros" But
      Script-Fu is more powerful than that. Script-Fu is based on an
      interpreting language called Scheme, and works by using querying
      functions to the Gimp database. You can do all kinds of things
      with Script-Fu, but an ordinary Gimp user will probably use it
      for automating things that:  
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      Script-Fu 在 Windows 世界中叫做“宏”，不过 Script-Fu 比那个更强大。Script-Fu 是基于一个叫 Scheme 的解释语言，通过查询 Gimp 数据库的功能来工作。您可以使用 Script-Fu 干各种各样的事，不过一般的 Gimp 用户可能用它做些自动化的操作如：
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem><para>
        You want to do frequently.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Are really complicated to do, and hard to remember.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem><para>
        您经常做的。
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        确实是麻烦的和很难记住的。
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Remember that you can do a whole lot with Script-Fu. The
      scripts that come with Gimp can be quite useful, but they can
      also serve as models for learning Script-Fu, or at least as a
      framework and source of modification when you make your own
      script. Read the Script-Fu Tutorial in the next section
      if you want to learn more about how to make scripts. 
    </para>
    <para>
      We will describe some of the most useful scripts in this
      chapter, but we won't cover them all. There are simply too many
      scripts. Some of the scripts are also very simple and you will
      probably not need any documentation to be able to use them. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Script-Fu (a dialect of Scheme) isn't the only scripting
      language available for Gimp. But Script-Fu is the only scripting
      language that is installed by default. Other available scripting
      extensions are Perl and Tcl. You can download and install both
      extensions at the <ulink url='http://registry.gimp.org'>Gimp
      Plugin Registry</ulink>. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Installing Script-Fus</title>
    <para lang="en">
      One of the great things about Script-Fu is that you can share your
      script with all your Gimp friends. There are many scripts
      that come with Gimp by default, but there are also vast
      quantities of scripts that
      are available for download all around the Internet. 
    </para>
    <tip>
      If you have downloaded a script, copy or move your new script to
      your <filename>.gimp-2.0/scripts</filename> directory and do a
      refresh. The script will now appear in one of your menus. If you
      don't find it, look for it under the root file menu filters. If
      it doesn't appear at all, something was wrong with the script. 
    </tip>
    <para>
      Note that you can't use more than one Script-Fu dialog at a
      time, so don't open a script and one more after that. The last
      one will never be opened and displayed. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Do's and Don'ts</title>
    <para lang="en">
      A common error when you are dealing with Script-Fus is that you
      simply bring them up and press the OK button. When nothing
      happens, you probably think that the script is broken or buggy,
      but there is most likely nothing wrong with it. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Think again. Did you really read the information in the dialog,
      or did you just press the button? If you forgot an input the
      script needs, or if you gave it the wrong input, the script will
      fail. One of the most common errors is that the font specified
      in the script dialog hasn't been installed on your system. So
      please check the information in the dialog before blaming the
      script. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Different Kinds Of Script-Fus</title>
    <para lang="en">
      There are two kinds of Script-Fus -- standalone scripts and
      image-dependent scripts. You will find the standalone variants
      under 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type of Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> in the main toolbox menu, 
      and the image-dependent scripts are placed under 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type of Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> in the image menu.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Standalone Scripts</title>
    <para lang="en">
      We will not try to describe every script in depth. Most
      Script-Fus are very easy to understand and use. At the time of
      this writing, the following types are installed by default:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem><para>
        Patterns
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Web page themes
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Logos
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Buttons
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utils
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Make Brush
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Misc.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <variablelist lang="en">

    <varlistentry><term>Patterns</term>
      <listitem><para>
        You will find all kinds of pattern-generating scripts
        here. Generally, they are quite useful because you can add many
        arguments to your own patterns.
      </para>
      <para>
        We'll take a look at the Land script. In this script you have to
        set the image/pattern size, and specify what levels of random to
        use for your land creation. The colors used to generate the land
        map are taken from the currently selected gradient in the
        gradient editor. You must also supply values for the level of
        detail, land and sea height/depth and the scale. Scale refers to
        the scale of your map, just as in an ordinary road map, 1:10
        will be typed as 10. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Web Page Themes</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Here is clearly a practical use for scripts. By creating a
        script for making custom text, logos, buttons arrows, etc., for
        your web site, you will give them all the same style and
        shape. You will also be saving a lot of time, because you don't
        have to create every logo, text or button by hand. 
      </para>
      <para>
        You will find the Gimp.org theme under the Web page theme
        submenu. If you want to create your own theme, this script
        will serve as an excellent template that you can modify to
        create a theme for your web site. 
      </para>
      <para>
  	Most of the scripts are quite self-explanatory, but here are
  	some hints: 
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          Leave all strange characters like ' and " intact.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Make sure that the pattern specified in the script exists.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Padding refers to the amount of space around your text.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          A high value for bevel width gives the illusion of a higher button.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          If you type TRUE for "Press", the button will look pushed down.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Choose transparency if you don't want a solid background. If
          you choose a solid background, make sure it is the same
          color as the web page background. 
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Logos</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Here you will find all kinds of logo-generating scrips. This
        is nice, but use it with care, as people might recognize your
        logo as being made by a known Gimp script. You should rather
        regard it as a base that you can modify to fit your needs. The
        dialog for making a logo is more or less the same for all such
        scripts:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          In the Text String field, type your logo name, like Frozenriver.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          In the Font Size text field, type the size of your logo in pixels.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          In the Font text field, type the name of the font that you
          want to use for your logo. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          To choose the color of your logo, just click on the color
          button. This brings up a color dialog. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          If you look at the current command field, you can watch the
          script run. 
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Make Buttons</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Under this headline you'll find a script that makes beveled
        buttons. The script has a dozen parameters or so, and most of
        them are similar to those in the logo scripts. You can
        experiment with different settings to come up with a button you
        like. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Utils</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Under Utils you will find a small but nice script: the Fontmap
        script, which makes an image of your fonts. You will have to
        type the names of the fonts you want displayed in the Fonts text
        field. 
      </para>
      <para>
        The Custom gradient script creates an image of the current
        custom gradient in the gradient editor. This can be useful if
        you want to pick colors from a gradient as in a palette. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Misc.</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Under Misc. you'll find scripts that can be quite useful, but
      aren't suitable for the other submenus. An example is the Sphere
      script. You will have to set the radius in pixels to determine
      the sphere size. The lighting angle is where at the sphere you
      point the spotlight. This value also has an impact on the sphere
      shadow. If you don't want a shadow, you will have to type
      FALSE. The last thing you have to select is background color,
      and the color of your sphere. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Make Brush</term>
      <listitem><para>
        This script lets you make your own custom rectangular/circular
        brushes, with or without feathered (blurred) edges. The script
        will automatically store your brush in your 
        personal brush directory. You just have to press refresh in the
        Brush Selection dialog to use your newly created brush. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Image-Dependent Scripts</title>
    <para lang="en">
      These are scripts that perform operations on an existing
      image. In many ways they are like the plug-ins in the Filters
      menu. The following script groups are installed by default: 
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem><para>
        Decor
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Modify
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Animators
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Stencil Ops
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Alchemy
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Shadow
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Render
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utils
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Selection
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <variablelist lang="en">
      <varlistentry><term>Stencil Ops</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Here, you'll find two scripts: Carve-It and Chrome-It, which
          can render some truly nice artistic effects on grayscale
          images. 
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Drop Shadow</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Drop Shadow will cast a shadow behind your selected
          object. It has three important parameters. X and Y offset
          determine where the shadow will be placed in relation to the
          selected object. Offset is measured in pixels. High values
          make the shadow look like it's far away, and low values will
          make it look closer to the object. The blur value is also
          important, because a shadow that is cast far from the object
          has a higher blur level. 
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Perspective Shadow</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Perspective Shadow has a very important parameter: the
          perspective angle. If this angle is set to 0 or 180, there
          will be no shadow, because the script assumes that the object
          has no thickness. This also means that this script looks fine
          in certain angles, but unnatural in others. The other
          parameters are quite self-explanatory. You'll get more blur if
          the horizon is far away, and the shadow length is the length
          in relation to the selected object. 
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>  	
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
