<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- Section history:
  2007-10-02 Updated English and German parts of first sect2
             for 2.4 by rubikcube
  2007-01-22 modified Korean Translation by Dust
  2006-09-11 Added Norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-12 Added Korean Translation by Dust.
  2006-06-13 Added para about using arrow keys by j.h
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-selections" lang="de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no">
  <sect1info lang="en;es;de;fr;ko;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-07-15</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-18</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-06</date>
        <authorinitials>manuelq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-13</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-22</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-11</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="de">Auswahlen erstellen und benutzen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Creating and Using Selections</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Creación y uso de selecciones</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Créer et utiliser les Sélections</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Creazione e uso delle selezioni</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">선택 만들기와 사용하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Å lage og bruke markeringar</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selections</primary>
    <secondary>Using</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Selecciones</primary>
    <secondary>Uso</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélections</primary>
    <secondary>Utilisation</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Selezioni</primary>
    <secondary>Uso</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>선택</primary>
    <secondary>사용하기</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Markeringar</primary>
    <secondary>Bruk</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-selections-moving">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Auswahl verschieben</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Moving a Selection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Desplazamiento de la selección</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Déplacer une sélection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Spostamento selezioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">선택 이동하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å flytte ei markering</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Auswahl</primary>
      <secondary>Verschieben</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Move selection</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Sélection</primary>
      <secondary>Déplacer</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Durch Verschieben der Auswahl erscheint die Hintergrundebene
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Moving the Selection Reveals the Background Layer
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Al mover la selección se revela el color de la capa de fondo
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Le fait de déplacer une sélection révèle l'arrière-plan
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Lo spostamento delle selezioni scopre il livello di sfondo.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">
          선택한 부분을 움직이면 배경 레이어가 드러나 보입니다.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Når du flyttar ei markering blir bakgrunnslaget avdekka
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/select-move.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      After creating a rectangular, elliptic or free selection, or when you
      are using the Magic wand, you can click-and-drag to move the selection 
      and its contents, while the initial position remains empty.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      If you only want to move the selection border and not its contents, then
      press the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key and click-and-drag the selection.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Nachdem Sie eine rechteckige, elliptische oder freie Auswahl erstellt
      oder den Zauberstab benutzt haben, können Sie den Inhalt der Auswahl
      mit der Maus direkt verschieben. An der Stelle, von welcher die
      Auswahl wegbewegt wird, erscheint dann der Hintergrund.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Falls Sie nur den Rahmen der Auswahl, nicht aber deren Inhalt
      verschieben möchten, halten Sie beim Klicken und Verschieben die
      <keycap>Alt</keycap>-Taste gedrückt.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Luego de haber creado una selección, ya sea con la herramienta
      rectangular, elíptica, libre, o con la varita mágica, el puntero del
      ratón predeterminado cambia a la cruz para mover. Presinando el botón
      del ratón y arrastrándolo, se puede mover la selección y su contenido,
      dejando la región en que estaba alojada vacía.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Si lo desea mover la selección pero no su contenido, mantenga
      presionada la tecla <keycap>Alt</keycap> al hacer clic para
      mover la selección.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Après création d'une sélection rectangulaire, elliptique, à main levée,
      ou avec la Baguette magique, le pointeur de la souris a, par défaut,
      l'aspect de la croix de déplacement. Le cliquer-glisser simple permet
      alors déplacer la sélection et son contenu tout en laissant vide son
      emplacement initial.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Si vous voulez ne déplacer que le contour de la sélection
      sans déplacer son contenu, maintenez l'appui sur la touche
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> et cliquez-glissez la sélection.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Dopo la creazione di una selezione rettangolare, ellittica o libera o
      con lo strumento «bacchetta magica», la forma del puntatore del mouse
      cambia nella croce di spostamento (una croce formata da quattro frecce).
      Il successivo trascinamento della selezione permette di spostarla con
      tutto il suo contenuto, mentre nella posizione iniziale rimane un vuoto.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se si desidera spostare solo il bordo della selezione senza il suo
      contenuto, premere contemporaneamente il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap>
      durante il trascinamento.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      사각형이나 타원, 혹은 자유 선택이나 매직완드 등으로 선택을 만들면,
      마우스 커서가 이동 모양으로 바뀝니다. 그리고 클릭-드래그로 선택한
      영역을 이동시킬 수 있게 됩니다. 이때 이동된 영역이 있던 원래 자리는
      빈공간이 됩니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      만약 선택된 영역이 아닌 선택 자체만 이동시키려면 <keycap>Alt</keycap>
      키를 누르고 선택을 클릭-드래그를 합니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Etter at du har laga ei rektangulær eller elliptisk markering,
      eller du lagar ho på frihand eller ved hjelp av tryllestaven, vil
      musemarkøren til vanleg vise flyttsymbolet. Dette viser at du kan
      klikke og dra markeringa rundt i biletet. Den opphavlege posisjonen
      markeringa hadde blir tom.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dersom du heller vil flytte ramma for markeringa, utan å flytte
      innhaldet, held du nede <keycap>Alt</keycap>-tasten medan du flytter
      markeringa.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        Sometimes the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is used by the window
        manager and you move the image window instead of the selection.
        If this is the case, you have two possibilities:
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Es besteht die Möglichkeit, dass die <keycap>Alt</keycap>-Taste
        vom Fenster-Manager benutzt wird. Sollte das der Fall sein, gibt
        es zwei Möglichkeiten, die Sie probieren können:
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        A menudo la tecla <keycap>Alt</keycap> es utilizada por el
        administrador de ventanas y se termina moviendo la ventana de
        la imagen en vez de la selección.  Si es éste el caso, tiene
        dos opciones: puede presionar la tecla <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        junto con la tecla <keycap>Shift</keycap> o cambiar a la
        herramienta de Mover y variar la opción
        <quote>Afectar</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Il se peut que la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap> soit déjà utilisée par
        le système et que vous déplaciez alors l'ensemble de l'image au lieu
        de la sélection. Dans ce cas, sélectionnez l'outil Déplacement et
        changez l'option <quote>Affecte</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Alle volte il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> viene usato dal gestore
        delle finestre ed il risultato è di trascinare l'intera finestra
        invece della sola selezione. In questo caso è possibile premere
        insieme il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> e <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>,
        oppure selezionare lo strumento di spostamento e cambiare l'opzione
        <quote>Influenza</quote> in «Trasforma la selezione».
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        때때로 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 키는 윈도우 관리자에 의해 선택이 아닌
        이미지 창을 움직이는데 쓰이기도 합니다. 이럴 경우 두 가지 방법을
        이용할 수 있습니다.:
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dersom <keycap>Alt</keycap>-tasten er i bruk av vindaugebehandlaren,
        blir kanskje heile biletet flytt i staden for markeringa. Du kan
        då prøve eitt av desse to:
      </para>

      <orderedlist lang="en;de;ko;no">
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Select the move tool and change the 
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-transform-options">
              <quote>Affect</quote>
            </link>
            option
            <guiicon> 
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata 
                      fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-selection.png" 
                      format="PNG" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon> to affect the selection only.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie benutzen das
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-move">Verschiebewerkzeug</link>
            und setzen die Option
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-transform-options">
              Wirkt auf Auswahl
            </link>
            <guiicon> 
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata 
                      fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-selection.png" 
                      format="PNG" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            이동 도구를 선택하여 <quote>적용</quote> 옵션을 바꿔줍니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Klikk på <link 
            linkend="gimp-tool-move">flyttverktøyet</link> og prøv ei 
            anna innstilling for <quote>Verkar på</quote> i 
            verktøyinnstillingane.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <!-- Not sure about this item, the old content does not make
               sense anymore.  The new content (change WM behaviour)
               might be inappropriate sometimes. -->
          <para lang="en">
            Configure your window manager to use a different modifier key
            for moving windows.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie ändern die Einstellungen Ihres Fenster-Managers so, dass
            die <keycap>Alt</keycap>-Taste nicht mehr abgefangen wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            키나
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            키를 눌러 선택을 이동합니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Prøv å halde nede anten tastane
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            eller <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            medan du flytter markeringa.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </note>

    <para lang="en">
      To move a selection and its contents, keep the
      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo> keys
      pressed when starting to click-and-drag on the image. 
      For moving a selection without emptying its initial position, press
      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
      instead.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Moving a selection automatically creates a floating layer
      (floating selection). See <link
      linkend='glossary-floatingselection'>Floating selection </link>.
      The mouse pointer then looks like an anchor when it is outside of
      the selection. This means that the selection will be permanently
      anchored at the place you choose when you click the mouse button.
    </para>
    <para lang="en"><!--added 060614-->
      As soon as this floating selection is created in the Layer dialog (and
      you can create it with Selection/Float), you can use the keyboard arrow
      keys to move the selection horizontally or vertically.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Um die Auswahl zu verschieben, halten Sie gleichzeitig die 
      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>-Tasten
      gedrückt und klicken und verschieben die Maus.  Um eine Auswahl zu 
      verschieben, ohne dass an deren ursprünglicher Position
      der Hintergrund erscheint, drücken Sie stattdessen 
      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Durch das Verschieben einer Auswahl wird automatisch eine
      <quote>schwebende Ebene</quote> (<quote>schwebende Auswahl</quote>)
      erzeugt. Beachten Sie hierzu das Kapitel
      <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection">Schwebende Auswahl</link>
      im Glossar. Der Mauszeiger stellt in einem solchen Fall einen Anker dar,
      sofern er außerhalb der Auswahl positioniert ist. Dies bedeutet, dass
      die Auswahl endgültig am gewählten Platz verankert wird, wenn die
      <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> gedrückt wird.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sobald diese schwebende Auswahl im Ebenendialog erstellt wurde (mit
      Auswahl/Schwebend), können Sie sie mit den Cursortasten horizontal
      oder vertikal bewegen.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Para mover una selección sin vaciar su región inicial tiene que
      mantener presionadas las teclas <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> y
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> simultáneamente, y luego mover la
      selección; o puede cambiar a la herramienta Mover y colocarla en
      modo Selección.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Al mover una selección automáticamente se crea una capa flotante
      (selección flotante). Luego el puntero del mouse cambia a un ancla
      cuando se encuentra fuera de la selección. Esto representa que la
      selección será fijada en el lugar escogido al hacer clic.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour déplacer la sélection avec son contenu sans vider l'emplacement
      initial, la manœuvre est plus complexe : maintenez l'appui sur la touche
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, déplacez un peu le pointeur de la souris,
      maintenez alors aussi l'appui sur la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap>
      et cliquez-glissez. Mais il est bien plus simple d'utiliser l'outil
      Déplacement en mode Sélection.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le fait de déplacer une sélection crée automatiquement une sélection
      flottante (un calque flottant). Voir
      <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection-fr">Sélection flottante</link>
      . Le pointeur de la souris est alors accompagnée d'une icône en forme
      d'ancre de marine quand il est en dehors de la sélection. Ceci indique
      qu'en cliquant, la sélection ne sera pas supprimée mais
      <emphasis>ancrée</emphasis>, c.-à-d. fixée définitivement à l'endroit
      choisi.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dès que cette sélection flottante est créée (et vous pouvez la créer
      avec Sélection/Flottante), vous pouvez utiliser les touches fléchées
      du clavier pour déplacer la sélection horizontalement ou verticalement.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Per spostare una selezione senza vuotarne la posizione iniziale basta
      premere il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> insieme al
      tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> e poi trascinare la selezione oppure usando
      lo strumento di spostamento in modalità selezione.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Spostando una selezione, automaticamente crea un livello fluttuante
      (selezione fluttuante). Vedere Selezione fluttuante. Il puntatore del
      mouse assume la caratteristica forma ad àncora mentre si esce dalla
      selezione. Ciò significa che la selezione verrà fissata definitivamente
      nel punto prescelto alla pressione del pulsante del mouse.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Non appena viene creata questa selezione fluttuante nella finestra di
      dialogo dei livelli (creabile con Seleziona/Fluttuante) è possibile
      usare anche i tasti freccia per spostare la selezione sia
      orizzontalmente che verticalmente.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      선택한 영역의 기존 위치를 비워두지 않으면서 선택을 이동하는 것은 다소
      복잡합니다. <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 키를 누른채 마우스를 조금 움직인
      다음, <keycap>Alt</keycap> 키를 같이 누르고 선택을 클릭해 드래그하면
      됩니다.(ctrl+alt 키가 글로벌 단축키로 설정되어 있지 않다면 동시에
      누르고 선택을 드래그해도 됩니다.) 이 방법은 선택모드에서 이동 도구를
      사용하는 것보다 편리합니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      선택을 이동시키면 자동적으로 떠있는 레이어(
      <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection">떠있는
      선택</link> -->
      떠있는 선택)가 생성됩니다. 이에 대한 자세한 내용은
      <!-- PENDING ko : <link
      linkend='glossary-floatingselection'>Floating selection </link> -->
      떠있는 선택에 있습니다. 마우스 커서를 선택 영역 밖으로 가져가면 고정
      모양으로 바뀌게 되고, 원하는 위치에서 클릭을 하면 선택 영역이 그
      자리에 완전히 고정됩니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      레이어 대화상자에 떠있는 선택이 생기면(또는 선택/띄우기를 통해
      만들거나), 키보드의 방향키를 이용해 선택을 상하좌우로 움직일 수
      있습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Det er råd å flytta ei markering utan å blanka ut startposisjonen.
      Hald nede <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten medan du flytter
      musepeikaren ørlite grann. Hald deretter også nede
      <keycap>Alt</keycap>-tasten medan du flytter markeringa. Ein enklare
      metode er å bruke flytteverktøyet i markeringsmodus.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Når du flytter på ei markering, vil det automatisk bli laga ei
      flytande markering (eit flytande lag). Sjå <link
      linkend='glossary-floatingselection'>Flytande markering</link>.
      Når musepeikaren er utanfor markeringinga vil han sjå ut som eit
      ankar for å minna deg om at markeringa vil bli fast forankra i denne
      posisjonen dersom du klikkar på venstre museknappen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Så snart den flytande markeringa er oppretta i lagdialogen kan du bruke
      piltastane for å flytte markeringa. (Du kan lage markeringa flytande
      ved å gå inn på
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Vel</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Gjer flytande</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> i biletmenyen).
    </para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="gimp-using-selections-free-select" lang="de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Creating a Free Selection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eine freie Auswahl erstellen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Creación de una selección libre</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Création d'une sélection à main levée</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Creazione di una selezione a mano libera</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">자유로운 선택 만들기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Frihandsmarkering</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Using the Free Selection Tool</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Das Werkzeug <quote>Freie Auswahl</quote> benutzen
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Empleo de la herramienta de selección libre
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Comment utiliser l'outil Sélection à main levée
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Uso dello strumento selezione a mano libera (Lazo)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">자유로운 선택 도구 사용하기</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Å bruke frihandsmarkeringa</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-lasso-ex1.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">A rather rough selection</para>
          <para lang="de">Eine ziemlich grobe Auswahl</para>
          <para lang="es">Una selección aproximada</para>
          <para lang="fr">Une sélection bien grossière</para>
          <para lang="it">Una selezione piuttosto approssimata</para>
          <para lang="ko">다소 거친 선택</para>
          <para lang="no">Ei nokså grov markering</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-lasso-ex2.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            Adding new selected areas to an existing selection.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Neu ausgewählte Bereiche einer bestehenden Auswahl hinzufügen.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Añadir una nueva región a la selección actual
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">기존 선택에 새로운 선택 영역 추가하기</para>
          <para lang="no">
            Å legge til ei markering i ei eksisterande markering
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      When using the lasso to select an object, some parts of the object
      and its proximity may be incorrectly either selected or not
      selected. You can correct these defects by pressing the
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> or <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> keys while using
      the lasso. Here is how to do it: While pressing
      <keycap>Shift</keycap>, draw the new border with the lasso and
      close the selection, including a part of the first selection. As
      soon as you release the mouse button, both selections are added
      together. You could subtract the extra part of the first selection
      in a similar way by pressing <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie Objekte mit dem Lasso auswählen, können Teile des Objekts
      und seiner näheren Umgebung fälschlicherweise ausgewählt beziehungsweise nicht
      ausgewählt werden. Solche Defekte können Sie korrigieren, indem Sie
      die <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>- oder <keycap>Strg</keycap>-Taste
      drücken, während Sie das Lasso benutzen. Und so wird's gemacht:
      Während Sie <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste drücken, zeichnen Sie
      mit dem Lasso einen neuen Umriss und schließen dann die Auswahl
      (einschließlich eines Teils der ersten Auswahl). Sobald Sie die
      Maustaste loslassen, werden beide Auswahlen zusammengefügt.
      Den überschüssigen Teil der ersten Auswahl können Sie in ähnlicher
      Weise mit der <keycap>Strg</keycap>-Taste entfernen.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Al emplear el lazo para seleccionar un objeto, algunas partes
      pueden quedar por fuera y otras por dentro.  Para corregir estos
      defectos se pueden presionar las teclas <keycap>Shift</keycap> o
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> mientras se emplea el lazo.  He aquí un
      ejemplo: Manteniendo presionado <keycap>Shift</keycap>, empieze
      a dibujar el nuevo borde con el lazo, cierre la selección
      incluyendo una parte de la primera selección.  Ni bien suelte el
      botón del mouse ambas selecciones son unidas.  Puede sustraer a
      la selección existente manteniendo presionado
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> al hacer clic para empezar a dibujar.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Quand vous utilisez le lasso pour sélectionner un objet, il arrive
      souvent que des parties de l'objet et de son environnement soient
      sélectionnées en plus ou en moins. L'utilisation du lasso associé à
      l'appui sur les touches Maj ou Ctrl peut vous permettre de corriger ces
      défauts. Voici un exemple : tout en appuyant sur la touche Maj, tracez
      avec le lasso la nouvelle bordure et fermez la sélection en englobant
      une partie de la première sélection. Notez le signe + accompagnant
      l'icône pointeur du lasso. Dès que vous relâchez le bouton de la souris,
      les deux sélections s'additionnent Vous pourriez de même soustraire
      l'excès de sélection en appuyant sur la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Usando il Lazo per selezionare un oggetto, alcune parti dell'oggetto
      potrebbero non essere selezionate e invece, erroneamente, potrebbero
      esserlo un po' dei suoi dintorni. È possibile correggere la selezione
      premendo i tasti <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> o
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> mentre si usa lo strumento. Ecco un esempio:
      mentre si preme  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>, disegnare un nuovo bordo
      con il lazo, chiudere la selezione includendo una parte della prima
      selezione. Non appena si rilascia il pulsante del mouse, le selezioni
      si sommano fondendosi assieme. Similmente è possibile sottrarre una
      selezione ad una parte della prima premendo invece il
      tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> insieme al pulsante del mouse.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      올가미 도구를 이용해 물체를 선택하면, 물체의 일부나 근접 부분이 잘못
      선택되는 경우가 있습니다. 이때는 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 키나
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 키를 누르고 올가미를 사용하면 선택을 교정할 수
      있습니다. 다음 예에서는 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 키를 누른 채, 올가미
      도구를 이용해 기존의 선택에 근접하는 새로운 경계를 만들었습니다.
      그런 뒤 마우스 버튼을 놓으면 두 선택은 자동적으로 합쳐집니다. 기존
      선택의 일부를 제거하는 것은 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 키를 누르고
      동일하게 하면 됩니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Lassoen er nokså unøyaktig når du bruker datamusa for å lage ei
      markering. Det er lett å treffe litt på sida av der du eigentleg hadde
      tenkt. Heldigvis finst det måtar å retta opp bommertane på. Har du
      behov for å utvida markeringa, held du nede <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten
      medan du teiknar dei nye grensene. Pass på at deler av den nye markeringa
      kjem innføre den eksisterande og at den nye markeringa er slutta. Så
      snart du slepp opp museknappen, vil den nye markeringa bli lagt til den
      gamle. Har du behov for å gjere markeringa mindre, bruker du
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten på same måten.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        To correct selection defects precisely, use the
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Quick Mask</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Um Auswahldefekte ganz präzise zu korrigieren, verwenden Sie die
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Schnellmaske</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Para corregir los defectos de la selección con más presición, emplee
        la <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Máscara rápida</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour une correction précise des défauts de sélection, utilisez le
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Masque rapide</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per correggere in maniera precisa le selezioni usare la funzione
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Maschera veloce</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        선택에서 미세하게 틀린 부분을 수정하려면
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">퀵마스크
        </link>-->
        퀵마스크를 이용합니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        For å arbeide meir nøyaktig kan du bruke
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">snarmaska</link>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
