<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- Section history:
  2009-02-24 j.h: added Add/Subtract selections
  2009-02-21 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2008-04-04 Mr.Dust : reviewed and added 'ko'
  2008-01-09 ude: updated de (Moving Selection section)
  2007-12-31 j.h: rewrote Moving Selection section
  2007-10-02 Updated English and German parts of first sect2
             for 2.4 by rubikcube
  2007-01-22 modified Korean Translation by Dust
  2006-09-11 Added Norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-12 Added Korean Translation by Dust.
  2006-06-13 Added para about using arrow keys by j.h
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-selections">
  <title>Creating and Using Selections</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selections</primary>
    <secondary>Using</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-selections-moving">
    <title>Moving or Resizing a Selection</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Move selection</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Resize selection</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Rectangular and elliptical selections have two modes. The default
      mode has handles on the selection. These handles can be used to resize the
      selection. Dragging from inside the selection, but not inside the handles,
      moves the selection. If you click the selection or press the
      <keycap>Enter</keycap> key, the handles disappear leaving only the dotted
      selection outline (<link linkend="glossary-marching-ants">marching ants</link>).
      You can return to the mode with handles by clicking inside the selection again.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you click-and-drag the selection without handles, you create a new
      selection.
      The other selection tools do not have this division in two modes.
    </para>

    <sect3>
      <title>
        Moving selections using the Rectangle and Ellipse Select tools
      </title>
      <para>
        As mentioned above, the <quote>Rectangle Select</quote> and
        <quote>Ellipse Select</quote> tools by default show a selection frame
        with handles.
        It is possible to change the size and location of the selection, but
        also to move the selection including the layer contents.
      </para>

      <sect4>
        <title>Moving and resizing the selection outline</title>
        <figure>
          <title>Moving the selection outline</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/select-move-1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Moving or resizing the selection frame, without moving the image
          contents, can be done both with the mouse and with the keyboard.
        </para>
        <para>
          To move the selection with the mouse, click inside the selection in
          an area that doesn't show one of the handles. Then drag it with the
          mouse towards your intended location.
        </para>
        <para>
          To move the selection with the keyboard, it is currently required that
          the mouse pointer is inside the selection frame, or it won't work.
          Press and hold <keycap>Alt</keycap> (or
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>),
          to move one pixel at a time. To move 25 pixels at a time add
          the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key to the above combination.
        </para>
        <para>
          To resize the selection with the mouse, place the mouse pointer in
          the handle area where you want to resize, and then click-drag in the
          desired direction.
          To resize in one direction, use the middle handles; to resize two
          neighboring directions, use the handles in one of the corners.
        </para>
        <para>
          To resize using the keyboard, move the mouse pointer inside the
          handles along the edges of the selection frame, and then use the
          keyboard shortcuts mentioned above for moving.
        </para>
      </sect4>

      <sect4>
        <title>Moving the selection with the image contents</title>
        <figure>
          <title>
            Moving a selection and its contents, emptying the original location
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/select-move-2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          To move the selection contents (i.e. the part of the layer inside the
          selection), you can press
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>
          and click-and-drag the selection. The original location of the
          selected part of the layer will be emptied (i.e. filled with the
          current background color).
        </para>
        <para>
          Note that this action will create a floating layer that needs to be
          <link linkend="anchor-floating-selection">anchored</link> to the
          layer below, or turned into
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-new">a new layer</link>.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            Moving a selection with a copy of the layer contents
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/select-move-3.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          To move the selection contents without changing the original, use
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>
          and click-and-drag the selection. The original location of the
          selected part of the layer will stay the same while you move a
          copy.
        </para>
        <para>
          Note that this action will create a floating layer that needs to be
          <link linkend="anchor-floating-selection">anchored</link> to the
          layer below, or turned into
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-new">a new layer</link>.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            On some systems, you must push <keycap>Alt</keycap> before
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> or <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>. On these
            systems, pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> or <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            first, causes GIMP to enter a mode that adds or subtracts from the
            current selection. After doing that, the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is
            ineffective!
          </para>
        </note>
      </sect4>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Moving using other Selection Tools</title>
      <para>
        The other selection tools (Free Select, Fuzzy Select, By Color Select,
        etc.) have no handles.
        Using click-and-drag doesn't move these selections. To move their
        contents, as with rectangular and elliptical selections, you have to
        press the
        <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> or
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> keys
        and then use click-and-drag.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you use keyboard arrow keys instead of click-and-drag, you move
        only the selection outline.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>A different method of moving a selection</title>
      <para>
        You can also use a more roundabout method to move a selection. Make
        the <link linkend="gimp-selection-float">selection floating</link>.
        Then you can move its content using the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-move">Move</link> tool, emptying the
        original location, by click-and-dragging or keyboard arrow keys.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-selections-add">
    <title>Adding or subtracting selections</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Add / Subtract selections</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Tools have options that you can configure.
      Each selection tool allows you to set the selection mode. The
      following selection modes are supported:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          Replace is the most used selection mode. In replace mode,
          a selection replaces any existing selection.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Add mode, causes new selections to be added to any existing
          selection. Press and hold the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while
          making a selection to temporarily enter add mode.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Subtract mode, causes new selections to be removed from any existing
          selection. Press and hold the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while
          making a selection to temporarily enter subtract mode.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Intersect mode, causes areas in both the new and
          existing selection to become the new selection.
          Press and hold both the <keycap>Shift</keycap> and
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while
          making a selection to temporarily enter intersect mode.
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>Enlarging a rectangular selection with Free Select</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/rectangular+free-select-example.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The figure shows an existing rectangular selection.
      Select <link linkend="gimp-tool-free-select">Free Select</link>.
      While pressing the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
      key, make a free hand selection that includes the existing selection.
      Release the mouse button and areas are included in the selection.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        To correct selection defects precisely, use the
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Quick Mask</link>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
