<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
 
<sect2 id='gimp-using-selection'>
  <title lang="en">The Selection</title>

  <para lang='en'>
    Often when you operate on an image, you only want part of it to be
    affected.  In Gimp, you make this happen by
    <emphasis>selecting</emphasis> that part.  Each image has a
    <emphasis>selection</emphasis> associated with it.  Most, but not
    all, Gimp operations act only on the selected portions of the
    image. 
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format='png'/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          How would you isolate the tree?
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    There are many, many situations where creating just the right
    selection is the key to getting the result you want, and often it
    is not very easy to do.  For example, in the image to the right,
    suppose I want to cut the tree out from its background, and paste
    it into a different image.  In order to do this, I need to create
    a selection that contains the tree and nothing but the tree.  It
    is difficult because the tree has a very complex shape, and in
    several spots is hard to distinguish from the objects behind it.  
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    To help you do these sorts of things, Gimp provides you with a
    whole array of tools for creating and manipulating selections.
    The most basic of them allow you to trace out the boundary between
    selected and unselected regions using the mouse.  Other, more
    intelligent, tools make it easier by being sensitive to various
    aspects of the structure of the image.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format='png'/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Selection shown as usual with dashed line
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    Now here is a very important point, and it is crucial to
    understand this.  Ordinarily when you create a selection, you see
    it as a dashed line enclosing a portion of the image.  The idea
    you could get from this is that the selection is a sort of
    container, with the selected parts of the image inside, and the
    unselected parts outside.  This concept of the selection is okay
    for many purposes, but it is not really correct.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Actually the selection is implemented as a
    <emphasis>channel</emphasis>.  In terms of its internal structure,
    it is identical to the red, green, blue, and alpha channels of an
    image.  Thus, the selection has a value defined at each pixel of
    the image, ranging between 0 (unselected) and 255 (fully
    selected).  The advantage of this approach is that it allows some
    pixels to be <emphasis>partially selected</emphasis>, by giving
    them intermediate values between 0 and 255.  As you will see,
    there are many situations where it is desirable to have smooth
    transitions between selected and unselected regions.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    What, then, is the dashed line that appears when you create a
    selection? 
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    It is a <emphasis>contour line</emphasis>, dividing areas that are
    more than half selected from areas that are less than half
    selected.  
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format='png'/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Same selection in QuickMask mode
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    You should always bear in mind, when looking at the dashed line
    that represents the selection, that it only tells you part of the
    story.  If you want to see the selection in complete detail, the
    easiest way is to click the QuickMask button in the lower left
    corner of the image window.  This causes the selection to be shown
    as a translucent overlay atop the image.  Selected areas are
    unaffected; unselected areas are reddened.  The more completely
    selected an area is, the less red it appears.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    QuickMask mode, and its uses, are described in detail below.
    Meanwhile, if you are following this discussion by trying things
    out in Gimp, you should know that many operations work differently
    in QuickMask mode, so go ahead and toggle it off again for now (by
    clicking the QuickMask button once more).
  </para>

  <formalpara lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png' format='png'/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Same selection in QuickMask mode after feathering
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    <title>Feathering</title>
    With the default settings, the basic selection tools, such as the
    Rectangle Select tool, create sharp selections.  Pixels inside the
    dashed line are fully selected, and pixels outside completely
    unselected.  You can verify this by toggling QuickMask: you see a
    clear rectangle with sharp edges, surrounded by uniform red.  In
    the Tool Options, however, is a checkbox called "Feather".  If you
    enable this, the tool will instead create graduated selections.
    The feather radius, which you can adjust, determines the distance
    over which the transition occurs.
  </formalpara>

  <para lang='en'>
    If you are following along, try this out with the Rectangle Select
    tool, and then toggle QuickMask.  You will now see that the
    clear rectangle has a fuzzy edge.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Feathering is particularly useful when you are cutting and
    pasting, in helping the pasted object to blend smoothly and
    unobtrusively with its surroundings.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Actually, it is possible to feather a selection at any time, even
    if it was originally created as a sharp selection.  You can do
    this from the image menu, by choosing 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Feather</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    This brings up a dialog that allows you to set the feather
    radius.  You can do the opposite--sharpen a graduated
    selection into an all-or-nothing selection--by choosing  
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Sharpen</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <note lang='en'>
    For technically oriented readers: feathering works by applying a
    Gaussian blur to the selection channel, with the specified
    blurring radius.
  </note>



  <!-- saving selections -->

</sect2>
