<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
 
<sect2 id='gimp-selection' lang="en;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">The Selection</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">选区</title>

  <para lang='en'>
    Often when you operate on an image, you only want part of it to be
    affected.  In Gimp, you make this happen by
    <emphasis>selecting</emphasis> that part.  Each image has a
    <emphasis>selection</emphasis> associated with it.  Most, but not
    all, Gimp operations act only on the selected portions of the
    image. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当对一个图像处理时，您常常只想处理其中的一部分。在 Gimp 中，通过<emphasis>选择</emphasis>那部分来实现。每个图像上都有一个相关的<emphasis>选区</emphasis>。大部分，但不是全部的 Gimp 操作只对图像选择部分进行操作。
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          How would you isolate the tree?
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    There are many, many situations where creating just the right
    selection is the key to getting the result you want, and often it
    is not very easy to do.  For example, in the image to the right,
    suppose I want to cut the tree out from its background, and paste
    it into a different image.  In order to do this, I need to create
    a selection that contains the tree and nothing but the tree.  It
    is difficult because the tree has a very complex shape, and in
    several spots is hard to distinguish from the objects behind it.  
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          如何把这个书独立出来？
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    这有很多，很多的情形，创建正确的选区是获取您所有结果的关键，常常这并不容易办到。比如，在右边的图像中，我准备将树从背景中剪切出来，并粘贴到其它的图像中。为了达到这个目的，我需要创建一个只包含树而没有其它任何东西的选区。这就比较困难，因为树有一个非常复杂的形状，而且在某些地方与其后的物体很难区分。
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    为了帮您完成这一类操作，Gimp 提供给您完整的一系列的创建和处理选区的工具。它们中最基本的允许您使用鼠标勾勒出选区和非选区间的边界，而其它更智能工具，对图像结构的许多方面比较敏感，这样是勾选变得容易。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Selection shown as usual with dashed line
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    Now here is a very important point, and it is crucial to
    understand this.  Ordinarily when you create a selection, you see
    it as a dashed line enclosing a portion of the image.  The idea
    you could get from this is that the selection is a sort of
    container, with the selected parts of the image inside, and the
    unselected parts outside.  This concept of the selection is okay
    for many purposes, but it is not really correct.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          选区通常用虚线表示
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    现在这是非常重要的地方了，弄明白这点是至关重要的。通常的，当创建一个选区，您会发现它是一条虚线环绕在图像一部分上。您可能决定选区好像一种容器，图像选择的部分在内，未选择部分在外。这种关于选区的观点在许多目的中没有问题，但它并不是完全正确的。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Actually the selection is implemented as a
    <emphasis>channel</emphasis>.  In terms of its internal structure,
    it is identical to the red, green, blue, and alpha channels of an
    image.  Thus, the selection has a value defined at each pixel of
    the image, ranging between 0 (unselected) and 255 (fully
    selected).  The advantage of this approach is that it allows some
    pixels to be <emphasis>partially selected</emphasis>, by giving
    them intermediate values between 0 and 255.  As you will see,
    there are many situations where it is desirable to have smooth
    transitions between selected and unselected regions.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    准确地说，选区是作为一个<emphasis>通道</emphasis>来实现的。在其内部结构方面，它与图像的红色，绿色，蓝色和 alpha通道完全相同。因此，选区中有一个定义每个图像像素的值，从 0 (未选中)到 255 (完全选中)。这种方式的优点是，它允许一些像素被<emphasis>部分选中</emphasis>，其值在 0 到 255 之间。正如您所见的，这有许多需要在选中和未选中区域间有个平滑的过渡的情况。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    What, then, is the dashed line that appears when you create a
    selection? 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    哪怎么当您创建一个选区时，虚线就出现了？
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    It is a <emphasis>contour line</emphasis>, dividing areas that are
    more than half selected from areas that are less than half
    selected.  
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    那是一个<emphasis>轮廓线</emphasis>，它区分被选中多于半个像素的区域和被选中少于半个像素的区域。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Same selection in QuickMask mode
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    You should always bear in mind, when looking at the dashed line
    that represents the selection, that it only tells you part of the
    story.  If you want to see the selection in complete detail, the
    easiest way is to click the QuickMask button in the lower left
    corner of the image window.  This causes the selection to be shown
    as a translucent overlay atop the image.  Selected areas are
    unaffected; unselected areas are reddened.  The more completely
    selected an area is, the less red it appears.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          在快速蒙板模式下的同一个选区
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>
    您需要一直牢记，当您看到表现选区的虚线时，它只告诉您部分信息。如果您想了解选区的完全细节，最简单的方法就是点击图像窗口左下角的快速蒙板按钮。它使选区好像被蒙上一层半透明的遮盖。选中的区域没有受影响，而非选中区域则呈红色。越完全选中的区域，显示的红色越少。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    QuickMask mode, and its uses, are described in detail below.
    Meanwhile, if you are following this discussion by trying things
    out in Gimp, you should know that many operations work differently
    in QuickMask mode, so go ahead and toggle it off again for now (by
    clicking the QuickMask button once more).
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    快速蒙板模式，及其使用，下面有详细描述。同时，如果您跟随该讨论并在 Gimp 中尝试，您会了解与许多操作在快速蒙板中工作方式不同，因此现在将其切换为关闭(再次点击快速蒙板按钮)。
  </para>

  <formalpara lang='en'>
    <title>Feathering</title>

    <para>
      <informalfigure>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png' format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<caption>
	  <para lang='en'>
	    Same selection in QuickMask mode after feathering
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </informalfigure>

      With the default settings, the basic selection tools, such as the
      Rectangle Select tool, create sharp selections.  Pixels inside the
      dashed line are fully selected, and pixels outside completely
      unselected.  You can verify this by toggling QuickMask: you see a
      clear rectangle with sharp edges, surrounded by uniform red.  In the
      Tool Options, however, is a checkbox called "Feather".  If you enable
      this, the tool will instead create graduated selections.  The feather
      radius, which you can adjust, determines the distance over which the
      transition occurs.
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
    <title>羽化</title>

    <para>
      <informalfigure>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png' format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<caption>
	  <para lang="zh_CN">
	    羽化后在快速蒙板模式下的同一个选区
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </informalfigure>
      默认设置下，基本的选择工具如矩形选择工具，生成锐利的选区。虚线内的像素被完全选中，而其外的像素则完全未选中。您可以通过切换快速蒙板来验证：您看到一个清晰带锐利边缘的矩形，并被统一的红色包围。而在工具选项有个“边缘羽化”勾选框。如果您勾选它，改工具将生成有层次的选区。羽化半径则可以用来调节在什么距离上进行过渡。
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <para lang='en'>
    If you are following along, try this out with the Rectangle Select
    tool, and then toggle QuickMask.  You will now see that the
    clear rectangle has a fuzzy edge.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果您沿着上面内容下来，可以用矩形选择工具来实践，然后切换到快速蒙板模式。您现在将看到带有一个模糊边界的清晰的矩形。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Feathering is particularly useful when you are cutting and
    pasting, in helping the pasted object to blend smoothly and
    unobtrusively with its surroundings.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当剪切和粘贴后，羽化特别有用，它可以使被粘贴的物体平滑而不引人注意地和周围环境混合在一起。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Actually, it is possible to feather a selection at any time, even
    if it was originally created as a sharp selection.  You can do
    this from the image menu, by choosing 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Feather</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    This brings up a dialog that allows you to set the feather
    radius.  You can do the opposite--sharpen a graduated
    selection into an all-or-nothing selection--by choosing  
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Sharpen</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    实际上，在任何时候羽化一个选区是可能的，甚至最开始创建的是一个锐利的选区。通过在图像菜单中选取
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>选择</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>羽化</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>。
    会弹出一个允许您设定羽化半径的对话框。也能干相反的--锐化一个有层次的选区为一个边界分明的选区--通过选取
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>选择</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>锐化</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <note lang='en'>
    For technically oriented readers: feathering works by applying a
    Gaussian blur to the selection channel, with the specified
    blurring radius.
  </note>
  <note lang="zh_CN">
    对于面向技术的读者：羽化实质上是对选区通道使用选定模糊半径的高斯模糊操作。
  </note>



  <!-- saving selections -->

</sect2>
