<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- Section history:
    2006-07-12 Added Korean Translation by Dust.
    2006-06-13 Added para about using arrow keys by j.h
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-selections" lang="de;en;es;fr;it;ko">
  <sect1info lang="en;fr;ko">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-06</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-13</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-12</date>
        <authorinitials>먼지군</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="de">Auswahlen erstellen und benutzen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Creating and Using Selections</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Crear y usar selecciones</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Créer et utiliser les Sélections</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Creazione e uso delle selezioni</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">선택 만들기와 사용하기</phrase>
  </title>
  
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selections</primary>
    <secondary>Using</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Selecciones</primary>
    <secondary>Uso</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélections</primary>
    <secondary>Utilisation</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Selezioni</primary>
    <secondary>Uso</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>선택</primary>
    <secondary>사용하기</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Auswahl verschieben</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Moving a Selection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Mover la selección</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Déplacer une sélection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Spostamento selezioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">선택 이동하기</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Durch verschieben der Auswahl erscheint die Hintergrundebene
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Moving the selection reveals the background layer
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Al mover la selección se revela el color de la capa de fondo
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Le fait de déplacer une sélection révèle l'arrière-plan
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Lo spostamento delle selezioni scopre il livello di sfondo.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">
          움직이는 선택은 배경 레이어를 드러내 보인다.
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/using/select-move.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para lang="en">
      After creating a rectangular, elliptic or free selection, 
      or when you are using the Magic wand, the default mouse pointer is the 
      moving cross. Click-and-drag then allows you to move the 
      selection and its contents, while the initial position 
      remains empty. 
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      If you only want to move the selection border and not
      its contents, then press the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key 
      and click-and-drag the selection.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Nachdem Sie eine rechteckige, elliptische oder freie Auswahl erstellt,
      oder den Zauberstab benutzt haben, nimmt der Mauszeiger die Form des
      Verschiebesymbols an. Mit klicken und verschieben können Sie dann die
      Auswahl und ihren Inhalt verschieben. An der Stelle von welcher die
      Auswahl wegbewegt wird, erscheint der Hintergrund.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Falls Sie nur den Rahmen der Auswahl, nicht aber deren Inhalt
      verschieben möchten, halten Sie die <keycap>Alt</keycap> Taste gedrückt
      beim klicken und verschieben.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Luego de haber creado una selección, ya sea con la herramienta
      rectangular, elíptica, libre, o con la varita mágica, el puntero
      del mouse por defecto cambia a la cruz para mover.  Mantener
      presionado el botón del mouse te permite mover la selección y su
      contenido, dejando la región en que estaba alojada vacía.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Si lo que quieres es mover la selección pero no su contenido,
      mantiene presionada la tecla <keycap>Alt</keycap> al hacer clic
      para mover la selección.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Après création d'une sélection rectangulaire, elliptique, à main levée,
      ou avec la Baguette magique, le pointeur de la souris a, par défaut,
      l'aspect de la croix de déplacement. Le cliquer-glisser simple permet
      alors déplacer la sélection et son contenu tout en laissant vide son
      emplacement initial.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr"> 
      Si vous voulez ne déplacer que le contour de la sélection 
      sans déplacer son contenu, maintenez l'appui sur la touche 
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> et cliquez-glissez la sélection.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Dopo la creazione di una selezione rettangolare, ellittica o libera o
      con lo strumento «bacchetta magica», la forma del puntatore del mouse
      cambia nella croce di spostamento (una croce formata da quattro frecce).
      Il successivo trascinamento della selezione permette di spostarla con
      tutto il suo contenuto, mentre nella posizione iniziale rimane un vuoto.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se si desidera spostare solo il bordo della selezione senza il suo
      contenuto, premere contemporaneamente il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap>
      durante il trascinamento.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      사각형이나 타원, 혹은 자유 선택이나 매직완드로 선택을 만들면, 마우스
      커서가 이동 모양으로 바뀐다. 그러면 클릭-드래그로 선택한 영역을 
      이동시킬 수 있게 된다. 이때 이동된 영역이 있던 원래 자리는 빈공간으로
      남게 된다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      만약 선택된 영역이 아닌 선택 자체만 이동시키려면 <keycap>Alt</keycap>
      키를 누르고 선택을 클릭-드래그를 하면 된다.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        Sometimes the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is used by the window
        manager and you move the image window instead of the selection.
        If this is the case, select the move tool and change the
        <quote>Affect</quote> option.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Es besteht die Möglichkeit, dass die <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        Taste vom Fenster-Manager benutzt wird. Sollte das der Fall sein,
        benutzen Sie das
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-transform-tool-options">
          Verschiebewerkzeug
        </link> und verändern sie die <quote>Wirkt auf</quote> Option.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        A menudo la tecla <keycap>Alt</keycap> es utilizada por el
        administrador de ventanas y terminas moviendo la ventana de la
        imagen en vez de la selección.  Si es éste el caso, tienes dos
        opciones: puedes presionar la tecla <keycap>Alt</keycap> junto
        con la tecla <keycap>Shift</keycap> o cambiar a la herramienta
        de Mover y variar la opción <quote>Afectar</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Il se peut que la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap> soit déjà utilisée par 
        le système et que vous déplaciez alors l'ensemble de l'image au lieu 
        de la sélection. Dans ce cas, sélectionnez l'outil Déplacement et 
        changez l'option «Affecte».
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Alle volte il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> viene usato dal gestore
        delle finestre ed il risultato è di trascinare l'intera finestra
        invece della sola selezione. In questo caso è possibile premere
        insieme il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> e <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>,
        oppure selezionare lo strumento di spostamento e cambiare l'opzione
        <quote>Influenza</quote> in «Trasforma la selezione».
        
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        때때로 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 키는 윈도우 관리자에 의해 선택대신 
        이미지 창을 움직이는데 쓰이기도 한다. 이럴 경우, 
        <keycap>Alt</keycap> 키와 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 키를 같이 누르거나
        이동 도구를 선택해 <quote>적용</quote> 옵션을 바꿔주면 된다.
      </para>
    </note>
    
    <para lang="de">
      Eine Auswahl zu verschieben, ohne das an deren ursprünglicher Position
      der Hintergrund erscheint ist ein bisschen schwieriger: drücken Sie die
      <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste, bewegen Sie den Mauszeiger ein kleines
      Stück und drücken Sie dann zusätzlich die <keycap>Alt</keycap> Taste.
      Nun klicken und verschieben Sie die Auswahl. Einfacher funktioniert es,
      wenn Sie das Verschieben Werkzeug im Auswahlmodus hierfür verwenden.
    </para> 
    <para lang="de">
      Durch das Verschieben einer Auswahl wird automaisch eine Schwebende
      Ebene (Schwebende Auswahl) erzeugt. Beachten Sie hierzu das Kapitel 
      <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection">Schwebende Auswahl</link>
      im Glossar. Der Mauszeiger stellt in einem solchen Fall einen Anker dar,
      sofern er ausserhalb der Auswahl positioniert ist. Dies bedeutet, dass
      die Auswahl endgültig am gewählten Platz verankert wird, sobald die
      <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> gedrückt wird.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="en">
      Moving a selection without emptying its initial position is more
      complicated: while pressing the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key, move
      the mouse pointer a little bit, then also press the
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> key, then click-and-drag the selection. This
      can be done more easily by using the Move tool in Selection mode.
    </para> 
    <para lang="en">
      Moving a selection automatically creates a floating layer
      (floating selection). See <link
      linkend='glossary-floatingselection'>Floating selection </link>.
      The mouse pointer then looks like an anchor when it is outside of
      the selection. This means that the selection will be permanently
      anchored at the place you choose when you click the mouse button. 
    </para>
    <para lang="en"> <!--added 060614-->
      As soon as this floating selection is created in the Layer dialog
      (and you can create it with Selection/Float), you can use the
      keyboard arrow keys to move the selection horizontally or
      vertically.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="es">
      Para mover una selección sin vaciar su región inicial tienes que
      mantener presionadas las teclas <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> y
      <keycap>Alt</keycap>, y luego mover la selección; o puedes
      cambiar a la herramienta Mover y colocarla en modo Selección.
    </para> 
    <para lang="es">
      Al mover una selección automáticamente se crea una capa flotante
      (selección flotante). Luego el puntero del mouse cambia a un ancla
      cuando se encuentra fuera de la selección. Esto representa que la
      selección será fijada en el lugar escogido al hacer clic.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour déplacer la sélection avec son contenu sans vider l'emplacement
      initial, la manœuvre est plus complexe: maintenez l'appui sur la touche
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>,
      déplacez un peu le pointeur de la souris, maintenez aussi l'appui sur
      la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap>
      et cliquez-glissez. Mais il est bien plus simple d'utiliser l'outil
      Déplacement en mode Sélection
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le fait de déplacer une sélection crée automatiquement 
      une sélection flottante (un calque flottant). Voir 
      <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection-fr">Sélection 
      flottante</link>. 
      Le pointeur de la souris est alors accompagnée d'une icône en 
      forme d'ancre de marine quand il est en dehors de la 
      sélection. Ceci indique qu'en cliquant, la sélection ne 
      sera pas supprimée mais <emphasis>ancrée</emphasis>, c-à-d 
      fixée définitivement à l'endroit choisi.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dès que cette sélection flottante est créée (et vous pouvez la créer
      avec Sélection/Flottante), vous pouvez utiliser les touches fléchées
      du clavier pour déplacer la sélection horizontalement ou verticalement.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="it">
      Per spostare una selezione senza vuotarne la posizione iniziale basta
      premere il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> insieme al
      tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> e poi trascinare la selezione oppure usando
      lo strumento di spostamento in modalità selezione.
    </para> 
    <para lang="it">
      Spostando una selezione, automaticamente crea un livello fluttuante
      (selezione fluttuante). Vedere Selezione fluttuante. Il puntatore del
      mouse assume la caratteristica forma ad àncora mentre si esce dalla
      selezione. Ciò significa che la selezione verrà fissata definitivamente
      nel punto prescelto alla pressione del pulsante del mouse.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Non appena viene creata questa selezione fluttuante nella finestra di
      dialogo dei livelli (creabile con Seleziona/Fluttuante) è possibile
      usare anche i tasti freccia per spostare la selezione sia
      orizzontalmente che verticalmente.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      For moving a selection without emptying its initial position you just
      have to press both the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> keys, then click-and-drag the selection or
      either using the Move tool in Selection mode.
    </para> 
    <para lang="ko">
      선택을 이동시키면 자동적으로 떠있는 레이어(
      <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection">떠있는
      선택</link> -->
      떠있는 선택)가 생성된다. 그리고 선택 영역 밖으로 마우스 커서를 
      가져가면 고정 모양으로 바뀌게 되는데, 이는 클릭을 할 경우 선택 영역은
      그 자리에 완전히 고정된다라는 의미이다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      레이어 대화상자에 떠있는 선택이 생기면(또는 선택/띄우기를 통해 
      만들거나), 키보드의 방향키를 이용해 선택을 상하좌우로 움직일 수 있다.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-selections-free-select" lang="en;es;fr;it;ko">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Creating a Free Selection</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Crear una selección libre</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Création d'une sélection à main levée</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Creazione di una selezione a mano libera</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">자유로운 선택 만들기</phrase>
    </title>
      
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Using the Free Selection Tool</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Uso de la herramienta de selección libre
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Comment utiliser l'outil Sélection à main levée
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Uso dello strumento selezione a mano libera (Lazo)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="KO">자유로운 선택 도구 사용하기</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-lasso-ex1.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">A rather rough selection</para>
          <para lang="es">Una selección aproximada</para>
          <para lang="fr">Une sélection bien grossière</para>
          <para lang="it">Una selezione piuttosto approssimata</para>
          <para lang="ko">다소 거친 선택</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-lasso-ex2.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            Adding new selected areas to an existing selection.
          </para>
        <para lang="es">
            Añadir una nueva región a la selección actual
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">기존 선택에 새로운 선택 영역 추가하기</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      When using the lasso to select an object, some parts of the object
      and its proximity may be incorrectly either selected or not
      selected. You can correct these defects by pressing the
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> or <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> keys while using
      the lasso. Here is how to do it: While pressing
      <keycap>Shift</keycap>, draw the new border with the lasso and
      close the selection, including a part of the first selection. As
      soon as you release the mouse button, both selections are added
      together. You could subtract the extra part of the first selection
      in a similar way by pressing <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="es">
      Al usar el lazo para seleccionar un objeto, algunas partes
      pueden quedar por fuera y otras por dentro.  Para corregir estos
      defectos se pueden presionar las teclas <keycap>Shift</keycap> o
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> mientras se usa el lazo.  Aquí hay un
      ejemplo: Manteniendo presionado <keycap>Shift</keycap>, comienza
      a dibujar el nuevo borde con el lazo, cierra la selección
      incluyendo una parte de la primera selección.  Ni bien sueltes
      el botón del mouse ambas selecciones son unidas.  Puedes
      sustraer a la selección existente manteniendo presionado
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> al hacer clic para empezar a dibujar.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="fr">
      Quand vous utilisez le lasso pour sélectionner un objet, il arrive
      souvent que des parties de l'objet et de son environnement soient
      sélectionnées en plus ou en moins. L'utilisation du lasso associé à
      l'appui sur les touches Maj ou Ctrl peut vous permettre de corriger ces
      défauts. Voici un exemple: Tout en appuyant sur la touche Maj, tracez
      avec le lasso la nouvelle bordure et fermez la sélection en englobant
      une partie de la première sélection. Notez le signe + accompagnant
      l'icône pointeur du lasso. Dès que vous relâchez le bouton de la souris,
      les deux sélections s'additionnent Vous pourriez de même soustraire
      l'excès de sélection en appuyant sur la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Usando il Lazo per selezionare un oggetto, alcune parti dell'oggetto
      potrebbero non essere selezionate e invece, erroneamente, potrebbero
      esserlo un po' dei suoi dintorni. È possibile correggere la selezione
      premendo i tasti <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> o
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> mentre si usa lo strumento. Ecco un esempio:
      mentre si preme  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>, disegnare un nuovo bordo
      con il lazo, chiudere la selezione includendo una parte della prima
      selezione. Non appena si rilascia il pulsante del mouse, le selezioni
      si sommano fondendosi assieme. Similmente è possibile sottrarre una
      selezione ad una parte della prima premendo invece il
      tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> insieme al pulsante del mouse.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="ko">
      올가미 도구를 이용해 물체를 선택하면, 물체의 일부나 근접 부분이 잘못 
      선택되는 경우가 있다. 이때는 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 키나
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 키를 누르고 올가미를 사용하면 선택을 교정할 수
      있다. 다음 예에서는 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 키를 누른 채, 올가미 
      도구를 이용해 새로운 경계를 만든 후 먼저 만든 선택에 근접시켰다.
      이때 마우스 버튼을 놓으면 두 선택은 자동적으로 합쳐진다. 기존 선택의
      일부를 제거하는 것은 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 키를 누르고 동일하게 하면
      된다.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        To correct selection defects precisely, use the 
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Quick Mask</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Para corregir los defectos de la selección con más presición,
        utiliza la  Máscara rápida.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour une correction précise des défauts de sélection, utilisez le
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Masque rapide</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per correggere in maniera precisa le selezioni usare la funzione
        <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">Maschera veloce</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        선택에서 미세하게 틀린 부분을 수정하려면 
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-using-quickmask">퀵마스크
        </link>-->
        퀵마스크를 이용하는 것이 좋다.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
