<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-using-setup-tile-cache' lang="cs;en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Jak nastavit vyrovnávací paměť dlaždic</title>
  <title lang="en">How to Set Your Tile Cache</title>
  <title lang='de'>Einstellen des Datenspeichers</title>
  <title lang="fr">Comment ajuster le cache d'image</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">如何设置平铺缓存</title>
  <para lang="cs">
    Zpracování obrázků může vyžadovat obrovské množství paměti. Gimp, do
    určitého okamžiku, používá ke správě paměti služby operačního systému.
    Pokud ho překročí, začne používat svůj vlastní systém, aby nespotřeboval
    všechny systémové paměťové zdroje. Stará data přitom odkládá na disk.
    Bod, kdy dochází k této změně chování, je dán právě velikostí vyrovnávací
    paměti dlaždic, což je maximální množství operační paměti použité pro
    obrazová data (měřeno v bajtech nebo jejich násobcích). Vlastní paměť
    Gimpu se do tohoto množství nezapočítává, pouze paměť určená pro obrazová
    data.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Bei der Bearbeitung und Manipulation von Bildern wird viel
    Arbeitsspeicher benötigt. Je mehr zur Verfügung steht, desto besser.
    <acronym>Gimp</acronym> benutzt die durch das Betriebssystem
    bereitgestellten Resourcen und diese so effektiv wie möglich, damit
    Sie schnell und bequem ihre Bilder bearbeiten können. Der
    Datenspeicher wird benutzt, um Bilddaten die aktuell in Bearbeitung
    sind, zwischenzuspeichern. Dabei besteht der Unterschied, welche
    Form des Datenspeichers benutzt wird: die langsame Festplatte oder
    der schnelle Arbeitsspeicher.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le traitement d'image peut nécessiter beaucoup de mémoire vive. Gimp
    utilise les services du système opératoire pour gérer cette mémoire, en
    particulier la mémoire virtuelle qui est mise en œuvre quand la RAM est
    pleine. mais il utilise aussi son propre système de mémoire virtuelle de
    façon à laisser de la place aux autres applications. Ce système consiste
    à envoyer les données les plus anciennes sur le disque dur dans un
    «répertoire d'échange». Le réglage du cache d'image détermine la quantité
    de mémoire vive utilisée par les images au-delà de laquelle les données
    les plus anciennes seront envoyées sur le disque dur dans le répertoire
    d'échange.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    图像处理需要大量的内存。GIMP 依赖操作系统来处理内存，直到超过一定数量时，它就使用自己的系统，这样就不会用光所有系统内存资源。该系统发送旧数据到磁盘文件上。该临界数量就由平铺缓存决定---能使用操作系统资源的最大值---用字节(或其倍数，象兆字节)。它不包括 GIMP 自身的内存，只是图像数据需求的空间。
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Příliš nízká hodnota znamená, že Gimp data zbytečně brzy ukládá na disk
    a plně nevyužívá dostupnou operační paměť. Příliš vysoká hodnota naopak
    znamená, že o paměť přchází ostatní aplikace, což je nutí odkládat na disk
    a v extrémním případě může vést i k jejich poruše.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    A low value means that Gimp sends data vey quickly to disk, not
    making real use of the available RAM, and making the disks work
    without any real reason. Too high a value, and other applications
    start to have less system resources, forcing them to use swap space,
    which also makes the disks work; or maybe some will even get
    killed or start to malfunction due lack of RAM.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Une faible valeur fera que, très rapidement, Gimp enverra les données
    sur le disque, sans utiliser la ressource en mémoire vive et obligeant
    le disque à tourner beaucoup. Une valeur trop forte handicapera les
    autres applications utilisées en multitâche et elles solliciteront elles
    aussi le disque dur, et pourra même entraîner un dysfonctionnement par
    manque de RAM.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Je kleiner der Wert des Datenspeichers wird, desto mehr wird die
    Festplatte zum Zwischenspeichern ihrer Daten benutzt. Der Vorteil
    hier ist, dass Sie weniger Arbeitsspeicher benötigen um auch große
    Bilder zu Bearbeiten. Nachteil ist jedoch, dass die Bearbeitung am
    Bild merklich langsamer von statten geht. Ein höherer Wert führt
    dazu, das <acronym>Gimp</acronym> mehr Arbeitsspeicher zum
    Zwischenspeichern der Bilddaten benutzt. Dabei wird das Bearbeiten
    der Bilder um einiges schneller werden, jedoch werden andere Programme
    die zeitgleich ausgeführt werden, weniger Arbeitsspeicher zur
    Verfügung haben.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一个低值意味着 GIMP 很快地发送数据到文件，并不真正使用可用到的 RAM，也不需要任何真正理由就使磁盘工作。太高的值意味着其它程序启动时使用更少的内存，使它们使用交换空间，而这也要使磁盘工作；或许一些会被杀掉或由于缺乏内存而发生故障。
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Jak tedy zvolit správnou velikost vyrovnávací paměti dlaždic?
    Pomoci vám mohou následující tipy a triky:
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    How to choose a number for the Tile Cache size?  Here are some
    ways you could decide what value to use, as well as a few tricks:
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Folgend ein paar Tips um die Entscheidung für eine gute Größe des
    Datenspeichers einzustellen:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Comment choisir une valeur pour la mémoire virtuelle? Voici quelques
    trucs pour vous aider:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如何选取一个平铺缓存的值？这有一些可行的办法和技巧：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
  <para lang="cs">
    Nejjednodušším způsobem je nelámat si hlavu a doufat, že výchozí hodnoty
    budou fungovat dobře. To je vyhovující v případě počítačů s malým
    množstvím operační paměti a uživatelů používajících Gimp k tvorbě malých
    obrázků a spouštějících vedle Gimpu jen málo dalších aplikací. Pokud
    používáte Gimp jen k jednoduché práci, například snímání obrazovky, bude
    vám toto řešení vyhovovat.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The easiest method is to just forget about this and hope the
    default works. This was a usable method when
    computers had little RAM, and most people just tried to make small
    images with Gimp while running one or two other applications at
    the same time. If you
    want something easy and only use Gimp to make screenshots and
    logos, this is probably the best solution.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Vergessen Sie die Entscheidungsfindung und benutzen die
    Vorgabeeinstellungen von 64 MegaByte. Für viele Benutzer ist die
    Einstellung ausreichend, da keine Bilder bearbeitet werden, die
    so groß sind, dass sich die Größe negativ auf den Arbeitsprozess am
    Computer auswirkt.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La méthode la plus simple est de ne pas y penser et d'espérer que la
    valeur par défaut conviendra. C'était valable quand les ordinateurs
    avaient peu de RAM, et que la plupart des gens s'essayaient à la
    création de petites images tout en faisant marcher une ou deux autres
    applications. Si vous utilisez Gimp simplement pour des logos ou des
    captures d'écran, ça peut aller.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    最简单的办法就是不用管它，并希望默认值能工作。当电脑有少量内存时是个可行办法，大部分人只是用 GIMP 生成小图像同时运行一个或两个其它的程序。假如您只是使用 GIMP 来生成截图和标志，这可能是最好的解决办法。
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para lang="cs">
      Pokud máte moderní počítač s dostatkem paměti, alespoň 512 MB, bude
      pravděpodobně vyhovující nastavení velikosti vyrovnávací paměti dlaždic
      na polovinu nebo dokonce tři čtvrtiny operační paměti počítače. V
      případě počítače s 512 MB paměti tedy na 256-384 MB.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      If you have a modern computer with plenty of memory–say, 512 MB
      or more–setting the Tile Cache to half of your RAM will probably
      give good performance for Gimp in most situations without
      depriving other applications.  Probably even 3/4 of your RAM would
      be fine.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Sie haben eine ausreichende Menge von Arbeitsspeicher im
      Computer – sagen wir beispielsweise 512 MegaByte. Setzen Sie den Wert
      des Datenspeichers auf ca. ¾ des zur Verfügung stehenden
      Arbeispeichers; also auf 384 MegaByte.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      假如您有一个现代的电脑和大量内存---512 MB 或更多---设置平铺缓存为一半的内存可能将使 GIMP 在大多数情况下有个好的表现，而且不会使其它程序丧失使用内存的权利。或许甚至是 3/4 的 RAM 都很好。
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Si vous avez un ordinateur récent avec quantité de mémoire -- disons
      512 Mo ou plus --, une valeur égale à la moitié de la RAM donnera de
      bons résultats dans la plupart des situations, sans pénaliser les autres
      applications en multi-tâches. Et même 3/4 de votre RAM serait bien.
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
    <para lang="cs">
      Můžete také požádat někoho zkušenějšího, aby vám Gimp nastavil. V
      případě, že počítač sdílíte s dalšími uživateli je to velmi dobrý nápad;
      vyhnete se tak hádkám a nařčení z toho, že počítač zneužíváte, ale
      zároveň nebudete mít zbytečně přiškrcený Gimp. Pokud je počítač jen váš,
      možná bude vhodné jako odměnu za nastavení nabídnout nějaké peníze,
      večeři nebo alespoň dobré pivo či víno.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Ask someone to do it for you, which in the case of a computer
      serving multiple users at the same time can be a good idea: that
      way the administrator and other users do not get mad at you for
      abusing the machine, nor do you get a badly underperfoming Gimp. If
      it is your machine and only serves a single user at a given time,
      this could mean money, or drinks, as price for the service. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Demander à quelqu'un de le faire pour vous. Dans le cas d'un ordinateur
      desservant plusieurs utilisateurs en même temps, ce peut être une
      bonne idée: cela évitera que l'administrateur ne se fâche parce que vous
      abusez de la machine. S'il s'agit de votre machine, ça vous vaudra
      l'obligation de payer une verre pour le service.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当电脑用于多用户环境中时，最好请别人帮您设置：这样管理员和其它用户就不会由于您错误的设置而发疯，也不会使 GIMP 表现地很差。
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
    <para lang="cs">
      Můžete také vyrovnávací paměť dlaždic při každém spuštění Gimpu opatrně
      zvyšovat a dávat pozor, zda sy operační systém nestěžuje na nedostatek
      paměti nebo se tento nedostatek neprojevuje poruchami jiných aplikací,
      například jejich nečekaným ukončováním.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Start changing the value a bit each time and check that it goes
      faster and faster with each increase, but the system does not
      complain about lack of memory. Be forewarned that sometimes lack
      of memory shows up suddenly with some applications being killed to
      make space for the others. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Augmenter un peu la valeur à chaque fois et voir si Gimp augmente sa
      vitesse sans qu'un manque de mémoire se manifeste. Sachez que le manque
      de mémoire peut apparaître subitement et que quelques applications
      peuvent être fermées pour faire de la place.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      每次稍微地改变其值，然后检查每次增加变得越来越快，而系统未报怨缺乏内存。预先警告您，有时突然出现的缺乏内存会使一些程序被杀掉来为其它腾出空间。
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
    <para lang="cs">
      Další možností je vhodnou hodnotu vypočítat. Možná ji bude později nutné
      doladit, ale to se může stát i u předešlých metod. Výhodou výpočtu je,
      že lépe poznáte funkci svého počítače a možná dostanete z Gimpu i více
      výkonu.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Do some simple math and calculate a viable value. Maybe you will
      have to tune it later, but maybe you have to tune it anyway with
      the other previous methods. At least you know what is happening
      and can get the best from your computer. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Faire un petit calcul d'une valeur viable. Vous pourrez
      toujours utiliser les autres méthodes si ça ne marche pas.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      做一些简单的数学运算来计算一个可用的值。也许您需要以后再调整，但是务必要用其它以前的方法调整。至少您明白将发生什么并得到适合您电脑的最佳值。
    </para>
  </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang="cs">
    Pokud se rozhodnete pro poslední možnost, potřebuejte nějaké údaje o vašem
    počítači. Je třeba znát množství nainstalované operační paměti (RAM),
    velikost systémového odkládacího prostoru (swap) a mít představu o
    rychlosti disků používaných pro odkládací prostor operačního systému
    a odkládací adresář Gimpu. Nemusíte disky složitě testovat nebo zjišťovat
    jejich přesné parametry. Podstatné je jen, pokud pro odkládací prostory
    používáte různé disky, zda je některý z nich výrazně rychlejší než druhý
    (a případně který). Umístění odkládacího adrsáře Gimpu můžete změnit na
    stránce předvoleb Adresáře.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Let's suppose you prefer the last option, and want to get a good value to
    start with. First, you need to get some data about your
    computer. This data is the amount of RAM installed in your system,
    the operating system's
    swap space available, and a general idea about the speed of the
    disks that store the operating system's swap and the directory
    used for Gimp's swap. You do not need to do disk tests, nor check
    the RPM of the disks, the thing is to see which one seems clearly
    faster or slower, or whether all are similar. You can
    change Gimp's swap directory in the Folders page of the
    Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Supposons que vous préfériez la dernière option et que vous vouliez
    trouver une valeur valable. Vous devez d'abord réunir quelques données
    sur votre ordinateur: la quantité de RAM installée, la taille du
    répertoire d'échange (swap) de votre système, la vitesse du disque dur
    utilisé pour le fichier d'échange du système et le répertoire du fichier
    d'échange de Gimp. Vous n'avez pas besoin de connaître vraiment le
    nombre de tours par minute de vos disques, simplement de savoir quel est
    le plus rapide. Vous pouvez changer le répertoire du fichier d'échange
    de Gimp dans la rubrique Dossiers des Préférences.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    我们假设您喜欢最后一种方式，并想用一个好的值来启动。首先，您需要从您的电脑知道一些数据。您系统安装的内存大小，操作系统可用的交换空间，和存储操作系统交换区和 GIMP 交换目录的磁盘大致速度。您并不需要进行磁盘测试，或检查磁盘的转速，只需知道哪一个看起来要明显得快或慢，或完全相同。您可以在首选项对话框的文件夹页来改变 GIMP 的交换目录。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Další důležitou informací je množství operační paměti vyžadované pro
    aplikace, které chcete používat současně s Gimpem. Spusťte je tedy takovou
    typickou skupinu aplikací (bez Gimpu) a chvíli s ní pracujte. Pak zjistěte
    využití operační paměti, například pomocí aplikací jako je free nebo top,
    podle vašeho operačního systému. Číslo, které vás zajímá, je zbývající
    volná paměť včetně souborové vyrovnávací paměti. Moderní unixové systémy
    ponechávají volnou část paměti velmi malou, aby mohly maximalizovat
    vyrovnávací paměti. Linuxový příkaz <emphasis>free</emphasis> provede vše
    potřebné za vás – požadované číslo najdete ve sloupci „free“ a řádku „-/+
    buffers/cache“. Poznamenejte si i systémový odkládací prostor (řádek
    „swap“).
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    The next thing to do is to see how much resources you require for
    other apps you want to run at the same time than Gimp. So start
    all your tools and do some work with them, except Gimp of course,
    and check the usage. You can use applications like free or top,
    depending in what OS and what environment you use. The numbers you
    want is the memory left, including file cache. Modern Unix keeps a
    very small area free, in order to be able to keep large file and buffer
    caches. Linux's <emphasis>free</emphasis> command does the maths
    for you: check the column that 
    says "free", and the line "-/+ buffers/cache". Note down also the
    free swap
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Ensuite, vous devez déterminer la quantité de mémoire nécessaire pour 
    les applications que vous voulez faire tourner en même temps que Gimp.
    Démarrez toutes vos applications, sauf Gimp, effectuez quelque travail 
    avec, et voyez le taux d'occupation de la mémoire. Sous Linux, les 
    commandes «free» et «top» vous fournissent ces données, en anglais. 
    Avec free, notez la valeur free "-/+ buffers/cache" et le free swap.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    下一件事就是看和 GIMP 一起运行的其它程序需要多少资源。因此启动您的所有工具并在上干些事，当然除了 GIMP，并检查使用率。您可使用 free 或 top 等程序，这和您使用何种 OS 和环境有关。您想知道的是剩余多少内存，包括文件缓冲。现代 Unix 只保留一小部分空闲，而为了保持大量的文件和缓存区缓存。Linux 的 <emphasis>free</emphasis> 命令帮您计算：查看“free”列，“-/+ buffers/cache”行。下面则是 free swap。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Nyní je nutno se rozhodnout, zda chcete veškerou vyrovnávací paměť dlaždic
    uchovávat v operační paměti (RAM), nebo v operační paměti (RAM) a
    systémovém odkládacím prostoru (swap):
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Now time for decisions and a bit of simple math. Basically the
    concept is to decide if you want to base all Tile Cache in RAM, or
    RAM plus operating system swap: 
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    C'est maintenant le temps de la décision et d'un peu de math. L'idée de 
    base est de décider si vous voulez baser tout le cache d'image en RAM ou le 
    partager entre la RAM et le fichier d'échange du système:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    现在是决定和进行一点简单数学计算的时候了，主要是决定是否想要基于 RAM 所有平铺缓存，或 RAM 加上操作系统交换区：
  </para>

  <procedure lang="cs">
    <step><para>
      Přecházíte hodně mezi jednotlivými aplikacemi? Nebo pracujete v Gimpu
      bez přerušení dlouhou dobu? Pokud dlouho bez přerušení setrváváte v
      Gimpu, můžete za volnou paměť považovat volnou operační paměť (RAM) plus
      volný systémový odkládací prostor (swap). Pokud nikoliv nebo si nejste
      jistí, projděte si následující kroky. Pokud naopak víte, že mezi
      jednotlivými aplikacemi přecházíte neustále, berte v úvahu pouze volnou
      operační paměť (RAM) a rovnou přejděte ke konečnému rozhodnutí.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Je systémový odkládací prostor (swap) umístěn na stejném fyzickém disku
     jako odkládací adresář Gimpu? Pokud ano, sečtěte operační paměť (RAM) a
     systémový odkládací prostor (swap). Jinak pokračujte dalším krokem.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Je disk se systémovým odkládacím prostorem (swap) rychlejší nebo stejně
     rychlý jako disk s odkládacím adresářem Gimpu? Pokud ano, sečtěte
     operační paměť (RAM) a systémový odkládací prostor (swap). Pokud je
     pomalejší, berte v úvahu pouze volnou operační paměť (RAM).
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Číslo, které jste získali (množství volné operační paměti nebo volné
     operační paměti včetně systémového odkládacího prostoru) o něco málo
     zmenšete a použijte jako velikost vyrovnávací paměti dlaždic v Gimpu.
   </para></step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure lang="en">
    <step><para>
      Do you change applications a lot? Or keep working in Gimp for a
      long time? If you spend a lot of time in Gimp, you can consider free
      RAM plus free swap as available; if not, you need to go to the
      following steps. (If you're feeling unsure about it,
      check the following steps.) If you are sure you switch apps
      every few minutes, only count the free RAM and just go to the
      final decision; no more things to check.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Does the operating system swap live in the same physical disk as
     Gimp swap? If so, add RAM and swap. Otherwise go to the next
     step. 
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Is the disk that holds the OS swap faster or the same speed as the
     disk that holds the Gimp swap? If slower, take only the free RAM; if
     faster or similar, add free RAM and swap.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     You now have a number, be it just the free RAM or the free RAM plus
     the free OS swap. Reduce it a bit, to be on the safe side, and
     that is the Tile Cache you could use as a good start.
   </para></step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure lang="fr">
    <step><para>
      Vous changez souvent d'application? Ou vous travaillez longtemps sur 
      Gimp? Alors vous pouvez considérer que le partage entre la RAM et le 
      fichier d'échange du système (OS swap) est valable. Sinon, vous allez 
      devoir suivre les étapes suivantes. (Si vous n'êtes pas sûr de vous, 
      passez-les). Si vous êtes certain que vous changez très souvent 
      d'application, ne comptez que la free RAM et passez à la décision 
      finale.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Le fichier d'échange du système opératoire réside sur le même disque 
     physique que le fichier d'échange de Gimp? Alors additionnez RAM et 
     OS swap. Sinon, passez à l'étape suivante.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Le disque portant le fichier d'échange du système est moins rapide que 
     le disque portant le fichier d'échange de Gimp? Alors ne prenez que la 
     free RAM. Sinon, additionnez free RAM et OS swap.
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     Vous avez maintenant un nombre, qu'il s'agisse seulement de la RAM 
     libre ou de la RAM libre plus le fichier d'échange libre du système.
     réduisez-le un peu par sécurité: c'est le cache d'image qu'il vous faut.
   </para></step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure lang="zh_CN">
    <step><para>
      您是否常常变换程序？或在一个很长时间保持 GIMP 工作？如果您在 GIMP 中花费许多时间，您可以考虑空闲 RAM 和可用的空闲交换区。否则，继续看下面步骤。(假如您对此不确定，也继续查看下面的步骤。)如果您确认每几分钟常常转换应用程序，就只把空闲 RAM 算在内，并到最后决定；无须检查更多东西。
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     操作系统交换区是否和 GIMP 交换目录在同一个物理磁盘上：如果是，加上 RAM 和交换区。否则，到下一步。
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     OS 交换区所在磁盘是否比包含 GIMP 交换目录的磁盘速度快或一样？如果更慢，只算空闲 RAM；如果更快或相等，加上 RAM 和交换区。
   </para></step>
   <step><para>
     您现在有一个数字，它要么是空闲 RAM 或空闲 RAM 加上空闲 OS 交换区。为安全起见减少一点，那就是能够有个好的开始的平铺缓冲值。
   </para></step>
  </procedure>


  <para lang="cs">
    Jak vidíte, jde hlavně o zjištění volných systémových zdrojů a rozhodnutí,
    zda se vyplatí používat systémový odkládací prostor (swap).
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    As you can see, all is about checking the free resources, and
    decide if the OS swap is worth using or will cause more problems
    than help.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Comme vous le voyez, tout tourne autour de la question des ressources 
    libres et de savoir s'il vaut le coup d'utiliser l'OS swap ou si ça ne 
    va pas causer encore plus de problèmes.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    正如您看到的，所有这些都是关于检查空闲资源，并决定OS 交换区是否值得使用，是否比它的所带来的帮助产生更多问题。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    V některých případech ale bude nutné takto nastavenou hodnotu upravit.
    Například tehdy, pokud se změní způsob využívání vašeho počítače nebo jeho
    hardwarová konfigurace. Takové změny mohou znamenat, že dříve provedená
    rozhodnutí již neodpovídají skutečnosti. Pak je nejlepší rozhodovací
    proces zopakovat.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    There are some reasons you want to adjust this value, though. The
    basic one is changes in your computer usage pattern, or
    changing hardware. That could mean your assumptions about how you
    use your computer, or the speed of it, are no longer valid. That
    would require a reevaluation of the previous steps, which can
    drive you to a similar value or a completly new value.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Il y a néanmoins de bonnes raisons d'ajuster cetle valeur. La principale 
    est une modification des capacités de votre ordinateur qui peuvent vous 
    permettre d'améliorer la vitesse de Gimp en multi-tâches.
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Dalším důvodem ke změně může být příliš pomalý běh Gimpu, zatímco
    přepínání do jiných aplikací je rychlé. Taková situace znamená, že Gimp
    může využít více paměti, aniž by ohrozil ostatní aplikace. Na druhou
    stranu, pokud si ostatní aplikace stěžují na nedostatek paměti, může být
    lepší vyrovnávací paměť dlaždic Gimpu snížit.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Another reason to change the value is because it seems that Gimp
    runs too slowly, while changing to other applications is fast:
    this means that Gimp could use more memory without impairing the
    other applications. On the other hand, if you get complaints from
    other applications about not having enough memory, then it may
    benefit you to not let Gimp hog so much of it.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Une autre raison est un Gimp trop lent, tandis que les autres 
    applications en multi-tâche fonctionnent normalement. Cela signifie que 
    Gimp pourrait être amélioré sans aggraver la situation des autres 
    applications. L'inverse signifierait que Gimp est trop gourmand.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN"> 
   另一个改变其值的原因是 GIMP 好像运行得太慢，而改给别的程序却快：这意味着 GIMP 能使用更多内存而不会损害其它程序。另一方面，如果其它程序报怨没有足够内存，这就让您知道不该让 GIMP 浪费这么多了。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Pokud jste se rozhodli používat pouze operační paměť (RAM) a Gimp běží
    pomalu, můžete velikost vyrovnávací paměti dlaždic opatrně zvýšit, ale
    nikoliv použít celý systémový odkládací prostor (swap). Pokud je situace
    opačná, používáte RAM + swap, a máte problémy s nedostatkem systémových
    zdrojů, velikost vyrovnávací paměti dlaždic snižte.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    If you decided to use only RAM and Gimp runs slowly, you could try
    increasing the value a bit, but never to use also all the free
    swap. If the case is the contrary, using both RAM and swap, and
    you have problems about lack of resources, then you should
    decrease the amount of RAM available to Gimp.
  </para>

  <para lang='fr'>
    Si vous avez décidé de n'utiliser que la RAM et que Gimp est lent, 
    essayez d'augmenter un peu la valeur mais sans jamais utiliser aussi 
    tout le free swap S'il s'agit au contraire d'utiliser la RAM et 
    l'OS swap, alors vous devez réduire le montant de RAM disponible pour 
    Gimp.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN"> 
    如果您决定只用 RAM，却发现 GIMP 运行得很慢，您能尝试稍微增加点该值，而不要使用任何空想交换区。如果情况刚好相反，使用 RAM 和交换区，并减少 GIMP 可用的 RAM 的数量。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Dobrým řešením je umístit odkládací adresář Gimpu na velmi rychlý disk
    nebo na jiný disk, než na kterém je většina vašich často používaných
    souborů. Rozložení systémového odkládacího prostoru (swap) na několik
    fyzických disků je také dobrý trik pro zvýšení výkonu. No a konečně si
    můžete přikoupit další operační paměť (RAM) nebo nespouštět najednou tolik
    programů.
  </para>
   <para lang='en'>
    Another tricks is to put the Swap Dir in a very fast disk, or in a
    different disk than the one where most of your files
    reside. Spreading the operating 
    system swap over multiple disks is also a good way to speed up
    things, in general. And of course, maybe you have to buy more RAM
    or stop using lots of programs at the same time: you can not
    expect to edit a poster in a computer with 16MB and be fast.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Une autre astuce consiste à placer le répertoire d'échange sur un disque 
    très rapide, ou sur un disque différent de celui où se trouvent la 
    majorité de vos fichiers. Répartir le fichier d'échange du système sur 
    plusieurs disques est aussi, en général, une bonne façon d'accélérer les 
    choses. Et bien sûr, vous pouvez acheter plus de mémoire ou éviter 
    d'utiliser trop de programmes en même temps.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    另一个技巧就是将交换目录设在一个非常快的磁盘，或与您大部分文件所在磁盘不同的磁盘。将操作系统交换区放置在多个磁盘上也是一种加速的好方式。当然，也许您可以买更多的 RAM 或不要同时运行这么多程序：您不能指望在 16 MB 的电脑上编辑招贴画而运行迅速。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Je také dobré udržovat si přehled o pamě'tových nárocích obrázků, se
    kterými parcujete. Čím větší obrázky, čím více dostupných kroků zpět, tím
    více zdrojů je potřeba. Velikost vyrovnávací paměti dlaždic můžete určit i
    podle editovaných obrázků, ale pouze v případě, že vždy pracujete s
    podobnými obrázky.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You can also check what memory requirements your images have. The
    larger the images, and the number of undos, the more resources you
    need. This is another way to choose a number, but it is only good
    if you always work with the same kind of images, and thus the real
    requirements do not vary. It is also helpful to know if you will
    require more RAM and/or disk space. 
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Vous pouvez aussi faire le point sur le besoin en mémoire de vos images, 
    et sur le nombre d'Annulations que vous utilisez. C'est une autre façon 
    de choisir une valeur de cache d'image. Mais ce n'est valable que si vous 
    utilisez à peu près toujours la même taille d'image.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您也能检查您的图像所需内存。更大的图像和撤消数需要更多的资源。这是另一种选取值的方法，不过这只适合一直处理同类的图像，这样其需求才不会改变。这对您是否需要更多的 RAM 或磁盘空间也很有用。
  </para>

</sect1>
