<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-04-14 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-01-22 modified Korean Translation by Dust
  2006-12-10 lexa: made sectinfo docbook compliant
  2006-08-19 Added Norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-22 dust: added ko translation
-->
<sect3 id="gimp-using-setup-tile-cache">
  <title>How to Set Your Tile Cache</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tile cache</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
  This section covers the <guilabel>Tile cache size</guilabel> setting under
  <link linkend="gimp-prefs-system-resources">System Resources</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    During the data processing and manipulation of images, GIMP can use
    a lot of memory. The more you have available, the better.
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses available memory and other resources
    as effectively as possible, striving to let you work on your images
    without more slowdowns than necessary.
   </para>
   <para>
     If GIMP needs more (RAM) memory than you have, it starts storing parts
     of the image data needed to work on your image on a hard disk. These
     parts are called tiles. Access to disk is slower, but at least it allows
     you to keep working. The disk storage is called a cache and the entire
     system is called <quote>tile cache</quote>.
  </para>
  <para>
    The tile cache value determines when GIMP starts using cache instead
    of faster RAM memory.
    A low value for the tile cache means that GIMP sends data to disk more
    quickly then needed, not making good use of the available RAM. Too high a
    value for tile cache, and other applications start to have less system
    resources, forcing them to use swap space and thus slow down, or it may
    cause some of them to start to malfunction or even terminate due to lack
    of RAM.
  </para>
  <para>
    How do you choose a number for the Tile Cache size? Here are some tips to
    help you decide what value to use, as well as a few tricks:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The easiest method is to just forget about this and hope the default
        works. This was a usable method when computers had little RAM, and
        most people just tried to make small images with GIMP while running
        one or two other applications at the same time. If you want something
        easy and only use GIMP to make screenshots and logos, this is probably
        the best solution.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        If you have a modern computer with plenty of memory,
        setting the Tile Cache to half of your RAM will probably give
        good performance for GIMP in most situations without depriving other
        applications. Probably even 3/4 of your RAM would be fine.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Start changing the value a bit each time and check that it goes faster
        and faster with each increase, but the system does not complain about
        lack of memory. Be forewarned that sometimes lack of memory shows up
        suddenly with some applications being killed to make space for the
        others.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Do some simple math and calculate a viable value. Maybe you will have
        to tune it later, but maybe you have to tune it anyway with the other
        previous methods. At least you know what is happening and can get the
        best from your computer.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Let's suppose you prefer the last option, and want to get a good value to
    start with. First, you need to get some data about your computer. This
    data is the amount of RAM installed in your system, the operating system's
    swap space available, and a general idea about the speed of the disks that
    store the operating system's swap and the directory used for GIMP's swap.
    You do not need to do disk tests, nor check the RPM of the disks, the
    thing is to see which one seems clearly faster or slower, or whether all
    are similar. You can change GIMP's swap directory in the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">Folders</link> page of the
    Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para>
    The next thing to do is to see how much resources you require for other
    apps you want to run at the same time as GIMP. So start all your tools
    and do some work with them, except GIMP of course, and check the usage.
    You can use applications like free, top, or Process Explorer, depending on
    what OS and what environment you use. The numbers you want is the memory
    left, including file cache.
  </para>
  <para>
    Linux's <emphasis>free</emphasis> command does the maths for you: check
    the column that says <quote>free</quote>, and the line
    <quote>-/+ buffers/cache</quote>. Note down also the free swap.
  </para>
  <para>
    Now time for decisions and a bit of simple math. Basically the concept is
    to decide if you want to base all Tile Cache in RAM, or RAM plus operating
    system swap:
  </para>
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
        Do you change applications a lot? Or keep working in GIMP for a long
        time? If you spend a lot of time in GIMP, you can consider free RAM
        plus free swap as available; if not, you need to go to the following
        steps. (If you're feeling unsure about it, check the following steps.)
        If you are sure you switch apps every few minutes, only count the free
        RAM and just go to the final decision; no more things to check.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Does the operating system swap live in the same physical disk as GIMP
        swap? If so, add RAM and swap. Otherwise go to the next step.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Is the disk that holds the OS swap faster or the same speed as the
        disk that holds the GIMP swap? If slower, take only the free RAM; if
        faster or similar, add free RAM and swap.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        You now have a number, be it just the free RAM or the free RAM plus
        the free OS swap. Reduce it a bit, to be on the safe side, and that is
        the Tile Cache you could use as a good start.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
    As you can see, all is about checking the free resources, and decide if
    the OS swap is worth using or will cause more problems than help.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are some reasons you want to adjust this value, though. The basic
    one is changes in your computer usage pattern, or changing hardware. That
    could mean your assumptions about how you use your computer, or the speed
    of it, are no longer valid. That would require a reevaluation of the
    previous steps, which can drive you to a similar value or a completely
    new value.
  </para>
  <para>
    Another reason to change the value is because it seems that GIMP runs too
    slowly, while changing to other applications is fast: this means that GIMP
    could use more memory without impairing the other applications. On the
    other hand, if you get complaints from other applications about not having
    enough memory, then it may benefit you to not let GIMP hog so much of it.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you decided to use only RAM and GIMP runs slowly, you could try
    increasing the value a bit, but never to use also all the free swap. If
    the case is the contrary, using both RAM and swap, and you have problems
    about lack of resources, then you should decrease the amount of RAM
    available to GIMP.
  </para>
  <para>
    Another trick is to put the Swap Dir on a very fast disk, or on a
    different disk than the one where most of your files
    reside. Spreading the operating
    system swap file over multiple disks is also a good way to speed
    things up, in general. And of course, you might have to buy more RAM
    or stop using lots of programs at the same time: you can not
    expect to edit a poster on a computer with insufficient RAM and be fast.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can also check what memory requirements your images have. The larger
    the images, and the number of undo steps, the more resources you need. This
    is another way to choose a number, but it is only good if you always work
    with the same kind of images, and thus the real requirements do not vary.
    It is also helpful to know if you will require more RAM and/or disk space.
  </para>
</sect3>
