<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id='gimp-using-simpleobjects' lang="en">
  <title lang="en">Drawing Simple Objects</title>

  <para lang="en">
    This sections will give you an introduction about the creation of
    simple objects in <acronym>Gimp</acronym>. It's pretty simple once
    you figured out how to do it. <acronym>Gimp</acronym> provides a
    huge set of <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">Tools</link>
    and Shortcuts in which most new users are lost. 
  </para>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-line" lang="en">
    <title lang="en">Drawing a straight line</title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Painting Tools</primary>
      <secondary>Straight Line</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      Lets begin by painting a straight line. The easiest way to create a
      straight line is by using your favorite <link
      linkend="gimp-tool-painting">painting tool</link>, the mouse and
      the keyboard.
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <title lang="en">Drawing a straight line</title>

      <step>
        <figure id="gimp-using-straightline1">
          <title lang='en'>
            The dialog shows a new image, filled with a white background.
          </title>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/straightline1.png'
                format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          Create a <link linkend="gimp-file-new">new image</link>.
          Select your favorite <link linkend="gimp-tool-painting">paint
          tool</link> or use the <link
          linkend="gimp-tool-pencil">pencil</link> if in doubt.  Select
          a <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-color-area">foreground
          color</link>, but be sure, that foreground and background
          color are different.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <figure id="gimp-using-straightline2">
          <title lang='en'>
            The dialog shows a new image, with the first dot indicating
            the start of the straight line. The dot has a black foreground
            color.
          </title>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/straightline2.png'
                format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          Create a start point by clicking on the <link
          linkend="co-imagewindow-display">image display</link> area
          with the left mouse button. Your canvas should look
          similar to <xref linkend="gimp-using-straightline1" />.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <figure id="gimp-using-straightline3">
          <title lang='en'>
            The screenshot shows the helpline, which indicates how the
            finished line will look like.
          </title>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/straightline3.png'
                format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          Now, hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap> button on your
          keyboard and move the mouse away from the created start point.
          You'll see a thin line indicating how the line will look like.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <figure id="gimp-using-straightline4">
          <title lang='en'>
            The created line appears in the image window after drawing
            the second point (or end point), while still having the
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> key pressed.
          </title>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/straightline4.png'
                format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          If you're satisfied with the line direction and length, click
          again the left mouse button to finish the line.  The
          <acronym>Gimp</acronym> shows a straight line now.  Please
          check the foreground and background color and if the
          <keycap>Shift</keycap> key was still pressed during painting
          in case no line appears. You can continuously creating lines by
          still holding the <keycap>Shift</keycap> and create additional
          end points.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='gimp-using-rectangular' lang="en">
    <title lang="en">Creating a Basic Shape</title>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Drawing shapes is not the main purpose for what the
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is used. Shapes are created either by
          painting them using the technique described in <xref
          linkend="gimp-using-straightline1" /> or by using the
          selection tools. Off course, there are various other ways to
          paint a shape, but we'll stick to the easiest ones here.  So,
          create a <link linkend="gimp-file-new">new image</link> and
          check that <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-color-area">foreground
          and background colors</link> are different.
        </para>
      </step>
      
      <step>
        <figure id="gimp-using-basicshape1">
          <title lang='en'>
            The screenshot shows how a rectangular selection is created.
            Move the mouse in the direction of the red arrow by holding
            the left mouse button pressed.
          </title>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/basicshape1.png'
                format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          Basic shapes like a rectangular, triangle or ellipse can be
          created using the <link
          linkend="gimp-tools-selection">selection tools</link>. The
          tutorial uses a rectangular selection as an example.  So,
          choose the <link linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select">rectangular
          selection tool</link> and create a new selection: hold the
          left mouse button pressed while moving the mouse to other
          positions in the image (illustrated in figure <xref
          linkend="gimp-using-basicshape1" />). The selection is created
          if you leave leave the mouse button pressed.  For more
          information about key modifiers look at the <link
          linkend="gimp-tools-selection">selection tools</link>.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <figure id="gimp-using-basicshape2">
          <title lang='en'>
            The screenshot shows how a rectangular selection fill with
            the foreground color.
          </title>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/using/basicshape2.png'
                format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          After creating the selection, you can either create a filled
          or an outlined shape with the foreground color of your choice.
          If you go for the first option, choose a <link
          linkend="gimp-toolbox-color-area">foreground color</link> and
          fill the selection with the <link
          linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">bucket fill tool</link>.
          If you choose the latter option, create an outline by using
          the<link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">Stroke
          selection</link> menu item from the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
          menu. If you're satisfied with the result, <link
          linkend="gimp-selection-none">remove the selection</link>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
