<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-using-toolbox' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title lang="en">The Main Toolbox</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/toolbox-description-en.png' format='png'/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Main Toolbox is the heart of the Gimp.  It is the only part of
    the application that you cannot duplicate or close.  Here is a
    quick tour of what you will find there.  
  </para>

  <tip lang='en'>
    In the Toolbox, as in most parts of Gimp, moving the mouse on top
    of something and letting it rest for a moment will usually bring
    up a "tooltip" message that may help you understand what the thing
    is or what you can do with it.  Also, in many cases you can press
    the <keycap>F1</keycap> key to get help about the thing that is
    underneath the mouse. 
  </tip>

  <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Toolbox Menu</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          This menu is special:  it contains some commands that cannot
          be found in the menus that are attached to images.  (Also
          some that can.)  These include commands for setting
          preferences, creating certain types of dialogs, etc.  The
          contents are described systematically in the <link
          linkend='gimp-tools-menu'>Toolbox Menu</link> section.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Tool icons</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          These icons are buttons that activate tools for a wide
          variety of purposes: selecting parts of images, painting on
          them, transforming them, etc.  The <link
          linkend='gimp-using-tools'>Using Tools</link> section gives
          an overview of how to work with tools, and each tool is
          described systematically in the <link
          linkend='gimp-toolbox'>Tools</link> chapter.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Foreground/Background colors</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          The color areas here show you Gimp's current foreground and
          background colors, which come into play in many operations.
          Clicking on either one of them brings up a color selector
          dialog that allow you to change to a different color.
          Clicking on the double-headed arrow swaps the two colors,
          and clicking on the small symbol in the lower left corner
          resets them to black and white.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Brush/Pattern/Gradient</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          The symbols here show you Gimp's current selections for: the
          Paintbrush, used by all tools that allow you to paint on the
          image ("painting" includes operations like erasing and
          smudging, by the way); for the Pattern, which is used in
          filling selected areas of an image; and for the Gradient,
          which comes into play whenever an operation requires a
          smoothly varying range of colors.  Clicking on any of these
          symbols brings up a dialog window that allows you to change
          it. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='en'>Active Image</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          (This is a new feature in Gimp 2.2) In Gimp, you can work
          with many images at once, but at any 
          given moment, one of them is the "active image".  Here you
          find a small iconic representation of the active image.
          Clicking on it brings up a dialog with a list of all the
          currently open images, allowing you to make a different one
          active if you want to.  (Clicking on the window where the
          image is displayed will accomplish the same thing, though.)  
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>
</sect2>
