<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-02-09 lexa: fixed de bug #515187 "german translation of internet"
  2007-03-25 lexa: reviewed de
  2006-09-19 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-27 Added Korean Translation by Mr.Dust
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
  050930 de replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
  050829 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-web">
<!--  <sect1info>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-07-15</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>-->
  <title>
    <phrase>Preparing your Images for the Web</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Web</primary>
    <secondary>Images for the web</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    One of the most common purposes <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is used for
    is to prepare images for adding them to a web site. This means that
    images should look as nice as possible while keeping the file
    size as small as possible.  This little step-by-step guide will tell
    you how to achieve a smaller file size with minimal degradation of
    image quality.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="gimp-using-web-size-vs-quality">
    <title>
      <phrase>Images with an Optimal Size/Quality Ratio</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      An optimal image for the web depends upon the image type and the file
      format you have to use. If you want to put a photograph with a lot of
      colors online, you have to use
      <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link>
      as your primary file format. If your image contains fewer colors, that
      is, if it is not a photograph, but is more a drawing you created (such
      as a button or a screenshot), you would be better off using
      <link linkend="file-png-load">PNG</link>
      format. We will guide you through the process of doing this.
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          First, open the image as usual. I have opened our Wilber as an
          example image.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            <phrase>The Wilber image opened in RGBA mode.</phrase>
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/preparing_for_web1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          The image is now in RGB mode, with an additional
          <link linkend="glossary-alpha">Alpha channel</link>
          (RGBA). There is usually no need to have an alpha channel for your
          web image. You can remove the alpha channel by
          <link linkend="gimp-image-flatten">flattening the image</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you open a photograph, you probably won't have to remove the
          alpha channel, because a photograph doesn't usually have one, so the
          file is already opened in RGB mode.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            If the image has a soft transition into the transparent areas, you
            cannot remove the alpha channel, since the information which would
            be used for fading out will not be saved in the file. If you would
            like to save an image with transparent areas which do not have a
            soft transition, (similar to
            <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF</link>),
            you can remove the alpha channel.
          </para>
        </note>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          After you have flattened the image, you are able to
          <link linkend="gimp-file-save">save the image</link>
          in <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG format</link>
          for your web site.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <note>
      <para>
        You can save your image in PNG format with the default settings, but
        using maximum compression. Doing this will have no negative affects on
        the quality of the picture, as it would have with
        <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link>
        format. If your image is a photograph with lots of colors, you would
        be better off saving it as jpeg. The main thing is to find the best
        tradeoff between quality and compression. You can find more
        information about this topic in <xref linkend="file-jpeg-save"/>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="gimp-using-web-reducing-file-size">
    <title>
      <phrase>Reducing the File Size Even More</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      If you want to reduce the size of your image a bit more, you could
      convert your image to Indexed mode. That means that all of the colors
      will be reduced to only 256 values. Converting images with smooth color
      transitions or gradients to indexed mode will often give poor results,
      because it will turn the smooth gradients into a series of bands. This
      method is also not recommended for photographs because it will make the
      image look coarse and grainy.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>The indexed image</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/preparing_for_web2.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            An indexed image can look a bit grainy. The left image is Wilber
            in its original size, the right one is zoomed in by 300 percent.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para><!-- 2007-03-25 enhanced by lexA -->
          Use the command described in <xref linkend="gimp-image-mode"/>
          to convert your RGB image to indexed mode.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          After you have converted the image to indexed mode, you are once
          again able to <link linkend="gimp-file-save">save</link> your
          image in <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG
          format</link>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="gimp-using-web-transparency">
    <title>
      <phrase>Saving Images with Transparency</phrase>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Transparency</primary>
      <secondary>Saving images with transparency</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      There are two different approaches used by graphic file formats
      for supporting transparent image areas: simple binary transparency
      and alpha transparency. Simple binary transparency is supported
      in <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF</link> format. Here, one color
      from the indexed color palette is marked as the transparent color.
      Alpha transparency is supported in <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link> format.  Here, the
      transparency information is stored in a separate channel, the
      <link linkend="glossary-alpha">Alpha channel</link>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        There is usually no need to save images in GIF format any more,
        because PNG supports all the features of GIF and offers additional
        features (e.g., alpha transparency). Nevertheless, this format is
        still used for animations.
      </para>
    </note>
    <procedure>
      <title>
        <phrase>
          Creating an Image with Transparent Areas (Alpha Transparency)
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <step>
        <para>
          First of all, we will use the same image as in the previous
          tutorials, Wilber the GIMP mascot.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            <phrase>The Wilber Image Opened in RGBA Mode.</phrase>
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/preparing_for_web1.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To save an image with alpha transparency, you must have an alpha
          channel. To check if the image has an alpha channel, go to the
          <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">channel dialog</link> and
          verify that an entry for <quote>Alpha</quote> exists, besides
          Red, Green and Blue. If this is not the case, <link linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add">add a new alpha channel</link>
          from the layers menu.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          You can now remove the background layer to get a completely
          transparent background, or create a gradient from color to
          transparency. You are only limited by your imagination. To
          demonstrate the capabilities of alpha transparency, we'll make a
          soft glow in the background around our Wilber.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          After you're done with your image, you can
          <link linkend="gimp-file-save">save</link> it in
          <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG format</link>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>
          Mid-Tone Checks in the background layer represent the transparent
          region of the saved image while you are working on it in
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/preparing_for_web-alphatransparency.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
