<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-03-17 alex falappa: added 'it'
  2008-02-17 ude: created 'en','de'
-->
<sect2 id="script-fu-glossy-logo-alpha">
  <title>Glossy</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Alpha to Logo</secondary>
    <tertiary>Glossy</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Glossy</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example for the <quote>Glossy</quote> filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/logo-glossy.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>The <quote>Glossy</quote> filter</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/glossy-script-fu.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>The <quote>Glossy</quote> logo</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      This filter applies gradients and patterns to the alpha. A slight 3D
      effect will be added using a bump map, and optionally the filter adds a
      drop shadow.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Here, as a language shortcut, we use <emphasis>alpha</emphasis> to
        mean the area of the active layer defined by the non-transparent
        pixels. You may think of it as a selection <quote>by
        visibility</quote>. Applying any effect <quote>to the alpha</quote>
        just means to apply this effect to all visible pixels of the active
        layer.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      The filter is derived from the <quote>Glossy</quote> script
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Create</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Logos</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Glossy</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> in the image window),
      which creates a logo (see above) with a glossy outlook when used with
      the default options, thus the name.
    </para>
    <para>
      This filter only works if the active layer has an alpha channel.
      Otherwise, the menu entry is insensitive and grayed out.
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>
        The image will always be resized to the active layer's size.
      </para>
    </warning>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activate the filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the image window menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Alpha to Logo</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Glossy</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Glossy</quote> options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/alpha-to-logo/glossy-options.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Blend gradient (text)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By default, the filter will fill the alpha with a
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">gradient blend</link>. Clicking on
            the swatch button will open a simple
            <link linkend="gimp-gradient-dialog">gradient dialog</link>, where
            you may select any gradient. <quote>Text</quote> refers to the
            <quote>Glossy</quote> logo, which creates a logo from a text, and
            is meaningless here.
          </para>
          <para>
            When <guilabel>Text gradient reverse</guilabel> is checked, the
            alpha will be filled with a gradient blend starting at the bottom.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pattern (text)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When <guilabel>Use pattern for text instead of gradient</guilabel>
            is checked, the alpha  will be filled with a pattern. You can open
            a <link linkend="gimp-pattern-dialog">patterns dialog</link> to
            select a pattern of your choice by clicking on the
            <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button. The preview area on the left
            will produce a popup preview of the current pattern when pressed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Outline size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the size of a kind of border, realised with a layer
            containing an enlarged copy of the alpha (details see below).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Blend gradient (outline); Pattern (outline)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Just like the <quote>text</quote> options for the active layer,
            these options specify the gradient or pattern (when <guilabel>Use
            pattern for outline instead of gradient</guilabel> is checked)
            used to fill the outline area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use pattern overlay</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, the original, not enlarged alpha of the outline
            layer will be filled with the specified pattern using the overlay
            <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint-options">mode</link>, so that the
            pattern and the previous contents (pattern or gradient) will be
            merged.
          </para>
          <para>
            Again, clicking on <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button will open
            a <link linkend="gimp-pattern-dialog">patterns dialog</link>,
            pressing the preview icon will produce a popup preview of the
            current pattern.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Default bumpmap settings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option does nothing, the filter will always apply a
            <link linkend="plug-in-bump-map">bump map</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Background color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The color of the background layer added by the filter. When you
            click on the color button, a
            <link linkend="gimp-color-dialog">color select dialog</link> pops
            up.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shadow</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Optionally the filter creates a layer containing a
            <link linkend="script-fu-drop-shadow">drop shadow</link>. The
            shadow layer will be moved <guilabel>Shadow X offset</guilabel>
            pixels to the right and <guilabel>Shadow Y offset</guilabel>
            pixels down. Note that this may enlarge the image, while the
            background layer will keep the size of the active layer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Filter details</title>
    <para>
      The numerous options may give the impression that this is a very
      complicate filter, but actually it is fairly simple. The interesting
      part is how the filter handles the active layer and the outline layer:
    </para>
    <para>
      In the active layer, the filter creates a
      <link linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-selection-replace">selection from the
      alpha channel</link> and fills the selection with the specified gradient
      blend or pattern.
    </para>
    <para>
      Then a new <quote>outline</quote> layer below the active layer will be
      created in a similar way: First, the active layer's alpha will be used
      to make a selection. But before filling the selection with a gradient or
      a pattern, the selection will be
      <link linkend="gimp-selection-grow">enlarged</link> by <guilabel>Outline
      size</guilabel> pixels.
    </para>
    <para>
      When you filled both layers with the same pattern or gradient blend, you
      will still see a border (<quote>outline</quote>), because
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          a 3D effect will be applied to the outline layer using the active
          layer as a <link linkend="plug-in-bump-map">bump map</link>;
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">layer mode</link> of
          the active layer will be set to <quote>Screen</quote>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The last (optional) step is to fill the outline layer with a pattern,
      using the <quote>overlay</quote> layer
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint-options">mode</link>. This will combine
      the pattern with the pattern or gradient used before. To learn more
      about the result of using the overlay mode, see the description in
      <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes"/>.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
