<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-10-20 j.h: initial version
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-metadata-editor">
  <title>Metadata Editor</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Metadata</primary>
    <secondary>Metadata Editor</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The metadata editor allows you to edit the most common XMP metadata tags.
    Tags that have a corresponding IPTC tag are synchronized when writing the
    metadata. When opening the editor, the IPTC metadata is also checked. When
    only IPTC is available, the values of those tags are used to fill in the
    XMP metadata fields. If both are available, but different, they are in
    most cases concatenated.
  </para>
  <para>
    It is currently not possible to edit Exif metadata.
  </para>
  <para>
    When you are finished editing the metadata press the
    <guibutton>Write Metadata</guibutton> button to update the metadata in
    the image, or use <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> if you don't want your
    changes to be added to the image. <guibutton>Write Metadata</guibutton>
    does not save the metadata to a file. Do that the usual way by saving or
    exporting your image.
  </para>
  <para>
    The metadata editor currently consists of the following tabs:
    <link linkend="gimp-metadata-editor-description">Description</link>,
    <link linkend="gimp-metadata-editor-iptc">IPTC</link>,
    <link linkend="gimp-metadata-editor-iptc-extension">IPTC Extension</link>,
    <link linkend="gimp-metadata-editor-categories">Categories</link>,
    <link linkend="gimp-metadata-editor-gps">GPS</link>, and
    <link linkend="gimp-metadata-editor-dicom">DICOM</link>. We will explain these in more detail below.
    At the bottom of the editor there is also a <guilabel>Select:</guilabel>
    drop-down button, where you can choose to <guilabel>Import
    metadata</guilabel> or <guilabel>Export metadata</guilabel>.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <quote>Metadata Editor</quote> dialog
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/menus/image/metadata-editor-dialog.png"
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <para>
      You can access this command from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Metadata</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Edit Metadata</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>General considerations when adding metadata to an image</title>
    <para>
      Adding metadata to an image is a good way to give others some general
      information about your image, like a description what the image is about,
      where it was taken if it is a photo, the creator and more specific
      Copyright information.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is good to realize that certain kinds of information can also be used
      to reveal personal information about you or others in the image. You have
      to make your own decision about what you are comfortable with in sharing
      with others.
    </para>
    <para>
      More specific, things like a GPS location, your name, an address, or
      recognizable people or buildings in an image may be used to identify
      you or others.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-metadata-editor-description">
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Description</guilabel> tab allows you to edit metadata
      that relates to general information about the image, such as the image
      creator, a description of the image, Copyright, etc.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Document Title</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Document Title</guilabel> field is used to give a
            short name consisting of text and/or numbers to reference your image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Author</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Author</guilabel> field is used to tell who made
            the image. Multiple names, one per line, can be entered here.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Author Title</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Author Title</guilabel> field is used to tell the
            job title of the creator of the image. This will generally only
            be useful if you created this image as part of your job.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Description</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Description</guilabel> field is used to give a longer
            description of your image. Sometimes this is also used to add
            Copyright information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Description Writer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Description Writer</guilabel> field is used to
            identify the person who wrote or edited the description metadata.
            Multiple names can be entered, separated by a comma.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rating</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Rating</guilabel> field is used to give a quality
            rating to this image. The drop-down list allows you to select a
            value from 1 to 5, or leave it unrated.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Keywords</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Keywords</guilabel> field allows you to add keywords
            to the image. Keywords are words or sentences that describe your
            image. Multiple keywords can be added; each keyword should be
            entered on its own line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Copyright Status</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Copyright Status</guilabel> field is used to tell
            what sort of Copyright the image has. You can choose between
            <guilabel>Unknown</guilabel> (default),
            <guilabel>Copyrighted</guilabel> (someone owns or claims the
            copyright for this image), or <guilabel>Public Domain</guilabel>
            (the rights to this image have been released to the Public Domain).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Copyright Notice</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Copyright Notice</guilabel> field allows you to
            write a text specifying what Copyright is attached to this image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Copyright URL</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>Copyright URL</guilabel> field can be used to
            direct the viewers of this image to an online website where more
            details can be found about the Copyright on this image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-metadata-editor-iptc">
    <title>IPTC</title>

    <figure>
      <title>IPTC tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/image/metadata-editor-dialog-iptc.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>IPTC</guilabel> tab allows you to edit more detailed
      creator, location and credits information, based on the IPTC metadata.
      As explained above, you have to decide what information you want to share.
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Contact Information</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These fields serve as contact information for the person or
            organization this image belongs to.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Address</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the address.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>City</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the city.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>State / Province</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the state or province.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Postal Code</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the postal code or zip code.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Country</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the country.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Phone(s)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the phone number(s).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Email(s)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the email address(es).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Website(s)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the website(s).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Creation Date</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This field is used to enter the date and optionally the time this
            image was created. This is not necessarily the same as the date and
            time a photo was taken.
          </para>
          <para>
            The button next to this field allows you to select a date. However,
            this does not let you to pick a time. You will have to enter that
            manually.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Intellectual Genre</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Describes the nature, intellectual, artistic or journalistic
            characteristic of an image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>IPTC Scene Code</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Describes the scene of an image. Specifies one or more terms from
            the IPTC "Scene-NewsCodes". Each Scene Code should be on a separate
            line and consists of a string of 6 digits.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Location Information</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These fields serve to identify the image location.
            All of the fields in this section are considered legacy, meaning
            you usually would not use these to add new information.
          </para>
          <para>
            We recommend instead to use similar named fields in the
            <guilabel>IPTC Extension</guilabel> tab for better compatibility
            with other apps using metadata.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Sublocation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the location shown in the image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>City</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the city.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>State / Province</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the state or province.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Country</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the name of the country.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Country ISO-Code</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the ISO code of a country.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Urgency</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A field originally defined by Photoshop and nowadays considered
            deprecated and mostly left alone.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Headline</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A brief synopsis of the caption. According to the IPTC
            <guilabel>Headline</guilabel> is not the same as
            <guilabel>Document Title</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="metadata-editor-iptc-subject-code">
        <term>IPTC Subject Code</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Specifies one or more subjects from the
            <ulink url="">IPTC Subject-NewsCodes</ulink> to
            categorize the image. Each subject is represented as a string of
            8 digits; each subject should be on a separate line.
            This field is also considered deprecated and rarely used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Job Identifier</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A field used to identify the job this image belongs to in a
            business environment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Instructions</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A field with instructions from the creator of the image to the
            receiver.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Credit Line</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A field that specifies who to give credit when using this image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A field that specifies the name of a person or party who had a role
            in the content supply chain of making the image. This can be
            someone else than the creator.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Usage Terms</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A field specifying the license for using this image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-metadata-editor-iptc-extension">
    <title>IPTC Extension</title>

    <figure>
      <title>IPTC Extension tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/image/metadata-editor-dialog-iptc-extension.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>IPTC Extension</guilabel> is an extension of the original
      IPTC metadata specification that allows more detailed information.
      In most cases it is recommended to enter your information here instead
      of similar fields in the IPTC tab.
    </para>
    <para>
      A lot of the metadata fields here are specifically targeted at
      professional use cases in organizations. There is no need to fill in all
      fields. You can limit yourself to what is relevant for you.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Person Shown</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This field can be used to list the names of persons in an image.
            Each name should be listed on a separate line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Information about the location the image was created</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Sublocation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the location.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>City</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the city.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>State / Province</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the state or province.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Country</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the name of the country.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Country ISO-Code</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the ISO code of a country.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>World Region</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This field is used to enter the name of the region of the
                  world.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="metadata-editor-editing-tables">
        <term>Editing metadata information in tables</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            We use tables to show and edit certain types of metadata. This is a
            short overview of how to edit data in a table.
          </para>
          <para>
            In a table, each row lists information about one specific event or
            occurrence, where each column pertains to one specific part of that
            information. Multiple rows can be added when needed.
          </para>
          <para>
            Below each table you see two buttons, one with a plus sign, to
            add a new row, and another with a minus sign, to remove an
            existing row.
          </para>
          <para>
            To edit the metadata in one of the columns, first select the
            corresponding row by clicking on it. Then double-click on the
            column you want to edit. You will see an edit cursor in that field
            that will allow you to add and change the text in that field.
          </para>
          <para>
            If you make a mistake while editing, you can use the
            <keycap>Esc</keycap> key to cancel your changes. If you are content
            with your text, use <keycap>Enter</keycap> or click somewhere else
            inside the table to finalize the change. If you click outside the
            table, the changes are cancelled.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Location Shown</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify one or more locations that are
            shown in your image. The columns use the same basic data as that
            for the location created shown at the top of this tab page.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Featured Organization</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify one or more names of organizations
            that are shown in your image, one per row.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Organization Code</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify one or more organization codes
            related to the organizations that are shown in your image,
            one per row.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Event</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This field allows you to enter the name or description of the event
            at which this image was taken.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Artwork or Object</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify one or more pieces of artwork or
            objects that are shown in your image, one per row.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The following types of metadata can be entered in the respective
            columns.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Title</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The title of the artwork or object.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Date Created</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The date and optionally the time the artwork or object was
                  created.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Creator</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The name of the artist that created the artwork or object.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Source</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The organization registering the artwork or object in the
                  image for inventory purposes.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Source Inventory ID</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The inventory identification issued by the source organization
                  for the artwork or object in the image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Copyright Notice</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The copyright notice for claiming the intellectual property
                  for the artwork or an object in the image.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Additional Model Info</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Information about the model(s) in the image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Model Age</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            List the age(s) of the models shown in the image, one per line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Minor Model Age Disclosure</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Age of the youngest model pictured in the image, at the time that
            the image was taken. Select one of the options from the
            drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Model Release Status</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enter information about the model releases, that authorize usage.
            Select one of the options from the drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Model Release Identifier</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify one or more model release
            identifiers that identify model release documents of models shown
            in your image, one per row.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Supplier Name</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The name of the supplier of the image, which is not necessarily
            the owner or creator.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Supplier ID</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The ID that identifies the supplier of the image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Supplier's Image ID</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The ID by which the supplier identifies the image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Registry Entry</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify a Registry Organization identifier
            and an Item identifier to record any registration of this image
            with a registry.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Max Available Width</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The maximum width in pixels of the original photo from which this
            image has been derived.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Max Available Heigth</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The maximum heigth in pixels of the original photo from which this
            image has been derived.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Digital Source Type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The type of the source of this digital image. Select one of the
            values from the drop-down list. This lists the values from the
            official <ulink
              url="https://cv.iptc.org/newscodes/digitalsourcetype/">Digital
            Source Type NewsCodes vocabulary</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Creator</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to enter the names and optionally
            identifiers of the creator(s) of the image, one creator per line.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Copyright Owner</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to enter the names and optionally
            identifiers of the copyright owner(s) of the image, one per line.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Licensor</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify details about the persons or
            organizations that can be contacted for obtaining a license to
            use this image, one per row.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The following types of metadata can be entered in the respective
            columns.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Name</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The name of a licensor.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Identifier</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The identifier with which the licensor can be identified.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Phone number 1</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The phone number at which the licensor can be reached.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Phone type 1</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The type of phone number can be selected from a drop-down
                  list.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Phone number 2</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The phone number at which the licensor can be reached.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Phone type 2</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The type of phone number can be selected from a drop-down
                  list.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Email address</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The email address at which the licensor can be reached.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Web address</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The website at which the licensor can be reached.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Property Release Status</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enter information about the property releases, that authorize usage
            of the properties appearing in the image.
            Select one of the options from the drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Property Release Identifier</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This table allows you to specify one or more property release
            identifiers that identify property release documents of properties
            shown in your image, one per row.
          </para>
          <para>
            For information about editing metadata in a table, see
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-editing-tables">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-metadata-editor-categories">
    <title>Categories</title>

    <figure>
      <title>Categories tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/image/metadata-editor-dialog-categories.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>Categories</guilabel> tab allows you to edit metadata
      that indicates what categories an image belongs to.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Category</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The category this image belongs to, usually a three-letter code.
          </para>
          <para>
            This is a deprecated field and should generally not be used to add
            new information. Use
            <link linkend="metadata-editor-iptc-subject-code">IPTC
            Subject Code</link> on the IPTC tab instead.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Supplemental Category</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The supplemental category this image belongs to, consisting of
            free-form text. This is a deprecated field and should generally not
            be used to add new information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-metadata-editor-gps">
    <title>GPS</title>

    <figure>
      <title>GPS tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/image/metadata-editor-dialog-gps.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>GPS</guilabel> tab allows you to edit metadata
      related to GPS information, the information that shows you at what
      exact location the image was taken.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Longitude</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The longitude part of the GPS location information. Note that
            this will only be valid and saved when the Longitude Reference
            is also set and not Unknown.
          </para>
          <para>
            This information is usually already set when taking an image with
            a digital camera.
          </para>
          <para>
            Valid values consist of 1, 2 or 3 numbers that specify the degrees,
            minutes, and seconds of the longitude.
          </para>
          <para>
            See the following examples:
            <literal>10deg 15' 20"</literal>, or
            <literal>10\u00b0 15' 20"</literal>, or
            <literal>10:15:20.45</literal>, or
            <literal>10 15 20</literal>, or <literal>10 15.30</literal>, or
            <literal>10.45</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Longitude Reference</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The longitude reference part of the GPS location information.
            This is required to be set for a valid longitude.
            Choose either <guilabel>East</guilabel> or <guilabel>West</guilabel>
            from the drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Latitude</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The latitude part of the GPS location information. Note that
            this will only be valid and saved when the Latitude Reference
            is also set and not Unknown. See longitude for information on
            how to enter this information.
          </para>
          <para>
            This information is usually already set when taking an image with
            a digital camera.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Latitude Reference</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The latitude reference part of the GPS location information.
            This is required to be set for a valid latitude.
            Choose either <guilabel>North</guilabel> or <guilabel>South</guilabel>
            from the drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Altitude</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The altitude part of the GPS location information, which
            is the height above, or below sea level. Note that
            this will only be valid and saved when the Altitude Reference
            is also set and not Unknown.
            The button to the right of this field let's you choose whether
            the altitude is specified in meters (m) or feet (ft).
            A valid value consists of one number, e.g. 100, or 12.24.
          </para>
          <para>
            This information is sometimes already set when taking an image with
            a digital camera.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Altitude Reference</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The altitude reference part of the GPS location information.
            This is required to be set for a valid altitude.
            Choose either <guilabel>Above sea level</guilabel> or
            <guilabel>Below sea level</guilabel> from the drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-metadata-editor-dicom">
    <title>DICOM</title>

    <figure>
      <title>DICOM tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/image/metadata-editor-dialog-dicom.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The <guilabel>DICOM</guilabel> tab allows you to edit metadata
      that relates to so-called DICOM metadata. That is medical information,
      usually related to x-ray images.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most images usually don't have this kind of information, these fields
      are empty most of the time. Even if you have images that contain this
      information, you should consider removing most if not all of this
      metadata when you intend to share it, since it can be highly sensitive
      personal health information.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Patient</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The name of the patient.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Patient ID</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The ID of the patient.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Date of birth</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The birth date of the patient.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Patient Sex</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Select the sex of the patient from the drop-down list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Study ID</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Study ID that identifies the specific study for which this
            image was used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Referring Physician</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The physician that referred the patient.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Study Date</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The date that the study took place.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Study Description</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A description of the study that was performed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Series number</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The series number of this image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Modality</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The date that the study took place.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Series date</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The date this series images was taken.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Series Description</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A description of this series.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Equipment Institution</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The institution that owns the equipment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Equipment Manufacturer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The maker of the equipment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Importing and Exporting metadata</title>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Select:</guilabel> drop-down button at the bottom of the
      dialog, is where you can choose to Import or Export metadata.
      A good way to have your metadata filled with pre-defined information,
      is to open a new image without metadata, then in the metadata editor
      fill in all fields that you care about.
      You then choose <guilabel>Export metadata</guilabel> here and save it
      under a name you can remember. Next time you need to fill in your
      information, you choose <guilabel>Import metadata</guilabel>, then select
      the file to read that information from, and all metadata fields will be
      overwritten or filled with the information you saved previously.
    </para>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
