<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-11-28 j.h: no change for v2.4
  2007-09-26 AntI: Added 'es'
  2005-01-07 en;fr reviewed by j.h
  2005/10/30 reviewed, de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-print-size">
  <title>Print Size</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Printing</primary>
    <secondary>Size and resolution</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Resolution</primary>
    <secondary>Printing</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Print size</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Print Size</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    This command opens the <quote>Set Image Print Resolution</quote> 
    dialog that allows you to change the <emphasis>dimensions of a printed 
    image</emphasis> and its <emphasis>resolution</emphasis>. This command 
    does not change the number of pixels in the image and it does not 
    resample the image. (If you want to change the size of an image by 
    resampling it, use the 
    <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scale Image</link> command.)
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Dialog</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this dialog from the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Print Size…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options in the <quote>Print Size</quote> Dialog</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Set Image Print Resolution</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/image/print-size.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The output resolution determines the number of pixels used per unit
      length for the printed image. Do not confuse the output resolution
      with the printer's resolution, which is a printer feature and expressed
      in dpi (dots per inch); several dots are used to print a pixel.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the dialog is displayed, the resolution shown in the boxes is the
      resolution of the original image. If you increase the output
      resolution, the printed page will be smaller, since more pixels are
      used per unit of length. Conversely, and for the same reason,
      resizing the image modifies the resolution.
    </para>
    <para>
      Increasing the resolution results in increasing the sharpness of the
      printed page. This is quite different from simply reducing the image
      size by scaling it, since no pixels (and no image information) are
      removed.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Width</term>
        <term>Height</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can set the printing Width and Height by using the
            text boxes. You can also choose the units for these values
            from the drop-down list.
          </para>
          <para>
            As soon as you change the Width or the Height, the X and/or
            Y resolution values automatically change accordingly. If the
            two resolution values remain linked, the relationship of the
            width to the height of the image is also automatically
            maintained. If you would like to set these values independently
            of each other, click on the
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-vchain.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            chain symbol to break the link.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>X resolution</term>
        <term>Y resolution</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can set the resolution used to calculate the printed
            width and height from the physical size of the image, that is,
            the number of pixels in it.
          </para>
          <para>
            Use the text boxes to change these resolution values.
            They can be linked to keep their relationship constant. The
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-vchain.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            closed chain symbol between the two boxes indicates that the
            values are linked together. If you break the link by clicking
            on the chain symbol, you will be able to set the values
            independently of each other.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              The default resolution unit used for the X and Y resolution
              may depend on the type of image you imported. PNG images that
              have a resolution set, are known to be imported with the
              unit set to metric, meaning you will see pixels/mm here in that
              case.
            </para>
            <para>
              GIMP currently does not have a preference that overrides the
              unit set in the image. However, if you change it here (and press
              OK to exit the dialog), it will be remembered for the current
              session.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
