<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-06-09 j.h: update to 2.8
  2007-11-28 j.h: updated v2.4. Lanczos interpolation added
  2007-09-26 AntI: Added 'es'
  2006-07-23 note added about the Scale tool by j.h
  2005/06/18 en Link added
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-scale">
  <title>Scale Image</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Scale Image</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Scale Image</guimenuitem> command enlarges or reduces
    the physical size of the image by changing the number of pixels it
    contains. It changes the size of the contents of the image and resizes
    the canvas accordingly.
  </para>
  <para>
    It operates on the entire image. If your image has layers of different
    sizes, making the image smaller could shrink some of them down to nothing,
    since a layer cannot be less than one pixel wide or high. If this happens,
    you will be warned before the operation is performed.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you only want to scale a particular layer, use the
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-scale">Scale Layer</link> command.
  </para>
  <anchor id="gimp-image-scale-warning"/>
  <note>
    <para>
      If scaling would produce an image larger than the
      <quote>Maximum new image size</quote> set in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-system-resources">System Resources</link> page
      of the Preferences dialog (which has a default of 128 MiB), you are
      warned and asked to confirm the operation before it is performed.
      You may not experience any problems if you confirm the operation, but
      you should be aware that very large images consume a lot of resources and
      extremely large images may take more resources than you have,
      causing <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to crash or not perform well.
    </para>
  </note>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this command from the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Scale Image…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>The <quote>Scale Image</quote> Dialog</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Scale Image</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/image/scale-image.png"/>
          <!--was: images/dialogs/scale-image.png-->
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You should keep in mind that an image can be located in one of
            four places: in the image file, in RAM after it has been loaded,
            on your screen when it is displayed, or on paper after it has been
            printed. Scaling the image changes the number of pixels (the
            amount of information) the image contains, so it directly affects
            the amount of memory the image needs (in RAM or in a file).
          </para>
          <para>
            However printing size also depends upon the resolution of the
            image, which essentially determines how many pixels there will
            be on each inch of paper. If you want to change the printing
            size without scaling the image and changing the number of pixels
            in it, you should use the
            <link linkend="gimp-image-print-size">Print Size</link> dialog.
            The screen size depends not only on the number of pixels, but
            also on the screen resolution, the zoom factor and the setting
            of the <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Dot for Dot</link>
            option.
          </para>
          <para>
            If you enlarge an image beyond its original size,
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> calculates the missing pixels by
            interpolation, but it does not add any new detail. The more you
            enlarge an image, the more blurred it becomes. The appearance of
            an enlarged image depends upon the interpolation method you
            choose. You may improve the appearance by using the
            <link linkend="gimp-filter-unsharp-mask">Sharpen (Unsharp 
            Mask)</link> filter after you
            have scaled an image, but it is best to use high resolution when
            you scan, take digital photographs or produce digital images by
            other means. Raster images inherently do not scale up well.
          </para>
          <para>
            You may need to reduce your image if you intend to use it on a web
            page. You have to consider that most internet users have
            relatively small screens which cannot completely display a large
            image, for example on mobile devices.
          </para>
          <para>
            Adding or removing pixels is called <quote>Resampling</quote>.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Width</term>
              <term>Height</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  When you click on the <guimenuitem>Scale</guimenuitem>
                  command, the dialog displays the dimensions of the
                  original image in pixels. You can set the
                  <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and the
                  <guilabel>Height</guilabel> you want to give to your
                  image by adding or removing pixels. If the
                  <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-vchain.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
                      </imageobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                  </guiicon>
                  chain icon next
                  to the Width and Height boxes is unbroken, the Width and
                  Height will stay in the same proportion to each other. If
                  you break the chain by clicking on it, you can set them
                  independently, but this will distort the image.
                </para>
                <para>
                  However, you do not have to set the dimensions in pixels.
                  You can choose different units from the drop-down menu.
                  If you choose percent as the units, you can set the image
                  size relative to its original size. You can also use
                  physical units, such as inches or millimeters. If you do
                  that, you should set the <guilabel>X resolution</guilabel>
                  and <guilabel>Y resolution</guilabel> fields to
                  appropriate values, because they are used to convert
                  between physical units and image dimensions in pixels.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>X resolution</term>
              <term>Y resolution</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  You can set the printing resolution for the image in the
                  <guilabel>X resolution</guilabel>
                  and <guilabel>Y resolution</guilabel>
                  fields. You can also change the units of measurement by
                  using the drop-down menu.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Quality</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            To change the image size, either some pixels have to be removed
            or new pixels must be added. The process you use determines the
            quality of the result. The <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel>
            drop-down list provides a selection of available methods of
            interpolating the color of pixels in a scaled image:
          </para>
          <para>
            Interpolation methods are described in 
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-interpolation-methods"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <note>
      <para>
        See also the <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scale tool</link>,
        which lets you scale a layer, a selection or a path.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
