<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-04-24 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-09-09 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id='plug-in-newsprint' lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no;ru">
  <sect2info lang="de" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-18</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Newsprint</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Novinový tisk</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Zeitungsdruck</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Papel de periódico</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Trame d'imprimerie</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Effetto giornale</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Avistrykk</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Газетная бумага</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Distorts</secondary>
    <tertiary>Newsprint</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Newsprint</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Novinový tisk</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary><secondary>Verzerren</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Zeitungsdruck</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Druckraster</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Filtros</primary>
    <secondary>Distorsiones</secondary>
    <tertiary>Papel de periódico</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Papel de periódico</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Distorsions</secondary>
    <tertiary>Trame d'imprimerie</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Trame d'imprimerie</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary><secondary>Distorsioni</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Effetto giornale</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Forvrengningar</secondary>
    <tertiary>Avistrykk</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Avistrykk (filter)</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Газетная бумага</primary></indexterm>

  <!--TODO cs it ru: Move this to "Options"-->
  <mediaobject lang="cs;it;ru">
    <imageobject lang="en;cs;es;it;ru">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-distort-newsprint.png'
        format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Přehled</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Wirkungsweise</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Generalidades</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Oversyn</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;it;ru">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Applying example for the Newsprint filter
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Anwendungsbeispiel für das Filter <quote>Zeitungsdruck</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Ejemplo de aplicación del filtro papel de periódico
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Exemple d'application du filtre Trame d'Imprimerie
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di applicazione del filtro Effetto giornale
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på bruk av filteret</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          То же изображение до применения фильтра <quote>Газетная бумага</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="en;de;es;no">
          <para lang="en">Original image</para>
          <para lang="de">Originalbild</para>
          <para lang="es">Original</para>
          <para lang="no">Originalbiletet</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/examples/distort-taj-newsprint.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="en;de;es;no">
          <para lang="en">Filter <quote>Newsprint</quote> applied</para>
          <para lang="de">Filter <quote>Zeitungsdruck</quote> angewandt</para>
          <para lang="es">
            Filtro <quote>Papel de periódico</quote> aplicado
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Etter bruk av filteret <quote>Avistrykk</quote>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distorts</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Newsprint</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter halftones the image using a clustered-dot dither. Halftoning
      is the process of rendering an image with multiple levels of grey or
      colour (i.e. a continuous tone image) on a device with fewer tones;
      often a bi-level device such as a printer or typesetter.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The basic premise is to trade off resolution for greater apparent tone
      depth (this is known as spatial dithering).
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      There are many approaches to this, the simplest of which is to throw
      away the low-order bits of tone information; this is what the posterize
      filter does. Unfortunately, the results don't look too good. However, no
      spatial resolution is lost.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter uses a clustered-dot ordered dither, which reduces the
      resolution of the image by converting cells into spots which grow or
      shrink according to the intensity that cell needs to represent.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Imagine a grid super-imposed on the original image.  The image is
      divided into cells by the grid - each cell will ultimately hold a single
      spot made up of multiple output pixels in order to approximate the
      darkness of the original image in that cell.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Obviously, a large cell size results in a heavy loss in resolution! The
      spots in the cells typically start off as circles, and grow to be
      diamond shaped. This change in shape is controlled by a <guilabel>spot
      function</guilabel>. By using different spot functions, the evolution
      in the shape of the spots as the cell goes from fully black to fully
      white may be controlled.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Zkreslení</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Novinový tisk</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr <!-- FIXME: cs content missing -->
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Základní myšlenkou je zvýšení zdánlivé barevné hloubky na úkor
      rozlišení (tzv. prostorové rozptylování, angl.
      <foreignphrase>spatial dithering</foreignphrase>).
    </para>
    <para lang="cs"><!-- FIXME: cs-->
      Existuje řada způsobů, jak snížit množství barev. Jedním z nich je
      zahození bitů nízkého řádu z barevné informace – přesně to dělá filtr
      Posterizovat. Výsledky však nevypadají příliš dobře (není-li cílem
      zvláštní efekt). Nicméně se tak neztrácí prostorové rozlišení.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter rastert das Bild unter Verwendung von im Zeitungsdruck
      üblichen Algorithmen. Rasterung ist ein Prozess, bei welchem ein Bild
      mit vielen verschieden Farben so aufbereitet wird, dass es auf einem
      Ausgabegerät, welches nur über wenige Farben verfügt, optimal
      dargestellt werden kann. Druckmaschinen sind typischerweise solche
      Geräte. Es gibt in der Wikipedia einen interessanten
      <ulink url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Druckraster">Artikel</ulink>,
      der sich mit diesem Thema beschäftigt.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der grundsätzliche Ansatz besteht darin, Bildauflösung zu Gunsten einer
      besseren Farbdarstellung zu <quote>opfern</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Es gibt viele verschiedene Algorithmen, um dies zu erreichen. Einer der
      einfachsten besteht darin, einen Teil der Farbinformationen (die
      niederwertigen Bits der Farbinformationen) einfach
      <quote>wegzuwerfen</quote> - das ist genau das, was Sie mit dem Werkzeug
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-posterize">Posterisieren</link> erreichen
      können. Allerdings ist das Ergebnis dieser Methode oft nicht
      befriedigend, dafür bleibt die Auflösung vollständig erhalten.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter verwendet einen Algorithmus, der die Auflösung des Bildes
      reduziert, indem Pixel zu Zellen zusammengefasst werden, welche je nach
      erforderlicher (Farb-)Intensität mehr oder weniger vollständig gefüllt
      werden.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Stellen Sie sich ein Gitter vor, welches über das originale Bild gelegt
      wird. Das Bild wird damit in Gitterzellen geteilt. Jede Zelle enthält
      genau einen Farbpunkt, dessen Größe die originale Helligkeit des
      Ausgangsbildes annähernd wiedergibt.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Offensichtlich führt eine große Zellengröße zu einem starken Verlust
      an Auflösung! Die Punkte in den Zellen starten typischerweise in Form
      eines kleinen Kreises. Wenn eine stärkere Füllung nötig ist, nehmen sie
      die Form eines Karos an. Diese Veränderung der Form können Sie in den
      Eigenschaften des Filters beeinflussen.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Puede encontrar este filtro en
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtros</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distorsiones</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Papel de periódico</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Este filtro hace un fotograbado de la imagen usando un motivo de puntos
      agrupados. Halftoning es el proceso de representación de una imagen con
      múltiples niveles de gris o color (p.e. una imagen de tono continuo) en
      un dispositivo con pocos tonos; a menudo, un dispositivo de dos niveles
      como una impresora.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      La premisa básica es sacrificar la resolución por una aparentemente
      mayor profundidad tonal (esto se conoce como spatial dithering).
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Hay muchas aproximaciones a esto, la más sencilla es ignorar los bits
      de menos peso de la información tonal; es lo que hace el filtro
      posterizar. Desafortunadamente, los resultados no parecen demasiado
      buenos. Sin embargo, no se pierde resolución espacial.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Este filtro usa un motivo de puntos agrupados ordenados, que reducen
      la resolución de la imagen al convertir las celdas en puntos que crecen
      o se encogen según la intensidad que las celdas necesitan representar.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Imagine una rejilla superimpuesta sobre la imagen original. La imagen
      se divide en celdas por la rejilla- cada celda mantendrá un punto
      compuesto de múltiples píxeles para aproximar la luminosidad de la
      imagen original a la celda.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      ¡Obviamente, un tamaño grande de celda producirá una perdida grande en
      la resolución! Los puntos en las celdas asumen, tipicamente, la forma
      de círculo, y crecen hacia una forma de diamante. Este cambio en la
      forma se controla con <guilabel>Función de puntos</guilabel>. Mediante
      el uso de las diferentes funciones de puntos, se puede controlar la
      evolución en las formas de los puntos como de la celda que va desde
      completamente negro a completamente blanco.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve dans
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distorsions</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Trame d'Imprimerie</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il fournit une image qui ressemble aux images en similigravure, en
      pointillés que l'on voit dans les journaux et qui deviennent plus
      précises quand on les regarde d'un peu loin. Il y a une trame de
      pointillés pour chacune des couleurs primaires RVB ou CMJ et il n'y a
      qu'un seul ton dans chaque trame (chaque trame subit un nivellement
      tonal en demi-teinte). Chaque trame est un peu décalée par rapport aux
      autres et c'est la fusion des couleurs vues à distance qui crée
      l'impression de nuances. La couleur sera plus ou moins foncée selon que
      la taille de chaque point sera plus ou moins grande.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En dehors de ces questions d'impression, le filtre est surtout utilisé
      pour des effets artistiques.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre utilise une méthode en pointillés groupés (clustered dots) qui
      réduit la résolution en transformant des cellules en points plus ou
      moins gros selon l'intensité (plus ou moins foncé) à représenter.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Imaginez une grille superposée à l'image. Elle divise l'image en
      cellules. Le contenu de chaque cellule sera finalement transformé en un
      «point» plus ou moins gros selon l'intensité de la cellule. Ce processus
      est appliqué à chacun des canaux de couleur, constituant ainsi des
      trames de chacune des couleurs RVB ou CMJ.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Évidemment, des cellules de grande taille entraîneront une
      grosse perte de résolution! Les points ont d'abord une forme
      circulaire puis s'accroissent progressivement pour prendre une
      forme en losange. Ce changement de forme est contrôlé par la
      <guilabel>Fonction point</guilabel>. En utilisant différentes
      Fonctions point, on peut contrôler la forme des points selon
      l'évolution des cellules du noir au blanc.
    </para>


    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro si trova nel menu immagine:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtri</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>D</accel>istorsioni</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Effet<accel>t</accel>o giornale</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro rende l'immagine a mezzitoni utilizzando un motivo a
      gruppi di punti. La resa in mezzitoni è un procedimento di resa delle
      immagini a più livelli di grigio o di colore (cioè un'immagine a toni
      continui) su un dispositivo con capacità tonali inferiori; spesso si
      tratta di dispositivi a due soli livelli come una stampante o una
      stampatrice tipografica.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il principio di base è quello di sacrificare la risoluzione a vantaggio
      di una maggiore profondità tonale apparente (questo procedimento è
      anche noto come dithering spaziale).
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono molteplici approcci il più semplice dei quali è quello di
      ignorare i bit meno significativi dell'informazione tonale, questo è ciò
      che fa il filtro di posterizzazione. Sfortunatamente i risultati non
      sono ottimali. Tuttavia la risoluzione spaziale non si perde.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro usa un motivo a gruppi di punti ordinati che riduce la
      risoluzione dell'immagine convertendo celle in punti che si
      ingrandiscono o si riducono a seconda dell'intensità rappresentata dalla
      cella.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Si immagini di sovrapporre una griglia all'immagine originale.
      L'immagine viene suddivisa in celle, ogni cella conterrà un singolo
      punto corrispondente a più pixel allo scopo di approssimare la
      luminosità dell'immagine originale in quella cella.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Naturalmente una grande dimensione delle celle produrrà una grande
      perdita di risoluzione. I punti delle celle tipicamente assumono la
      forma di cerchi e via via crescendo si trasformano in quadrangoli.
      Il cambiamento di forma è controllato da una <guilabel>funzione
      spot</guilabel>. Utilizzando funzioni spot differenti si può controllare
      l'evoluzione della forma dei punti man mano che si procede dal nero
      completo al bianco completo.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du har tilgang til filteret frå biletmenyen via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Forvrengningar</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Avistrykk</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dette filteret rasterer biletet og gir ein effekt ikkje ulik den som blir
      brukt på avisbilete. Difor namnet. Rastering er ein prosess der bilete
      med mange ulike fargar blir omforma slik at dei kan trykkast på
      maskiner med få fargar og likevel sjå tilnerma ut som originalen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Det grunnleggande i denne prosesse er å minska oppløysinga for
      å oppnå ein tilsynelatande betre fargedjupn. (Såkalla
      <quote>spatiell utjamning</quote> ).
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Det er mange måtar å gjere dette på. Den enklaste er rett og slett å
      fjerna dei minst viktige informasjonane om tonestyrke, slik
      verktøyet <link linkend="gimp-tool-posterize">posterisering</link>
      gjer det. Denne metoden gir ikkje alltid like godt resultat, men
      biletoppløysinga blir i alle fall uendra.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dette filteret bruker ein metode som går ut på å redusera
      biletoppløysinga ved å omforma biletmceller til større eller mindre
      punkt, avhengig av intensiteten punktet skal representere.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Tenk deg at det blir lagt eit rutenett over biletet. Dette rutenettet
      vil dele biletet opp i celler som kvar inneheld eit fargepunkt sett
      saman av gjennomsnittet av pikslane i cella. Storleiken på cella
      blir bestemt ut frå intensiteten i originalbiletet.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dersom desse cellen er store, vil dette sjølvsagt føre til merkbar
      dårlegare oppløysing i biletet. Punkta i cellene er som oftast frå
      først av sirklar, men blir meir rombeforma når dei blir større.
      Denne endringa av utsjånaden kan kontrollerast av kontrollen
      <guilabel>Punktfunksjon</guilabel>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр находится в
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Фильтры</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Искажение</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Газетная бумага</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр преобразует изображение в полутоновые точки, чтобы добиться
      эффекта газетной печати. Полутонирование - создание изображения со
      многими уровнями серого или цвета (т.е. слитный тон) на аппарате с
      меньшим количеством тонов, обычно чёрно-белый принтер.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В принципе, задача в том чтобы уменьшить разрешение, увеличивая видимую
      глубину тона (так называемое пространственное полутонирование).
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Существуют много путей достижения эффекта. Простейший заключается в
      выбрасывании нижние биты тоновой информации; это делается фильтром
      <quote>Posterize</quote>. Результат выглядит неважно, но
      пространственное разрешение не потеряно.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр использует полутонирование сгрупированными точками. Это
      уменьшает разрешение изображения за счёт преобразования ячеек в капли,
      которые уменьшаются или увеличиваются в зависимости от того,
      какой цвет нужно передать.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Представте сетку, наложенную на начальное изображение. Изображение
      разделено сеткой на ячейки, каждая из которых будет содержать одну
      каплю, состоящее из группы точек. Интенсивность точек выбирается так,
      чтобы приблизить результат к темноте ячейки начального изображения.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Чем больше размер ячейки, тем меньше разрешение. Пятна в ячейках
      сначала круглой формы, а потом принимают форму ромба. Форма капли
      определяется параметром <guilabel>Капельная функция</guilabel>. Выбирая
      разные функции капли, можно контролировать эволюцию капли, когда ячейка
      переходит из полностью чёрной в полностью белую.
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3 lang="de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Filteraufruf</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter lässt sich über das Menü
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Ver<accel>z</accel>erren</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>eitungsdruck</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      im Bildfenster aufrufen.
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;no;ru">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
            <quote>Newsprint</quote> filter options
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
            Eigenschaften für das Filter <quote>Zeitungsdruck</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
            Opciones del filtro <quote>Papel de periódico</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
            Options du filtre <quote>Trame d'imprimerie</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for filteret <quote>Avistrykk</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры фильтра <quote>Газетная бумага</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;es;ru">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-distort-newsprint.png'
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/de/options-distort-newsprint.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-distort-newsprint.png'
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/no/options-distort-newsprint.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="cs">Náhled</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="es">Vista previa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <term lang="it">Anteprima</term>
        <term lang="no">Førehandsvising</term>
        <term lang="ru">Просмотр</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            All your setting changes will appear in the Preview without
            affecting the image until you click on <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.
            Note that the preview displays the whole image, even if the
            final result will concern a selection. Don't keep
            <emphasis>Do Preview</emphasis> checked if your computer is too
            much slow.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Všechny změny se promítnou v náhledu ještě před stisknutím
            tlačítka <guibutton>Budiž</guibutton> a aplikací do obrázku.
            Náhled zobrazuje celý obrázek, i když se výsledek bude týkat pouze
            výběru. Vypnutí volby <emphasis>Náhled</emphasis> může pomoci na
            slabších strojích.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In der Vorschau wird ein Ausschnitt des Bildes so dargestellt,
            als wäre das Filter mit den aktuellen Einstellungen auf das Bild
            angewandt worden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Todos sus cambios aparecerán en la vista previa sin afectar a la
            imagen hasta que pulse <guilabel>Aceptar</guilabel>.
            Nótese que la vista previa muestra la imagen entera, aunque el
            resultado final concierna a una selección. No marque 
            <emphasis>Vista previa</emphasis> si su ordenador es lento.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            L'Aperçu fournit une vignette de l'image reproduisant tous les
            réglages effectués sans agir sur l'image jusqu'à ce que vous
            cliquiez sur <guilabel>Valider</guilabel>. Notez qu'il donne un
            aperçu de toute l'image, même si le résultat final ne portera
            que sur une sélection. Il ne sera effectué que si la case est
            cochée, cette option étant surtout utile pour les ordinateurs
            lents.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Tutte le regolazioni dei parametri appariranno nell'anteprima
            senza essere riportate sull'immagine fino alla pressione del
            pulsante <guilabel>OK</guilabel>. Si noti che l'anteprima mostra
            l'intera immagine anche se il risultato finale interesserà solo
            la selezione. Non si selezioni l'opzione <emphasis>Anteprima</emphasis>
            se si possiede un computer particolarmente lento.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Førehandsvisinga syner endringane i biletet etter kvart som du
            endrar parametra. Endringane blir ikkje lagt inn i biletet før du
            trykker på knappen <guilabel>OK</guilabel>. Legg merke til at
            førehandsvisinga i dette filteret i noen oppsett viser heile biletet
            sjølv om du bare arbeider på ein del av det.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Результат изменения настроек появится в <quote>Просмотре</quote>,
            не изменяя изображение пока вы не нажмёте кнопку
            <guilabel>OK</guilabel>. В <quote>Просмотре</quote> показано всё
            изображение, даже если работа ведётся только над выделением.
            Выбор <emphasis>Автопросмотр</emphasis> требует больших ресурсов
            и быстрого компьютера.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Resolution</term>
        <term lang="cs">Rozlišení</term>
        <term lang="de">Auflösung</term>
        <term lang="es">Resolución</term>
        <term lang="fr">Résolution</term>
        <term lang="it">Risoluzione</term>
        <term lang="no">Oppløysing</term>
        <term lang="ru">Разрешение</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This group controls the cell size, either by setting the input and
            output resolutions, or directly.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">Zde se nastavuje velikost buněk.</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Gruppe von Eigenschaften können Sie die Größe der
            Zellen einstellen. Dies geschieht entweder durch Einstellen der
            Ein- und Ausgabeauflösung oder direkt.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Este grupo controla el tamaño de la celda, configurando las
            resoluciones de entrada y salida, o directamente.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette rubrique permet le contrôle de la taille des cellules soit
            en réglant les résolutions d'entrée et de sortie soit directement.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo gruppo controlla la dimensione delle celle impostando la
            risoluzione di ingresso e di uscita oppure in maniera diretta.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Denne gruppa kontrollerer cellestorleiken, anten ved å setje
            storleiken direkte eller ved å setje verdiar for oppløysinga for
            inngang og utgang.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Эта группа определяет размер ячейки, либо задавая вводное или
            выходное разрешение, либо напрямую.
          </para>

          <variablelist lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;ru">
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Input SPI</term>
              <term lang="de">Eingabe-SPI</term>
              <term lang="es">Muestras/pulgada de entrada</term>
              <term lang="fr">D'entrée (EPP)</term>
              <term lang="it">SPI in ingresso</term>
              <term lang="no">Inngangs-SPI</term>
              <term lang="ru">SPI на входе</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Input SPI</guilabel>
                  : Resolution of the original input image, in Samples Per
                  Inch (SPI). This is automatically initialised to the input
                  image's resolution.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Eigenschaft stellen Sie die Auflösung (Punkte pro
                  Zoll) des Originalbildes ein. Diese Eigenschaft wird
                  automatisch aus der im Bild hinterlegten Auflösung
                  eingestellt.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>SPI de entrada</guilabel>
                  : Resolución de la imagen original de entrada, en muestras
                  por pulgada (SPI). Se inicializa automaticamenteal entrar
                  la resolución de la imagen.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>D'entrée (EPP)</guilabel>: Résolution de l'image
                  d'origine, en entrée (Echantillons Par Pouce). Cette valeur
                  est initialisée automatiquement à la résolution que possède
                  déjà l'image en entrée.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>SPI in ingresso</guilabel>: Risoluzione dell'immagine
                  originale in Campioni Per Pollice (Samples Per Inch ovvero
                  SPI in inglese).  Questo valore è automaticamente impostato
                  alla risoluzione propria dell'immagine.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Inngangs-SPI</guilabel>:
                  <quote>SPI</quote> er eit mål for oppløysing. (Forkorting for
                  det engelske <quote>Samples Per Inch</quote>. Denne verdien
                  blir sett automatisk ut frå oppløysinga til originalbiletet.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>SPI на входе</guilabel>: Разрешение начального
                  изображения, в Замерах на дюйм (Samples Per Inch SPI).
                  Этот параметр автоматически установлен на разрешение
                  входного изображения.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Output LPI</term>
              <term lang="de">Ausgabe-LPI</term>
              <term lang="es">Líneas/pulgada de salida</term>
              <term lang="fr">De sortie (LPP)</term>
              <term lang="it">LPP in uscita</term>
              <term lang="no">Utgangs-LPI</term>
              <term lang="ru">LPI на выходе</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Output LPI</guilabel>: Desired output
                  resolution, in Lines Per Inch (LPI).
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie die gewünschte
                  Ausgabeauflösung (Zeilen pro Zoll) einstellen.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>LPI de salida</guilabel>: La resolución deseada
                  de salida, en líneas por pulgadas (LPI).
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>De sortie (LPP)</guilabel>: Résolution de sortie
                  souhaitée, en Lignes Par Pouce. C'est la linéature.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>LPP in uscita</guilabel>: Desired output
                  resolution, in Lines Per Inch (LPI).
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Utgangs-LPI</guilabel>:
                  <quote>LPI</quote> er eit anna mål for oppløysing.
                  (Forkorting for det engelske <quote>Lines Per
                  Inch</quote>. Her kan du setje ønskt oppløysing for
                  utgangen, dvs. det ferdige biletet.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>LPI на выходе</guilabel>: выходное разрешение,
                  в линиях на дюйм (Lines Per Inch LPI).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Cell Size</term>
              <term lang="de">Zellgröße</term>
              <term lang="es">Tamaño de celda</term>
              <term lang="fr">Taille des cellules</term>
              <term lang="it">Dimensione cella</term>
              <term lang="no">Cellestorleik</term>
              <term lang="ru">Размер ячейки</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Cell Size</guilabel>: Resulting cell size, in
                  pixels.  Most often you will want to set this directly.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Zellgröße wird automatisch aus den Werten Ein- und
                  Ausgabeauflösung berechnet. Sie können diese aber auch
                  direkt einstellen, in diesem Fall wird die Ausgabeauflösung
                  entsprechend angepasst.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Tamaño de celda</guilabel>: Tamaño de las celdas
                  resultantes, en píxeles. Es la opción que se utiliza más
                  frecuentemente.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Taille des cellules</guilabel>: Il s'agit de
                  cellules carrées, en pixels. C'est l'option que vous
                  utiliserez le plus souvent.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Dimensione cella</guilabel>: dimensione finale
                  delle celle in pixel. Il più delle volte questo è il valore
                  da regolare.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Cellestorleik</guilabel>: Dette er den vanlegaste
                  måten å bestemma oppløysinga på. Set du cellestorleiken
                  direkte, vil oppløysinga stille seg inn automatisk.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Размер ячейки</guilabel>: конечный размер ячейки,
                  в пикселях. Обычно рамер параметра устанавливается напрямую.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Screen</term>
        <term lang="cs">Obrazovka</term>
        <term lang="de">Schirm</term>
        <term lang="es">Pantalla</term>
        <term lang="fr">Trames</term>
        <term lang="it">Schermo</term>
        <term lang="no">Skjerm</term>
        <term lang="ru">Экран</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Určuje způsob separace.
          </para>

          <variablelist lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;ru">
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Separate To RGB, CMYK, Intensity</term>
              <term lang="de">Separiere nach RGB; CMYK; Intensität</term>
              <term lang="es">Separar a RGB, CMYK, Intensidad</term>
              <term lang="fr">Séparer en RVB, CMJN, Intensité</term>
              <term lang="it">Separa in RGB, CMYK, Intensità</term>
              <term lang="no">Separer til RGB, CMYK, Intensitet</term>
              <term lang="ru">Разделить на RGB, CMYK, Интенсивность</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Separate To RGB, CMYK, Intensity</guilabel>:
                  Select which colorspace you
                  wish to operate in.  In <emphasis>RGB</emphasis> mode, no
                  colorspace conversion is performed. In
                  <emphasis>CMYK</emphasis>, the image is first
                  internally converted to CMYK, then each colour channel is
                  separately halftoned, before finally being
                  recombined back to an RGB image.
                  In <emphasis>Intensity</emphasis> mode, the
                  image is internally converted to grayscale,
                  halftoned, then the result used as the alpha channel
                  for the input image.  This is good for special
                  effects, but requires a little experimentation to
                  achieve best results.  Hint: try CMYK if you don't know
                  which to go for initially.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, für welchen
                  Farbraum die Separation vorgenommen wird. In der Einstellung
                  <guilabel>RGB</guilabel> wird keine Farbraumkonvertierung
                  vorgenommen. In der Einstellung <guilabel>CMYK</guilabel>
                  wird das Bild zunächst in den CMYK-Farbraum konvertiert und
                  dann wird die Separation vorgenommen. Abschließend wird
                  das Bild zurück in den RGB-Farbraum transformiert. In der
                  Einstellung <guilabel>Intensität</guilabel> wird das Bild
                  intern zunächst in ein Graustufenbild konvertiert und dann
                  als Transparenzkanal für die Separation verwendet. Diese
                  Einstellung ist sehr gut für spezielle Effekte geeignet.
                  Wenn Sie nicht sicher sind, welche Einstellung die richtige
                  ist, sei Ihnen <guilabel>CMYK</guilabel> empfohlen.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Separar a RGB, CMYK, Intensidad</guilabel>:
                  Selecciona el espacio de color con el que desea operar.
                  En modo <emphasis>RGB</emphasis>, no se realiza conversión
                  del espacio de color. En <emphasis>CMYK</emphasis>,
                  primero, la imagen se convierte, internamente, a CMYK,
                  entonces a cada canal de color se hace mediotono,
                  separadamente, para finalmente recombinarlos a una imagen
                  RGB. En modo <emphasis>Intensidad</emphasis>, La imagen se
                  convierte, internamente, a escala de grises, mediotono, y
                  el resultado se usa como canal alfa de la imagen de
                  entrada. Esto es bueno para efectos especiales, pero
                  requiere experimentar para conseguir los mejores
                  resultados. Se sugiere el modo CMYK para iniciarse.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Séparer en RVB, CMJN, Intensité</guilabel>:
                  Vous permet de choisir dans quel espace de couleur vous
                  voulez opérer. En mode <emphasis>RVB</emphasis>, aucune
                  conversion d'espace de couleur n'est effectuée. En mode
                  <emphasis>CMJN</emphasis>, l'image est d'abord convertie
                  en CMJN, puis chaque canal de couleur subit un nivellement
                  tonal avant d'être finalement recombinés en une image RVB.
                  En mode <emphasis>Intensité</emphasis>, l'image est
                  convertie en niveaux de gris, subit un nivellement tonal
                  et le résultat est utilisé comme canal Alpha pour l'image
                  d'entrée. Cette option convient aux effets spéciaux, mais
                  nécessite plusieurs essais vant d'obtenir le meilleur
                  résultat. Un conseil: essayez CMJN si vous ne savez pas
                  par quoi commencer.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Separa in RGB, CMYK, Intensità</guilabel>:
                  Seleziona lo spazio di colore in cui si vuole operare.
                  In modalità <emphasis>RGB</emphasis> non viene effettuata
                  alcuna conversione dello spazio di colore. In modalità
                  <emphasis>CMYK</emphasis> l'immagine è dapprima convertita
                  internamente nello spazio CMYK, poi ciascun canale di colore
                  viene reso a mezzotinta separatamente prima di essere
                  nuovamente ricombinato in una immagine RGB.
                  In modalità <emphasis>Intensità</emphasis> l'immagine viene
                  convertita internamente in scala di grigi, resa a
                  mezzotinta poi il risultato viene usato come canale alfa
                  per l'immagine in ingresso. E' utile per effetti speciali ma
                  richiede un po' di sperimentazione per ottenere risultati
                  interessanti. Si suggerisce di utilizzare la modalità CMYK
                  per iniziare.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Separer til RGB, CMYK, Intensitet</guilabel>:
                  Her bestemmer du kva for fargemodell biletet skal lagast
                  i. I <emphasis>RGB</emphasis>-modus blir biletet ikkje
                  forandra. Vel du <emphasis>CMYK</emphasis> vil biletet
                  først bli omforma til CMYK, deretter blir kvar fargekanal
                  gjort om til halvtoner og endeleg sett saman igjen til
                  eit RGB-bilete. Desse omformingane skjer internt i filteret.
                  I modus <emphasis>Intensitet</emphasis> blir biletet
                  omforma internt i filteret til gråskala, halvtoner, og
                  resultatet blir brukt som ein alfakanal for inngangsbiletet.
                  Denne metoden kan gi ein del spesielle effektar, men krev
                  ein del eksperimentering. Er du usikker på kva metode
                  du skal velje, er det sikraste å byrja med CMYK.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Разделить на RGB, CMYK, Интенсивность</guilabel>:
                  Определяет цветовую модель для работы. В режиме
                  <emphasis>RGB</emphasis> цветовая модель не преобразуется.
                  В режиме <emphasis>CMYK</emphasis>, изображение сначала
                  преобразуется (внутренне) в CMYK, затем каждый цветовой
                  канал полутонируется отдельно, и результат преобразуется
                  обратно в RGB.
                  В режиме <emphasis>Интенсивность</emphasis>, изображение
                  сначала преобразуется (внутренне) в серое, полутонируется,
                  и результат используется как канал альфа для входного
                  изображения. Это полезно для спец-эффектов, но требует
                  экспериментирования для лучших результатов. Подсказка:
                  Если вы не знаете, какой выбрать, попробуйте
                  <emphasis>CMYK</emphasis>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Black Pullout (%)</term>
              <term lang="de">Schwarz-Auszug (%)</term>
              <term lang="es">Extracción de negro (%)</term>
              <term lang="fr">Retirer du noir (%)</term>
              <term lang="it">Estrazione del nero (%)</term>
              <term lang="no">Svartandel (%)</term>
              <term lang="ru">Черная составляющая (%)</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Black Pullout (%)</guilabel> When doing
                  RGB->CMYK conversion, how much K (black) should be used?
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Zusammenmischung der Grundfarben Cyan (C), Magenta (M)
                  und Gelb (Y) ergibt theoretisch Schwarz, in der Praxis aber
                  meistens nur eine dunkle Mischfarbe. Daher wird beim Druck
                  zusätzlich echtes Schwarz (K) verwendet. Mit dieser
                  Eigenschaft legen Sie fest, wie hoch der Anteil des echten
                  Schwarz für die Konvertierung von RGB nach CMYK ist.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Extracción de negro (%)</guilabel> Al convertir
                  RGB->CMYK, ¿Cuanto K (negro) debería usar?
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Retirer du noir (%)</guilabel>: Quand vous
                  faites une conversion RGB/CMJN, indiquez ici quelle
                  quantité de noir doit être utilisée (La synthèse
                  soustractive CMJ ne permet pas d'obtenir une couleur
                  vraiment noire ou bien foncée, d'où la nécessité d'ajouter
                  du noir).
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Estrazione del nero (%)</guilabel>: La percentuale
                  del nero (K) da utilizzare durante la conversione da RGB a
                  CMYK.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Når du omformar eit bilete til CMYK vil teorien ikkje stemme
                  heilt med praksis. Ei blanding av grunnfargane Cyan, Magenta
                  og Gul (Y) skal i teorien bli svart, men dette skjer ikkje. Difor
                  må det setjast til ein større eller mindre del svart (K i CMYK)
                  for å få same svartmengda som i RGB-biletet. (Det er same
                  fenomenet som er årsak til at blekkskrivaren har ein ekstra
                  patron for svart).
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Черная составляющая (%)</guilabel>: определяет,
                  сколько чёрного (К) использовать при преобразовании
                  RGB->CMYK.
                </para>
             </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Lock Channels</term>
              <term lang="de">Kanäle verbinden</term>
              <term lang="es">Fijar los canales</term>
              <term lang="fr">Bloquer les canaux</term>
              <term lang="it">Blocca canali</term>
              <term lang="no">Lås kanalane</term>
              <term lang="ru">Фиксировать каналы</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Lock Channels</guilabel>: Make channel
                  modifications apply to all channels.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Wenn Sie diese Eigenschaft aktivieren, werden die
                  Einstellungen für die Farbkanäle für alle Kanäle gemeinsam
                  vorgenommen.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Fijar los canales</guilabel>: Hace que las
                  modificaciones de canal se apliquen a todos los canales.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Bloquer les canaux</guilabel>: les modifications
                  s'appliqueront à tous les canaux.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Blocca canali</guilabel>: Le modifiche ad un canale
                  si applicano a tutti i canali.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Lås kanalane</guilabel>: Gjer at endringar på ein
                  kanal også blir gjort gjeldande for dei andre kanalane.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Фиксировать каналы</guilabel>: преобразования
                  будут применятся ко всем каналам.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Factory Defaults</term>
              <term lang="de">Fabrikeinstellungen</term>
              <term lang="es">Valores de fábrica</term>
              <term lang="fr">Réglages par défaut</term>
              <term lang="it">Valori predefiniti</term>
              <term lang="no">Fabrikkinnstillingar</term>
              <term lang="ru">По умолчанию</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Factory Defaults</guilabel>: Restore the
                  default settings which should give pleasing results.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Schaltfläche können Sie die Eigenschaften der
                  Farbkanäle wieder auf die Vorgabe-Einstellungen
                  zurücksetzen.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Valores de fábrica</guilabel>: Restaura los
                  valores de fábrica, lo que debería dar buenos.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Réglages par défaut</guilabel>: Restaure les
                  paramètres par défaut.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Valori predefiniti</guilabel>: Reimposta i valori
                  predefiniti che dovrebbero fornire buoni risultati.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Fabrikkinnstillingar</guilabel>: Trykk på denne
                  for å setje alle innstillingane tilbake til utgangspunktet.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>По умолчанию</guilabel>: востанавливает начальные
                  настройки для приемлимых результатов.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Angle</term>
              <term lang="de">Winkel</term>
              <term lang="es">Angulo</term>
              <term lang="fr">Angle</term>
              <term lang="it">Angolo</term>
              <term lang="no">Vinkel</term>
              <term lang="ru">Угол</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: Cell grid angle for this
                  channel.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Einstellung können Sie den Rasterwinkel
                  einstellen. Gebräuchliche Rasterwinkel beim vierfarbigen
                  Offsetdruck sind nach DIN 16 547 zum einen
                  Cyan = 75°, Magenta = 15°, Gelb = 0°, Schwarz = 135° (-45°)
                  oder Cyan = 15°, Magenta = 75°, Gelb = 0°, Schwarz = 45°.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Angulo</guilabel>: Angulo para la rejilla de la
                  celda en este canal.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: angle de la grille de cellules
                  pour le canal concerné.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Angolo</guilabel>: Angolo della griglia di celle
                  per il rispettivo canale.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Dette er rastervinkelen, eller vinkelen på
                  <quote>rutenettet</quote> du la over biletet. Ut frå
                  DIN 16 547 er brukbare rastervinklar for eit firefargetrykk
                  for eksempel: Cyan = 75°, Magenta = 15°, Gul = 0°,
                  Svart = 135° (-45°) eller Cyan = 15°, Magenta = 75°,
                  Gul = 0°, Svart = 45°.
                </para>

                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Угол</guilabel>: угол сетки для этого канала.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Spot Function</term>
              <term lang="de">Punktfunktion</term>
              <term lang="es">Función de puntos</term>
              <term lang="fr">Fonction point</term>
              <term lang="it">Funzione spot</term>
              <term lang="no">Punktfunksjon</term>
              <term lang="ru">Капельная функция</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Spot Function</guilabel>: Spot function to
                  be used for this channel (see preview in blue cell-boxes).
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, welche Form
                  die Füllung der Zellen haben wird.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Función de puntos</guilabel>: Función de puntos
                  que se usará para este canal (mire la vista previa en la
                  caja de celdas azul).
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Fonction point</guilabel>: Les pixels de la
                  couleur du canal concerné présents dans une cellule seront
                  rassemblés en un «point» de forme et de taille variable,
                  au choix.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Funzione spot</guilabel>: La funzione spot da
                  utilizzare per il rispettivo canale (si osservi l'anteprima
                  nelle caselle blu a lato).
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Punktfunksjon</guilabel>: Her bestemmer du
                  kva form punkta skal ha for denne kanalen. Sjå
                  førehandsvisinga i celleboksane.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Капельная функция</guilabel>: определяет форму
                  капли для ячейки.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Antialiasing</term>
        <term lang="cs">Vyhlazování</term>
        <term lang="de">Kantenglättung</term>
        <term lang="es">Alisado</term>
        <term lang="fr">Lissage</term>
        <term lang="it">Antialiasing</term>
        <term lang="no">Kantutjamning</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сглаживание</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Proper halftoning does not need antialiasing: the aim is to
            reduce the colour depth after all!  However, since this
            plugin is mainly for special effects, the results are
            displayed on screen rather than by a black/white printer.
            So it is often useful to apply a little anti-aliasing to
            simulate ink smearing on paper.  If you do want to print the
            resulting image then set the antialising to 1 (ie, off).
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">Zde se nastavuje způsob vyhlazování.</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Kantenglättung ist für die Druckrasterung selbst nicht
            angebracht oder gar notwendig. Wenn Sie dieses Filter jedoch
            ausschließlich als Effekt verwenden, kann es sehr vorteilhaft
            wirken, wenn die Kanten geglättet werden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            El procedimiento no necesita antialias: después de todo, la meta
            es reducir la profundidad de color. Sin embargo, como este
            añadido es, principalmente, para efectos especiales, los
            resultados se muestran en pantalla más que en una impresora en
            blanco/negro. Así que a menudo es útil aplicar un poco de
            antialias para simular manchas de tinta en el papel. Si no quiere
            imprimir la imagen resultante seleccionelo a 1.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le nivellement tonal ne nécessite pas par lui même de lissage.
            Toutefois, ce greffon étant utilisé surtout pour des effets
            spéciaux et comme le résultat sera affiché sur écran au lieu
            d'être imprimé avec une imprimante noir et blanc, il sera souvent
            utile d'appliquer un peu de lissage pour simuler l'encre s'étalant
            sur le papier. Et si vous voulez vraiment imprimer l'image, réglez
            le lissage à 1 (c-à-d sans).
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il procedimento di mezzotinta non necessita di antialiasing poichè
            lo scopo è quello di ridurre la profondità di colore. Tuttavia,
            poichè questo filtro è destinato ad effetti speciali i risultati
            sono mostrati su schermo piuttosto che da una stampante in bianco
            e nero. Spesso è utile applicare un modesto antialiasing per
            simulare l'espansione dell'inchiostro sulla carta. Se si intende
            stampare l'immagine risultante si imposti l'antialiasing a 1
            (cioè disattivato).
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Kantutjamninga blir ikkje brukt, og er heller ikkje nødvendig for
            utskriving av papirkopi. Denne funksjonen er lagt inn for å lage
            spesielle effektar på bilete som skal visast på skjermen. Legg
            du til lite grann kantutjamning, vil dette kunne simulere t.d. uklare
            blekkutskrifter. Ønskjer du å skrive ut eit bilete som har
            kantutjamning, sett utjamningsgraden til 1, dvs. avslått.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Правильное полутонирование не нуждается в сглаживании: задача-то
            уменьшить глубину цвета. Однако, поскольку этот фильтр
            используется в основном для спец-эффектов, результат обычно
            показан на экране, а не на чёрно-белом принтере. Поэтому полезно
            применить немного сглаживания, чтобы имитировать расрлывшиеся
            чернила на бумаге. Значение 1 отключает сглаживание.
          </para>

          <variablelist lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;ru">
            <varlistentry>
             <term lang="en">Oversample</term>
             <term lang="de">Oversample</term>
             <term lang="es">Sobremuestreo</term>
             <term lang="fr">Sur-échantillonnage</term>
             <term lang="it">Sovracampionamento</term>
             <term lang="no">Utjamningsgrad</term>
             <term lang="ru">Перекрывание</term>

             <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Oversample</guilabel>: Number of subpixels to
                  sample to produce each output pixel.  Set to 1 to disable
                  this feature.  Warning: large numbers here will lead to
                  very long filter runtimes!
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, wie viele
                  Subpixel zur Kantenglättung verwendet werden. Setzen Sie
                  diesen Wert auf 1, so wird die Kantenglättung ausgeschaltet.
                  Vorsicht: hohe Werte führen hier zu einem hohen
                  Rechenaufwand und damit zu einer langen Wartezeit bei der
                  Anwendung des Filters.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  <guilabel>Sobremuestreo</guilabel>: Número de subpíxel de
                  muestra para producir cada píxel resultante. Seleccionelo
                  a 1 para desactivar  esta característica. Precaución: un
                  número grande alargaría considerablemente el tiempo de
                  ejecución del filtro.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <guilabel>Sur-échantillonnage</guilabel>
                  : Nombre de sous-pixels à utiliser pour produire chaque
                  pixel résultant. Réglez-le à 1 pour désactiver cette
                  fonction. Attention, un nombre élevé risque d'allonger
                  considérablement le temps de traitement!
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <guilabel>Sovracampionamento</guilabel>: il numero dei
                  sottopixel da campionare per produrre ciascun pixel
                  risultante. Si imposti il numero a 1 per disabilitare questa
                  caratteristica. Attenzione: grandi valori renderanno il tempo
                  di esecuzione del filtro molto lungo!
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <guilabel>Utjamningsgrad</guilabel>: Denne glidebrytaren
                  bestemmer kor mange subpikslar som skal brukast for
                  kantutjamninga. Sett til 1 for å kopla frå denne funksjonen.
                  Skriv du inn høge tal her, kan dette føre til at datamaskinen
                  bruker svært lang tid på operasjonen.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  <guilabel>Перекрывание</guilabel>: определяет, сколько
                  нужно выбрать под-пикселей, чтобы сделать один пиксель.
                  Значение 1 отключает эту настройку. Внимание! Большие
                  значения этого параметра требуют много ресурсов.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Example</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Beispiel</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Exemple</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs;it;no;ru">Example</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Example for Newsprint</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">
          Malá ukázka použití filtru z galérie autora:
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Beispiel für Zeitungsdruck</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo para papel de periódico</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Exemple pour Trame d'Imprimerie</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Segue un esempio tratto dalla galleria dell'autore:
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Her er eit eksempel frå forfattaren si samling:
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">Вот пример из галлереи автора:</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/newsprint.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">An example from plug-in author</para>
          <para lang="de">Ein Beispiel vom Plugin-Autor</para>
          <para lang="es">Un ejemplo del autor del plugin</para>
          <para lang="fr">Un exemple de l'auteur du greffon</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
