<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-lighting' lang="en;cs;fr">
  <title lang="en">Lighting Effects</title>
  <title lang="cs">Světelné efekty</title>
  <title lang="fr">Effet d&apos;éclairage</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Lighting Effects</primary>
    <primary lang="cs">Světelné efekty</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Effets d&apos;éclairage</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-light-lightingeffects.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-light-lightingeffects.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
   <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-light-lightingeffects.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>    
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filters/Light Effects/<accel>L</accel>ighting Effects</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter simulates the effect you get when you light up a wall with a spot. It doesn't 
      produce any drop shadows and, of course, doesn't reveal any new details in dark zones.
    </para> 

    <para lang="cs">
      tento filtr naleznete v nabídce
      <guimenuitem>Obrázek&gt;Filtry/Efekty se světlem/Světelné efekty</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr simuluje efekt svícení na baterkou na zeď.
      Nevytváří ale žádné stíny a samozřejmě nedokáže ani odhalit nové detaily
      v tmavých částech obrazu.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filtres/Effets de lumière/<accel>E</accel>ffet d'éclairage</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'Effet d'éclairage évoque l'effet obtenu en éclairant un mur avec un spot. Il ne produit pas 
      d'ombres portées et, bien entendu, ne révèle pas de détails nouveaux dans les zones sombres.
    </para> 
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Preview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Náhled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Aperçu</title>

        <para lang="en">
          When <guilabel>Interactive</guilabel> is checked, parameter setting results are 
          interactively displayed in preview without modifying the image until you click on 
          <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button.
        </para> 
        <para lang="en">
          If "Interactive" is not checked, changes are displayed in preview only when you click 
          on the <guilabel>Update</guilabel> button. This option is useful with a slow computer.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Je-li zaškrtnuta volba <guilabel>Interaktivní</guilabel>, je
          nastavení filtru interaktivně promítáno v náhledu. Kliknutím
          na tlačítko <guilabel>Budiž</guilabel> filtr na obrázek aplikujete.
        </para> 
        <para lang="cs">
          Pokud volba <guilabel>Interaktivní</guilabel> není aktivní, změny v
          nastavení se projeví pouze po kliknutí na tlačítko
          <guilabel>Aktualizovat</guilabel>. Tato volba je užitečná pro
          majitele pomalých a líných počítačů.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Quand l'option <guilabel>Interactif</guilabel> est cochée, le résultat du 
          réglage des paramètres est affiché en temps réel dans l'aperçu, sans affecter l'image 
          elle-même jusqu'à ce que vous cliquiez sur <guilabel>Valider</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Si «Interactif» n'est pas cochée, les modifications ne seront affichées dans l'Aperçu 
          que lorsque vous cliquerez sur le bouton <guilabel>Mettre à jour</guilabel>. Cette 
          option est utile sur un ordinateur lent.
        </para>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">General Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Obecné volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options générales</title>
    <itemizedlist lang='en'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Transparent Background</guilabel>: Makes destination image transparent when 
          bumpmap height is zero (height is zero in black areas of the bumpmapped image).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Create New Image</guilabel>: Creates a new image when applying filter.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>High Quality Preview</guilabel>: For quick CPU...
        </para>  
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Enable Antialiasing</guilabel>: Lowers the scale effect on lines.
          <emphasis>Depth</emphasis> is the strength of antialiasing. 
          <emphasis>Threshold</emphasis> determines which transitions will be 
          considered as a border. High values will limit the effect 
          to strong transitions. 
        </para> 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang='cs'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Průhledné pozadí</guilabel>: Výsledný obrázek bude
          průhledný v oblastech nulové výšky mapy vyvýšení (výška je nulová v
          černých oblastech mapy vyvýšení)-
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Vytvořit nový obrázek</guilabel>: Aplikace filtru vytvoří
          nový obrázek.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Náhled ve vysoké kvalitě</guilabel>: Pro rychlé počítače.
        </para>  
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          <guilabel>Arrière-plan Transparent</guilabel>: Rend l'image destination 
          transparente là où 
          le relief est nul dans le cas d'une image qui a subi un Repoussage 
          (la hauteur est nulle dans les parties noires). 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Créer une nouvelle image</guilabel>: Crée une nouvelle image 
          quand le filtre est appliqué.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Aperçu de haute qualité</guilabel>: Pour les microprocesseurs rapides...
        </para>  
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Activer l'anti-crénelage</guilabel>: Diminue l'effet d'escalier sur les lignes.
          <guilabel>Profondeur</guilabel> est la force de l'anticrénelage. <guilabel>Seuil</guilabel> 
          détermine quelles seront les transitions concernées par l'anticrénelage. Une valeur 
          élevée limitera l'effet aux transitions marquées.
        </para> 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Light</title>
    <title lang="cs">Světlo</title>
    <title lang="fr">Lumière</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Light Settings</term>
        <term lang="cs">Nastavení světla</term>
        <term lang="fr">Paramètres de la lumière</term>
        <listitem lang="en"> 
          <para>
            <guilabel>Light Type</guilabel>: Three types are available. 
            <emphasis>Point</emphasis> 
            displays a blue point at center of preview. You can click and 
            drag it to move light all 
            over the preview. <emphasis>Directional</emphasis>: the blue point 
            is linked to preview 
            center by a line which indicates direction of light. The white light halo has an 
            elliptic shape. <emphasis>None</emphasis>: there is no blue point. Light comes 
            from the top left corner, the best to give a good relief effect.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Light Source Color</guilabel>: When you click on the color dwell, 
            you bring a 
            dialog up where you can select the light source color. 
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Position</guilabel>: Determines the light point position 
            according to three coordinates: X coordinate for horizontal position, 
            Y for vertical position, Z for source 
            distance (the light darkens when distance increases). Values are from -1 to +1.
          </para>
        </listitem>  
        <listitem lang="cs">
          <para>
            <guilabel>Typ</guilabel>: K dispozici jsou tři typy světla.
            <emphasis>Bodové</emphasis> se projeví zobrazením modrého bodu v
            náhledu. Když na něj kliknete, můžete ho přesouvat po obrázku.
            <emphasis>Směrové</emphasis>: modrý bod je spoken s modlu linkou,
            která představuje směr světla. Světelné haló má eliptický tvar.
            <emphasis>Nic</emphasis>: Žádný modrý bod. Světlo přichází z
            levého horního rohu.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Barva</guilabel>: Barva světla. Kliknutím na barevnou
            plochu se otevře standardní dialog pro výběr barev.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Poloha</guilabel>: Určuje polohu zdroje světla pomocí
            třech souřadnic: X pro vodorovnou polohu, Y pro svilsou polohu, a
            Z pro vzdálenost zdroje (čím větší, tím méně světla). Hodnoty se
            mohou pohybovat v rozmezí -1 až +1.
          </para>
        </listitem>  
        <listitem lang="fr"> 
          <para>
            <guilabel>Type de lumière</guilabel>: Trois types sont disponibles. 
            <emphasis>Point</emphasis> 
            affiche un point bleu au centre de l'aperçu. Vous pouvez le déplacer avec 
            la souris. <emphasis>Directional</emphasis>: Le point bleu est relié au 
            centre par une ligne qui indique 
            la direction de la lumière. La tache lumineuse a une forme elliptique. 
            <emphasis>Aucun</emphasis>: Il n'y a pas de point bleu. La lumière provient 
            du coin en haut à gauche, ce qui convient bien aux effets de relief.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Couleur de la lumière</guilabel>: Quand vous cliquez sur le 
            rectangle source de couleurs, vous ouvrez une fenêtre où vous pouvez 
            choisir la couleur de la lumière.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Position</guilabel>: Détermine la position de la tache de 
            lumière selon trois coordonnées: X pour la position horizontale, 
            Y pour la position verticale, Z pour la 
            distance de la source (la lumière s'assombrit quand la distance augmente). 
            Les valeurs vont de -1 à +1.
          </para>
        </listitem>   
 
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Material</title>
    <title lang="cs">Materiál</title>
    <title lang="fr">Matériau</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Intensity Levels</term>
        <term lang="cs">Vlastnosti materiálu</term>
        <term lang="fr">Niveaux d'intensité</term>
        <listitem lang="en"> 
          <para>
            These options don't concern light itself, but light reflected by objects.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Ambient</guilabel>: Sets the ambient light, i.e the indirect light which 
            lightens all the scene out of the light spot 
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Diffuse</guilabel>: When you increase this value, 
            light progressively diffuses to the whole image
          </para>
        </listitem>  
        <listitem lang="cs"> 
          <para>
            Tyto volby se netýkají přímo světla, ale světla odráženého od
            objektů.
          </para>
        </listitem>  
        <listitem lang="fr"> 
          <para>
            Ces options concernent non pas la lumière émise elle même, 
            mais la lumière renvoyée par 
            les objets sur lesquels elle s'applique.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Ambiant</guilabel>: Cette option règle la lumière d'ambiance, 
            c-à-d la lumière indirecte qui éclaire la scène en dehors de la tache lumineuse. 
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Diffusion</guilabel>: Quand vous augmentez cette valeur, la 
            lumière diffuse progressivement au reste de l'image. 
          </para>
        </listitem>   
 
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Reflectivity</term>
        <term lang="cs">Reflektivita</term>
        <term lang="fr">Pouvoir réfléchissant</term>
        <listitem lang="en"> 
          <para>
            <guilabel>Diffuse</guilabel>: Higher values make the object reflect more light.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Specular</guilabel>: Controls how intense will be the highlights.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Highlights</guilabel>: Higher values make the highlights more focused.
          </para>
        </listitem>  
        <listitem lang="cs"> 
          <para>
            FIXME
          </para>
        </listitem>  
         <listitem lang="fr"> 
          <para>
            <guilabel>Diffusion</guilabel>: Des valeurs élevées rendent l'objet plus réfléchissant.  
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Spéculaire</guilabel>: Contrôle l'intensité de la tache lumineuse.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Tache lumineuse</guilabel>: Des valeurs élevées rendent la tache lumineuse plus 
            focalisée.
          </para>
        </listitem>   
 
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
    
  <simplesect>  
    <title lang="en">Bump Map</title>
    <title lang="cs">Mapa vyvýšení</title>
    <title lang="fr">Repoussage d'après une carte</title>

    <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Enable Bump Mapping</term>
      <term lang="cs">Povolit mapování vyvýšení</term>
      <term lang="fr">Activer le repoussage</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          Combined with "Environment Map", this option allows interesting bump mapping. Only 
          greyscale images can be used for bumpmaps (light areas are bumped, dark areas remain 
          unchanged). So, if you want to bumpmap against a RGB image, you have to turn it to 
          greyscale first (&lt;Image&gt;Image/Mode/Grayscale). When you check this box, following 
          options are enabled:
        </para>  
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            <guilabel>Bump Map Image</guilabel>: You have to select there the greyscale image.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Curve</guilabel>: Four curve types are available: 
               <emphasis>Linear</emphasis>, 
               <emphasis>Logarithmic</emphasis>, <emphasis>Sinusoidal</emphasis> and 
               <emphasis>Spherical</emphasis>. See Bump Map plug-in for explanations.
               <!-- LINK TO BE DONE-->
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Maximum Height</guilabel>: This is the maximum height of bumps.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Minimum Height</guilabel>: This is the minimum height of bumps.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Autostretch to fit Value Range</guilabel>: There is correspondence 
              between grey level and height. If difference between black and lightest 
              grey is not enough to 
              fill the height value range determined above, then values are stretched.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="cs">
        <para>
          Společně s mapováním prostředí umožňuje tato volba zajímavé mapování
          vyvýšení. Jako mapy vyvýšení lze používat pouze obrázky v odstínech
          šedi (světlé oblasti jsou vyvýšeny, tmavé zůstávají beze změny).
          Pokud tedy chcete použít barevný obrázek, musíte ho nejdříve převést
          do odstínů šedi.(&lt;Obrázek&gt;/Režim/Odstíny šedi). Pokud tuto
          volbu aktivujete, budou povoleny následující možnosti:
        </para>  
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            <guilabel>Obrázek vyvýšení</guilabel>: Zde musíte zvolit obrázek v
            odstínech šedi.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Křivka</guilabel>: Jsou dostupné čtyři typy křivek:
               <emphasis>Lineární</emphasis>, 
               <emphasis>Logaritmický</emphasis>, <emphasis>Sinusoidní</emphasis> a
               <emphasis>Kulový</emphasis>. Vysvětlení viz <!-- FIXME-->
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Maximální výška</guilabel>: ,aximální vyvýšení.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          Combinée à la Carte d'environnement, cette option permet d'intéressants effets de 
          repoussage éclairés. Seules les images en niveaux de gris peuvent être repoussées. 
          (Les parties claires sont repoussées, les parties noires restent au même niveau). 
          Si donc vous voulez repousser une image RVB, vous devez d'abord la transformer en 
          Niveaux de gris (&lt;Image&gt;Image/Mode/Niveaux de gris). Quand vous cochez cette 
          option, les options suivantes sont activées:
        </para>  
          <para>
            <guilabel>Image à repousser</guilabel>: Vous devez sélectionner là l'image en niveaux 
            de gris.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Courbe</guilabel>: Quatre types de courbe sont disponibles: 
            <emphasis>Linéaire</emphasis>, <emphasis>Logarithmique</emphasis>, 
            <emphasis>Sinusoïdal</emphasis>  et <emphasis>Sphérique</emphasis>. 
            Voir le filtre Repoussage pour informations.
               <!-- LIEN À FAIRE -->
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Hauteur maximum</guilabel>: Il s'agit de la hauteur maximum des bosses.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Hauteur minimum</guilabel>: Il s'agit de la hauteur minimum des bosses.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Étaler automatiquement les valeurs pour les adapter à l'intervalle</guilabel>: 
            Il y a correspondance entre le niveau de gris et la hauteur. Il se peut que la variation 
            entre le noir et le gris le plus clair soit insuffisante pour remplir l'intervalle déterminé 
            ci-dessus. En cochant cette case, les valeurs seront étalées.
          </para>
      </listitem>

    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Environment Map</title>
    <title lang="cs">Mapování prostředí</title>
    <title lang="fr">Carte d'environnement</title>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Enable Environment Mapping</term>
      <term lang="cs">Povolit mapování prostředí</term>
      <term lang="fr">Activer le mappage de l'environnement</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          When you check this box, the following option is enabled:
        </para>  
        <itemizedlist> 
          <listitem> 
            <para>
              <guilabel>Environment Image</guilabel>: You have to select there a RGB image.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="cs">
        <para>
          Zaškrtnutím této volby aktivujeté následující volby:
        </para>  
        <itemizedlist> 
          <listitem> 
            <para>
              <guilabel>Obrázek prostředí</guilabel>: Zde musíte zadat RGB
              obrázek.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          Quand vous cochez cette case, l'option suivante est activée.
        </para>  
        <itemizedlist>  
          <listitem> 
          <para>
            <guilabel>Image d'environnement</guilabel>: Vous devez choisir là une image RVB.
          </para>
          <para>
            Un exemple d'utilisation peut être trouvé à www.home.unix-ag.org/simon/gimp/golden.html
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
