<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<sect1 id='toolbox-crop'>
  <title>Crop Tool</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Crop</secondary>
    <tertiary>Clip</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-crop.png' format='png'/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
    The Crop Tool is used to crop or clip an image or layer.
  </para>

  <variablelist><title>Options</title>
    <varlistentry><term>Overview</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The available tool options for the Crop Tool can be accessed by
          double clicking the Crop Tool.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Tool Toggle</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Tool Toggle for the Crop Tool alternates between Crop mode and
          Resize mode.
        </para>
        <para>
          Crop Mode is the standard mode of operation for the Crop Tool.
          Cropping an image or layer will change a layer by eliminating
          everything outside the cropping area. The cropping area can be set by
          either dragging the tool to form a rectangle area or manually
          setting the origin, width, and height. Cropping areas can also be set
          based on an existing selection or by using the Auto Shrink button.
          These options are available within the Crop And Resize Information
          dialog which is shown when the Crop Tool is clicked on an image or
          layer.
        </para>
        <para>
          Resize Mode works in a similar fashion to Crop Mode with the
          exception that the layer or layers affected by the cropping are not
          changed in size. That is to say that the layer size remains as it is,
          but the pixel information outside the cropping region is removed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Current Layer Only</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option will make the crop or resize affect only the active
          layer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Allow Enlarging</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option allows the crop or resize to take place outside the image
          or layer boundary.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist><title>Crop And Resize Information</title>
    <varlistentry><term>Origin</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Origin selectors allow the manual setting of the top left corner
          of the cropping region. The units may also be chosen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Width/Height</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Width and Height selectors allow the manual setting of both the
          width and the height of the cropping area. The units may also be
          chosen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>From Selection</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This button will resize the cropping area to encompass all active
          selections contained within the image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Auto Shrink</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Auto Shrink button will attempt to locate a border from which to
          draw dimensions from.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <variablelist><title>Defaults</title>
      <varlistentry><term>Shortcut</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>c</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            shortcut will change the active tool to the Crop Tool.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> will switch the Crop Tool mode
            between Crop and Resize.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Alt</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Alt</keycap> will toggle the use of Allow
            Enlarging.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
