<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<sect1 id='toolbox-hostogram'>
  <title>Histogram</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Histogram</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata
        fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-histogram.png'
        format='png'
      />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <para>
    The Histogram tool is designed to provide you with detailed information
    about the image value structure.
  </para>
  <variablelist><title>Histogram Dialog</title>
    <varlistentry><term>Overview</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When you click on the image with the Histogram tool, a dialog will be
          displayed showing detailed information about the way your image is
          structured by value.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Information on Channel</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The dropdown list will allow you to select the color channel or alpha
          channel that you wish to have the information displayed for.
        </para>
        <para>
          Value is a composite channel containing the information for all
          channels. Red, Green, and Blue are channels that relate directly to
          the color component of the named color. Alpha shows the information
          regarding the alpha channel of the image. For further information on
          channels, see the glossary entry
          <link linkend='glossary-channels'>Channels</link>.
          For further information regarding Alpha, see the glossary entry
          <link linkend='glossary-alpha'>Alpha</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Intensity Range</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The two spinboxes allow manual control of the range currently under
          scrutiny. The left spinbox indicates the left or start value and the
          right spinbox indicates the right or end value.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can select a range using the mouse by clicking and dragging
          within the visual histogram representation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Mean</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This number represents the mean value of the currently selected range
          of values.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Std Dev</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This number represents the standard deviation of the currently
          selected range of values.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Median</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This number represents the median value of the currently selected
          range of values.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Pixels</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This number represents the total number of pixels in the image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Count</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This number indicates the number of pixels in the current range.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Percentile</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This figure represents the percentage of the total number of pixels
          that are currently in range.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>
