<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<sect1 id='toolbox-rotate'>
  <title>Rotate Tool</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Rotate</secondary>
    <tertiary>Transformation</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-rotate.png' format='png'/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
    The Rotate Tool is used to rotate layers.
  </para>

  <variablelist><title>Options</title>
    <varlistentry><term>Overview</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The available tool options for the Rotate Tool can be accessed by
          double clicking the Rotate Tool icon.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Transform Direction</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Transform Direction sets which way or direction a layer is
          rotated. The Traditional mode will rotate the layer as one might
          expect. If a layer is rotated 10 degrees to the right, then the layer
          will be rendered as such. This behaviour is contrary to Corrective
          rotation.
        </para>
        <para>
          Corrective Rotation is primarily used to repair scanned images that
          are not straight. If the image is 13 degrees askew then you need not
          try to rotate by that angle. By using Corrective Rotation you can
          rotate visually and line up the layer with the image. Because the
          transformation is reversed, or performed backwards, the image will be
          rotated with sufficient angle to correct the error.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Interpolation</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel> drop-down list allows you to
          choose the quality of the transformation. For more information about
          the different methods that can be employed, see the glossary entry
          <link linkend='glossary-interpolation'>Interpolation</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Clip Result</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option will clip the rotated layer to the original layer size.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Grid Options</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The three available grid options are used to change the visual
          display of the rotation grid.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Don't Show Grid</guilabel> will display only the outline of
          the rotation rectangle.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Number of Grid Lines</guilabel> will allow control over the
          total number of displayed grid lines. Use the
          <guilabel>Density</guilabel> slider to set the number of grid lines.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Grid Line Spacing</guilabel> allows control over the
          distance between the grid lines. Use the <guilabel>Density</guilabel>
          slider to set the distance.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Show Path</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          FIXME
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Constraints</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>15 Degrees</guilabel> will constrain the rotation to angles
          divisible by 15 degrees.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <variablelist><title>Defaults</title>
      <varlistentry><term>Shortcut</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>r</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            key combo will change the active tool to Rotate.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> will constrain the rotation angles to
            those only evenly divisible by 15 degrees.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
