<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<sect1 id='toolbox-bycolor-selection'>
  <title>Select By Color Tool</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata
        fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-selbycolor.png'
        format='PNG'
      />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
    The Select By Color tool is designed to select areas of the current layer
    or image based on color.
  </para>

  <variablelist><title>Options</title>
    <varlistentry><term>Overview</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The available tool options for Select By Color can be accessed by
          double clicking the Select By Color tool icon.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Mode</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Replace mode will cause any existing selection to be destroyed or
          replaced when the new selection is created.
        </para>
        <para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Add mode will cause the new selection to be added to any existing
          selection regions.
        </para>
        <para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Subtract mode will remove the new selection area from any
          existing selection regions.
        </para>
        <para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Intersection mode will make a new selection from the area
          where the existing selection region and the new selection region
          overlap. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Antialiasing</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option will make your selection appear more correct by anti
          aliasing the edge of the selection with the neighbouring pixels.
          Antialiasing is discussed in further detail under the glossary entry
          <link linkend='glossary-antialiasing'>Antialiasing</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Feather Edges</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Radius</guilabel> slider adjusts the amount of
          feathering in pixels for the next selection that is created. For
          further information regarding feathering, see the glossary entry
          <link linkend='glossary-feathering'>Feathering</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Finding Similar Colors</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Select Transparent Areas</guilabel> gives the Select By
          Color tool the ability to select areas which are transparent. If this
          checkbox is not selected, transparent areas are completely immune to
          being selected.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Sample Merged</guilabel> will change the way the Select By
          Color tool determines where to start and end selections. When
          <guilabel>Sample Merged</guilabel> is enabled, limits are set using
          color and pixel information from all layers. For further information
          regarding Sample Merge, see the glossary entry
          <link linkend='glossary-samplemerge'>Sample Merge</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Threshold</guilabel> is a slider that determines how
          aggressively the Select By Color finds areas to include in the
          selection region.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <variablelist><title>Defaults</title>
      <varlistentry><term>Shortcut</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <keycap>c</keycap> key will change the active tool to Select By
            Color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> while creating a free selection will
            place the selection into subtraction mode (see above).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Alt</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Alt</keycap> will allow movement of the current
            selection.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Shift</keycap> while creating a free selection will
            ensure that the selection mode is changed to addition (see above).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Using
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            will change the selection mode to intersection (or union).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Additional information</title>
    <warning>
      <para>
        When moving a selection beyond the boundaries of the image canvas, the
        selection will be cropped to the image area. Selections can only exist
        on the visible canvas. Selection movements and changes are however kept
        in the undo buffer should you have the need of repairing an error.
      </para>
    </warning>
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
