<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-04-17 small spelling fix for german
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-09-15 de added by axel.wernicke
  2005-11-07 small add in Overview by julien hardelin
-->
<sect2 id="gimpressionist-orient-map-editor" lang="en;de;fr;ru">
  <sect2info lang="de;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-04-17</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-10-20</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">GIMPressionist - Orientation Map Editor</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">GIMPressionist - Orientation-Map Editor</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">GIMPressionist - Éditeur de carte d'orientation</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">
      Гимпрессионист - редактор карт ориентации (мазков кисти)
    </phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Orientation Map Editor</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>GIMPressionist</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Éditeur de carte d'orientation</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Редактор карт ориентации</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Überblick</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Orientation-map editor is an annexe of the <link
      linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link> filter. You
      can get to it by clicking on the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button
      in the <quote>Orientation</quote>> tab. With this editor, you can set
      the direction that brush strokes given by filter will have.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Der Orientation-Map Editor ist Bestandteil des Filters <link
      linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>. Er dient Ihnen
      zur Einstellung der Richtung in der die Pinselstriche ausgeführt werden,
      mit denen das Filter das Bild malt.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      L'Éditeur de carte d'orientation est une annexe du filtre <link
      linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressioniste</link>. Vous y
      accédez en cliquant sur le bouton <guibutton>Éditer</guibutton> dans
      l'onglet <quote>Orientation</quote>.Il vous sert à régler la direction
      que prendront les coups de brosse que donne le filtre.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Редактор карт ориентации - часть фильтра <link
                                                    linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">Гимпрессионист</link>. Вы можете
      вызвать его нажатием кнопки <guibutton>Правка</guibutton> в закладке
      <quote>Ориентация</quote>. С помощью этого редактора устанавливается
      направление мазков кисти фильтра.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Parameter Settings</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Réglage des paramètres</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Options of the <quote>Orientation-map Editor</quote> dialog
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften des Dialoges <quote>Orient-Map Editor</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Paramètres de réglage de l'Éditeur de carte d'orientation
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Настройки <quote>Редактора карт ориентации</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/options-artistic-gimpressionist-orientmap.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/de/options-artistic-gimpressionist-orientmap.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/fr/options-artistic-gimpressionist-orientmap.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <para lang="en">
        You can place one or several vectors. You can set their direction and
        their strength. They will act ont the corresponding area of the image.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Vous pouvez placer un ou plusieurs vecteurs dont vous pouvez régler
        la direction et la force et qui agiront chacun sur la partie
        correspondante de l'image.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Вы можете создать один или несколько векторов, указав для них
        направление и силу. Они будут действовать на  соответствующую
        область изображения.
      </para>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Vectors</term>
        <term lang="de">Vektoren</term>
        <term lang="fr">Vecteurs</term>
        <term lang="ru">Векторы</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            In the left windows (Vectors) you can manage your vectors. By
            default, a vector is at center. Vectors are red when they are
            active, and grey when they are not with a white point at tip.
            By clicking on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button, you add a
            vector at center of the window, whereas clicking with the mouse
            <emphasis>Middle Button</emphasis> puts it where you click.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In diesem Bereich können Sie die Vektoren bearbeiten, welche die
            Richtung der Pinselstriche für diesen Bildbereich vorgeben.
            Die Vektoren werden als kleine Striche dargestellt, welche
            einen Ankerpunkt (weiss) und eine Stärke für eine bestimmte
            Richtung vorgeben. Die Stärke wird dabei durch die Länge des
            Vektors dargestellt. Der aktive Vektor wird rot dargestellt.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch Betätigen der Schaltfläche <guibutton>Hinzufügen</guibutton>
            können Sie neue Vektoren einsetzen. Alternativ können Sie durch
            Klicken mit der <mousebutton>Mittleren Maustaste</mousebutton>
            neue Vektoren an einer beliebigen Stelle hinzufügen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            C'est dans cette fenêtre que vous pouvez placer vos vecteurs.
            Le clic sur le bouton <guibutton>Ajouter</guibutton>, place un
            vecteur au centre de la fenêtre, tandis que le clic avec le
            <emphasis>Bouton du milieu</emphasis> de la souris le place à
            l'endroit du clic. Ces vecteurs apparaissent comme de fins
            traits, rouges quand ils sont actifs, gris quand il ne sont pas
            actifs. Un point blanc marque leur pointe.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            В левой части диалога (<quote>Векторы</quote>)
            осуществляется управление векторами. Изначально каждый
            вектор находится в центре окна. Создать новый вектор в
            центре можно при помощи кнопки
            <guilabel>Добавить</guilabel>. Чтобы создать вектор не в
            центре окна, нажмите <emphasis>средней кнопкой
              мыши</emphasis> там, где должен быть вектор. Выбранный
            вектор изображается  красным, остальные - серым с белой
            точкой на конце.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Clicking with the mouse <emphasis>Left Button</emphasis>
            displaces the selected vector to the clicked point.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch einen Klick mit der <mousebutton>Linken
              Maustaste</mousebutton> wird der aktive Vektor an die Stelle des
            Bildes verschoben, welche Sie angeklickt haben.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Avec un <emphasis>Clic gauche</emphasis>, le vecteur actif vient
            se placer à l'endroit du clic.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Чтобы переместить вектор в другое место, нажмите на
            него <emphasis>левой кнопкой мыши</emphasis>.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            When clicking with the mouse <emphasis>Right Button</emphasis>,
            the selected vector points to where you have clicked.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Ein Klick mit der <mousebutton>Rechten Maustaste</mousebutton>
            legt die Richtung des aktuellen Vektors fest.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Avec un <emphasis>Clic droit</emphasis>, le vecteur actif pointe
            vers l'emplacement du clic.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Чтобы изменить направление вектора, нажмите
            <emphasis>правой кнопки мыши</emphasis> в нужном направлении
            от вектора. Вектор повернётся к точке нажатия.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Clicking on <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> and
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> buttons displaces focus from a
            vector to another.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit den Schaltflächen <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> und
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> können Sie den aktiven Vektor
            wechseln.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les boutons <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> et
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> vous permettent de faire passer
            le focus d'un vecteur à l'autre.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            С помощью кнопок <guilabel>&lt;&lt;</guilabel> и
            <guilabel>&gt;&gt;</guilabel> вы можете переместить фокус с
            одного вектора на другой.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> button allows you to delete the
            selected vector.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Entfernen</guibutton>
            betätigen, wird der aktuelle Vektor gelöscht.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le bouton <guilabel>Supprimer</guilabel> vous permet de supprimer
            le vecteur actif.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Кнопка <guilabel>Удалить</guilabel> позволяет удалять выбранный
            вектор.
          </para>

          <tip>
            <para lang="en">
              With the scroll bar on the right of the Vectors panel, you can
              set the image brightness. This can be very useful if the image
              is very dark/bright and you cann't see vectors well.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Mit dem Schieberegler neben dem Vorschaubild können Sie die
              Helligkeit des Bildes einstellen. Dies kann sehr nützlich sein,
              wenn das Bild sehr hell ist und Sie die Vektoren sehr schlecht
              erkennen können.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              La barre de défilement à la droite du panneau Vecteurs vous
              permet de régler la clatée de l'affichage. C'est très utile
              si l'image est trop claire/sombre et que vous ne voyez pas
              bien les vecteurs.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Линейкой прокрутки в правой части панели устанавливается
              яркость изображения. Это помогает в тех случаях, когда
              изображение слишком темное, и векторы плохо видно.
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <term lang="ru">Просмотр</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"> <!--Changed 061020-->
            This Preview gives you an idea of the action of the various
            vectors. The slider on the right border lets you change the
            luminosity of this preview.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In diesem Vorschaufenster werden für das gesamte Bild die
            aktuellen Richtungen der Pinselstriche angezeigt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cet Aperçu vous donne une idée de l'action des différents
            vecteurs. La glissière sur le bord droit vous permet de modifier
            la luminosité de cet aperçu.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            В окне просмотра отображается схема действия всех векторов.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Type</term>
        <term lang="de">Typ</term>
        <term lang="fr">Type</term>
        <term lang="ru">Тип</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You have there some types to arrange the brush strokes within the
            selected vector domain. Describing them is difficult, but you can
            see the result in the Preview.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie haben mit dieser Eigenschaft die Möglichkeit zu bestimmen,
            wie aus den von Ihnen erzeugten Vektoren ein Vektorfeld erzeugt
            wird, welches für jeden Bereich des Bildes eine Richtung für die
            Pinselstriche enthält. Die verschiedenen Einstellungen haben sehr
            komplexe Wirkungsmechanismen, daher ist es am leichtesten die
            verschiedenen Möglichkeiten auszuprobieren und in der Vorschau
            zu begutachten.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous disposez là de différents type d'arrangement des coups de
            brosse dans le domaine du vecteur actif. Difficiles à décrire,
            leur effet apparaît nettement dans l'aperçu.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Существует несколько типов расположения мазков кисти
            в пределах области действия вектора. Описать их действие сложно,
            но вы можете увидеть результат в окне просмотра.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Voronoi</term>
        <term lang="de">Voronoi</term>
        <term lang="fr">Voronoï</term>
        <term lang="ru">Вороной</term>

        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en;de"><primary>Voronoi</primary></indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Voronoï</primary></indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Вороной</primary></indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            A Voronoi's diagram consists in
            partitioning a plane with n master points into n polygons
            where each polygon has only one of these n master points and
            where any given other point of the polygon is closer to the
            master point than to any other. So each polygon limit is
            midway between two master point. Here is an example of a
            Voronoi's diagram:
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/voronoi.png"
                          format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Here, when this option is checked, only the vector closest to
            a given point of the image influences this point.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Ein Varonoi Diagramm zerteilt eine Fläche mit n Hauptpunkten in
            n Poygone. Dabei hat jedes der Polygone einen Hauptpunkt und jeder
            Punkt des Polygons ist näher an diesem Hauptpunkt als an jedem
            anderen. Daher ist die Grenze für jedes Poygon die halbe
            Entfernung zwischen zwei Hauptpunkten. Die folgende Abbildung
            enthält ein Beispiel:
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/voronoi.png"
                          format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Wenn diese Eigenschaft aktiviert ist, beeinflusst nur der Vektor,
            welcher einem bestimmten Punkt am nächsten ist diesen Punkt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Un diagramme de Voronoï consiste à partitionner un plan
            comportant n points maîtres en n polygones où chaque polygone ne
            possède qu'un seul de ces n points et où tous les autres points
            du polygone sont plus près de ce point maître que de n'importe
            quel autre des points maîtres. Ainsi, les limites des polygones
            sont à mi-distance entre deux points maîtres. Voici un exemple
            de diagramme de Voronoï:
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/voronoi.png"
                          format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Ici quand cette option est cochée, cela aboutit au fait qu'un
            point donné de l'image ne subira l'influence que du vecteur
            le plus proche.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Диаграмма Вороного состоит из плоскости разделенной n главными
            точками на n полигонов, где каждый полигон имеет только одну
            главную точку, и где любая точка полигона находится ближе к своей
            главной, чем к остальным. Таким образом, границы полигонов
            находятся посередине между двумя главными точками.
            Вот пример использования режима Вороного:
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/voronoi.png"
                          format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            В режиме Вороного только ближайший к заданной точке вектор
            оказывает воздействие.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Angle</term>
        <term lang="de">Winkel</term>
        <term lang="fr">Angle</term>
        <term lang="ru">Угол</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: Direction of the selected vector.
            This slider has the same action as right-clicking (see above).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft legen Sie die Richtung des aktiven (also
            rot markierten) Vektors fest. Sie können Die Einstellung mit
            Hilfe eines Schiebereglers oder des zugeordneten Eingabefeldes
            im Bereich von 0° bis 360° vornehmen. Alternativ haben Sie die
            Möglichkeit die Richtung durch einen Klick mit der
            <mousebutton>Rechten Maustaste</mousebutton> festzulegen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>: C'est la direction du vecteur
            actif. Ce curseur a la même action que le clic droit vu
            ci-dessus.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            <guilabel>Угол</guilabel>: направление выбранного вектора.
            Этот ползунок действует так же, как правая кнопка мыши (см.
            выше).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Angle Offset</term>
        <term lang="de">Winkel-Versatz</term>
        <term lang="fr">Décalage de l'angle</term>
        <term lang="ru">Угол смещения</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider allows you to change the angle of ALL vectors.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft haben Sie die Möglichkeit die Richtung
            <emphasis>aller</emphasis> Vektoren zu verändern. Die Einstellung
            können Sie mit Hilfe eines Schiebereglers oder des zugeordneten
            Eingabefeldes im Bereich von 0° bis 360° vornehmen. Eine
            Vergrößerung des Wertes führt zu einer Drehung im Uhrzeigersinn.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce curseur permet de faire varier l'angle de TOUS les vecteurs.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            <guilabel>Угол смещения</guilabel>: этот ползунок позволяет
            менять направление ВСЕХ векторов.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Strength</term>
        <term lang="de">Stärke</term>
        <term lang="fr">Force</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сила</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider acts on the influence domain of the selected vector.
            This influence lowers with distance. Strength is showed with the
            vector length.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie die Stärke des Vektors
            einstellen. Durch seine Stärke beeinflusst der Vektor die ihn
            umgebenden Vektoren.Die Einstellung können Sie über einen
            Schieberegler oder mit Hilfe des zugeordneten Eingabefeldes im
            Bereich von 0,1 bis 5,0 vornehmen. In Abhängigkeit von seiner
            Stärke wird der Vektor mit verschiedenen Längen dargestellt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce curseur agit sur le domaine d'influence du vecteur actif.
            Cette influence décroît avec la distance. La force est
            représentée par la longueur du vecteur.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот ползунок изменяет область влияния
            активного вектора. Она уменьшается с расстоянием. Сила
            показывается длиной вектора.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Strength Exp.</term>
        <term lang="de">Stärke Exp.</term>
        <term lang="fr">Exp. longueur</term>
        <term lang="ru">Экспонента силы</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider acts on the length of ALL vectors, and so changes
            the strength of all brush strokes.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie die Stärke
            <emphasis>aller</emphasis> Vektoren, und damit die Stärke aller
            Pinselstriche beeinflussen. Die Einstellung wird mit Hilfe eines
            Schiebereglers oder des zugeordneten Eingabefeldes im Bereich von
            0,1 bis 10,9 vorgenommen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce curseur agit sur la longueur de TOUS les vecteurs, et donc
            modifie la force de tous les coups de brosse.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот ползунок изменяет длину ВСЕХ векторов, и таким образом
            изменяет силу всех мазков кисти.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
