<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-01-18 it added by alessandro falappa
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050915 de added by axel.wernicke
  051107 small add in Overview by julien hardelin
-->
<sect2 id="gimpressionist-size-map-editor" lang="en;de;fr;it;ru">
  <sect2info lang="de" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-04</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">GIMPressionist - Size Map Editor</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">GIMPressionist - Size-Map Editor</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">GIMPressionist - Éditeur de carte de taille</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">GIMPressionista - Editor Mappa Dimensione</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Гимпрессионист - редактор карты размеров</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Size Map Editor</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>GIMPressionist</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Éditeur de carte de taille</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Editor Mappa Dimensione</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Редактор карты размеров</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Überblick</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Size-map editor is an annexe of the <link
                                                  linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link> filter. You
      can get to it by clicking on the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button
      in the "Size" tab. With this editor, you can set the size that
      brush strokes given by filter will have.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Der Size-Map Editor ist Bestandteil des Filters <link
                                                          linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>. Er dient Ihnen
      zur Einstellung der Grösse in der die Pinselstriche ausgeführt werden,
      mit denen das Filter das Bild malt.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      L'Éditeur de carte de taille est une annexe du filtre <link
                                                                linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressioniste</link>. Vous y
      accédez en cliquant sur le bouton <guibutton>Éditer</guibutton> de
      l'onglet «Taille». Il vous sert à régler la taille qu'auront les
      coups de brosse que donne le filtre.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      L'Editor di mappe di dimensione è un annesso del filtro <link
      linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionista</link>. Si può
      richiamare premendo il pulsante <guibutton>Modifica</guibutton> nella
      linguetta <quote>Dimensione</quote>. Mediante questo editor si può
      immpostare la dimensione delle pennellate create dal filtro.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Редактор карты размеров - часть фильтра <link
                                                  linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">Гимпрессионист</link>. Вы можете
      вызвать его нажатием кнопки <guibutton>Правка</guibutton> в
      закладке <quote>Размер</quote>. С помощью этого редактора определяется
      размер мазков кисти фильтра.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Parameter Settings</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Réglage des paramètres</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Regolazione dei parametri</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Size-map editor options</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften des Dialoges <quote>Grössen-Map Editor</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Les options de l'«Éditeur de carte de taille»
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Opzioni dell'<quote>Editor mappa orientamento</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры <quote>Редактора карты размеров</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;it;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/options-artistic-gimpressionist-sizemap.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/de/options-artistic-gimpressionist-sizemap.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/fr/options-artistic-gimpressionist-sizemap.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <para lang="en">
        You can place one or several vectors. You can set their strength. They
        will act on the corresponding area of the image.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Vous pouvez placer un ou plusieurs vecteurs dont vous pouvez régler la
        force et qui agiront chacun sur la partie correspondante de l'image.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Si possono posizionare uno o più vettori. Per ciascuno di essi si può
        impostare l'intensità. Ogni vettore agisce sull'area corrispondente
        dell'immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Вы можете создать несколько векторов, указав их силу.
        Они будут действовать на соответствующую область изображения.
      </para>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Smvectors</term>
        <term lang="de">Sm-Vektoren</term>
        <term lang="fr">Vecteurs</term>
        <term lang="it">Vettori sm</term>
        <term lang="ru">Sm-вектор</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            In this window you can place your vectors. By clicking on
            the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button, you add a vector at the
            center of the window, whereas clicking with the mouse
            <emphasis>Middle Button</emphasis> puts it where you
            click.  Vectors are red when selected, and gray when they
            are not, with a white point at tip.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In diesem Bereich können Sie die Vektoren bearbeiten, welche die
            Grösse der Pinselstriche für diesen Bildbereich vorgeben.
            Die Vektoren werden als kleine Kreuze dargestellt. Der aktive
            Vektor wird rot dargestellt.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch Betätigen der Schaltfläche <guibutton>Hinzufügen</guibutton>
            können Sie neue Vektoren einsetzen. Alternativ können Sie durch
            Klicken mit der <mousebutton>Mittleren Maustaste</mousebutton>
            neue Vektoren an einer beliebigen Stelle hinzufügen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            C'est dans cette fenêtre que vous pouvez placer vos
            vecteurs.  Le clic sur le bouton
            <guibutton>Ajouter</guibutton>, place un vecteur au centre de
            la fenêtre, tandis que le clic avec le <emphasis>Bouton du
              milieu</emphasis> de la souris le place à l'endroit du clic.
            Ces vecteurs apparaissent comme de fins traits, rouges quand
            ils sont actifs, gris quand il ne sont pas actifs. Un point
            blanc marque leur pointe.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            In questa finestra si possono posizionare i vettori di dimensione.
            Premendo il pulsante <guibutton>Aggiungi</guibutton> si aggiunge
            un vettore al centro del pannello mentre premendo il 
            <emphasis>tasto centrale</emphasis> del mouse aggiunge un
            vettore nel punto in cui si è fatto click. I vettori sono di
            colore rosso quando selezionati e grigi quando non selezionati
            e con un punto bianco ad una estremità.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            В этом окне осуществляется управление векторами. Чтобы
            добавить вектор в центр окна, нажмите на кнопку
            <guilabel>Добавить</guilabel>. Чтобы добавить вектор в
            определенное место окна, нажмите в нем <emphasis>средней
              кнопкой мыши</emphasis>. Выбраный вектор будет красным,
            остальные - серыми с белой  точкой в середине.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Clicking with the mouse <emphasis>Left Button</emphasis>
            displaces the selected vector to the clicked point.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch einen Klick mit der <mousebutton>Linken
              Maustaste</mousebutton> wird der aktive Vektor an die Stelle des
            Bildes verschoben, welche Sie angeklickt haben.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Avec un <emphasis>Clic gauche</emphasis>, le vecteur actif
            vient se placer à l'endroit du clic.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Premendo il <emphasis>tasto sinistro</emphasis> del mouse si
            sposta il vettore selezionato nel punto in cui si è fatto click.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Нажатие <emphasis>левой кнопки выши</emphasis> перемещает
            выбраный вектор в место нажатия.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Clicking on the mouse <emphasis>Right Button</emphasis>, has
            no evident action.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le <emphasis>Clic droit</emphasis>, paraît sans objet ici et
            n'a aucune action.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Нажатие <emphasis>правой кнопки мыши</emphasis> не будет иметь
            последствий.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Clicking on <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> et
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> buttons displaces focus from a
            vector to another.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit den Schaltflächen <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> und
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> können Sie den aktiven Vektor
            wechseln.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les boutons <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> et
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> vous permettent de faire
            passer le focus d'un vecteur à l'autre.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Premendo i pulsanti <guibutton>&lt;&lt;</guibutton> e
            <guibutton>&gt;&gt;</guibutton> si selezionano ciclicamente i
            vettori.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            С помощью кнопок <guilabel>&lt;&lt;</guilabel> и
            <guilabel>&gt;&gt;</guilabel> вы можете переместить фокус с
            одного вектора  на другой.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            The <guibutton>Kill</guibutton> button allows you to delete
            the selected vector.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Entfernen</guibutton>
            betätigen, wird der aktuelle Vektor gelöscht.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le bouton <guibutton>Supprimer</guibutton> vous permet de
            supprimer le vecteur actif.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il pulsante <guilabel>Rimuovi</guilabel> consente di eliminare il
            vettore selezionato.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Кнопка <guilabel>Удалить</guilabel> удаляет выбранный вектор.
          </para>
          <tip>
            <para lang="en">
              With the scroll bar on the right of the Vectors panel, you can
              set the image brightness. This can be very useful if the image
              is very dark/bright and you cann't see vectors well.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Mit dem Schieberegler neben dem Vorschaubild können Sie die
              Helligkeit des Bildes einstellen. Dies kann sehr nützlich sein,
              wenn das Bild sehr hell ist und Sie die Vektoren sehr schlecht
              erkennen können.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              La barre de défilement à la droite du panneau Vecteurs vous
              permet de régler la clatée de l'affichage. C'est très utile
              si l'image est trop claire/sombre et que vous ne voyez pas
              bien les vecteurs.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              Si può cambiare la luminosità dell'immagine attraverso la barra
              di scorrimento alla destra del pannello dei vettori. Può essere
              molto utile se l'immagine è molto chiara/scura e non si
              distinguono bene i vettori.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Линейкой прокрутки в правой части панели устанавливается
              яркость изображения. Это помогает в тех случаях, когда
              изображение слишком темное, и векторы плохо видно.
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <term lang="it">Anteprima</term>
        <term lang="ru">Просмотр</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This Preview gives you an idea of the action of the different
            vectors. The size of squares represent the size of the brushes
            and their strength.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In diesem Vorschaufenster werden für das gesamte Bild die
            aktuellen Grössen und Stärken der Pinselstriche angezeigt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cet Aperçu vous donne une idée de l'action des différents vecteurs.
            La taille des carrés représentent la taille des coups de brosse et
            leur force.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questa anteprima dà un'idea dell'azione dei diversi vettori. La
            dimensione dei quadrati rappresenta la dimensione delle pennellate
            e la loro intensità.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            В окне просмотра отображается схема действия всех векторов. Размер
            квадратов показывает размер кисти в этом месте и ее силу.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Size</term>
        <term lang="de">Grösse</term>
        <term lang="fr">Taille</term>
        <term lang="it">Dimensione</term>
        <term lang="ru">Размер</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Change the size of the brush strokes in the selected vector
            domain.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie die Grösse der Pinselstriche
            einstellen. Hierzu stehen Ihnen ein Schieberegler, sowie ein
            Eingabefeld zur Verfügung. Der Wert kann zwischen 0,0 und 100,0
            eingestellt werden.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Modifie la taille des coups de brosse dans le domaine du vecteur
            actif.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Cambia la dimensione delle pennellate nell'area di influenza del
            vettore selezionato.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Изменяет размер мазка кисти в области выбранного вектора.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Strength</term>
        <term lang="de">Stärke</term>
        <term lang="fr">Force</term>
        <term lang="it">Forza</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сила</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider acts on the influence domain of the selected vector.
            This influence lowers with distance.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie die Stärke des Vektors
            einstellen. Durch seine Stärke beeinflusst der Vektor die ihn
            umgebenden Vektoren.Die Einstellung können Sie über einen
            Schieberegler oder mit Hilfe des zugeordneten Eingabefeldes im
            Bereich von 0,1 bis 5,0 vornehmen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce curseur agit sur le domaine d'influence du vecteur actif.
            Cette influence décroît avec la distance.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo cursore agisce sull'area di influenza del vettore
            selezionato. L'area di influenza decresce con la distanza.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот ползунок изменяет область влияния выбранного вектора. Это
            влияние уменьшается с расстоянием.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Strength Exp.</term>
        <term lang="de">Stärke Exp.</term>
        <term lang="fr">Exp. force</term>
        <term lang="it">Esponente forza</term>
        <term lang="ru">Экспонента силы</term>

        <listitem>
          <!-- TODO: de en fr it explain more detailed what this is for -->
          <para lang="en">
            Change the exponent of the stroke.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie den Exponent der Stärke
            einstellen. Hierzu stehen Ihnen ein Schieberegler sowie ein
            Eingabefeld zur Verfügung. Die Einstellung können Sie im Bereich
            von 0,1 bis 10,9 vornehmen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Modifie l'exposant de la force. (?)
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Cambia l'esponente della pennellata.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Изменяет экспоненту силы мазка.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;de;it">Voronoi</term>
        <term lang="fr">Voronoï</term>
        <term lang="ru">Вороной</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            See <link linkend="gimpressionist-orient-map-editor">
              Orientation Map Editor</link> for an explanation.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Ein Varonoi Diagramm zerteilt eine Fläche mit n Hauptpunkten in
            n Poygone. Dabei hat jedes der Polygone einen Hauptpunkt und jeder
            Punkt des Polygons ist näher an diesem Hauptpunkt als an jedem
            anderen. Daher ist die Grenze für jedes Poygon die halbe
            Entfernung zwischen zwei Hauptpunkten. Die folgende Abbildung
            enthält ein Beispiel:
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/voronoi.png"
                          format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Wenn diese Eigenschaft aktiviert ist, beeinflusst nur der Vektor,
            welcher einem bestimmten Punkt am nächsten ist diesen Punkt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Voir <link linkend="gimpressionist-orient-map-editor">
              Éditeur de carte d'orientation</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Si veda <link linkend="gimpressionist-orient-map-editor">Editor
            Mappa Orientamento</link> per la spiegazione.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Информация об этом параметре содержится в разделе
            <link linkend="gimpressionist-orient-map-editor">
              Карта редактирования ориентации</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
