<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050916 added by axel.wernicke
  051022 en;fr by julien hardelin
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-photocopy" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;ru">
  <sect2info lang="cs;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-04-19</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-04</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-10-19</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Photocopy</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Fotokopie</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Fotokopie</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Photocopie</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Fotocopia</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Фотокопия</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Artistic</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Photocopy</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Filtry</primary>
    <secondary>Umění</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Fotokopie</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Künstlerisch</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Fotokopie</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Artistique</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Photocopie</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary>
    <secondary>Artistici</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Fotocopia</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Фильтры</primary>
    <secondary>Имитация</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Фотокопия</primary></indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Přehled</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Wirkungsweise</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          The same image, before and after applying Photocopy filter
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">
          Stejný obrázek před a po aplikaci filtru Fotokopie.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Anwendungsbeispiel für das Filter <quote>Fotokopie</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          La même image, avant et après application du filtre Photocopie
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di applicazione del filtro <quote>Fotocopia</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Изображение до и после применения фильтра <quote>Фотокопия</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="en;de">
          <para lang="en">Original image</para>
          <para lang="de">Originalbild</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/examples/artistic-taj-photocopy.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="en;de">
          <para lang="en">Filter <quote>Photocopy</quote> applied</para>
          <para lang="de">Filter <quote>Fotokopie</quote> angewandt</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      The Photocopy filter modifies the active layer or selection so that it
      looks like a black and white photocopy, as if toner transfered was
      based on the relative darkness of a particular region. This is
      achieved by darkening areas of the image which are measured to be
      darker than a neighborhood average, and setting other pixels to white.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs"><!--FIXME-cs: popis algoritmu?-->
      Filtr Fotokopie upravuje aktivní vrstvu či výběr tak, aby vypadala jako
      černobílá fotokopie, jako by byl toner přenášen na základě relativní
      tmavosti dané oblasti. Dosáhne se toho ztmavením oblastí, které jsou
      tmavší než je průměr okolí, a nastavením ostatních pixelů na bílou
      barvu.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Mit diesem Filter können Sie Ihrem Bild das Aussehen einer Fotokopie
      geben. Es stehen Ihnen verschiedene Eigenschaften zur Verfügung, um
      den Effekt nach Ihren Wünschen zu gestalten.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre modifie le calque actif ou la sélection pour les faire
      ressembler à une photocopie en noir et blanc, comme si l'encre
      transférée du toner dépendait de l'obscurité relative d'une région
      particulière. Cela est réalisé en noircissant les zones de l'image plus
      sombres que la moyenne de leur voisinage, et en rendant blancs les
      autres pixels.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il filtro Fotocopia modifica il livello o la selezione correnti in modo
      tale che assomiglino ad una fotocopia in bianco e nero, come se
      l'inchiostro trasferito fosse basato sulla percentuale di aree scure di
      una certa regione. Lavora scurendo le aree dell'immagine che
      risultano essere più scure della media delle aree circostanti e
      colorando di bianco gli altri pixel.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Фильтр <quote>Фотокопия</quote> изменяет текущий слой или
      выделение так, что он выглядит как чёрно-белая копия, как если бы
      количество чернил  зависело от относительной темноты определённой
      области. Это достигается путём затемнения тех областей
      изображения, где цвет темнее среднего цвета окружения и придания
      оставшимся пикселам значения белого цвета.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Starting filter</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Spuštění filtru</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Filteraufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Lancement du filtre</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Richiamare il filtro</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Расположение</phrase>
    </title>
    <para lang="en">
      You can find this filter from the image menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filte<accel>r</accel>s</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>rtistic</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>hotocopy</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr najdete v nabídce okna obrázku jako
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Umění</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fotokopie</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter lässt sich über das Menü
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>K</accel>ünstlerisch</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>otokopie</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      im Bildfenster aufrufen.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      On accède à ce filtre par le menu d'image, en suivant
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filt<accel>r</accel>es</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>rtistique</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>hotocopie</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      Larges emprunts au Exts/Navigateur de greffons/.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro si trova nel menu immagine:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtri</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>rtistici</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>F</accel>otocopia</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр находится в меню
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Фильтры</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>И<accel>м</accel>итация</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Фотокопия</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Photocopy</quote> filter options
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">
          Volby filtru <quote>Fotokopie</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften für das Filter <quote>Fotokopie</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Options du filtre <quote>Photocopie</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Opzioni del filtro <quote>Fotocopia</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры для фильтра <quote>Фотокопия</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;it;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/options-artistic-photocopy.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/options-artistic-photocopy.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/de/options-artistic-photocopy.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/fr/options-artistic-photocopy.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry lang="de">
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Dieses Filter stellt Ihnen eine kleines Vorschaufenster zur
            Verfügung, in dem Sie die Wirkung der aktuellen Einstellungen
            der Filtereigenschaften ansehen können, ohne das Filter bereits
            direkt auf das Bild angewendet zu haben.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mask radius</term>
        <term lang="cs">Poloměr masky</term>
        <term lang="de">Masken Radius</term>
        <term lang="fr">Rayon du masque</term>
        <term lang="it">Raggio di mascheratura</term>
        <term lang="ru">Радиус маски</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This parameter controls the size of the pixel neighbourhood over
            which the average intensity is computed and then compared to
            each pixel in the neighborhood to decide whether or not to
            darken it. Large values result in very thick black areas
            bordering the regions of white and much less detail for black
            areas. Small values result in less toner overall and more
            details everywhere.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tento parametr nastavuje velikost sousedství pixelů, ve kterém je
            počítána průměrná intenzita pro porovnání s jednotlivými pixely a
            rozhodnutí, zda mají být ztmaveny. Vyšší hodnoty vytváří velmi
            silné tmavé oblasti okolo oblastí bílých a mnohem méně detailů
            v tmavých oblastech. Nižší hodnoty způsobují použití menšího
            množství barvy a více podrobností ve všech oblastech.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, wie stark das
            Filter wirkt. Die Einstellung können Sie über einen
            Schieberegler oder das zugeordnete Eingabefeld vornehmen. Der
            Wert kann im Bereich von 3,0 bis 50,0 Pixel liegen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce paramètre contrôle la taille de l'entourage du pixel qui
            permettra de calculer l'intensité moyenne et de décider s'il
            faut ou non noircir le pixel. Des valeurs élevées donnent
            d'épaisses plages de noir bordant les zones blanches et beaucoup
            moins de détails dans les zones noires. Des valeurs faibles
            donnent une charge d'encre moindre et plus de détails partout.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo parametro controlla la dimensione dell'area di pixel sulla
            quale viene calcolata l'intensità media per decidere se il pixel
            debba essere scurito o meno. Alti valori producono aree nere
            confinanti con le regioni di bianco molto spesse. Bassi valori
            producono un minor trasferimento di inchiostro e più dettagli
            ovunque.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот параметр устанавливает размер рабочей области фильтра,
            в которой вычисляется среднее значение яркости и
            сравнивается с окружением. Большее значение параметра
            создает более плотные области черного цвета с минимумом
            деталей. Меньшее значение параметра создает больше деталей и
            меньше чёрного.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Sharpness</term>
        <term lang="cs">Ostrost</term>
        <term lang="de">Schärfe</term>
        <term lang="fr">Augmentation de contraste</term>
        <term lang="it">Nitidezza</term>
        <term lang="ru">Резкость</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            With this option, you can set photocopy sharpness, from 0.0 to
            1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tato volba umožňuje nastavit ostrost fotokopie. Možné hodnoty
            jsou od 0.0 do 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, wie scharf die
            Fotokopie sein soll. Die Einstellung können Sie über einen
            Schieberegler oder das zugeordnete Eingabefeld im Bereich von
            0,0 bis 1,0 vornehmen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Avec cette option, vous pouvez régler la netteté de la
            photocopie, de 0,0 à 1,0.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Con questa opzione si può impostare la nitidezza della fotocopia
            da 0.0 a 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот параметр управляет резкостью фотокопии.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Percent black</term>
        <term lang="cs">Procento černé</term>
        <term lang="de">Schwarz (%)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Pourcentage de noir</term>
        <term lang="it">Percentuale del nero</term>
        <term lang="ru">Процент чёрного</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This parameter controls the amount of black color added to the
            image. Small values make the blend from color regions to blackened
            areas smoother and dark lines themselves thinner and less
            noticeable. Larger values make the lines thicker, darker and
            sharper. The maximum value makes the lines aliased. The best, most
            natural results are usually achieved with an intermediate value.
            Values vary from 0.0 to 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tento parametr ovlivňuje množství černé barvy přidané do obrázku.
            Je-li hodnota malá, jsou přechody do černých oblastí jemnější
            a tmavé čáry jsou užší a méně patrné. Vysoké hodnoty vytváří
            silnější, tmavší a ostřejší černé oblasti. Maximální hodnota
            vytváří nevyhlazené (aliasované) černé oblasti. Nejlepší a
            nejpřirozenější výsledky je obvykle možno dosáhnout středními
            hodnotami. Hodnota se může pohybovat mezi 0.0 a 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie den Prozentsatz der
            abgedunkelten Pixel einstellen, die geschwärzt werden. Die
            Einstellung können Sie im Bereich von 0,0 bis 1,0 mit Hilfe eines
            Schiebereglers oder des zugeordneten Eingabefeldes vornehmen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce paramètre contrôle le taux de noir ajouté à l'image. Les
            faibles valeurs noircissent à peine les zones sombres et ne
            modifient guère les lignes sombres. Les valeurs élevées donnent
            des lignes plus épaisses, parfois crénelées. Les valeurs
            moyennes donnent les meilleurs résultats. Valeurs de 0,0 à 1,0.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo parametro controlla la quantità di colore nero aggiunta
            all'immagine. Valori bassi rendono più graduale la miscelazione
            dalle aree colorate alle aree scurite e le linee scure stesse più
            sottili e meno evidenti. Alti valori rendono le linee scure più
            spesse, più scure e nitide. Il valore massimo rende le linee
            scalettate. I valori migliori, dai risultati più naturali si
            ottengono con un valore intermedio. Il parametro varia tra 0.0 e
            1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот параметр устанавливает количество чёрного цвета,
            добавляемого к изображению. Маленькие значения делают
            переход области цвета в затемнённую область сглаженным, а
            сами тёмные линии - более тонкими и незаметными. Значения
            побольше делают линии толще, темнее и чётче. Для получения
            лучших, более натуральных результатов, используйте
            промежуточные значения.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Percent White</term>
        <term lang="cs">Procento bílé</term>
        <term lang="de">Weiß (%)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Pourcentage de blanc</term>
        <term lang="it">Percentuale del bianco</term>
        <term lang="ru">Процент белого</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This parameter increases white pixels percentage.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tento parametr ovlivňuje procento bílé barvy.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie den Prozentsatz der
            aufgehellten Pixel einstellen, die weiß gefärbt werden. Die
            Einstellung können Sie im Bereich von 0,0 bis 1,0 mit Hilfe eines
            Schiebereglers oder des zugeordneten Eingabefeldes vornehmen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ce paramètre augmente le pourcentage de pixels blancs.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questo parametro aumenta la percentuale dei pixel bianchi.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот параметр устанавливает количество белого цвета по сравнению
            с чёрным.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
