<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2010-04-21 liangtai: created initial version
-->
<sect2 id="script-fu-weave">
  <title>Weave</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Artistic</secondary>
    <tertiary>Weave</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Weave</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example of Weave</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/artistic-taj-weave.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>Weave</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The <guimenuitem>Weave</guimenuitem> command is a Script-Fu script
      which creates a new layer filled with a weave effect and adds it to
      the image as an overlay or bump map.  The result of the image looks
      as if it were printed over woven ribbons of paper, thin wooden sheet,
      or stripped bamboo.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the image is in indexed colors, this menu entry is disabled.
    </para>
    <para>
      This filter adds a <quote>Multiply</quote> mode layer upon the layer
      where you activate this command. The weave texture is rendered in gray
      levels.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the main menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Artistic</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Weave…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Weave</quote> filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/artistic/weave.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      For to make coarse mesh texture, increase the ribbon spacing and/or
      decrease the ribbon width.
    </para>
    <para>
      For to strain ribbons hard, decrease the shadow depth.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Ribbon width</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the tape width in pixel between
            0.0 and 256.0.  In default, 30.0 pixels is set.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Ribbon spacing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the distance to the neighboring
            ribbon or the size of black square hole in pixel between 0.0
            and 256.0.  In default, 10.0 pixels is set.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shadow darkness</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the darkness at crossings of lower
            ribbon in percentage.  Lower value shows ribbons thinner.  75.0
            percent is the default value.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shadow depth</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the bent strength of ribbons in
            percentage.  Higher value shows ribbons more wavy, lower value
            for flat surface.  The actual effect is limited by the
            <guilabel>Shadow darkness</guilabel>.
            75.0 percent is the default value.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Thread length</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the regularity of stripe texture.
            If this value is shorter than the summary of the ribbon width
            and twice of the ribbon spacing, the surface of ribbon becomes
            speckled.  Set this value in pixel on range between 0.0 to
            256.0.  The default value is 200.0.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Thread density</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the density of fiber-like parallel
            short stripes on the surface of ribbons. To populate stripes
            increase this value.  50.0 percent is the default value.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Thread intensity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option you can set the opacity of stripe texture.
            Lower value shows threads vague.  To clear off threads set the
            value to 0.0 percent.  The default value is 100.0 percent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Another usage</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Adding a lattice using <quote>Weave</quote> texture</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/artistic-weave-as-lattice.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Narrower the ribbon width, wider the ribbon spacing, and
            filled with the <quote>Wood&nbsp;#1</quote> pattern.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      This texture can be a lattice that you can see the original image
      through its mesh holes.  Add a new, transparent layer over the active
      layer for the lattice, and apply this filter.  Select a black regular
      square in the texture layer using the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Select By Color</link> tool,
      then delete black squares in selection on the texture layer to be chink
      holes.  Reverse the selection, and activate the transparent layer so
      that you can fill the lattice surface with a pattern, then drag and drop
      your favorite pattern over the image window.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
