<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect3 id='Image_window-menus-edit-paste_into'>
  <title lang="en">Paste Into</title>
  <title lang="fr">Coller dans</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Paste Into</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Coller dans</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect>
    <varlistentry>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          This command is found in 
          <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Edit/Paste <accel>I</accel>nto...</guimenuitem>.     
        </para>         
        <para>
          The Paste Into command acts in a similar method to the Paste 
          command. The primary difference becomes apparent if there is a 
          selection within the canvas. Unlike a Paste which will merely 
          center the pasted image data over the selection and remove the old 
          selection replacing it with its own, Paste Into will clip the 
          pasted data using the existing selection. The new selection can be 
          moved as per normal, but will always remain clipped by the 
          original selection area. 
        </para>
        <para>
          If no selection exists, the command will place the data from the 
          Clipboard in the center of the canvas as per the Paste command. 
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          Cette commande se trouve dans 
          <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Édition/Coller <accel>d</accel>ans...</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para>
          La commande «Coller dans» fonctionne de la même façon que la 
          commande Coller. Son originalité apparaît quand il existe une 
          sélection sur le canevas. À la différence de Coller qui simplement 
          centre le collage sur la sélection et vient l'écraser, Coller dans 
          découpera le collage selon les limites de la sélection. 
          La nouvelle sélection peut être déplacée normalement 
        </para>
        <para>
          Si aucune sélection n'existe, la commande placera les données du 
          presse-papier au centre du canevas comme avec la commande Coller.
        </para>    
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </simplesect>

</sect3>
