<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2009-06-25 ude: updated (incl. new screenshots)
  2006-10-21 lexa: added german translation
  2006-02-27 no added by kolbjoern stuestoel
  2005-12-12 moved to the appendix and made it valid docbook by lexa
-->
<appendix id="gimp-introduction-bugs">
  <title>Reporting Bugs and Requesting Enhancements</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Bugs</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Bugs</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Sad to say, no version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    has yet been absolutely perfect. Even sadder, it is likely that no version
    ever will be. In spite of all efforts to make everything work, a program
    as complicated as <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    is bound to screw things up occasionally, or even crash.
  </para>
  <para>
    But the fact that bugs are unavoidable does not mean that they should be
    passively accepted. If you find a bug in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, the
    developers would like to know about it so they can at least try to fix it.
  </para>
  <para>
    Suppose, then, that you have found a bug, or at least think you have: you
    try to do something, and the results are not what you expect. What should
    you do? How should you report it?
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      The procedure for making an <emphasis>enhancement
      request</emphasis>&mdash;that is, for asking the developers to add a
      missing feature&mdash;is nearly the same as the procedure for reporting
      a bug. The only thing you do differently is to mark the report as an
      <quote>enhancement</quote> at the appropriate stage, as described below.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
    In common with many other free software projects,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses a bug-reporting mechanism called
    <emphasis>Bugzilla</emphasis>.
    This is a very powerful web-based system, capable of managing thousands
    of bug reports without losing track. In fact, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    shares its Bugzilla database with the entire Gnome project. At the time
    this is being written, Gnome Bugzilla contains 148632 bug reports–no, make
    that 148633.
  </para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Making sure it's a Bug</title>
    <para>
      The first thing you should do, before reporting a bug, is to make
      an effort to verify that what you are seeing really
      <emphasis>is</emphasis> a bug.  It is hard to give a method for
      doing this that applies to all situations, but reading the
      documentation will often be useful, and discussing the question on
      IRC or a mailing list may also be quite helpful.  If you are
      seeing a <emphasis>crash</emphasis>, as opposed to mere
      misbehavior, the odds that it is a true bug are pretty high: well
      written software programs are not designed to crash under
      <emphasis>any</emphasis> circumstances.  In any case, if you have
      made an conscientious effort to decide whether it is really a bug,
      and at the end still aren't sure, then please go ahead and report
      it:  the worst that can happen is that you will waste a bit of
      time for the development team.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Actually there are a few things that are known to cause
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to crash but have turned out to be too
        inconvenient to be worth fixing.  One of them is asking
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to do something that requires vast amounts of
        memory, such as creating an image one million pixels on a side.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      You should also make sure that you are using an up-to-date version
      of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>: reporting bugs that have already been
      fixed is just a waste of everybody's time.  (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1
      is no longer maintained, so if you use it and find bugs, either
      upgrade to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 or live with
      them.)  Particularly if you are using the development version of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, make sure that you can see the bug in the
      latest release before filing a report.
    </para>
    <para>
      If after due consideration you still think you have a legitimate
      bug report or enhancement request, the next step is to go to
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s bugzilla query page
      (<ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/query.cgi"/>),
      and try to see whether somebody else has already reported the same
      thing.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are two forms you can use for searching bugs: a simple
      <quote>short</quote> form, and an advanced <quote>complicated</quote>
      form.
    </para>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-query-short">
      <title>The Short Bug Search Form</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Short Bug Search Form</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/query-short.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Searching for bugs using the short bug search form</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Using the short form, you just have to enter some (space separated)
        search terms, e.g.
        <blockquote>
          <para>
          <userinput>gimp&nbsp;filter&nbsp;crash</userinput>
          </para>
        </blockquote>
        in the text box and click on <guilabel>Search</guilabel>.  Even
        elaborate terms like
        <blockquote>
          <para>
          <userinput>product:gimp severity>=major</userinput>
          </para>
        </blockquote>
        are possible.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <para>
          Clicking on <quote>Help</quote> will lead you to an excellent help
          page, including some instructive <quote>Examples with
          Explanations</quote>.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-query-complicated">
      <title>The Complicated Bug Search Form</title>
      <para>
        The alternative form, the advanced query page, allows you to search
        the bug database in a variety of ways:
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Complicated Bug Search Form</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/query-complicated.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Searching for bugs using the complicated bug search form
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Unfortunately this page is a bit more <quote>complicated</quote> to
        use than it really ought to be (at least, some items are hyperlinks
        leading to detailed help), but here is basically what you should do:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Summary</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Set this to <quote>contains any of the words/strings</quote>.
            </para>
            <para>
              In the adjoining text box, give one or more words that somebody
              would be likely to use in writing a one-sentence summary of a
              bug similar to yours. For example, if the problem is that
              zooming too much causes <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to crash, the
              word <quote>zoom</quote> would be good.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Classification</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Other (since <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is not part of the GNOME
              Desktop suite).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Product</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Set this to <quote>GIMP</quote> (or <quote>GEGL</quote>,
              <quote>GIMP-manual</quote> etc., if appropriate).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Component, Version, Target Milestone</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Don't do anything for these.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Comment, Whiteboard, Keywords</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              For now, leave this alone. If your search does not turn up
              anything, it might be worth entering your search terms in the
              <quote>Comment</quote> area here, but this often turns out to
              give you either great masses of stuff or nothing.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Status</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This field encodes the status of a bug report: whether it is
              still open, has been resolved, etc. You want to see all relevant
              bug reports, regardless of status, so you should hold down the
              mouse and sweep it across all entries. Leaving it alone will not
              work.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Resolution, Severity, Priority, OS</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Usually you shouldn't touch these items.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>(Any other items)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Don't do anything for these.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        When you have set these things up, click on the <quote>Search</quote>
        button at either the top or bottom; they both do the same thing. The
        result is either a list of bug reports &ndash; hopefully not too long
        &ndash; or a message saying <quote>Zarro boogs found</quote>. If you
        don't find a related bug report by doing this, it may be worth trying
        another search with different terms. If in spite of your best efforts,
        you file a bug report and it ends up being resolved as
        <quote>Duplicate</quote>, don't be too upset: it has happened
        repeatedly to the author of this documentation, who works with
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Bugzilla nearly every day.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <para>
          Depending on your browser configuration (i.e. whether JavaScript is
          enabled), you may see a link
          <guilabel>Give&nbsp;me&nbsp;some&nbsp;help</guilabel>. If you click
          on this link, the page will be reloaded and then moving the mouse
          pointer over an input widget produces a little help popup.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </simplesect>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Reporting the Bug</title>
    <para>
      Okay, so you have done everything you could to make sure, and you still
      think it's probably a bug. You should then go ahead and file a bug
      report on the Bugzilla page.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        The first time you file a bug report, you will be asked to create a
        Bugzilla account. The process is easy and painless, and you probably
        won't even get any spam as a result.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      There are two ways to file a bug report: a simple way using a guided
      tour, or a more advanced way using a single page.
    </para>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-simple-bug-guide">
      <title>The Simple Bug Guide</title>
      <para>
        If you go to
        <ulink url=" http://bugzilla.gnome.org/simple-bug-guide.cgi"/>,
        you have to login, of course, and then you start a guided tour
        with the following dialog:
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Simple Bug Guide</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/simple-bug-guide.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>First dialog window of the simple bug guide</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        First you will have to answer a few questions, that is you just have
        to select one of several choices.  As you can see in the above figure,
        you will always get some useful explanations.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <para>You will be asked for</para>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Bug type</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <quote>Normal</quote> is usually a good choice (but have a look
              at the explanations).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Classification and Application</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Select Classification <quote>Other</quote>, and Application
              <quote>GIMP</quote>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Component</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Set this to the part of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that the bug
              affects. You have to pick something here, but if you aren't
              sure, make a guess and don't worry about it.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Severity</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In most cases you should either leave this as
              <quote>Normal</quote> or set it to <quote>Enhancement</quote>,
              if it is an enhancement request rather than a malfunction. The
              maintainers will adjust the severity if they think it is
              warranted.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Version</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Set this to the version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that you are
              using. See
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        Then you get to the guided bug report form, which you should fill out
        as follows:
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Enter bug information</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/enter-bug-info.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist id="bugzilla-bug-information">
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Summary</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Give a one-sentence summary that is descriptive enough so that
              somebody searching for similar bugs would find your bug report on
              the basis of the words this summary contains.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Description</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Describe the problem. Be as specific as you can, and include all
              information that you think might possibly be relevant. The
              classic totally useless bug report is, <quote>GIMP crashes. This
              program sucks</quote>.  There is no hope that the developers can
              solve a problem if they can't tell what it is.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Steps to reproduce the bug</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If at all possible, give a procedure that will reliably
              reproduce the buggy behavior, and give it in enough detail so
              that a moron could follow it.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Additional information</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Here you may add any additional information that might be
              relevant, but it's not necessary to duplicate your previous
              reports.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-advanced-bugreport">
      <title>The Advanced Bugreport</title>
      <para>
        To use the advanced bug form, go to
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi"/>,
        and scroll down the page until you can select the product
        <quote>GIMP</quote>.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Enter Bug (pick a product)</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/pick-product.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Select the product: <acronym>GIMP</acronym></para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <tip>
        <para>
          You can skip this step by using
          <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=GIMP"/>.
        </para>
      </tip>

      <para>
        Selecting <quote>GIMP</quote> as product takes you to the following
        bug report form, which you should fill out as follows. Note that most
        of the information you enter can be changed later by the developers if
        you get it wrong, so try to get it right but don't be obsessive about
        it.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Enter Bug (<acronym>GIMP</acronym>)</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/enter-bug.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>The main bugreport page</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Version, Severity</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              See <link linkend="bugzilla-simple-bug-guide">Simple Bug
              Guide</link>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Operating System</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Set this to your OS unless you have a very good reason for
              thinking that the bug applies to all operating systems.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Summary, Description</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              See <link linkend="bugzilla-bug-information">Enter bug
              information</link>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <!--
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Priority</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In most cases you should leave this at <quote>Normal</quote>,
              and allow the maintainers to adjust it. Setting the priority to
              <quote>Immediate</quote> or <quote>Urgent</quote> usually just
              manages to annoy people.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        -->
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        You can ignore the rest. When you have filled out all of these things,
        press the <guilabel>Commit</guilabel> button and your bug report will
        be submitted. It will be assigned a number, which you may want to make
        note of; you will, however, be emailed any time somebody makes a
        comment on your bug report or otherwise alters it, so you will receive
        reminders in any case. You can see the current state of your bug
        report at any time by going to
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org"/> and, at the
        bottom of the page, in the <quote>Actions:</quote> area, entering the
        bug number and pressing the <guilabel>Find</guilabel> button.
      </para>
      <para>
        Sometimes it is very helpful to augment a bug report with a screenshot
        or some other type of data. If you need to do this, go to the web page
        for your bug report, click on the link <quote>Create a New
        Attachment</quote>, and follow the directions. But please don't do
        this unless you think the attachment is really going to be
        useful&mdash;and if you need to attach a screenshot, don't make it any
        larger than necessary. Bug reports are likely to remain on the system
        for years, so there is no sense in wasting memory.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>What Happens to a Bug Report after you Submit it</title>
    <para>
      At any time after it is submitted, a bug report has a
      <quote>Status</quote>
      that describes how it is currently being handled.  Here are the
      possible values of <emphasis>Status</emphasis> and what they mean:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unconfirmed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the initial status of a bug report, from the time it is
            submitted until one of the maintainers reads it and decides
            whether it is really a valid bug report. Sometimes the maintainers
            aren't sure, and in the meantime leave the status as
            <quote>Unconfirmed</quote>. In the worst cases, a bug report can
            stay
            unconfirmed for a year or longer, but this is considered a bad
            thing and does not happen very often.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>New</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This means that the bug report has been read by one of the
            maintainers, and is considered, for the moment at least, to be
            valid. It does not necessarily mean that anything is going to be
            done about it immediately: some bug reports, especially
            enhancement requests, may be perfectly valid and still go for a
            long time before anybody is able to deal with them. Many bugs, on
            the other hand, are fixed within hours of being reported.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Assigned</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This means that a specific person has agreed to work on the bug.
            It does not, this world being the kind of world that it is, mean
            that that person will actually <emphasis>do</emphasis>
            anything in particular, so for practical purposes this status
            means nearly the same thing as <quote>New</quote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reopened</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This means that the bug report was at some point considered by the
            maintainers to be resolved (i.e., finished), but new information
            came in that caused them to change their minds: most likely, a
            change that was intended to fix the problem did not completely
            work.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Needinfo</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is a status you should pay particular attention to. It means
            that you did not supply enough information in your bug report to
            enable anything to be done about it. In most cases, no further
            action will be taken on the bug report until you supply additional
            information (by adding a comment). If too much time goes by
            without any input from you, the bug report will eventually be
            resolved as <quote>Incomplete</quote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Resolved</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This means that the maintainers believe that they have finished
            dealing with the bug report. If you disagree, you can re-open it,
            but since you cannot force anybody to work on a bug against their
            will, you should have a good reason for doing so. Bugs can be
            resolved in a variety of ways. Here are the possible values of
            <emphasis>Resolution</emphasis> and what they mean:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Fixed</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The bug report is considered valid, and
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has been
                  changed in a way that is considered to fix it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Wontfix</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The maintainers agree that the bug report is valid, but it
                  would take so much effort to fix, in relation to its
                  importance, that it is not worth the trouble.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Duplicate</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This means that the same bug has already been reported by
                  somebody else. If you see this resolution, you will also see
                  a pointer to the earlier bug report, which will often give
                  you a lot of useful information.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Notabug</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This means that the behavior described in the bug
                  report is intentional. It may seem like a bug to you
                  (and there may be many people who agree with you), but
                  the program is working the way it was intended to
                  work,  and the developers don't want to change it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>NotGnome</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The bug report is valid, but it can't be addressed by
                  changing <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Problems in operating
                  systems, window managers, or libraries that
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> depends on will often be
                  given this resolution. Sometimes the next appropriate step
                  is to file a bug report for the software that is really at
                  fault.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Incomplete</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The bug report did not contain enough information for
                  anything to be done about it, and the reporter did not
                  respond to requests for more information. Usually a bug
                  report will be open for at least a month or two before it is
                  resolved in this way.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Invalid</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Something is wrong with the form of the bug report: most
                  commonly, the reporter has accidentally submitted the same
                  bug report multiple times. (This can easily happen by
                  mistake with some web browsers.) Bug reports that
                  incorrectly describe how the program behaves may also be
                  resolved as Invalid.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <note>
            <para>
              If you disagree with the resolution of a bug report, you are
              always free to add your comments to it. Any comment added to any
              bug report, resolved or not, causes email to be sent to the
              <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
              Bugzilla mailing list, so it will at least be seen by the
              maintainers. This does not, of course, mean that they will
              necessarily respond to it.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
