<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2009-08-25 ude: updated again due to the recent Bugzilla upgrade
  2009-06-25 ude: updated (incl. new screenshots)
  2006-10-21 lexa: added german translation
  2006-02-27 no added by kolbjoern stuestoel
  2005-12-12 moved to the appendix and made it valid docbook by lexa
-->
<appendix id="gimp-introduction-bugs">
  <title>Reporting Bugs and Requesting Enhancements</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Bugs</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Bugs</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Sad to say, no version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    has yet been absolutely perfect. Even sadder, it is likely that no version
    ever will be. In spite of all efforts to make everything work, a program
    as complicated as <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    is bound to screw things up occasionally, or even crash.
  </para>
  <para>
    But the fact that bugs are unavoidable does not mean that they should be
    passively accepted. If you find a bug in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, the
    developers would like to know about it so they can at least try to fix it.
  </para>
  <para>
    Suppose, then, that you have found a bug, or at least think you have: you
    try to do something, and the results are not what you expect. What should
    you do? How should you report it?
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      The procedure for making an <emphasis>enhancement
      request</emphasis>&mdash;that is, for asking the developers to add a
      missing feature&mdash;is the same as the procedure for reporting
      a bug.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
    In common with many other free software projects,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses a bug-reporting mechanism called
    <emphasis>GitLab</emphasis>.
    This is a very powerful web-based system, capable of managing thousands
    of bug reports without losing track. In fact, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    shares its GitLab database with the entire Gnome project.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="gimp-bug-confirm">
    <title>Making sure it's a Bug</title>
    <para>
      The first thing you should do, before reporting a bug, is to make
      an effort to verify that what you are seeing really
      <emphasis>is</emphasis> a bug.  It is hard to give a method for
      doing this that applies to all situations, but reading the
      documentation will often be useful, and discussing the question on
      IRC or on Discourse may also be quite helpful.  If you are
      seeing a <emphasis>crash</emphasis>, as opposed to mere
      misbehavior, the odds that it is a true bug are pretty high: well
      written software programs are not designed to crash under
      <emphasis>any</emphasis> circumstances.  In any case, if you have
      made a conscious effort to decide whether it is really a bug,
      and at the end still aren't sure, then please go ahead and report
      it:  the worst that can happen is that you will waste a bit of
      time for the development team.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Actually there are a few things that are known to cause
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to crash but have turned out to be too
        inconvenient to be worth fixing.  One of them is asking
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to do something that requires vast amounts of
        memory, such as creating an image one million pixels on a side.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      You should also make sure that you are using an up-to-date version
      of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>: reporting bugs that have already been
      fixed is just a waste of everybody's time.  (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1
      is no longer maintained, so if you use it and find bugs, either
      upgrade to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 or live with
      them.)  Particularly if you are using the development version of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, make sure that you can see the bug in the
      latest release before filing a report.
    </para>
    <para>
      If after due consideration you still think you have a legitimate
      bug report or enhancement request, the next step is to go to
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s list of issues
      (<ulink url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp/issues/"/>),
      and try to see whether somebody else has already reported the same
      thing.
    </para>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-find-specific-bug">
      <title>Find a Specific Bug</title>
      <para>
        Enter some (space separated) search terms, e.g.
        <blockquote>
          <para>
          <userinput>filter&nbsp;crash</userinput>
          </para>
        </blockquote>
        in the "Search or filter results..." text box and press Enter. By
        default you only see open reports; you can change this by clicking "All"
        above the search field.
      </para>
      <para>
        The result is either a list of bug reports &ndash; hopefully not too
        long &ndash; or a message saying <quote>Sorry, your filter produced no
        results</quote>. If you
        don't find a related bug report by doing this, it may be worth trying
        another search with different terms. If in spite of your best efforts,
        you file a bug report and it ends up being closed as a
        duplicate, don't be too upset: it has happened
        repeatedly to the author of this documentation.
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-bug-report">
    <title>Reporting the Bug</title>
    <para>
      Okay, so you have done everything you could to make sure, and you still
      think it's probably a bug. You should then go ahead and file a bug
      report on the GitLab page.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        The first time you file a bug report, you will be asked to create a
        GitLab account. The process is easy and painless, and you probably
        won't even get any spam as a result.
      </para>
    </note>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <title>File a New Issue</title>
        <para>
          Go to <ulink url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp/issues"/>, and
          select <guibutton>New issue</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <!-- IMHO a screenshot is not useful here (ude 2009-08-25) -->
        <para>
          If you are not logged in, you are automatically redirected to the
          login page. After entering your user name (login) and password,
          you get back to the <quote>New Issue</quote> page.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title>Fill out the Template</title>
        <para>
          Select <guimenu>Choose a template</guimenu> and choose whether you
          plan to report a bug or to request a feature.
          Note that most of the information you enter can be changed later
          by the developers if you get it wrong, so try to get it right but
          don't be obsessive about it.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Title</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Give a one-sentence summary that is descriptive enough so that
                somebody searching for similar bugs would find your bug report
                on the basis of the words this summary contains.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Description</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Describe the problem. Be as specific as you can, try to provide
                all the information requested from you, and include
                all information that you think might possibly be relevant.
                The classic totally useless bug report is, <quote>GIMP
                crashes. This program sucks</quote>. There is no hope that the
                developers can solve a problem if they can't tell what it is.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>
          Sometimes it is very helpful to augment a bug report with a
          screenshot or some other type of data. If you need to do this, click
          on the button <guibutton>Attach&nbsp;a&nbsp;file</guibutton>,
          and follow the directions. But please don't do this unless you think
          the attachment is really going to be useful&mdash;and if you need to
          attach a screenshot, don't make it any larger than necessary. Bug
          reports are likely to remain on the system for years, so there is no
          sense in wasting memory.
        </para>
        <para>
          When you have filled out all of these things, press the
          <guibutton>Submit issue</guibutton> button and your bug report will be
          submitted. It will be assigned a number, which you may want to make
          note of; you will, however, be emailed any time somebody makes a
          comment on your bug report or otherwise alters it, so you will
          receive reminders in any case. You can see the current state of your
          bug report at any time by going to
          <ulink url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp/issues/"/>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>

<!--  <sect1 id="gimp-bug-submitted">
    <title>What Happens to a Bug Report after you Submit it</title>
    <para>
      At any time after it is submitted, a bug report has a
      <quote>Status</quote>
      that describes how it is currently being handled.  Here are the
      possible values of <emphasis>Status</emphasis> and what they mean:
    </para>
  </sect1>
-->
</appendix>
