<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<appendix id="gimp-contributing">
  <title>How to Contribute</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>How to contribute</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    Welcome to the GIMP-Help team!
  </para>
  
  <para>
    This tutorial is intended for writing documentation. If you want to 
    <emphasis>translate</emphasis> the documentation or the user interface, 
    please go to "https://l10n.gnome.org/teams/xx" where "xx"  
    is your language code: ISO 639-1 language codes can be found at
    <ulink url="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/php/code_list.php"/>.
  </para>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Join our mailing list></title>
      <para>You can join our mailing list at
        <ulink url='https://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/gimp-docs-list'/>.
        Please, feel free to ask questions.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Create a Local Working Copy of Code</title>
      <para>
        The GIMP help Manual is lodged in a central repository at
        http://git.gnome.org. Creating a local copy of this repository to work
        on makes sure that everyone can work on his own without fuzzing around
        into works of other contributors.
      </para>
      <para>
        As a newbie, you will access the git repository anonymously (without an
        account). Open a terminal and type:
        <emphasis>git clone git://git.gnome.org/gimp-help-2</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you have a GNOME account, the command is:
        <emphasis>git clone ssh://yourusername>@git.gnome.org/git/gimp-help-2
        </emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        This will create a <quote>gimp-help-2</quote> folder in your current
        directory. Be patient! That's a big download: about 700 MB.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Installing your sandbox</title>
      <para>
        After downloading your local copy, run:
        <emphasis>cd gimp-help-2</emphasis> then
        <emphasis>./autogen.sh --without-gimp</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>
        When running ./autogen.sh, you can notice some not found packages, for
        example <quote>checking for dblatex... no</quote>. Most of them are
        related to PDF files and you have to install them before running
        ./autogen.sh again if you want to create PDF files.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The gimp-help-2 folder</title>
      <para>
        The GIMP User Manual is maintained in the xml files of the
        <quote>src</quote> folder. These xml files are used by developers. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Workflow</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <para>
        The language is English (USA).
      </para>
      <para>
        To edit XML files, use your preferred text editor. Personally I use 
        Kate. You must set the editor for:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              English language.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Indent with 2 spaces (the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key must move
              pointer by two spaces).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Replace tabs with spaces (for compatibility with all text
              editors and web browsers).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              80 characters per line.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Automatic spell checking with English (USA) for default 
              language.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
        Source files are written in the XML language according to the DocBook
        DTD. DocBook specifications can be found at
        <ulink url='http://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.0/docbook.html'/>.
      </para>

      <para>
        Don't be afraid. We don't use all these items and you will learn XML
        progressively reading existing XML files. For new files, please use
        the templates you can find in the gimp-help-2/docs/templates folder.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          If you write a new file, you must add it in the src/gimp.xml file, 
          or in the XML file that calls it (for example, the 
          src/menus/edit.xml file calls undo.xml, redo.xml, fade.xml... and so 
          on).
        </para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Validating</title>
      <para>
        When you have finished writing, you must validate your work:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In command line, for a single file, you can use: 
              <command>xmllint --noout your-file.xml</command>. This command 
              displays nothing if your file is OK. Else it indicates where the 
              error is. This command is for quickly sorting an xml file out; it 
              can miss or may not find some errors.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Else just run: <command>make validate-en</command>. You must
              get a <quote>No error</quote> message.
            </para>
            <para>
              Else, a list of validity errors is displayed with line numbers 
              referring to the en.xml log file that you can find in the /log 
              folder.
            </para>
            <para>
              Open this en.xml file in a text editor, type <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>G</keycap></keycombo> and enter 
              the line number to jump to the concerned line in the en.xml 
              file. There,you will find the error.
            </para>
            <para>
              if you have worked on several XML files, look above in the en.xml 
              file to find (in the <quote>xml:base</quote> field of the 
              <quote>id</quote> tag), in which xml file the error is. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
              Fix the error. Don't forget to save the file and run 
              <command>make validate-en</command> again.
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                A frequent foolish mistake is editing the en.xml log file 
                instead of the XML file.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Images</title>
      <para>
        You also have to manage screenshots. Here are some hints for 
        making good screenshots:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              reduce screenshot area as much as possible cropping the window
              manager borders and disabling the help button (you can do it
              in the preference dialog),
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              set the image mode to indexed 255 colors
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>
            </para>
            <para>
              This is not necessary for icons and if your image has only few 
              colors. In these cases, indexed images are bigger than 
              non-indexed.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              set print resolution to 144 ppi (not for small images like 
              icons). You can do this easily with GIMP from
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Print Size...</guisubmenu>
              </menuchoice>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Export images in the PNG format.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Don't include English text in images. Translators can't translate it 
        and many users don't like that. Use XML captions instead, or provide a 
        .xcf file in the <guimenuitem>docs</guimenuitem> folder, indicating 
        it by a comment in the XML file: "TRANSLATORS: there is a .xcf file for 
        this image in the docs folder."
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Icons for GIMP are in usr/share/gimp/2.0/icons. GTK icons are in 
        usr/share/gtk-doc/html/gtk2.
      </para>
      
        <para>
          To include an icon in the text:
          <literallayout>
            <guiicon><inlinegraphic fileref="path-to-icon"/></guiicon>
          </literallayout>
        </para>

      <para>
        Three commands to manage your images:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <command>make check-image-resolutions-en</command>: gives the
              references of images whose resolution is not 144 ppi.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <command>make check-images-en</command>: give references of
              missing or orphaned images.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <command>mogrify units PixelsPerTrack -density 144x144 
              *.png</command> to set the print resolution of all PNG images.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
      
    <sect2>
      <title>Create HTML Files</title>
      <para>
        Once XML files have been validated, run <command>make 
        html-en</command>. Creating HTML files is important to have 
        an idea about what users will see. You will probably notice 
        some improvements to be made on your XML file.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can make an HTML draft (when the folder xml/en has been created 
        during validation) for a single source xml file, by running, for 
        instance, the command         
        <command>make xml/en/concepts/brushes.draft</command>. This create 
        the brushes-draft.html for the brushes.xml file. But images are not 
        embedded in draft files.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can also use <acronym>yelp</acronym> and run <command>yelp 
        file:///your-file.xml</command>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Sending your files</title>
      <para>
        When your files are ready:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>You don't have a GNOME account</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              if you don't have a GNOME account, you must find a correspondent 
              who accepts to "push" files for you; that will not be difficult 
              if you send a message to the list. Either you send your xml 
              files and the attached images in a compressed file, (in a tree 
              reproducing that of the scr and images folders if you send 
              several files to make your correspondent's task easier), or you 
              send a "patch" that you have to create.
            </para>
            <para>
              Before creating a patch, you have to get all your xml files 
              and images in the index. Being in the gimp-help-2 folder, do 
              <command>git status</command>. If you have files in the 
              Untracked files section, run <command>git add -A</command>.
            </para>
            <para>
              Then run <command>diff --full-index --binary origine > 
              name-of-the-patch</command> to create the patch.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>You have a GNOME account</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>All being well, you know how to manage Git. There are many 
              tutorials for that on the Web.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Annexes</title>
    <variablelist>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>XML notes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">ID's</emphasis></para>
          <para>
            ID's, which identify commands and are used when pressing the F1 key 
            in the GIMP interface, are in 
            https://git.gnome.org/browse/gimp/tree/app/widgets/gimphelp-ids.h
          </para>
          
          <para><emphasis role="bold">XML Tags Examples</emphasis></para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>procedure</emphasis>: in using/web.xml.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>table</emphasis>: in 
            toolbox/tools-painting.xml.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>programlisting</emphasis>: in 
            filters/web/slice.xml.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>segmentedlist</emphasis>: in 
            dialogs/path-dialog.xml for a n columns list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Parents and Children</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Here is a diagram I often use.
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/contribute/xml-tags.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Working under Windows</title>
    <para>
      If you are using Windows you have to install Cygwin or a similar program 
      to simulate Linux to be able to install the programs used in writing. This 
      chapter will tell you how to install Cygwin on Windows and what packages 
      needed to work on the GIMP manual.   
    </para>
    <para>
      The first thing to do is downloading the <quote>setup.exe</quote> from 
      <ulink url='http://www.cygwin.com/' /> and save it on your computer. You 
      need this program every time you have to do changes in Cygwin, so save it 
      on a place easily to find, e.g. <quote>D:/cygwin/cygwin.exe</quote>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Open the program setup.exe by double-clicking on it. This will open the 
      start window. Click on the <quote>Next</quote> button to open a window 
      where you have to choose how to install Cygwin. The default setting is 
      <quote>Install from Internet</quote>. This means that the downloaded 
      files will be saved on your computer before the files will be used to 
      install Cygwin. This is the easiest way to do it.  
    </para>
    <para>
      In the next window you have to choose where to install Cygwin on your 
      computer. The default is C:\cygwin which is a good choice. Normally you 
      also choose the installation for all users. 
    </para>
    <para>
      If you marked the <quote>Download without Installing</quote> in the 
      previous window you will instead get a window where you determines where 
      to save the files. This window will be the next window if you install 
      from internet.
    </para>
    <para>
      The next window is how the computer is connected to internet. Normally 
      you choose the default setting.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the window <quote>Choose A Download Site</quote> you will find lots 
      of sites to download from. You may choose any of those starting with 
      <quote>http://</quote>, but it is a good rule to select one near you. 
      The installation program makes a folder with the same name as the site 
      you downloads from. If you change site, all the previous downloads will 
      be downloaded again in the new folder. That is not a problem. Normally 
      the program remember the last site used the next time you open it.    
    </para>
    <para>
      The next window lists all package categories available in Cygwin. A 
      package contains programs or program parts to be used in Cygwin. You do 
      not need all of them. As you see, every category is followed by a symbol 
      and the word <quote>Default</quote>. This means that the installer 
      will only load the packages necessary to run a minimum version of Cygwin. 
      So go on and press the <quote>Next</quote> button and admire the progress 
      of the downloading in the next window.  
    </para>
    <para>
      When downloading and installing is finished your copy of Cygwin is ready 
      to be adapted to GIMP.
    </para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Adapting Cygwin to use with GIMP documentation tools</title>
      <para>
        I am not able to guarantee that the procedure described here will work 
        for you. It is a resume of the way I did it. Tested on Windows XP and 
        Windows 7.
      </para>
      <para>
        To be sure that Cygwin will use your language and the char code used in 
        GIMP documentation I changed the batch file used to open Cygwin. (After 
        saving a copy of the original batch file.) If you used the default 
        installation you will find the batch file in 
        <filename>C:/cygwin/Cygwin.bat</filename>. Rewrite the batch file to
        <literallayout>
          @echo off
          C:
          chdir C:\cygwin\bin
          set LANG=[language-code].UTF-8
          bash --login -i  
        </literallayout>
          If you have put Cygwin in another location than the default, you have 
          to write the new path instead of <quote>C:\cygwin\bin</quote> above. 
          You may find your language code in 
          <ulink       
  url='http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/libstdc++/manual/localization.html'/>.      
 
      </para>
      <para>
        Then you are ready for the next step. Open <quote>cygwin/startup.exe
        </quote> and click on <quote>Next</quote> until you reach the package 
        window. You need the following packages:
        <literallayout>
            Devel/automake 1.12
            Devel/gettext-devel
            Devel/gettext
            Libs/libxml2
            Libs/libxml2-devel
            Interpreters/m4
            Devel/make
            Devel/pkg-config
            Libs/libxslt
            Libs/libxslt-devel
            Python/python
            Python/python-libxml2
            Python/python-libxslt
            Text/docbook-xml45
            Graphics/ImageMagic
            ....../wget
            ....../dblatex
            ....../pngcrush             
        </literallayout>
        The first package to be installed is the <quote>automake 1.12</quote> 
        in the <quote>Devel</quote> category. Click on the + mark in front of 
        the category's name (Devel) to open the package list. Search down the 
        rightmost column to find the package name <quote>automake 1.12</quote>. 
        Click once on the word <quote>Skip</quote>. The text will change to 
        <quote>1.12.3-1</quote> which is the version number for the choosed 
        package. Do the same with the other packages in the list above. Some 
        packages will be marked <quote>Keep</quote> instead of <quote>Skip
        </quote>. This means that these packages already are installed. Do not 
        alter these settings unless you know for certain that this package 
        should be deleted, or reloaded, or something else.    
      </para>
      <para>
        When you have marked all packages to be added to Cygwin you press 
        <quote>Next</quote>. You will then be told that the packages you 
        selected needs some additional packages. Accept this. When you reaches 
        the end of the updating, your Cygwin copy is ready for all that stuff 
        mentioned in the start of this side.
      </para>
      <para>
        Some packages, especially those needed for PDF, can't be found with
        setup.exe. You can try installing them from sources. You can use
        "wget url-to-the-package" to download the
        wanted package, but, as you have to know the url, the best way is
        browsing the web under Windows; download the package (usually a
        .tar.gz file) and copy-paste into the Cygwin folder.
      </para>
      <para>
        Then run <userinput>tar -xvzf your-package</userinput> to decompress
        the package.
      </para>
      <para>
        Go into the new folder and read the INSTALL file for instructions about
        installation.
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          pngnq cannot be installed from sources under Cygwin (dark problems
          with the libz library).
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        If you run into problems as mysterious error messages and so one, feel 
        free to ask for help on the mailing list mentioned on the top of this 
        page.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
