<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
      2008-03-21 Mr.Dust: added 'ko'
      2007-11-08 KoSt: added 'no'
      2007-09-21 AntI: Added 'es'
      2007-09-02 lexa: copied content from gimp.org as a start for 2.4 for en de
      2007-09-02 lexa: moved 2.2 content to the appendix to make room for 2.4 news
      -->
<sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-2-4">
  <title>
    <phrase>What's New in GIMP 2.4?</phrase>
  </title>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Refreshed Look</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A whole new default icon theme has been created for 2.4. The icons
          comply with the Tango style guidelines so GIMP doesn't feel out of
          place on any of the supported platforms. Regardless of whether you
          run GIMP under Microsoft Windows, Mac OS X or Linux (GNOME, KDE or
          Xfce), GIMP provides a polished, consistent look.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            <phrase>New Look of the toolbox in GIMP 2.4</phrase>
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/24-refreshed-look.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Additionally the icons also have enhanced usability on dark widget
          themes, which is a common setting among digital artists.
        </para>
        <para>
          For artists preferring more desaturated color theme for their icons
          is an alternative icon theme available for download
          <xref linkend="bibliography-online-jimmac01"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Scalable Brushes</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The tool options now include a brush size slider that affects both
          the parametric and bitmap brushes. This has been an oft-requested
          feature from both digital painters and photo editors.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            <phrase>Scalable brushes in GIMP 2.4</phrase>
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/24-scalable-brushes.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Unlike previous versions of GIMP, regardless of whether you're using
          a bitmap brush, parametric brush or even a picture tube (multiple
          bitmaps), you can easily set the brush size with either the tool
          options dock slider or an external device such as a MIDI slider or
          knob or a USB device like the Griffin Powermate.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Selection Tools</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The selection tools have been rewritten from scratch to allow
          resizing of existing selections. Additionally the rectangular
          selection tool includes a setting for creating rounded corners as
          this has been identified as a very common task among web designers.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            <phrase>Selection tools in GIMP 2.4</phrase>
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/24-selection-tools.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          The learning curve for the tools has been flattened as the key
          functionality is available without obscure shortcuts that confused
          GIMP beginners. Most of the existing shortcuts still work, but the
          functionality is either available through the tool options or made
          obsolete due to the interactive move and resize on canvas.
        </para>
        <para>
          While the tools have been redesigned to make them easier to
          understand for the newbies, all the former functionality is there.
          You can still constrain aspect ratios or specific sizes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Foreground Select Tool</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Selecting individual objects on images is easier now with a new
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-foreground-select">
            foreground select tool
          </link>. It is done in two steps. First, you make
          select region of interest which contains the entire object. Then you
          paint over selected area with a brush, not crossing object’s border.
          Release mouse button when you’re done and look, if there are dark
          blue spots on your objects. If there are some, paint with a brush
          over them again and release to refine selection. When there are no
          more blue areas inside the object, press Enter and there you have a
          perfectly selected object.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Align Tool</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          While GIMP has provided a grid and guideline functionality, the
          actual alignment of objects had to be done manually. A new tool
          comes at rescue <link linkend="gimp-tool-align">...</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Changes in menus</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Most notable is the new top-level Color menu that accumulates most
          tools, plug-ins and scripts that adjust colors in RGB/Grayscale mode
          and color palettes in Indexed mode. So now you can reach functions
          like Levels or Curves much faster than before, unless you define
          your own keyboard shortcuts for them using the improved keyboard
          shortcuts manager.
        </para>
        <para>
          In the new version of GIMP, some menu entries have changed their
          names and position. It was done mostly to simplify learning curve
          and improve user experience. After all, "HSV Noise" and "RGB Noise"
          sound more meaningful than "Scatter HSV" and "Scatter RGB", don't
          they? And status bar hints for all plug-ins and scripts are quite
          helpful too.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Support for file formats</term>
      <listitem>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Support for Photoshop ABR brush format;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Improved reading/writing EXIF in JPEG;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Importing clipping paths in TIFF;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Layer masks can be saved to PSD;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              16/32 bit bitmaps and alpha-channel support in BMP;
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              24 bit and Vista icons can be opened and saved.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Fullscreen Editing</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The fullscreen mode has been improved to not only allow getting a
          full scale preview of the artwork, but also allow comfortable
          editing. The artist has maximum screen estate available while all
          functionality is quickly accessible by pressing the Tab key (toggles
          visibility of all docks) when working fullscreen.
        </para>
        <para>
          Whether painting or touching up photos, fullscreen editing keeps all
          the distracting elements out of sight on a key press. It's like
          observing stars in a field as opposed to a light-polluted city.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Color Management and Soft-proofing</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          GIMP now provides full support for color profiles allowing precise
          color modification throughout the whole
          <quote>digital darkroom</quote> process.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>
            <phrase>Color management in GIMP 2.4</phrase>
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/using/24-color-management.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>New Crop Tool</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Just like the selection tools, the new crop tool has been enhanced
          since the last release. The resize handles actually resize the crop
          rectangle instead of providing both resize and move functionality.
          The tool behaves more naturally and consistently with other GIMP
          tools. For details see <xref linkend="gimp-tool-crop"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
          To move, simply drag the rectangle clicking within the area.
          Resizing is possible in one or two axes at the same time dragging
          the handle-bars on the sides and corners. The outside area is
          darkened with a nice passepartout effect to better get the idea of
          how the final crop will look like.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Red Eye Removal</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          While numerous red-eye workflows exist already, GIMP now features a
          very convenient auto-magic filter to remove red eye from your shots.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Healing Brush</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The healing brush is a new tool, similar in the working of the
          clone tool, that permits to quickly fix small defects or
          imperfections due to scratching or dust. In fact the tool is smart
          enough to being able to <emphasis>understand</emphasis> where and
          how to modify an image to cure these defects based on image color
          context.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Perspective Clone</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Here is another clone-like new tool that is able to adapt the
          destination geometry, instead of color as does the healing brush,
          based on preselected distortion settings. As the name suggests,
          perfect when copying images blocks with some type of prospective
          changes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Lens Distortion</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A very common problem exposing itself especially when using cheaper
          lenses is barrel distortion and vignetting. Luckily GIMP provides a
          brand new filter to compensate for both problems. Saving
          photographer's pocket is our mission!
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Various Other Improvements</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In addition to all the above, GIMP has been improved in other areas
          such as:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Better status information for tools in the window status bar.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Various speedups in composing functions and gradient drawing.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Zoomable preview widget for plugins.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>
