<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2007-05-27 ude: removed <acronym> tags for
             C, Linux, Lisp, LISP, Motiv, Perl, Python, Scheme,
             Unix, UNIX, X, yacc
  2007-04-21 lexa: fixed bug #420007
  2006-09-29 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2005-12-12 fixed cs lang tags by lexa
  2005-12-12 moved to the appendix by lexa
  2005-12-11 added de description for version 2.0 to the history by lexa
  2005-12-10 added de translation, made the file valid docbook by lexa
-->
<appendix xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-introduction-history">
  <title>GIMP History</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>History</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-beginning">
    <title>The Very Beginning</title>
    <para>
      According to Peter Mattis and Spencer Kimball, the original creators of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, in their announcement of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      0.54:
    </para>
    <para>
      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> arose from the ashes of a hideously
      crafted CS164 (compilers)
      class project. The setting: early morning. We were both weary from lack
      of sleep and the terrible strain of programming a compiler in
      LISP. The limits of our patience had long been
      exceeded, and yet still the dam held.
    </para>
    <para>
      And then it happened. Common LISP
      messily dumped core when it could not allocate the 17 MB it needed to
      generate a parser for a simple grammar using <application>yacc</application>.
      An unbelieving moment passed, there was one shared look of disgust,
      and then our project was vapor. We had to write something...
      <emphasis>ANYTHING</emphasis> ... useful. Something in
      C. Something that did not rely on nested lists to
      represent a bitmap. Thus, the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was born.
    </para>
    <para>
      Like the phoenix, glorious, new life sprung out of the burnt remnants of
      LISP and <application>yacc</application>. Ideas went
      flying, decisions were made, the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> began to take form.
    </para>
    <para>
      An image manipulation program was the consensus. A program that would at
      the very least lessen the necessity of using commercial software under
      <quote>Windoze</quote> or on the <quote>Macintoy</quote>. A program
      that would provide the features missing from the other
      X painting and imaging tools. A program
      that would help maintain the long tradition of excellent and free
      UNIX applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Six months later, we've reached an early beta stage. We want to release
      now to start working on compatibility issues and cross-platform
      stability. Also, we feel now that the program is actually usable and
      would like to see other interested programmers developing plug-ins and
      various file format support.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-early-days">
    <title>The Early Days of GIMP</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 0.54</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Version 0.54 was released in February 1996, and had a major impact
            as the first truly professional free image manipulation program.
            This was the first free program that could compete with the big
            commercial image manipulation programs.
          </para>
          <para>
            Version 0.54 was a beta release, but it was so stable that you
            could use it for daily work. However, one of the major drawbacks
            of 0.54 was that the toolkit (the slidebars, menus, dialog boxes,
            etc.) was built on Motif, a commercial
            toolkit. This was a big drawback for systems like
            <quote>Linux</quote>, because you had to buy
            Motif if you wanted to use the faster,
            dynamically linked <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Many
            developers were also students running Linux,
            who could not afford to buy Motif.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 0.60</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When 0.60 was released in July 1996, it had been under S and P
            (Spencer and Peter) development for four months. Main programming
            advantages were the new toolkits, <acronym>GTK</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolkit) and <acronym>gdk</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Drawing Kit), which eliminated the
            reliance on Motif. For the
            graphic artist, 0.60 was full of new features like: basic layers;
            improved painting tools (sub-pixel sampling, brush spacing); a
            better airbrush; paint modes; etc.
          </para>
          <para>
            Version 0.60 was only a developer's release, and was not intended
            for widespread use. It served as a workbench for 0.99 and the
            final 1.0 version, so functions and enhancement could be tested
            and dropped or changed. You can look at 0.60 as the alpha version
            of 0.99.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 0.99</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In February 1997, 0.99 came on the scene. Together with other
            developers, S and P had made several changes to
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and added
            even more features. The main difference was the new API
            (Application Programming Interface) and the
            <quote>PDB</quote>, which made it possible to write scripts;
            Script-Fus (or
            macros) could now automate things that you would normally do by
            hand. <acronym>GTK/gdk</acronym> had also changed and was now
            called <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. In
            addition, 0.99 used a new form of tile-based memory handling that
            made it possible to load huge images into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            (loading a 100 MB image into <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is no
            problem). Version 0.99 also introduced a new
            native <acronym>GIMP</acronym> file format called XCF.
          </para>
          <para>
            The new API made it really easy to write extensions and plug-ins
            for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Several new plug-ins and extensions
            emerged to make <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            even more useful (such as <acronym>SANE</acronym>, which enables
            scanning directly into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>).
          </para>
          <para>
            In the summer of 1997, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> had reached
            version 0.99.10, and S and
            P had to drop most of their support since they had graduated and
            begun jobs. However, the other developers of
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> continued under
            the orchestration of Federico Mena to make
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ready for prime time.
          </para>
          <para>
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> was separated from
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in September 1997.
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> had been
            recognized as an excellent toolkit, and other developers began
            using it to build their own applications.
          </para>
          <para>
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> went into feature freeze in October
            1997. This meant that no
            new features would be added to the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            core libraries and program. <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP Users
            Manual) version 0.5 was also released early in October 1997.
            The developing work continued to make <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            stable and ready for version 1.0.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-1-0">
    <title>The One to Change the World</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 1.0</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.0 was released on June 5,
            1998. Finally, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was
            considered stable enough to warrant a worldwide announcement and
            professional use.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 1.2</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.2.0 was released on
            December 25, 2000.
            Compared to the version 1.0, it included mostly fixes
            and improvements of the user interface.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <xi:include href="history-20.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="history-22.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="history-24.xml"/>
</appendix>
