<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE appendix
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--  section history:
  2006-09-29 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2005-12-12 fixed cs lang tags by lexa
  2005-12-12 moved to the appendix by lexa
  2005-12-11 added de description for version 2.0 to the history by lexa
  2005-12-10 added de translation, made the file valid docbook by lexa
-->
<appendix id="gimp-introduction-history" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;nl;no;zh_CN">
  <appendixinfo role="cvs" lang="en;de">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en;de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-02</date>
        <authorinitials>romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-29</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </appendixinfo>
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">GIMP History</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Historie Gimpu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Die Geschichte von GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Historique de GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">La storia di GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">De geschiedenis van GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Historia til GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">GIMP 的历史</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>The GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">History</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Historie</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Geschichte</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Historique</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="it">La storia</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="nl">Geschiedenis</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="no">Historisk oversyn</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">历史</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-beginning">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;fr;zh_CN">The very beginning</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Úplné začátky</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">I primordi</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Die Anfänge</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Het begin</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Den spede starten</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      According to Peter Mattis and Spencer Kimball, the original creators of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, in their announcement of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      0.54:
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Podle Petera Mattise a Spencera Kimballa, původních autorů Gimpu, a
      jejich zprávy o vydání Gimpu 0.54:
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der Anfang der Geschichte von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gestaltete sich
      nach Aussagen von Peter Mattis und Spencer Kimball, den Vätern von
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, wie folgt:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Selon Peter Mattis et Spencer Kimball, les créateurs à l'origine de
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, dans leur annonce de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      0.54:
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Secondo Peter Mattis e Spencer Kimball, i creatori originali di
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, nel loro annuncio di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      0.54:
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Volgens Peter Mattis en Spencer Kimball, de oorspronkelijke bouwers
      van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, in hun aankondiging van versie 0.54:
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Då Peter Mattis og Spencer Kimball, opphavsmennene til
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, gav ut <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 0.54 fortalde
      dei denne historia:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      GIMP 原作者 Peter Mattis，Spencer 和 Kimball 宣布 GIMP 0.54 版诞生：
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> arose from the ashes of a hideously
      crafted CS164 (compilers)
      class project. The setting: early morning. We were both weary from lack
      of sleep and the terrible strain of programming a compiler in
      <acronym>LISP</acronym>. The limits of our patience had long been
      exceeded, and yet still the dam held.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      GIMP se zrodil z popela příšerného školního projektu cs164
      (kompilátory). Situace: brzy ráno. Smrtelné vyčerpáni nedostatkem spánku
      a úsilím naprogramovat kompilátor v LISPu. Trpělivost je dávno pryč a
      přeci ještě nejsme u cíle.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der Saga nach stieg <acronym>GIMP</acronym> aus der Asche eines
      scheußlichen, handgemachten
      cs164 (Compiler) Projektes. Die Umstände waren die Folgenden: Früher
      Morgen, die beiden Helden (Peter &amp; Spencer) niedergekämpft vom
      fehlenden Schlaf und der furchtbaren Anstrengung einen Compiler in
      <acronym>LISP</acronym>
      zu programmieren. Die Grenzen ihrer Geduld waren längst überschritten.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> a émergé des cendres d'un projet de
      compilateur cs164 abominable.
      Le décor: de bon matin. Nous étions tous deux épuisés par le manque de
      sommeil et le terrible effort de programmation d'un compilateur en
      <acronym>LISP</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> nasce dalle ceneri dall'abominevole progetto
      di compilatori cs164.
      Scena: primo mattino. Eravamo ambedue stanchi e con carenza di sonno nel
      terribile sforzo della creazione di un compilatore in
      <acronym>LISP</acronym>. I limiti
      della nostra pazienza erano già stati superati da un pezzo, ma
      resistevamo ancora.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      De
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is ontstaan uit een afzichtelijk vormgegeven
      cs164 (compileer-)schoolwerkstuk. Gezet in de vroege ochtend waren we
      allebeide vermoeid door slaapgebrek en de vreselijke spanning door het
      programmeren van een compiler met <acronym>Lisp</acronym>.
      De grens van ons incasseringsvermogen was allang bereikt, maar toch
      was de bom nog niet gebarsten.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> steig fram frå oska av eit forferdeleg dårleg
      laga cs164 (compiler) prosjekt. Ramme: Tidleg morgon. Vi var begge
      trøytte av mangel på svevn og stresset med å programmere ein compiler
      i LISP. Grensene for tålmodet vårt var overskride for lenge sidan, men
      det heldt likevel.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      GIMP 诞生于让人厌烦的 cs164 (编译器)一个课程项目。那是一个清晨，我们极度缺乏睡眠，正处在用 LISP
      编写一个编译器的极大压力中，显得非常疲劳。那早已经超过了我们忍耐的极限，但是我们又不得不继续。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      And then it happened. Common <acronym>LISP</acronym> messily dumped
      core when it could not
      allocate the 17 MB it needed to generate a parser for a simple grammar
      using <acronym>yacc</acronym>. An unbelieving moment passed, there was
      one shared look of
      disgust, and then our project was vapor. We had to write something...
      <emphasis>ANYTHING</emphasis>... useful. Something in
      <acronym>C</acronym>. Something
      that did not rely on nested lists to represent a bitmap. Thus, the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was born.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      A pak se to stalo. Common LISP se zhroutil, když nemohl alokovat 17 MB
      potřebných k vygenerování jednoduchého parseru pomocí yaccu. Chvíli jsme
      nevěřili vlastním očím, vyměnili si pohledy plné zhnusení. Náš projekt
      se rozplynul. Potřebovali jsme něco napsat... COKOLIV... užitečného.
      Něco v C. Něco, co nespoléhalo na vnořené seznamy pro reprezentaci
      bitmapy. A tak se zrodil GIMP.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Doch dann geschah es. Das <acronym>LISP</acronym> Programm stürzte mit
      einem hässlichen <quote>Core Dump</quote>
      ab, als es nicht die 17MB Speicher reservieren konnte, welche zur
      Erzeugung des Parsers für eine einfache Grammatik in
      <acronym>yacc</acronym> notwendig
      gewesen wären. Ein Moment des Unglaubens ging vorbei, dann warfen sich
      die Beiden einen angewiderten Blick zu und damit hatte sich das Projekt
      in Luft aufgelöst. Es reichte; Peter &amp; Spencer mussten etwas
      ...<emphasis>IRGENDETWAS</emphasis>... sinnvolles programmieren. Etwas
      in der Programmiersprache <acronym>C</acronym>. Etwas, dass nicht von
      eingebetteten Listen abhängig war, um eine Bitmap darzustellen. Damit
      war <acronym>GIMP</acronym> geboren.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Et soudain tout s'est effondré quand notre programme n'a pu allouer les
      17 Mo nécessaires. Un moment d'incrédulité et de dégoût est passé. Il
      fallait que nous écrivions quelquechose d'utile, en
      <acronym>C</acronym>. Quelque chose qui
      ne reposait pas sur des listes imbriquées et qui représenterait une
      image bitmap. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> était né.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Poi successe. Il common <acronym>LISP</acronym> andò in crisi quando
      non ce la fece ad
      allocare i 17MB necessari per generare un parser per una semplice
      grammatica <acronym>yacc</acronym> e fece un core dump. Passò il
      momento di incredulità, ci
      fu un comune sguardo di disgusto e il nostro progetto si vaporizzò.
      Dovevamo scrivere qualcosa...<emphasis>QUALSIASI COSA</emphasis>...di
      utile. Qualcosa in <acronym>C</acronym>.
      Qualcosa che non facesse affidamento sulle liste nidificate per
      rappresentare un bitmap. Era nato <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Toen gebeurde het; <acronym>Lisp</acronym> had de volledige
      geheugeninhoud weer in eens in een core gedumpt omdat het niet de 17 MB
      ruimte kon reserveren om met <acronym>yacc</acronym>
      wat eenvoudige gramatica te ontleden. Na een moment van ontzetting
      keken we elkaar met een blik vol afschuw aan en op dat moment loste
      het hele project op. We moesten iets
      schrijven...<emphasis>IETS</emphasis>...nuttigs;
      iets in <acronym>C</acronym>, iets dat niet van de gekoppelde
      punt-afbeeldingen aan elkaar hing. Aldus was de geboorte van
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Då hende det forferdelege. LISP gjekk amok då det ikkje greidde å
      fordele dei 17 MB det trengde til ein analysemodul for enkel grammatikk
      i yacc. LISP spytta ut programkjerner. Ein utruleg augneblink. Noen
      grusamme sekund, og heile prosjektet vårt hadde dampa bort. Vi måtte
      bare skrive eit eller anna. Sama kva det var, bare det var brukbart til
      eitkvart. Noe i C. Noe som ikkje trengde nøsta lister for å representere
      eit bitkart. Slik blei <acronym>GIMP</acronym> født.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当 LISP 无法为 yacc 一个简单语法所需生成的一个解释器分配 17 MB时，出现了常见的糟糕的 core
      dump。大家都感到厌倦，接着项目停止了。我们强烈地感觉到必须写些什么...有用的、用 C 语言、要是不靠嵌套列表(Nested
      Lists)来显示位图的东西。这天，GIMP 就诞生了。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Like the phoenix, glorious, new life sprung out of the burnt remnants of
      <acronym>LISP</acronym> and <acronym>yacc</acronym>. Ideas went
      flying, decisions were made, the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> began to take form.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Jako bájný pták Fénix se z doutnajících zbytků LISPu a yaccu zrodil nový
      život. Nápady jen létaly, rozhodnutí padala a GIMP začínal nabírat tvar.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wie ein Phönix aus der Asche, prächtiges neues Leben erwachte aus den
      Überresten von <acronym>LISP</acronym> und <acronym>yacc</acronym>.
      Ideen wurden entwickelt, Entscheidungen
      getroffen und langsam nahm <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Gestalt an.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Tel le Phénix, une vie nouvelle est sortie des cendres de notre
      programme <acronym>LISP</acronym>. Les idées s'envolèrent, des
      décisions furent prises et <acronym>GIMP</acronym> commença à prendre
      forme.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Come la Fenice, gloria e nuova vita rinacquero dalle ceneri del
      <acronym>LISP</acronym> e di <acronym>yacc</acronym>. Le idee vennero
      volando, le decisioni pure e
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> cominciò a prendere forma.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Zo ontstond er als een Phoenix, uit de puinhopen van
      <acronym>Lisp</acronym> en <acronym>yacc</acronym>
      nieuw leven. Er ontstonden allerlei nieuwe idee-en, knopen werden
      doorgehakt en de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> nam gestalte aan.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Liksom ein fugl Føniks kom det eit strålande nytt liv ut av dei
      brende restane av LISP og yacc. Ideane flaug, avgjerder blei tatt.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> var i ferd med å ta form.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      它象一只凤凰，从 LISP 和 yacc 的灰烬中光辉地飞出。GIMP 慢慢开始成形...
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      An image manipulation program was the consensus. A program that would at
      the very least lessen the necessity of using commercial software under
      <quote>Windoze</quote> or on the <quote>Macintoy</quote>. A program
      that would provide the features missing from the other
      <acronym>X</acronym> painting and imaging tools. A program
      that would help maintain the long tradition of excellent and free
      <acronym>UNIX</acronym> applications.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Dohodli jsme se, že stvoříme program pro práci s obrázky. Program, který
      nás zbaví potřeby používat komerční programy pro „Wokýnka“ či
      „Jablíčka“. Program, který poskytne to, co zatím neumí žádný grafický
      program pro X. Program, který se zařadí mezi tradiční skvělé a svobodné
      unixové aplikace.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Ein Bildbearbeitungsprogramm war der Konsens. Ein Programm, das die
      Notwendigkeit kommerzielle Software unter <quote>Windoze</quote>
      oder <quote>Macintoy</quote>
      einzusetzen zumindest reduzierte. Ein Programm, welches die in anderen
      Malprogrammen und Werkzeugen unter <acronym>X</acronym> vermissten
      Funktionen bereitstellen
      würde. Ein Programm, das helfen sollte die lange Tradition
      hervorragender <acronym>UNIX</acronym> Anwendungen zu pflegen.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un programme de manipulation d'images était le consensus. Un programme
      qui permettrait de se passer d'un logiciel commercial sous
      <quote>Windoze</quote> ou sur <quote>Macintoy</quote>.
      Un programme qui fournirait les fonctions absentes dans
      les autres programmes de traitement d'image. Un programme qui
      perpétuerait la tradition des excellentes, et gratuites, applications
      <acronym>UNIX</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Un programma di fotoritocco fu l'accordo. Un programma che rendesse la
      necessità di usare un software commerciale sotto Windows o Mac almeno
      meno impellente. Un programma che fornisse delle caratteristiche che
      mancavano negli altri programmi di grafica per <acronym>X</acronym>.
      Un programma che ci
      aiutasse a mantenere la lunga tradizione di eccellenti e libere
      applicazioni per <acronym>UNIX</acronym>.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Het zou een programma om afbeeldingen te bewerken worden, besloten we;
      Een programma dat de noodzakelijkheid van allerlei commerciele
      programmatuur onder `windoos' of `makkentoch' zou verminderen. Een
      programma dat de missende mogelijkheden van alle andere X-teken- en
      beeldbewerkingsprogramma's zou herbergen. Een programma dat vol trots in
      de traditie van gratis, hogekwaliteit
      <acronym>Unix</acronym>-programma's zou passen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Målet var å lage eit biletbehandlingsprogram. Eit program som i det
      minste skulle gjere det mindre nødvendig å bruke kommersielle program
      under <quote>Windoze</quote> og <quote>Macintoy</quote>. Eit program
      som skulle innehalde dei verktøya andre teikne- og biletbehandlingsprogram
      mangla. Eit program som skulle hjelpe til å halda oppe den lange
      tradisjonen med gode og gratis UNIX-appliksjonar.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      一个图像处理程序是大家的共识；一个至少能使在“Windoze”或“Macintoy”下，商业软件不是唯一选择的程序；一个将提供其它 X
      画图和图像工具所没有的特性的程序；一个将帮助保持 UNIX 下拥有完美和自由应用程序这个长久传统的程序。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Six months later, we've reached an early beta stage. We want to release
      now to start working on compatibility issues and cross-platform
      stability. Also, we feel now that the program is actually usable and
      would like to see other interested programmers developing plug-ins and
      various file format support.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      O šest měsíců později jsme před sebou měli ranou beta verzi. Chtěli jsme
      ji zveřejnit, abychom mohli začít pracovat na kompatibilitě a
      multiplatformní stabilitě. Také jsme měli pocit, že program je již
      použitelný pro běžnou práci, a chtěli jsme, aby další programátoři
      začali vyvíjet zásuvné moduly a podporu pro nejrůznější formáty souborů.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sechs Monate später wurde ein frühes Beta Stadium erreicht. Peter &amp;
      Spencer wollten das Programm jetzt veröffentlichen und begannen mit der
      Arbeit an Kompatibilitätsproblemen und Stabilität auf verschiedenen
      Plattformen. Außerdem betrachteten sie das Programm als benutzbar und
      wollten, dass andere interessierte Programmierer erste Erweiterungen und
      die Unterstützung für neue Dateiformate entwickeln.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Six mois plus tard, nous avons atteint un premier stade beta. Nous
      voulions diffuser cette version pour commencer à travailler sur les
      problèmes de compatilités selon les plateformes. Le programme étant
      vraiment utilisable, nous voulions voir d'autres programmeurs développer
      des greffons et le soutien de divers formats de fichiers.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Sei mesi più tardi avevamo raggiunto il primo stadio beta. Volevamo
      rilasciarlo subito per lavorare sui problemi di compatibilità e
      stabilità multipiattaforma. Sentivamo che ora il programma era
      utilizzabile e che avrebbe attratto altri programmatori interessati a
      svilupparne dei plug-in e il supporto ad altri formati di file.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Zes maanden later hadden we een eerste testversie klaar. We wilden nu
      beginnen aan uitwisselbaarheidsvraagstukken en portabiliteit voor
      verschillende besturingssystemen. Verder hadden we het idee gekregen dat
      het programma werkelijk nuttig was en wilden we graag zien dat andere
      ontwikkelaars toevoegingen en ondersteuning voor meerdere
      bestandsformaten ontwikkelen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Seks månadar seinare hadde vi kome fram til ein tidleg betaversjon. Vi
      ville frigje programmet nå for å kunne byrja å gjere programmet
      kompatibelt og å tilpassa det ulike plattformar. Vi meinte programmet var
      absolutt brukbart, og ønskte at andre, interesserte programmerarar kunne
      lage tilleggsprogram (plug-ins) og støtte for ulike filformat.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      六个月后，进入早期的 beta
      阶段。我们决定此时发布，并开始着手兼容性问题和交叉平台的稳定性，而且觉得程序现在已经能用了，希望有兴趣的程序员加入开发插件和支持不同文件格式。
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-early-days">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;fr;zh_CN">The early days of GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Úsvit GIMPu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Die ersten Tage von GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">I primi giorni di GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">De eerste dagen van GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">GIMP sine første dagar</phrase>
    </title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;fr;zh_CN">Version 0.54</term>
        <term lang="cs">Verze 0.54</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Version 0.54</term>
        <term lang="it">La versione 0.54</term>
        <term lang="nl">Versie 0.54</term>
        <term lang="no">Versjon 0.54</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Version 0.54 was released in February 1996, and had a major impact
            as the first truly professional free image manipulation program.
            This was the first free program that could compete with the big
            commercial image manipulation programs.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Verze 0.54 byla uveřejněna v únoru 1996 a proslavila se jako první
            skutečně profesionální program pro úpravu obrázků. První svobodný
            program, který mohl soupeřit s velkými komerčními grafickými
            aplikacemi.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Version 0.54 wurde im Februar 1996 freigegeben und hatte große
            Bedeutung als erstes wirklich professionelles, freies
            Bildbearbeitungsprogramm. Es war das erste freie Programm, welches
            mit den großen kommerziellen Bildbearbeitungsprogrammen
            konkurieren konnte.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La version 0.54 est sortie en février 1996, et a eu un impact
            majeur en tant que premier programme, professionnel et gratuit, de
            manipulation d'images.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La versione 0.54 fu rilasciata nel febbraio del 1996 e fu di
            grande impatto visto che era il primo programma libero di
            fotoritocco professionale. Era il primo programma libero che
            poteva competere con i grandi programmi commerciali di
            fotoritocco.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Versie 0.54 is in februari 1996 vrijgegeven en heeft veel
            veranderd, zijnde het eerste echte gratis professionele
            beeldbewerkingsprogramma. Het was het eerste gratis programma dat
            kon concurreren met de grote commerciele
            beeldbewerkingsprogramma's.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Versjon 0.54 blei frigitt i februar 1996, og hadde god støtte i at
            det var det første profesjonelle, frie biletbehandlingsprogrammet.
            Dette var det første frie programmet som kunne konkurrere med dei
            store kommersielle programma.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            0.54 版本在 1992
            年二月发布，作为第一个正真的专业自由图像处理软件产生了很大影响，并且这也是第一个能够与大型商业图像处理程序竞争的自由软件。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Version 0.54 was a beta release, but it was so stable that you
            could use it for daily work. However, one of the major drawbacks
            of 0.54 was that the toolkit (the slidebars, menus, dialog boxes,
            etc.) was built on <acronym>Motif</acronym>, a commercial
            toolkit. This was a big drawback for systems like
            <acronym>Linux</acronym>, because you had to buy
            <acronym>Motif</acronym> if you wanted to use the faster,
            dynamically linked <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Many
            developers were also students running <acronym>Linux</acronym>,
            who could not afford to buy <acronym>Motif</acronym>.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Verze 0.54 byla pouhá beta, ale byla natolik stabilní, že se dala
            používat pro běžnou práci. Nicméně měla jednu zásadní chybu.
            Motif, knihovna použitá pro zobrazení grafického rozhraní (menu,
            dialogů atd.) byla komerční. Pro uživatele Linuxu to byl skutečný
            problém, neboť je nutil zaplatit a koupit Motif, bez kterého
            nemohli používat rychlejší, dynamicky slinkovaný GIMP. A mnozí
            vývojáři byli studenti, kteří si koupi Motifu nemohli dovolit.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Version 0.54 war einen Betaversion, aber sie war bereits so
            stabil, dass sie für die tägliche Arbeit benutzt werden konnte.
            Allerdings bestand einer der großen Nachteile von 0.54 darin, dass
            <acronym>Motif</acronym> als Basis für die Oberfläche benutzt
            wurde. <acronym>Motif</acronym> ist ein
            kommerzielles Produkt und musste für Plattformen wie
            <acronym>Linux</acronym> gekauft
            werden, wenn man das schnellere dynamisch gelinkte
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> verwenden
            wollte. Viele Entwickler waren jedoch Studenten, die
            <acronym>Linux</acronym>
            verwendeten, aber sich die Lizenz für <acronym>Motif</acronym>
            nicht leisten konnten.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La version 0.54 était une version beta, mais elle était si stable
            qu'on pouvait l'utiliser pour le travail quotidien. Mais elle
            avait un défaut majeur, c'est que la trousse d'outils (pour les
            menus, les barres de défilement, les boîtes de dialogue) utilisait
            <acronym>Motif</acronym>, un logiciel commercial. C'était
            rédhibitoire pour de
            nombreux utilisateurs, comme les étudiants, qui ne pouvaient se
            payer <acronym>Motif</acronym>.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La versione 0.54 era una versione beta, ma era così stabile che
            poteva essere usata per il lavoro di tutti i giorni. Comunque, uno
            dei maggiori difetti della versione 0.54 era che il toolkit (i
            cursori, i menu, le finestre di dialogo, i pulsanti) era basato su
            <acronym>Motif</acronym>, una libreria commerciale. Questo era
            un grosso difetto per
            i sistemi come <acronym>Linux</acronym> perché era necessario
            avere <acronym>Motif</acronym> se si
            voleva utilizzare la più veloce versione a link dinamico di
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            Inoltre molti sviluppatori erano studenti che usavano
            <acronym>Linux</acronym> e non si sarebbero potuti permettere di
            comperare <acronym>Motif</acronym>.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Versie 0.54 was een testversie, maar al zo stabiel dat het voor
            dagelijks gebruik geschikt was. Een van de nadelen was echter dat
            de vensteronderdelen (de schuifbalken, menu's, dialoogvensters
            entc.) uit een commerciele pakket; <acronym>Motif</acronym>
            kwamen. Dit was een belangrijk nadeel voor systemen als,
            <acronym>Linux</acronym>, omdat men <acronym>Motif</acronym>
            moest kopen als men <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            sneller, met dynamisch gekoppelde elementen wilde uitvoeren. Veel
            ontwikkelaars waren bovendien studenten die het zich niet konden
            veroorloven om <acronym>Motif</acronym> te kopen.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Versjon 0.54 var ei betautgåve, men var så stabil at det kunne
            nyttast i det daglege arbeidet. Det hadde likevel ein stor ulempe.
            Verktøysamlinga (glidebrytarane, menyane, dialogvindauga osv.) var
            bygde på <acronym>Motif</acronym>, som var kommersielt. Dette var
            ei stor ulempe for ideen bak system som <acronym>Linux</acronym>,
            fordi du måtte kjøpe <acronym>Motif</acronym> dersom du ønskte å
            bruke <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Mange av utviklarane var også
            studentar som køyrde <acronym>Linux</acronym>, med lite råd, eller
            lyst, til å kjøpe <acronym>Motif</acronym>.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            0.54 版本是一个 beta 版本，不过它已经足够稳定，您能在日常工作中使用它。尽管如此，0.54
            版本其中一个最大的缺点就是其工具包(滑条，对话框等。)是基于一个商业工具包 -- Motif 的。这对象 Linux
            一样的系统是个大问题，因为如果您想用更快的动态链接的 GIMP，您就不得不买 Motif，而您可能买不起。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;fr;zh_CN">Version 0.60</term>
        <term lang="cs">Verze 0.60</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Version 0.60</term>
        <term lang="it">La versione 0.60</term>
        <term lang="nl">Versie 0.60</term>
        <term lang="no">Versjon 0.60</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When 0.60 was released in July 1996, it had been under S and P
            (Spencer and Peter) development for four months. Main programming
            advantages were the new toolkits, <acronym>GTK</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolkit) and <acronym>gdk</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Drawing Kit), which eliminated the
            reliance on <acronym>Motif</acronym>. For the
            graphic artist, 0.60 was full of new features like: basic layers;
            improved painting tools (sub-pixel sampling, brush spacing); a
            better airbrush; paint modes; etc.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Po čtyřech měsících další Spencerovy a Peterovy práce, v červenci
            1996, byla uveřejněna verze 0.60. Největší novinkou byly nové
            knihovny, GTK (GIMP Toolkit) a gdk (GIMP Drawing Kit), které
            přinesly nezávislost na Motifu. Z pohledu grafika byl GIMP 0.60
            také plný novinek, obsahoval základy vrstev, zdokonalené kreslící
            nástroje (subpixelové vzorkování, rozestup štětce), lepší
            rozprašovač, režimy malování atd.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Version 0.60 wurde im Juli 1996 veröffentlicht und war durch
            Spencer und Peter vier Monate weiterentwickelt worden. Die
            bedeutensten Fortschritte waren ein neues Toolkit namens
            <acronym>GTK</acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolkit) und
            <acronym>gdk</acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Drawing Toolkit) mit
            denen die Abhängigkeit von <acronym>Motif</acronym> aufgehoben
            wurde. Für die Grafikkünstler war diese
            Version voll von neuen Funktionen wie Ebenen, verbesserten
            Malwerkzeugen mit Subpixelgenauigkeit, einer verbesserten
            Sprühpistole (Airbrush), Malmodi und vielen mehr.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Quand la version 0.60 est sortie, elle avait été développée
            pendant quatre mois par S et P (Spencer et Peter). La grande
            innovation étaient les trousses d'outils <acronym>GTK</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolkit) et <acronym>GDK</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            Drawing Kit). Pour l'artiste, 0.60 était pleine de nouvelles
            fonctions comme les calques, des outils améliorés (échantillonnage
            au niveau du sous-pixel, espacement des brosses...).
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Quando fu rilasciata la versione 0.60 nel luglio del 1996 essa fu
            sotto lo sviluppo di S e P (Spencer e Peter) per quattro mesi. I
            principali vantaggi portati da questo sviluppo furono i nuovi
            toolkit <acronym>GTK</acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolkit)
            e <acronym>gdk</acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Drawing Kit), che
            eliminarono la dipendenza da <acronym>Motif</acronym>. Per
            l'artista grafico la
            versione 0.60 fu piena di nuove caratteristiche come: supporto
            base ai livelli, strumenti di disegno migliorati (campionamento
            subpixel, brush spacing), un aerografo migliore, modalità di
            disegno, ecc.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Toen versie 0.60 in juli 1996 werd gepresenteerd hadden S en P
            vier maanden aan de ontwikkeling gewijd. Belangrijke verbeteringen
            in de programmering waren de nieuwe verzamelingen
            vensterelementen; <acronym>GTK</acronym> (GIMP ToolKit) en
            <acronym>GDK</acronym> (GIMP Drawing Kit), die aan de
            afhankelijkheid van <acronym>Motif</acronym>
            een einde maakten. Vanuit het perspectief van de graficus zat deze
            nieuwe verder versie vol met nieuwe mogelijkheden zoals
            elementaire lagen gebruik; verbeterde tekengereedschappen;
            sub-beeldpunt sampelen, ruimte tussen penseelstreken, een betere
            verfspuit; teken modi; etc.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Då 0.60 blei sleppt laus i juli 1996, hadde S og P (Spencer og
            Peter) arbeidd med programmet i fire månader. Det viktigaste i denne
            endringa var dei nye verktøysetta GTK (GIMP ToolKit) og gdk (Gimp
            Drawing Kit) som gjorde <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uavhengig av
            <acronym>Motif</acronym>. For den grafiske artisten var
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> full av nye bruksområde: grunnleggjande
            lag, forbetra teikneverktøy, betre sprøytepistol osv.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            当0.60 版本在 1996 年七月发行时，它已经在 S 和 P (Spencer 和
            Peter)手下开发了四个月。最主要进步是其工具包，GTK (GIMP Toolkit)和 gdk (GIMP Drawing
            Kit)，它们解决了对 Motif 的依靠。而对图像艺术家而言，0.60
            版本包括完整的特性如：基本的图层；加强的涂画工具(半像素采样，画笔空间)；一个更好的喷笔；涂画模式等。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            Version 0.60 was only a developer's release, and was not intended
            for widespread use. It served as a workbench for 0.99 and the
            final 1.0 version, so functions and enhancement could be tested
            and dropped or changed. You can look at 0.60 as the alpha version
            of 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Verze 0.60 byla ovšem určena pouze pro vývojáře, nikoliv pro běžné
            použití. Byla to vývojová verze pro budoucí GIMP 0.99 a 1.0, na
            které bylo možno testovat nové funkce a vylepšení. Byla to svým
            způsobem alfa verze budoucího Gimpu 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Version 0.60 war eine reine Entwicklerversion und nicht für
            die Allgemeinheit bestimmt. Sie diente als Grundlage für die
            Versionen 0.99 und 1.0 zum Test von Funktionen die gelegentlich
            auch wieder verworfen oder geändert wurden. Man könnte die Version
            0.60 auch als Alphaversion der Version 0.99 betrachten.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La version 0.60 n'était qu'une version de développeur, et n'était
            pas destinée à un large usage. Elle servait de banc d'essai à 0.99
            et à la version 1.0 finale. Vous pouvez considérer la 0.60 comme
            la version alpha de la 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La versione 0.60 fu una versione per sviluppatori, non era intesa
            per un uso diffuso. Servì come ambiente di prova per le versioni
            0.99 e 1.0 per verificare se le funzioni e i miglioramenti
            apportati potevano essere applicati o se andavano scartati. Si può
            guardare alla versione 0.60 come la versione alfa della 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Versie 0.60 was bedoeld als een ontwikkelingsversie en niet
            bedoeld voor wijdverspreidt gebruik. Het diende als startpunt voor
            versie 0.99 en de definitieve versie 1.0, functies en
            verbeteringen konden hieraan toegevoegd, in veranderd of uit
            verwijderd worden. 0.60 is de kapstok voor de ontwikkeling van
            versie 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Verson 0.60 var tenkt brukt til vidareutvikling, og var ikkje meint
            til utstrakt bruk som teikneprogram. Det fungerte som ei
            arbeidsplattform for 0.99, og den endelege 1.00 versjonen, slik at
            nye funksjonar og andre utvidingar kunne bli utprøvde og bli fjerna
            eller forbetra alt etter som. Vi kan sjå på versjonen 0.60 som
            alfaversjonen av 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            不过 0.60 版本只是一个开发者的版本，并不准备广泛使用。它作为 0.99 和最终 1.0
            版本的工作平台，让功能和加强改进能测试，丢弃和更改。可以把 0.60 看成是 0.99 的 alpha 版本。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;fr;zh_CN">Version 0.99</term>
        <term lang="cs">Verze 0.99</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Version 0.99</term>
        <term lang="it">La versione 0.99</term>
        <term lang="nl">Versie 0.99</term>
        <term lang="no">Versjon 0.99</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            In February 1997, 0.99 came on the scene. Together with other
            developers, S and P had made several changes to
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and added
            even more features. The main difference was the new API
            (Application Programming Interface) and the
            <quote>PDB</quote>, which made it possible to write scripts;
            Script-Fus (or
            macros) could now automate things that you would normally do by
            hand. <acronym>GTK/gdk</acronym> had also changed and was now
            called <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. In
            addition, 0.99 used a new form of tile-based memory handling that
            made it possible to load huge images into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            (loading a 100 MB image into <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is no
            problem). Version 0.99 also introduced a new
            native <acronym>GIMP</acronym> file format called XCF.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            V únoru 1997 vstoupila na scénu verze 0.99. Spencer a Peter
            společně s ostatními vývojáři přidali mnoho nových vlastností a
            provedli mnoho změn. Nejvýznamnějšími byly zejména nové API a PDB,
            což přineslo možnost psát skripty. Makra Script-Fu umožnily
            automatizovat postupy, které bylo dříve nutné dělat ručně. I
            GTK/gdk se změnilo a bylo přejmenováno na GTK+. Navíc verze 0.99
            přinesla novou správu paměti založenou na dlaždicích, což umožnilo
            práci s rozsáhlými soubory a velkými obrázky. A konečně přinesl
            GIMP 0.99 i nový nativní formát souborů nazvaný XCF.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Version 0.99 erblickte im Februar 1997, also geradeeinmal ein
            Jahr nach der allerersten Version 0.54 das Licht der Welt.
            Zusammen mit anderen Entwicklern hatten Spencer &amp; Peter
            verschiedene Änderungen vorgenommen und sogar weitere neue
            Funktionen hinzugefügt. Die bedeutendsten Neuerungen waren ein
            neues API (eine Programmierschnittstelle) and die
            <quote>PDB</quote> (Prozedurendatenbank), welche es ermöglichten
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> mittels
            einfacher Skripte zu erweitern. Mit Skript-Fu konnten nun Abläufe
            automatisiert werden, die bis dahin manuel ausgeführt werden
            mussten. <acronym>GTK</acronym> und <acronym>gdk</acronym>
            wurden ebenfalls überarbeitet und nun <acronym>GTK+</acronym>
            genannt. Zusätzlich verwendete die Version 0.99 eine neue,
            kachelbasierte Speicherverwaltung, mit welcher das Laden von 100MB
            Bilddateien kein Problem mehr darstellte. Außerdem wurde mit
            dieser Version das <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigene Dateiformat
            .xcf eingeführt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En février 1997 apparut la 0.99. Avec d'autres développeurs, S et
            P avaient apporté de nombreuses modifications et beaucoup
            d'améliorations. La nouvelle API et la <quote>PDB</quote> qui
            rendait possible
            l'écriture de Scripts. Les script-fus (ou macro) permettaient
            d'automatiser ce que vous faisiez manuellement.
            <acronym>GTK/gdk</acronym> avaient changé et s'appelaient
            désormais <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. En plus,
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> utilisait
            maintenant une mémoire virtuelle sur disque dur permettant de
            charger des images très volumineuses, plus grandes que la mémoire
            vive. La version 0.99 a aussi introduit le format natif de
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> appelé XCF.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            In febbraio 1997, venne alla luce la 0.99, Insieme con altri
            sviluppatori S e P fecero diversi cambiamenti e aggiunsero ancora
            altre caratteristiche. La principale differenza fu la nuova API e
            il <quote>PDB</quote> che rese possibile la scrittura degli
            scripts; gli
            script-fu (o macro) potevano ora automatizzare le cose che prima
            dovevano essere eseguite a mano. Anche <acronym>GTK/gdk</acronym>
            cambiò e venne chiamato <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. Inoltre la
            0.99 usava una nuova gestione della
            memoria <quote>tile-based</quote> che rese possibile il
            caricamento di immagini
            molto grandi, per esempio, un'immagine di 100MByte. La versione
            0.99 introdusse anche un nuovo formato di file nativo per
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> chiamato XCF.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            In februari 1997 verscheen versie 0.99. Samen met andere
            ontwikkelaars hadden S en P verschillende wijzigingen en meerdere
            mogelijkheden in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> aangebracht. Het grootste
            verschil waren de nieuwe <acronym>API</acronym>en
            <acronym>PDB</acronym>, die het mogelijk maakten scripts
            (opdrachtrecepten) te
            schrijven; met Script-Fu's (of macros) konden nu opdrachten die
            voorheen arbeidsintensief met de hand gedaan moesten worden,
            worden geautomatiseerd. <acronym>GTK/gdk</acronym>
            waren ook gewijzigd en werden nu <acronym>GTK+</acronym>
            genoemd. Daarbij was er nieuwe manier gebaseerd op tegelvorming
            gecre-eerd waardoor het mogelijk werd enorme afbeeldingen met
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            te bewerken (het laden van afbeeldingen van 100 MB levert geen
            problemen op in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ) in deze versie werd ook
            het eigen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-formaat; genaamd
            <acronym>XCF</acronym> geintroduceerd.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            I februar 1997 kom versjon 0.99 på scenen. Saman med mange andre
            hadde S og P nå lagt inn fleire endringar og lagt til fleire nye
            bruksområde. Hovudskilnaden var den nye API og PDB som gjorde det
            mogleg å lage skript. Script-Fu (ei form for makroar) automatiserte
            ting som før måtte gjerast med hand. GTK/gdk var også blitt
            forandra, og fekk namnet GTK+. I tillegg brukte 0.99 ei ny form for
            filbasert minnehandtering som gjer det mogleg å laste inn store
            bilete. (Det er ikkje noe problem å laste inn 100MB bilete i
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>). Versjon 0.99 introduserte også
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt eit eige filformat XCF.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            在 1997 年二月，0.99 出台了。和其它开发者一道，S 和 P 对 GIMP 进行了多处改进并添加了更多特性。主要变化是新的
            API 和 PDB，它们使编写插件成为可能；Script-Fu(或者说宏)能使通常需要手工操作步骤自动化。GTK/gdk
            现在改名叫做 GTK+。另外。0.99 使用新的基于平铺的(Tile-based)内存处理使在 GIMP
            中打开特大文件成为可能(读取一个 100 MB 的图像不是问题)。0.99 版本还引进了一个新的 GIMP 内部文件格式 XCF。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            The new API made it really easy to write extensions and plug-ins
            for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Several new plug-ins and extensions
            emerged to make <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            even more useful (such as <acronym>SANE</acronym>, which enables
            scanning directly into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>).
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Psát rozšíření a zásuvné moduly pro GIMP bylo s novým API opravdu
            snadné. Brzy se objevilo mnoho nových rozšíření, které hodnotu
            Gimpu mnohonásobně zvyšovaly (např. SANE umožňující skenování
            přímo do Gimpu).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die neue Programmierschnittstelle machte die Erstellung von
            Erweiterungen sehr einfach. Verschiedene neue Erweiterungen fanden
            ihren Weg in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, darunter einige sehr
            wichtige wie <acronym>SANE</acronym> (<acronym>SANE</acronym>
            erlaubt es Bilder direkt in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zu scannen).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La nouvelle API rendait facile l'écriture d'extensions et de
            greffons pour <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. De nombreux greffons sont
            apparus, multipliant les possibilités de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            (comme <acronym>SANE</acronym> qui permet l'utilisation d'un
            scanneur).
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La nuova API semplificò la scrittura di estensioni a plug-in per
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Emersero molte nuove estensioni e
            plug-in che resero <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            ancora più utile (come <acronym>SANE</acronym> che abilitò la
            capacità di effettuare
            digitalizzazioni direttamente da <acronym>GIMP</acronym>).
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            De nieuwe <acronym>API</acronym>
            vereenvoudigde het schrijven van uitbreidingen en plug-ins voor
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Verschillende nieuwe plug-ins en
            uitbreidingen waren toegevoegd  waardoor <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            nog bruikbaarder werd (zoals <acronym>SANE</acronym>,
            waardoor een afbeeldig direkt in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            gescand kan worden).
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Den nye API-en gjorde det lett å skrive programutvidingar og
            tilleggsprogram (plug-ins) for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Det blei
            utvikla mange nye programsnuttar som gjorde <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            mykje betre. (T.d. SANE som gjorde det mogleg å skanne direkte inn
            i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>).
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            新的 API 使编写 GIMP 的扩展和插件非常容易。加入许多新的插件和扩展使 GIMP 更加有用(如
            SANE,它使扫描图像能直接进入 GIMP)。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            In the summer of 1997, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> had reached
            version 0.99.10, and S and
            P had to drop most of their support since they had graduated and
            begun jobs. However, the other developers of
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> continued under
            the orchestration of Federico Mena to make
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ready for prime time.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            V létě 1997 dosáhl GIMP verze 0.99.10, ale Spencer i Peter museli
            omezit další práci na Gimpu, neboť ukončili školu a našli si
            zaměstnání. Ale ostatní vývojáři pokračovali pod vedením Federica
            Mena a vytrvale připravovali GIMP na jeho velký a slavný den.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Im Sommer 1997 erreichte <acronym>GIMP</acronym> die Version
            0.99.10 und S &amp; P
            sahen sich gezwungen ihre Unterstützung für das Projekt sehr
            einzuschränken, da Sie das Studium beendet und ihren ersten Job
            angetreten hatten. Trotzdem setzten die anderen Entwickler unter
            der Leitung von Federico Mena ihre Arbeit an
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> fort.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            A l'été 1997, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en était à la version
            0.99.10. S et P avaient
            obtenu leurs diplomes, trouvé du travail et avaient dû laisser
            tomber leur contribution à <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Heureusement,
            d'autres ont pris la suite sous la direction de Federico Mena.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Nell'estate del 1997, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> raggiunse la

            versione 0.99.10, S e P
            dovettero ridimensionare il loro contributo dato che si laurearono
            e cominciarono a lavorare. Comunque altri sviluppatori
            continuarono sotto la dirigenza di Federico Mena a rendere
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> pronto per il debutto.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Ten tijde van de zomer van 1997, was
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            versie 0.99.10 bereikt en hadden S en P zich steeds verder uit de
            ondersteuning teruggetrokken omdat ze afgestudeerd waren en aan
            reguliere banen begonnen waren. Andere ontwikkelaars namen het
            stokje echter over en onder aansturing van Federico Mena werd er
            verder gewerkt aan een definitieve gebruikersversie.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Sommaren 1997 hadde <acronym>GIMP</acronym> nådd versjon 0.99.10.
            S og P var ferdige med studiane sine og hadde fått jobb, og hadde
            difor ikkje tid til å støtte arbeidet med <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            Dei andre som arbeidde med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> heldt fram
            under leiing av Federico Mena.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            1997 年夏天，GIMP 进入 0.99.10 版本。而此时， S 和 P
            不得不停下大部分的开发工作，因为他们毕业并开始工作。尽管如此，其它 GIMP 开发者在 Federico Mena
            的指挥下继续前进并准备迎接其黄金时刻。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> was separated from
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in September 1997.
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> had been
            recognized as an excellent toolkit, and other developers began
            using it to build their own applications.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            V září 1997 se GTK+ osamostatnilo, neboť si získalo výbornou
            pověst pro své kvality a vývojáři jej začali využívat i pro jiné
            aplikace.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Im September 1997 wurde das <acronym>GTK+</acronym> aus dem
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Projekt herausgelöst und separat
            fortgeführt. <acronym>GTK+</acronym> wurde bereits zu dieser
            Zeit als hervorragendes Toolkit wahrgenommen und andere
            Entwickler verwendeten es zur Entwicklung eigener Anwendungen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> a été détaché de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            en septembre 1997. Il est reconnu comme
            étant une excellente trousse à outils, et d'autres programmeurs
            l'utilisent pour bâtir leurs propres applications.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La libreria <acronym>GTK+</acronym> fu separata da
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> nel settembre del 1997.
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym>
            era stato riconosciuto come eccellente toolkit e molti
            sviluppatori cominciarono ad usarlo per le proprie applicazioni.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            In september 1997 werd <acronym>GTK+</acronym>
            als een zelfstandig project van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            afgesplitst, het was toen al herkend als een uitmuntende
            vensterwerkset (`toolkit'), en ook andere ontwikkelaars begonnen
            het te gebruiken in hun eigen programma's.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> blei skild ut frå
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> i september 1997. <acronym>GTK+</acronym>
            synte seg å vere eit framifrå verktøysett, og andre
            programmerarar hadde tatt det i bruk for å bygge eigne program.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            1997 年九月，GTK+ 从 GIMP 中分离。GTK+ 被认为是及其出色的工具包，它被其它开发人员用作编写自己的应用程序。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> went into feature freeze in October
            1997. This meant that no
            new features would be added to the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            core libraries and program. <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP Users
            Manual) version 0.5 was also released early in October 1997.
            The developing work continued to make <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            stable and ready for version 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            V říjnu 1997 bylo pozastaveno přidávání nových vlastností do
            Gimpu. Vývojáři měli nyní za úkol GIMP učinit co nejstabilnějším a
            připravit ho na uveřejnění finální verze 1.0. Ve stejné době byl
            uveřejněn uživatelský manuál ke Gimpu — GUM 0.5.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Im Oktober 1997 wurden die Funktionen von
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> festgeschrieben,
            das heißt es ganze Aufmerksamkeit der Entwickler lag auf der
            Beseitigung von Fehlern. Es wurden keine neuen Funktionen zu den
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Bibliotheken und dem Programm selbst
            mehr hinzugefügt. <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP Users Manual)
            0.5 wurde ebenfalls im frühen Oktober 1997 veröffentlicht. Die
            Entwicklungsarbeiten an <acronym>GIMP</acronym> wurden mit dem
            Ziel fortgesetzt eine
            stabile Version 1.0 veröffentlichen zu können.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> a été gelé en octobre 1997. Cela
            signifie qu'aucune autre
            caractéristique ne pouvait être ajoutée au programme. Le
            <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP Users Manual) 0.5
            est également sorti en octobre 1997. Le travail de mise au point
            s'est poursuivi pour rendre <acronym>GIMP</acronym> stable et
            prêt pour la version 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> entro nella fase di
            <quote>feature freeze</quote> (congelamento dei
            miglioramenti, una fase necessaria per la
            <quote>stabilizzazione</quote> dei
            prodotti software sotto forte sviluppo) in ottobre del 1997.
            Questo significò che nessun nuovo miglioramento fu più aggiunto al
            programma e alle librerie principali di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
            Fu rilasciato nei
            primi di ottobre del 1997 anche <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP
            Users Manual) versione 0.5. Il lavoro di
            sviluppo continuò per rendere <acronym>GIMP</acronym> stabile e
            pronto per la versione 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            De eigenschappen van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            werden vastgelegd in oktober 1997; er zouden geen nieuwe
            mogelijkheden toegevoegd worden aan de basiswerking van
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            tot de ontwikkelaars klaar waren om de stabiele versie 1.0 vrij te
            geven. In oktober 1997 werd ook versie 0.5 van de
            <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP gebruikershandleiding)
            gepresenteerd.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Bruksområda til <acronym>GIMP</acronym> blei fastfrose i oktober
            1997. Dette betydde at ingen nye bruksområde skulle leggjast til
            i kjernebiblioteket eller programmet elles. GUM versjon 0.5 blei
            frigitt tidleg i oktober same året. Arbeidet med å gjere
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> stabil og klar for versjon 1.0 heldt fram.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            GIMP 在 1997 年十月进入特性冻结。也就是说 GIMP 核心函数库和程序不在接受新特性。GUM 0.5
            版本也在十月早些时候发布。开发工作还在继续使 GIMP 变稳定并为 1.0 版本做最后准备。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-1-0">
    <sect1info lang="en;cs;de;no" role="cvs">
      <revhistory>
        <revision lang="en">
          <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
          <date lang="en">2006-02-08</date>
          <authorinitials lang="en">jfriedl</authorinitials>
        </revision>
        <revision lang="cs">
          <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
          <date lang="cs">2006-02-08</date>
          <authorinitials lang="cs">jfriedl</authorinitials>
        </revision>
        <revision lang="de">
          <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
          <date>2006-10-10</date>
          <authorinitials>lexA</authorinitials>
        </revision>
        <revision lang="no">
          <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
          <date lang="no">2006-09-29</date>
          <authorinitials lang="no">KoSt</authorinitials>
        </revision>
      </revhistory>
    </sect1info>

    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;fr;zh_CN">The One to change the world</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ten, který změnil svět</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Der große Schritt die Welt zu ändern</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">L'uno per cambiare il mondo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">De grote stap voorwaarts</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Det store steget ut i verda</phrase>
    </title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;fr;zh_CN">Version 1.0</term>
        <term lang="cs">Verze 1.0</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Version 1.0</term>
        <term lang="it">La versione 1.0</term>
        <term lang="nl">Versie 1.0</term>
        <term lang="no">Versjon 1.0</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.0 was released on June 5,
            1998. Finally, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was
            considered stable enough to warrant a worldwide announcement and
            professional use.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            GIMP 1.0 byl uveřejněn 5. června 1998. Byl konečně natolik
            stabilní, aby mohl být představen celosvětové odborné veřejnosti a
            byl přijat skutečnými profesionály.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die lang ersehnte Version 1.0 von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> wurde
            am 5. Juni 1998
            freigegeben. Zu diesem Zeitpunkt wurde das Programm für stabil
            genug erachtet, um eine weltweite Ankündigung und einen
            professionellen Einsatz zu rechtfertigen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La version 1.0 est sortie le 5 juin 1998.
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> était suffisamment
            stable pour permettre une annonce mondiale et un usage
            professionnel.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La versione 1.0 di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> fu rilasciata il
            5 giugno del 1998.
            Finalmente <acronym>GIMP</acronym> era considerato abbastanza
            stabile e pronto per
            l'uso professionale da meritare un'annuncio mondiale.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> versie 1.0 verscheen op 5 juni 1998;
            Eindelijk werd <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            stabiel genoeg geacht en waardig voor een wereldwijde aankondiging
            als een professioneel bruikbaar pakket.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Versjon 1.0 blei sleppt ut 5. juni 1998. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            var endeleg stabil nok til å kunne annonserast over heile verda
            til profesjonell bruk.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            GIMP 1.0 版本最终在 1998 年六月五号发布，GIMP 向全世界宣布，它已经足够稳定来进行专业的图像处理了。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;cs;de;no">
        <term lang="en;fr;zh_CN">Version 1.2</term>
        <term lang="cs">Verze 1.2</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Version 1.2</term>
        <term lang="it">La versione 1.2</term>
        <term lang="nl">Versie 1.2</term>
        <term lang="no">Versjon 1.2</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.2.0 was released on
            December 25, 2000.
            Compared to the version 1.0, it included mostly fixes
            and improvements of the user interface.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            GIMP verze 1.2.0 byl uvolněn 25. prosince 2000. Novinky oproti
            verzi 1.0 zahrnovaly zejména opravy a vylepšení uživatelského
            rozhraní.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Version 1.2.0 wurde am 25. Dezember
            2000 freigegeben. Die
            Neuerungen gegenüber der Version 1.0 halten sich in Grenzen, neben
            vielen Fehlerbereinigungen wurde vor allem an der
            Benutzeroberfläche gearbeitet.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.2.0 kom 25. desember 2000.
            Denne utgåva var stort sett ei feilretta utgåve av 1.0, med
            eit litt forbetra brukargrensesnitt.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-2-0" lang="cs;en;de;fr;it;nl;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">New in GIMP 2</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Novinky v GIMPu 2</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">GIMP 2 - Schöne neue Welt</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Quoi de neuf dans GIMP 2?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Le novità di GIMP 2</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Nieuw in GIMP 2</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Nytt i GIMP 2</phrase>
    </title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;fr">Version 2.0</term>
        <term lang="cs">Verze 2.0</term>
        <term lang="de">Die Version 2.0</term>
        <term lang="it">La versione 2.0</term>
        <term lang="nl">Versie 2.0</term>
        <term lang="no">Versjon 2.0</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Nejprve pár čísel: zdrojové kódy Gimpu obsahují asi 230 000 řádků
            jazyka C. Většina z nich byla během přechodu z verze 1.2 na 2.0
            přepsána. Z uživatelského pohledu se však GIMP příliš nezměnil,
            vlastnosti a funkce jsou natolik podobné, že se uživatelé zvyklí
            na verzi 1 neztratí. Kód Gimpu byl vyčištěn a zrevidován, což sice
            uživatel na první pohled nepozná, ale usnadňuje to další
            vylepšování rozšiřování funkcí Gimpu. Zdrojové kódy Gimpu 2 jsou
            mnohem přehlednější a snadněji udržovatelné, než tomu bylo v
            dobách Gimpu 1.2.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            First, a statistic: the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> code base
            contains about 230,000 lines of <acronym>C</acronym> code, and
            most of these lines were rewritten in the
            evolution from 1.2 to 2.0. From the user's point of view, however,
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 is fundamentally similar to
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1; the features are similar enough that
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 users won't be lost. As part of the
            restructuring work, the developers cleaned up the code greatly, an
            investment that, while not directly visible to the user, will ease
            maintenance and make future additions less painful. Thus, the
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            2 code base is significantly better organized and more
            maintainable than was the case for <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Version 2.0.0 wurde am 24. März 2004 freigegeben.
            Um das Ausmaß der Neuerungen in der Version 2.0 deutlich zu machen
            zunächst ein wenig Statistik: Der Programmcode von
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> besteht aus etwa 230.000 Zeilen
            <acronym>C</acronym> Code und fast jede dieser Zeilen wurde
            bei der Arbeit an der neuen Version geändert! Aus der Sicht des
            Anwenders ist <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 jedoch grundsätzlich
            sehr ähnlich zur Version
            1. Auch die Funktionen sind ähnlich genug, um den Anwender nicht
            völlig zu verwirren. Als Teil der Restrukturierungsarbeiten
            wurde der Sourcecode gründlich aufgeräumt, eine Investition, die
            auch wenn sie für den Anwender nicht direkt sichtbar ist, die
            Wartung und Erweiterung von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zukünftig
            deutlich erleichtern wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Liste der neuen Funktionen und Möglichkeiten ist sehr lang,
            um Sie nicht unnötig zu langweilen ist sie auf die wesentlichen
            Neuerungen beschränkt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Tout d'abord quelques chiffres: la base de code
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> contient à peu près 230.000 lignes de
            code <acronym>C</acronym>, et la plupart de ces lignes ont
            été réécrites depuis la version 1.2. Néanmoins, l'utilisateur de
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2 ne sera pas désorienté. Les
            développeurs ont beaucoup
            nettoyé le code, investissement qui, s'il n'est pas immédiatement
            visible pour l'utilisateur, facilite la maintenance et rendra les
            additions futures moins pénibles.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Prima di tutto una statistica: il codice di
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> contiene circa 230.000 linee di codice
            in linguaggio <acronym>C</acronym> e la maggior parte di esse
            è stata riscritta nell'evoluzione dalla versione 1.2 alla 2.0. Da
            punto di vista dell'utente <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 è molto
            simile a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1; è
            abbastanza simile da consentire all'utente di
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 di orientarsi a sufficienza con
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2. Come parte del lavoro di
            ristrutturazione, gli sviluppatori hanno fatto una grande pulizia
            del codice; un lavoro che, anche se non è direttamente visibile
            all'utente, è un investimento che faciliterà la manutenzione e
            renderà i miglioramenti futuri più semplici. Questo vuol dire che
            la base del codice di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 è meglio
            organizzata e
            manutenzionabile che in passato con la versione 1.2.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Eerst een gegeven: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            bestaat uit 230.000 regels C-code, de meeste daarvan zijn herzien
            tijdens de ontwikkeling van versie 1.2 naar 2.2. Voor de gebruiker
            is er aan de werking van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            weinig fundamenteels veranderd tijdens deze overgang. Alle
            bedieningsorganen zijn zodanig gelijkvormig gebleven dat de
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1 gebruiker snel verder kan werken in
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2. In de herziening tussen de twee versies
            hebben de ontwikkelaars veel tijd gestoken in het opruimen van de
            programmeercode. De verwachting is dat deze investering toekomstig
            onderhoud en uitbreiding van de functionaliteit van het programma
            stukken eenvoudiger zal maken. De <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2
            programmacode is stukken overzichtelijker geworden dan ze in
            versie 1.2 was.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Først litt statistikk: Kjeldekodene for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            inneheld nå omlag 230,000 linjer med C-kode. Dei fleste av desse
            måtte skrivast om for å kome frå versjon 1.2 til 2.0. Sett frå
            brukarane si side, er <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 likevel såpass lik
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 at det er nokså uproblematisk å skifte til
            siste versjonen. Sidan koden skulle skrivast om, blei programmet
            også strukturert på nytt, med reinare kodar. Dette vil forenkle
            arbeidet med å leggje til nye kodar seinare, men er elles lite
            merkbar for dei fleste.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Lista over forbetringar er svært lang. Difor har vi i det
            følgjande bare tatt med dei viktigaste.
          </para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Základní nástroje</term>
              <term lang="en">Basic tools</term>
              <term lang="de">Grundlegende Werkzeuge</term>
              <term lang="fr">Outils de base</term>
              <term lang="it">Strumenti di base</term>
              <term lang="nl">Basisgereedschappen</term>
              <term lang="no">Hovudverktøya</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Základní nástroje v Gimpu 2 se od svých předchůdců z verze 1
                  zásadně neliší. Nástroj Výběr podle barvy je nově umístěn i
                  v panelu nástrojů, ale v nabídce <guimenu>Výběr</guimenu>
                  byl přítomen již v Gimpu 1. Transformační nástroj byl

                  rozdělen do několika samostatných nástrojů: Rotace, Změna
                  velikosti, Naklonění a Perspektiva. Barevné operace jsou
                  nyní svázané s vrstvami přes nabídku
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Vrstva</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Barvy</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>, ale opět se jedná pouze o přesun položek,
                  původně nelogicky umístěných v nabídce
                  <guimenu>Obrázek</guimenu>. V Gimpu 2.0 se tedy neobjevily
                  žádné zcela nové nástroje,
                  ale dva ze starých byly od základu přepracovány: nástroj pro
                  práci s textem a nástroj pro práci s cestami. Podrobnosti
                  jsou popsány dále.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The basic tools in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 are not very
                  different from their predecessors in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. The
                  <quote>Select Regions by Color</quote> tool
                  is now shown in the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> toolbox, but
                  was already included in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 as a
                  menu option in the Select menu. The Transform
                  tool has been divided into several specialized tools:
                  Rotation, Scale, Shearing and Perspective. Color operations
                  are now associated with layers in the menu
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Colors</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>,
                  but this is merely a cleanup: they were already present in
                  the Image menu (illogically, since they are layer
                  operations). Thus no completely new tools appear in this
                  release, but two of the tools have been totally revamped
                  compared to the older versions: the Text tool and the Path
                  tool. More on this below.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Basiswerkzeuge in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2
                  unterscheiden sich nicht wesentlich von ihren Vorgängern
                  in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. Das Werkzeug
                  <quote>Nach Farbe auswählen</quote>
                  hat jetzt seinen Weg in das Werkzeugfenster gefunden, war
                  jedoch auch in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 schon über das
                  Menü erreichbar. Das
                  Transformationswerkzeug wurde in die spezialisierten
                  Werkzeuge <quote>Drehen</quote>, <quote>Skalieren</quote>,
                  <quote>Scheren</quote> und <quote>Perspektive</quote>
                  aufgeteilt. Außerdem wurden die Werkzeuge
                  <quote>Text</quote> und <quote>Pfad</quote> grundlegend
                  überarbeitet. Die Farboperationen sind jetzt mit Ebenen
                  assoziiert und über das Menü
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Ebene</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Farben</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>
                  erreichbar. Dies zählt jedoch fast schon in die Kategorie
                  Fehlerbehebung, denn zuvor waren diese Funktionen dem
                  Menü <guimenu>Bild</guimenu> zugeordnet, was jedoch
                  unlogisch ist, da sie auf Ebenen wirken.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Les outils de base de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 ne sont
                  pas très différents de ceux de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.
                  L'outil <quote>Sélection de régions par couleur</quote>
                  se trouve maintenant dans la Boîte à outils, mais
                  il existait déjà dans le menu Sélection. L'outil
                  Transformation a été scindé en plusieurs outils spécialisés:
                  Rotation, Changer d'échelle, Cisaillement et Perspective.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Gli strumenti di base di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 non
                  sono molto differenti dai loro predecessori in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. Ora lo strumento
                  <quote>Seleziona regioni per colore</quote> viene mostrato
                  nella barra degli strumenti ma era già incluso in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 come opzione di menu.

                  Lo strumento di trasformazione è stato diviso in diversi
                  strumenti specializzati: rotazione, scala, inclinazione e
                  prospettiva. Le operazioni di colore sono ora associate ai
                  livelli nel menu
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Livelli</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Colori</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>
                  ma è solo un'operazione
                  di pulizia: erano già presenti nel menu immagine (illogico
                  visto che erano operazioni di livello). Perciò non c'è stata
                  l'apparizione di nessuno strumento completamente nuovo in
                  questa versione ma due di essi sono stati completamente
                  riorganizzati rispetto alle vecchie versioni: lo strumento
                  Testo e lo strumento Tracciati. Di seguito verranno
                  analizzati in maniera più approfondita.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  De basisgereedschappen in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  2 verschillen niet zoveel van die van
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. Het <quote>Gebieden op kleur
                    selecteren</quote> wordt nu in het <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  -gereedschapsvenster getoond, maar was al beschikbaar in
                  versie 1 als een menu-optie in het Selecteren menu. Het
                  transformatie gereedschap is opgesplits in verschillende
                  specifieke gereedschappen: Draaien, Schalen, Hellen
                  (Scheeftrekken) en perspectief veranderen. Kleurbewerkingen
                  zijn nu mogelijk in de lagen via het menu
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Lagen</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Kleuren</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>,
                  maar dit is voornamelijk een opruim-actie: ze waren al
                  beschikbaar in het <quote>Afbeelding</quote>-menu (ten
                  onrechte omdat het
                  laag-bewerkingen zijn). Er zijn dus geen nieuwe
                  gereedschappen bijgekomen in deze uitgave, maar twee
                  gereedschappen hebben een volledige gedaanteverwisseling
                  ondergaan sinds de voorgaande versie: Het Tekst en
                  Pad-gereedschap. Daar gaan we in het onderstaande stuk
                  dieper op in.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Basisverktøya i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 er nokså mykje dei
                  same som i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. <quote>Markering etter
                    farge</quote>-verktøyet er nå plassert i Verktøyskrinet, medan
                  det tidlegare låg i Vel-menyen. Omformingsverktøya er nå delte
                  i fleire spesialiserte verktøy: rotér, skalér, deling og
                  perspektiv. Fargeoperasjonar er lagt til Lag-menyen i
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Lag</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Farge</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice>,
                  men dette er nærast bare ei opprydding. Tidlegare var dei
                  plasserte i bilet-menyen, men dette er ulogisk sidan dei er
                  lag-operasjonar. Det finst altså ingen heilt nye verktøy i
                  denne utgåva, men eit par verktøy er heilt omdefinert i høve
                  til versjon 1.2, nemleg tekst-verktøyet og bane-verktøyet.
                  Meir om dette seinare.
                </para>

                <para lang="cs">
                  Uživatelské rozhraní nástrojů se změnilo poměrně výrazně.
                  Dialog Volby nástrojů nyní nemění svou velikost při změně
                  aktivního nástroje, protože to většina uživatelů považovala
                  za nepříjemné. Nyní je tento dialog ve výchozím nastavení
                  trvale otevřený a ukotven pod panelem nástrojů, kde ho lze
                  snadno nalézt.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The user interface for tools has also changed significantly.
                  The <quote>Tool Options</quote> dialog box was modified to
                  not resize
                  itself when a new tool is chosen. Most users felt that the
                  window changing size when a new tool was selected was
                  annoying. Now, by default the <quote>Tool Options</quote>
                  dialog is
                  constantly open and docked under the toolbox, where it can
                  easily be found.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Benutzeroberfläche für die Werkzeuge wurde merklich
                  überarbeitet. Der Dialog
                  <quote>Werkzeugeinstellungen</quote> ändert jetzt seine
                  Größe nicht mehr, wenn das Werkzeug gewechselt wird, da
                  dies von vielen Anwendern als störend empfunden wurde.
                  In der Standardeinstellung wird der Dialog jetzt unterhalb
                  des Werkzeugfensters ständig eingeblendet, um schnell
                  zugreifbar zu sein.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  L'interface utilisateur des outils a aussi changé
                  significativement. La fenêtre
                  <quote>Options des outils</quote> reste
                  maintenant constamment ouverte même si on change d'outil et
                  elle peut être attachée en permanence sous la Boîte à
                  outils.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  L'interfaccia utente per gli strumenti è anch'essa cambiata
                  in maniera significativa. La finestra di dialogo
                  <quote>Opzioni strumento</quote>
                  è stata modificata per non ridimensionarsi
                  automaticamente quando si seleziona un nuovo strumento.
                  molti utenti riferirono di trovare stancante una finestra
                  che si modificava per ogni nuovo strumento selezionato. Ora,
                  il comportamento predefinito è che le opzioni siano mostrate
                  in una finestra sempre aperta ed agganciata sotto la barra
                  degli strumenti, dove è facile da raggiungere.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Het bedieningspaneel voor de gereedschappen is ook
                  verregaand gewijzigd. Het dialoogvenster met de
                  gereedschapsopties veranderd niet meer vanzelf van
                  afmetingen als er een ander gereedschap actief gemaakt
                  wordt. De meeste gebruikers raakten hierdoor ge-irriteerd.
                  Nu staat het venster met de gereedschap-opties altijd open
                  en is hangt het onder het gereedschapsvenster waar het
                  makkelijk te vinden is.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Utsjånaden til verktøyvindauget er også merkbart forandra.
                  Dei fleste brukarane fann det irriterande at dialogvindauget
                  for verktøyinnstillingane forandra storleik når nye
                  verktøy blei valde. Difor er dette forandra slik at det nå
                  har fast storleik. Vindauget er normalt ope heile tida, og er
                  lett å finna der det er plassert like under verktøyskrinet.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Volby nástrojů</term>
              <term lang="en">Tool options</term>
              <term lang="de">Werkzeugeinstellungen</term>
              <term lang="fr">Options des outils</term>
              <term lang="it">Opzioni strumento</term>
              <term lang="nl">Gereedschap opties</term>
              <term lang="no">Verktøyinnstillingane</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Volby nástrojů mají nové možnosti, v Gimpu 1 nevídané. Mezi
                  nejdůležitější patří následující:
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The <quote>Tool Options</quote> for many tools have new
                  possibilities that weren't available in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. Without being exhaustive,
                  here are the most noticeable improvements.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Werkzeugeinstellungen habe jetzt für viele Werkzeuge
                  neue Eigenschaften, welche in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1
                  nicht verfügbar waren.
                  Ohne diese hier einzeln aufzulisten — sie sind ein
                  bemerkenswerter Fortschritt.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Les <quote>Options des outils</quote> ont plusieurs
                  possibilités nouvelles:
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Le <quote>Opzioni strumento</quote> per molti strumenti,
                  hanno nuove possibilità che non esistevano nella versione
                  di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.
                  Senza la pretesa di essere esaustivi, ecco una lista dei
                  principali miglioramenti.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Er zijn veel mogelijkheden aan de optie-vensters van
                  gereedschappen toegevoegd die niet in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1
                  beschikbaar waren. Zonder al te uitgebreid te worden
                  sommen we hier de meest opmerkelijke verbeteringen op.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Mange av verktøya har fått ein god del fleire innstillingar
                  i høve til det som var mogleg i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.
                  Dei mest synlege forandringane er lista opp nedføre.
                </para>

                <para lang="cs">
                  Všechny nástroje pro výběr mají tlačítka režimu:
                  <guibutton>Nahradit</guibutton>,
                  <guibutton>Přidat</guibutton>,
                  <guibutton>Ubrat</guibutton>a
                  <guibutton>Průnik</guibutton>.
                  V Gimpu 1 bylo stejné funkcionality možno dosáhnout pouze
                  pomocí modifikačních kláves <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                  nebo <keycap>Shift</keycap>,
                  což bylo pro některé uživatele matoucí, neboť tyto klávesy
                  mají i jiné funkce. FIXME
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  All selection tools now have mode buttons: Replace, Add,
                  Subtract and Intersect. In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 the
                  only way to change the
                  selection mode was to use the
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> or <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                  buttons, which
                  could get very confusing because those buttons also had
                  other functions. For example, pressing and holding the
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                  key while using the Rectangle selection tool forces the
                  rectangle to be a square. Thus, to add a square selection
                  you would first press <keycap>Shift</keycap>, then click
                  the mouse, then release <keycap>Shift</keycap>, then press
                  <keycap>Shift</keycap> again, then sweep out the
                  selection with the mouse, then release <keycap>Shift</keycap>.
                  It can now be done more easily.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Alle Auswahlwerkzeuge verfügen mit der neuen Version über
                  eine Schaltfläche unter deren Verwendung Sie zwischen den
                  Modi Ersetzen, Hinzufügen, Subtrahieren und Schnittmenge
                  wechseln können. In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 konnte dies
                  nur durch das
                  zusätzliche Drücken verschiedener Tasten erreicht werden.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Tous les outils de sélection ont maintenant trois boutons
                  pour changer de mode: Remplacer, Ajouter, Soustraire et
                  Intersection ce qui est plus pratique que le jeu de touches
                  complexe antérieur.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Tutti gli strumenti di selezione adesso hanno pulsanti di
                  modalità: Rimpiazza, Aggiungi, Sottrai e Interseca. In
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  1 l'unico modo per cambiare la modalità di selezione era
                  usare il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> o
                  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>, ma la cosa poteva indurre
                  molta confusione perché questi tasti hanno anche altre
                  funzioni. Per esempio, mantenendo premuto il tasto
                  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
                  per un po' di tempo si forza la trasformazione del
                  rettangolo di selezione in quadrato. Perciò, per aggiungere
                  una selezione quadrata bisognava prima premere
                  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>, poi
                  fare clic con il mouse, poi rilasciare il tasto
                  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> poi
                  premerlo nuovamente, uscire velocemente dalla selezione con
                  il mouse e rilasciare il tasto
                  <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>. Adesso può essere
                  fatto tutto in maniera molto più semplice.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Alle selectie-gereedschappen hebben nu modus knoppen:
                  Vervang, Toevoegen, Aftrekken en Snijden. In
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  -1 kon deze toestand alleen gewijzigd worden door de
                  <keycap>CTRL</keycap> of <keycap>SHIFT</keycap> toetsen
                  te gebruiken, wat veel verwarring op kon
                  leveren omdat deze toetsen ook andere functies hadden. Als
                  de <keycap>SHIFT</keycap> toets bijvoorbeeld bij het
                  tekenen van een
                  rechthoek ingedrukt wordt gehouden worden alle zijden van de
                  rechthoek even lang wat een vierkant opleverd. Om een
                  vierkante selectie toe te voegen moest u dus eerst
                  <keycap>SHIFT</keycap>
                  ingedrukt worden, dan de linkermuisknop indrukken,
                  vervolgens <keycap>SHIFT</keycap> loslaten en weer
                  indrukken dan met de muis het vierkant slecteren en
                  tenslotte de <keycap>SHIFT</keycap> toets weer
                  loslaten. Dit is nu veel makkelijker.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Alle markeringsverktøya har nå fått modusknappane Erstatt,
                  Legg til, Subtraher og Snitt. I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 var
                  den einaste måten å forandra modus på å bruke Ctrl- eller
                  Shift-tastane. Noe som kunne vere forvirrande all den tid
                  desse tastane også i mange tilfelle hadde andre funksjonar.
                  Heldt du t.d. nede Shift-tasten medan du brukte
                  rektangelmarkeringa, gjorde dette at rektanglet blei eit
                  kvadrat. For å legge til eit kvadrat måtte du altså først
                  halde nede Shift-tasten medan du klikka på musebrytaren,
                  deretter sleppe opp Shift-tasten og trykke han ned att medan
                  du teikna opp markeringa og så endeleg sleppe Shift-tasten.
                  Ingen tvil om at nåverande metode er ei forbetring.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  For transformation tools, buttons now control which object
                  (layer, selection or path) is affected by the
                  transformation. You can for example transform a rectangular
                  selection to various quadrilateral shapes. Path
                  transformation in particular is now easier than it was
                  before.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Für die Transformationswerkzeuge können Sie nun mit einer
                  Schaltfläche in den Werkzeugeigenschaften einstellen, ob
                  das Werkzeug auf die Ebene, die Auswahl oder einen Pfad
                  angewendet werden soll. Auch dies stellt einen großen
                  Fortschritt im Vergleich zu <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 dar.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Avec les outils de transformation, les boutons permettent de
                  choisir sur quel objet, calque, sélection ou chemin, portera
                  la transformation.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Per gli strumenti di trasformazione, ora dei pulsanti
                  controllano che oggetto viene coinvolto (livello, selezione
                  o tracciato). Per esempio è possibile trasformare una
                  selezione rettangolare in varie forme quadrilate. In
                  particolare la trasformazione dei tracciati è stata molto
                  semplificata.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Bij de transformatie-gereedschappen bepalen de knoppen nu
                  welk voorwerp (laag, selectie of pad) bewerkt wordt door de
                  transformatie. Een rechthoekige selectie kan nu naar
                  verschillende vierzijdige vormen vervormd worden. In het
                  bijzonder is het vervormen van paden gemakkelijker dan
                  voorheen geworden.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  For transformasjonsverktøya er det sett inn knappar der du
                  kan bestemma kva objekt, dvs. lag, markering og bane, desse
                  skal verka på. Spesielt er omforminga av banar sterkt
                  forbetra.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  <quote>Fade out</quote> and
                  <quote>Paint Using Gradient</quote> are now available for
                  all drawing tools. In fact, all drawing tools now have their
                  own individual brush, gradient and pattern settings, in
                  contrast to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 where there was a
                  single global setting
                  that applied to all drawing tools. Now you can select
                  different brushes for the Pencil and the Paint Brush, or
                  different patterns for the Clone and Fill tools. You can
                  change these setting by using your mouse wheel over the
                  relevant resource button (this is most useful for quickly
                  and easily choosing a brush).
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Eigenschaften <quote>Ausblenden</quote> und <quote>Mit
                    Verlauf füllen</quote> stehen nun in allen Malwerkzeugen
                  zur Verfügung. Genau betrachtet hat nun jedes Malwerkzeug
                  seine eigenen Einstellungen für Pinselform, Verlauf und
                  Muster.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Les outils de dessin ont maintenant leurs propres paramètres
                  de brosse, de dégradé et de motif. L'utilisation la roue de
                  la souris sur l'aperçu de brosse y fait défiler l'ensemble
                  des brosses.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <quote>Sfumatura in uscita</quote> e
                  <quote>Usa il colore del gradiente</quote> sono
                  ora disponibili per tutti gli strumenti di disegno. E ora
                  tutti gli strumenti di disegno hanno impostazioni dei
                  pennelli, gradienti e motivi individuali al contrario di
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 nel quale esisteva solo
                  un'impostazione globale. Ora
                  è possibile selezionare pennelli diversi per la matita e per
                  il pennello o motivi diversi per lo strumento clona e per lo
                  riempimento. È possibile cambiare queste impostazioni usando
                  la rotella del mouse sopra il tasto specifico della risorsa
                  (molto utile per scegliere velocemente un pennello).
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  <quote>Uitvloeien</quote> en tekenen met een kleurverloop
                  kan nu met alle
                  tekengereedschappen. Alle tekengereedschappen hebben hun
                  eigen penseel, kleurenverloop en patroon instellingen, in
                  tegenstelling tot de situatie in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1
                  waarbij dezelfde instelling voor alle gereedschappen
                  geldt. U kunt nu verschillende penselen voor de het potlood
                  en de verfspuit instellen, of verschillende vulpatronen voor
                  de Kloon en Vul gereedschappen. U kunt deze instelling
                  veranderen met het muiswieltje en de muiscursor op de
                  corresponderende instellingsknop (dit is verreweg de snelste
                  en eenvoudigste manier om een penseel te kiezen).
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  <emphasis>Uttoning</emphasis>og <emphasis>Bruk farge frå
                    fargeovergang</emphasis> er nå tilgjengeleg for alle
                  teikneverktøya. Faktisk har kvart teikneverktøy sine eigne
                  innstillingar for pensel, fargeovergang og mønster. Du kan
                  velje ein pensel for blyanten og ein annan for malepenselen,
                  eller ulike fargeovergangar for klone- og fyllverktøyet. I
                  tillegg kan du endra desse innstillingane med musehjulet
                  når musepeikaren er over vindauget for fargeovergangar.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Uživatelské rozhraní</term>
              <term lang="en">User Interface</term>
              <term lang="de">Benutzeroberfläche</term>
              <term lang="fr">Interface utilisateur</term>
              <term lang="it">Interfaccia utente</term>
              <term lang="nl">Bedieningspaneel</term>
              <term lang="no">Brukargrensesnittet</term>

              <listitem>
                <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The most visible changes in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2
                  concern the user interface. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> now
                  uses the <acronym>GTK2+</acronym> graphical toolkit in
                  place of <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. One of the nice features
                  brought by the new
                  libraries is dockable dialogs, and tab navigation between
                  dialogs docked in the same window — a feature present in
                  several popular web browsers. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1
                  was famous for opening dialogs anywhere on your screen;
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 can be told to use
                  fixed boxes. Dialogs now include a little tab-customization
                  menu, which provides maximum flexibility in organizing your
                  workspace.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  In diesem Bereich haben wohl die am deutlichsten sichtbaren
                  Veränderungen stattgefunden. Damit trägt die Entwicklung den
                  Problemen Rechnung, die viele Anwender mit
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 hatten.
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 verwendet das
                  <acronym>GTK2+</acronym> Toolkit, an
                  Stelle von <acronym>GTK+</acronym>.
                  Daraus ergibt sich für <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 die
                  Möglichkeit Dialoge in
                  Fenstern zusammenzufassen (zu docken) und so eine der
                  größten Schwächen von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1, nämlich
                  die zur Unübersichtlichkeit neigende große Anzahl von lose
                  herumliegenden Dialogen, zu beseitigen. Mit
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 können Sie die verschiedenen
                  Paletten und Dialog von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> so
                  anordnen, wie sie diese für Ihre Arbeitsweise benötigen.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 utilise maintenant l'ensemble de
                  librairies <acronym>GTK2+</acronym>.
                  L'une des caractéristiques les plus intéressantes est la
                  possibilité d'avoir plusieurs dialogues réunis au sein
                  d'onglets dans une même fenêtre. On peut avoir des boîtes de
                  dialogue fixes sur l'écran. Les boîtes de dialogue offrent
                  un petit menu de personnalisation qui vous donne plus de
                  flexibilité dans l'organisation de votre espace de travail.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  I cambiamenti più evidenti in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2
                  riguardano l'interfaccia utente. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  ora usa il toolkit <acronym>GTK2+</acronym> al posto
                  di <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. Una delle caratteristiche più
                  evidenti che porta
                  questo cambiamento di librerie è la possibilità di
                  agganciare le finestre di dialogo alla stessa finestra
                  tramite la navigazione a schede — una caratteristicha
                  presente nei moderni software di navigazione pagine web.
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 era (tristemente) famoso per
                  aprire le finestre dappertutto sullo schermo;
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 può essere istruito per
                  mantenere le stesse posizioni. Ora le finestre di dialogo
                  includono un piccolo menu di personalizzazione delle schede
                  che fornisce la massima flessibilità nell'organizzazione
                  dello spazio di lavoro.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  De meest in het oog springende veranderingen in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2 zijn in de bedieningsorganen.
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> maakt nu gebruik van de grafische
                  bibliotheek van <acronym>GTK2+</acronym> in plaats van
                  <acronym>GTK+</acronym>.
                  Dit maakt koppelbare dialoogvakken en tab-navigatie tussen
                  dialoogvakken in hetzelfde venster — een bekende eigenschap
                  van verschillende populaire webbrowsers— mogelijk.
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1 was berucht om de dialoogvensters
                  die overal in het scherm verschenen,
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> -2 kunt u zo instellen dat het
                  vaste vakken gebruikt.
                  Dialogen bevatten nu ook een kleine tab waarin u uw eigen
                  voorkeuren kunt instellen en biedt u hiermee maximale
                  vrijheid om uw werkblad volledig naar wens in te richten.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Den mest synlege forandringa i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 er
                  utsjånaden til skjermen. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 bruker nå
                  det grafiske verktøyet GTK2+ i staden for, som tidlegare,
                  GTK+. Som ei fylgje av dette, kan du nå feste dialogar til
                  menyane etter eige ønskje og bruke arkfaner for å navigera
                  mellom dialogane i same vindauget. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  1 var berømt for å kunna opna dialogar kvar som helst på
                  skjermen. I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 kan du opne dialogane
                  i faste vindauge om du heller vil det. Dialogane inneheld
                  ein liten fanemeny som hjelper deg å organisera
                  arbeidsplassen din.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  The Image window has some interesting new features. These
                  are not necessarily activated by default, but they can be
                  checked as options in the
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Interface</guisubmenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Image Windows</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>
                  menu. <quote>Show Brush Outline</quote>, for example,
                  allows you
                  to see the outline of the brush when using drawing tools. In
                  the <quote>Appearance</quote> sub-section, you can toggle
                  whether a menu
                  bar is present at the top of image windows. You can set an
                  option to work with the new fullscreen mode. Viewing options
                  are also available from all image windows using right click
                  to bring up the menu, then selecting <quote>View</quote>.
                  The so-called <quote>image</quote> menu is also available
                  by clicking on a little
                  triangle in the top left corner of the drawing space. The
                  setting you choose in the <quote>Preferences</quote>
                  dialog is used as

                  the default value, and options you set from an image are
                  used only for that image. (You can also toggle fullscreen
                  mode by using the <keycap>F11</keycap> key; the
                  <keycap>Esc</keycap> key also exits fullscreen mode).
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Das neue Bildfenster verfüg ebenfalls über einige
                  interessante, neue Funktionen. So ist es jetzt möglich den
                  Umriss der Pinselspitze bei der Arbeit mit den Malwerkzeugen
                  anzuzeigen. Ausserdem lässt sich dem Bildfenster eine
                  Menüleiste hinzufügen und Sie können im Vollbildmodus
                  arbeiten, um die Größe Ihrer Arbeitsfläche zu maximieren.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  La fenêtre d'image offre de nouvelles fontionnalités. Elles
                  ne sont pas activée par défaut mais peuvent l'être dans le
                  menu
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Préférences</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Interface</guisubmenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Fenêtres d'images</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>.
                  Par exemple
                  <quote>Afficher le contour de la brosse</quote> vous
                  permet ce voir le
                  contour de la brosse quand vous utilisez un outil de dessin.
                  Dans la sous-section <quote>Apparence</quote> vous pouvez
                  décider si une
                  barre de menu est présente ou non en haut de la fenêtre
                  d'image. Vous pouvez choisir de travailler en mode
                  plein-écran. Les options de visibilité sont également
                  disponibles par un clic droit sur l'image faisant apparaître
                  un menu local avec l'entrée <quote>Affichage</quote>. On
                  peut aussi
                  accéder à ce menu en cliquant sur le petit bouton marqué
                  d'un triangle en haut à gauche de la fenêtre d'image. Les
                  options choisies dans Préférences sont des options utilisées
                  par défaut pour toutes les images. Les mêmes options fixées
                  à partir du menu local ne sont valables que pour l'image
                  actuelle. (La touche <keycap>F11</keycap> permet de
                  basculer le mode plein-écran.)
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  La finestra immagine ha alcune nuove interessanti
                  caratteristiche. Queste non sono sempre predefinite attive,
                  ma possono essere abilitate nel menu
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Preferenze</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Interfacccia</guisubmenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Finestre immagine</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>.
                  <quote>Mostra bordo del pennello</quote>, per esempio,
                  permette di vedere il bordo
                  esterno del pennello quando si usano gli strumenti di
                  disegno. Nella sotto sezione <quote>Aspetto</quote>
                  è possibile commutare
                  la visualizzazione di una barra del menu in cima alla
                  finestra immagine oppure impostare le stesse opzioni
                  diversamente per il lavoro a schermo pieno. Le opzioni di
                  visualizzazione sono disponibili anche per tutte le finestre
                  immagine usando il tasto destro per richiamare il menu e poi
                  selezionando <quote>Visualizza</quote>. Il cosiddetto menu
                  <quote>immagine</quote> è
                  disponibile anche facendo clic su un piccolo triangolo
                  presente nell'angolo il alto a sinistra dello spazio di
                  disegno. Le impostazioni che si sceglieranno nella finestra
                  di dialogo <quote>Preferenze</quote> vengono usate come
                  valori
                  predefiniti e le opzioni che vengono impostate dall'immagine
                  valgono solo per quell'immagine La modalità a schermo pieno
                  è commutabile anche tramite la pressione del tasto
                  <keycap>F11</keycap> e per uscirne funziona c'è pure il
                  tasto <keycap>Esc</keycap>.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Het afbeeldingsscherm heeft enkele interesante nieuwe
                  eigenschappen. Deze staan niet standaard ingeschakeld, maar
                  kunnen via opties in `Voorkeuren->Afbeeldingsvensters'-menu
                  aangezet worden. Met `Penseelomtrek tonen' ingeschakeld ziet
                  u voor het indrukken van de rechter muiknop al de omtrek
                  waarbinnen het tekenen plaatsvindt bij de
                  tekengereedschappen. in het `Weergave' deelmenu, kunt u
                  kiezen of u al dan niet de menubalk bovenin het
                  afbeeldingsvenster wilt hebben. Verder kunt u deze opties
                  expliciet kiezen voor als u het <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  in het volledige scherm
                  gebruikt. er zijn ook afbeeldings mogelijkheden beschikbaar
                  in een menu dat verschijnt als u op de rechtermuisknop klikt
                  en dan `Beeld' selecteert. He zogeheten `Afbeelding' menu
                  kan nu ook geopend worden door op een klein driehoekje in de
                  linkerbovenhoek van het tekenblok te klikken. De instelling
                  die u kiest in het `Voorkeuren' scherm zijn de
                  voorkeursinstellingen en opties die u in een
                  afbeeldingsvenste instelt zijn alleen van toepassing op het
                  bewuste afbeeldingsvenster (U kunt ook naar de volledige
                  schermvulling gaan door op de functietoets `F11' te drukken;
                  met de `Esc' toets keert u dan weer naar een
                  venseterweergave terug.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Også biletvindauget har fått ein del nye og interessante ting.
                  Ikkje alle av desse er synlege til vanleg, men kan
                  aktiviserast etter ønskje. Du kan velje om musemarkøren skal
                  vise omrisset til teikneverktøyet eller ikkje, om du ønskjer
                  ein biletmeny på toppen av biletet osv. Du kan ha ulike
                  innstillingar for eit bilete vist i normalmodus og i
                  fullskjermmodus. (Du kan forresten visa biletet i full skjerm
                  ved å trykka på F11-tasten, og gå tilbake til normalvising med
                  tasten Esc). Biletmenyen  kan du henta fram, om han ikkje er
                  på toppen av biletet, ved å høgreklikka i biletet og deretter
                  velja vis, eller du kan klikka på det vesle triangelet i øvre,
                  venstre hjørne av biletvindauget. Innstillingane du gjer i
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Innstillingar</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice>
                  i hovudmenyen vil bli normalinnstillingane til du endrar dei
                  igjen, medan innstillingane du gjer i biletmenyen bare gjeld
                  det aktuelle biletet.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 features keyboard accelerators
                  to ease menu access.
                  If you find that navigating through menus using your mouse
                  is onerous, the solution may be to use the keyboard. For
                  example, if the menu bar is present, to create a new image
                  just hit
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                    <keycap>F</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>.
                  Without the menu bar, hit
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>F10</keycap>
                  </keycombo> to
                  open the top-left menu, and use direction keys or
                  <keycap>F</keycap> then <keycap>N</keycap>
                  to create the new image. Keyboard accelerators are different
                  from shortcuts: accelerators are useful to navigate through
                  menus, whereas shortcuts call a specific menu item directly.
                  For example,
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo> is a shortcut, and the quickest way to
                  open a new image.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Les accélérateurs clavier de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2
                  facilitent l'accès aux
                  menus. Par exemple, si la barre de menus est présente, tapez
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                    <keycap>F</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  pour créer une nouvelle image. Sans barre de menus, tapez
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    <keycap>F10</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  pour ouvrir le menu local qui reproduit les
                  entrées de la barre de menus, et utilisez les touches
                  fléchées ou <keycap>F</keycap> puis <keycap>N</keycap>
                  pour créer la nouvelle image. Les
                  accélérateurs clavier sont différents des raccourcis
                  clavier: les accélérateurs permettent de naviguer dans les
                  menus tandis que les raccourcis permettent d'accéder
                  directement à une fonction. Par exemple, le raccourci
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  est la façon la plus rapide de créer une nouvelle image.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 fornisce tasti scorciatoia per
                  facilitare l'accesso
                  ai menu. Se si trova che la navigazione attraverso i menu
                  usando il mouse è faticosa, la soluzione può essere usare la
                  tastiera. Per esempio se la barra dei menu è presente, per
                  creare una nuova immagine basta premere
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Alt</keycap>
                    <keycap>F</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>

                  </keycombo>.
                  Senza la barra dei menu premere
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
                    <keycap>F10</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  per aprire il primo menu a
                  sinistra e poi usare i tasti freccia o <keycap>F</keycap>
                  e poi <keycap>N</keycap> per creare
                  una nuova immagine. I tasti acceleratori sono differenti
                  dalle scorciatoie: i tasti acceleratori servono per navigare
                  nei menu invece le scorciatoie chiamano direttamente una
                  voce specifica di menu. Per esempio
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  è una scorciatoia
                  ed è anche il modo più veloce per aprire una nuova immagine.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  -2 ondersteunt het gebruik van sneltoetsen om sneller
                  specifieke menu's te kiezen. Bij veelvuldig gebruik is het
                  telkens opnieuw kiezen met de muis nogal omslachtig, de
                  oplossing hiervoor is het gebruik van het toetsenbord. Als u
                  bijvoorbeeld een nieuwe afbeelding wilt maken en de
                  menu-balk getoond wordt in uw huidige afbeelding hoeft u
                  slechts
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>ALT</keycap>
                    <keycap>F</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  in te toetsen. Als de Menubalk niet getoond
                  wordt, dient u
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>SHIFT</keycap>
                    <keycap>F10</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  in te drukken en manouvreren met de
                  pijltjestoetsen of de toetsen
                  <keycap>F</keycap> en daarna <keycap>N</keycap> om een
                  nieuwe afbeelding te maken. Sneltoetsen verschillen van
                  snelkoppelingstoetsen: Sneltoetsen laten u versneld door de
                  menuopties gaan, terwijl snelkoppelingen direkt een
                  specifieke menuoptie opstarten.
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>CTRL</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  is bijvoorbeeld een
                  snelkoppeling en de snelste manier om een nieuwe afbeelding
                  te maken.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Dersom du bruker <acronym>GIMP</acronym> mykje, vil du truleg
                  gå trøytt av å bruke datamusa i tide og utide. I
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 er det lagt inn snartastar slik at
                  du kan bruke tastaturet til mange av vala. Dersom menylinja
                  er synleg, kan du laga eit nytt bilete med tastane
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>ALT</keycap>
                    <keycap>F</keycap>
                    <keycap>N</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  Dersom menyen ikkje er synleg, kan du kalla han fram med
                  tastane
                  <keycombo>
                    <keycap>SHIFT</keycap>
                    <keycap>F10</keycap>
                  </keycombo>
                  og deretter bruke piltastane eller dei snartastane som står
                  på menyen.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  To ease access to your most commonly used menu items, the
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has provided dynamic shortcuts for
                  many years. When a
                  menu is open, you can hover over the desired menu item and
                  hold down your shortcut combination. This feature is still
                  present, but is deactivated by default in the
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0, to
                  avoid accidental re-assigning of existing shortcuts.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Pour faciliter l'accès à vos commandes les plus utilisées,
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> a fourni depuis longtemps la
                  possibilité de créer vos
                  propres raccourcis clavier: quand un item de menu est
                  sélectionné, il suffisait de taper les touches voulues pour
                  le raccouci pour qu'il soit créé. Cette possibilité existe
                  toujours mais a été désactivée par défaut dans
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 afin
                  d'éviter les conflits accidentels avec les raccourcis
                  existants.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Per facilitare l'accesso alle voci di menu più
                  frequentemente utilizzate, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è da
                  molti anni fornito
                  di scorciatoie dinamiche. Quando un menu viene aperto è
                  possibile sorvolare la voce desiderata e premere la
                  combinazione desiderata. Questa caratteristica è ancora
                  presente ma normalmente disabilitata in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 per
                  evitare di riassegnare accidentalmente le scorciatoie
                  predefinite.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Om de toegang tot veelgebruikte functies te
                  vergemakkelijken, zijn er in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  al veel jaren instelbare snelkoppelingen beschikbaar. Als
                  een menu open is hoeft u de muiscursor slechts naar het
                  gewenste menu-item te brengen en de gewenste
                  snelkopplings-toetscombinatie in te drukken. Deze
                  mogelijkheid is nog steed beschikbaar, maar staat standaard
                  uit in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.0 om toevallige ongewenste
                  herdefinities van bestaande snelkoppelingen te voorkomen.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  For å lette bruken, har <acronym>GIMP</acronym> i årevis hatt
                  dynamiske snarvegar for mange av dei mest brukte menyvala.
                  Altså snarvegar som du kan definere sjølv ved å halde nede
                  aktuell tastekombinasjon medan du rasar over menyen. Dette
                  kan du framleis gjere, men valet er til vanleg deaktivert
                  for ikkje å kome i konflikt med eksisterande snarvegar.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also ships with a number of
                  sets of key-bindings
                  for its menus. If you would like to replace the default
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  keybindings by Photoshop bindings, for example, you can move
                  the file <filename>menurc</filename> in your user data
                  directory to <filename>oldmenurc</filename>, rename
                  <filename>ps-menurc</filename> to
                  <filename>menurc</filename> and restart
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> werden nicht nur mehrere Sets
                  an Einstellungen für
                  die Tastenkürzel geliefert. Sollten Sie beispielsweise mit
                  den Tastenkürzeln von Photoshop vertraut sein und lieber
                  diese, statt der <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigenen verwenden
                  wollen, so bennenen
                  Sie einfach die Datei <filename>ps-menurc</filename> in
                  <filename>menurc</filename> um, und starten
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> erneut.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> possède ses propres combinaisons
                  de touches pour les
                  entrées de ses menus. Si vous voulez remplacer ces
                  combinaisons par celle de Photoshop, renommez le
                  <filename>menurc</filename> de votre répertoire
                  utilisateur en <filename>oldmenurc</filename> et renommez
                  <filename>ps-menurc</filename> en
                  <filename>menurc</filename>.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è fornito anche di un
                  considerevole numero di
                  collegamenti fra tasti e menu. Se si desidera modificare i
                  tasti predefiniti di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> e, per
                  esempio, abilitare quelli
                  più usati con Photoshop, basta rinominare il file
                  <filename>menurc</filename> nella directory di lavoro
                  dell'utente in <filename>oldmenurc</filename> e
                  rinominare <filename>ps-menurc</filename> in
                  <filename>menurc</filename>.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  kan er voor een bepaalde verzameling van toetsinstellingen
                  gekozen worden. Als u bijvoorbeeld liever
                  toetsenbord-combinaties als in Photoshop gebruikt, dan de
                  standaard <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  -combinaties kunt u het bestand `menurc' in uw
                  gebruikers-map naar bijvoorbeeld `oudmenurc' hernoemen om
                  vervolgens, door de naam van het bestand `ps-menurc' naar
                  `menurc' te veranderen, de photoshop toetsencombinaties te
                  activeren.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Dersom du ønskjer å endra dei førehandsinnstilte snartastane i
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> til slik dei er i Photoshop, finn du
                  fila <filename>menurc</filename> i
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-mappene og endrar namnet til t.d.
                  <filename>menurc-orig</filename>. Deretter endrar du namnet på
                  fila <filename>ps-menurc</filename> til
                  <filename>menurc</filename>.
                </para>
              </listitem>


            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry lang="cs;en;fr;it;nl;no">
              <term lang="cs">Práce s kartami a doky</term>
              <term lang="en">Handling Tabs and Docks</term>
              <term lang="fr">Gérer les Onglets et les fenêtres attachables</term>
              <term lang="it">Gestione schede e ancoraggi</term>
              <term lang="nl">Tabladen koppelen</term>
              <term lang="no">Handtering av faner og festeplassar</term>

              <listitem>
                <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 introduces a system of
                  tabbed dialogs to allow
                  you to make your workspace look the way you want it to be.
                  Almost all dialogs can be dragged to another dialog window
                  and dropped to make a tabbed dialog set.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 introduit un système de
                  dialogues en onglets vous
                  permettant de regrouper plusieurs dialogues dans une même
                  fenêtre. Presque toutes les boîtes de dialogue peuvent être
                  glissées-déposées dans une autre fenêtre de dialogue et y
                  apparaître sous forme d'onglet.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 introduce un sistema a
                  finestre multischeda che
                  permette di gestire a piacimento il proprio spazio di
                  lavoro. Quasi tutte le finestre di dialogo possono essere
                  trascinate su di un'altra finestra di dialogo e rilasciate
                  per formare una finestra a schede.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.0 is het mogelijk geworden om
                  verschillende
                  dialoogvensters achter elkaar als tabbladen in een enkel
                  dialoogvenster te schikken, bijna alle dialoogvensters
                  kunnen zo getabt samengevoegd worden.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Frå og med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 blei det innført eit
                  system med dialogfaner som gir deg høve til å komponera
                  skrivebordet ditt etter eigne ønskje. Nesten alle dialogane
                  kan flyttast til eit anna dialogvindauge og bli sleppt der
                  for å lage ein fanedialog.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  Furthermore, at the bottom of each dialog, there is a
                  dockable area: drag and drop tabs here to attach dialogs
                  beneath the bottom tab group.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  En outre, en bas de chaque boîte de dialogue se trouve une
                  barre d'attachement des dialogues où vous pouvez déposer les
                  dialogues attachables sous le groupe d'onglets du haut.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Inoltre, sul fondo di ogni finestra di dialogo, c'è un area
                  agganciabile: trascinando in questa posizione le schede le
                  si attacca in fondo, sotto l'area delle schede.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Verder is er onderaan elk dialoogvenster een koppelingsvlak:
                  u kunt tabbladen hiernaartoe slepen en laten vallen waarmee
                  deze aan de onderkant van de tab-groep gecombineerd worden.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Vidare er det nedst i kvar dialog eit festeområde der du kan
                  lima inn dialogar under faneområdet. Dette er lettare å sjå
                  i praksis enn å forklara her.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Skriptování</term>
              <term lang="en">Scripting</term>
              <term lang="de">Erstellung von Skripten</term>
              <term lang="fr">Rédaction de scripts</term>
              <term lang="it">Scripting</term>
              <term lang="nl">Recepten (`Scripting')</term>
              <term lang="no">Skript</term>

              <listitem>
                <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                <para lang="cs">Python Fu. Hadi hadi hadi:) FIXME</para>
                <para lang="en">
                  <quote>Python-fu</quote> is now the standard external
                  scripting interface for <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2. This
                  means that you can now use <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  functions in <acronym>Python</acronym> scripts, or
                  conversely use <acronym>Python</acronym> to write
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plug-ins. <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  is relatively easy to understand even for a
                  beginner, especially in comparison to the
                  <acronym>Lisp</acronym>-like <acronym>Scheme</acronym>
                  language used for Script-fu in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.
                  The <acronym>Python</acronym> bindings
                  are augmented by a set of classes for common operations, so
                  you are not forced to search through the complete
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  Procedural Database in order to carry out basic operations.
                  Moreover, <acronym>Python</acronym> has integrated
                  development environments and
                  a gigantic library, and runs not only on
                  <acronym>Linux</acronym> but also on
                  Microsoft Windows and Macintosh OS X. The biggest drawback,
                  for <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0, is that the standard user
                  interface offered in
                  Python-fu does not use the complete power of the
                  <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  language. The interface is currently designed to support
                  simple scripts, but a more sophisticated version is a goal
                  of future development.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Standardschnittstelle zur Erstellung von Skripten in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 ist <quote>Python-fu</quote>.
                  Dies bedeutet, dass <acronym>Python</acronym> Skripte auf
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Funktionen zugreifen könne, oder
                  umgekehrt, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Erweiterungen komplett
                  in der Programmiersprache <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  geschrieben werden könnne. Damit
                  wird das in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 eingesetzte,
                  <acronym>LISP</acronym> basierte Skript-Fu
                  um eine leicht zu lernende Schnittstelle ergänzt.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <quote>Python-fu</quote> est maintenant l'interface
                  d'écriture extene standard de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Cel
                  signifie que vous pouvez utiliser des fonctions
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en <acronym>Python</acronym> ou
                  inversement utiliser <acronym>Python</acronym> pour
                  écrire des greffons <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> est relativement facile à
                  comprendre même par les débutants, surtout si on le compare

                  au langage <acronym>Sheme</acronym>, qui rappelle
                  <acronym>LISP</acronym>, précédemment utilisé
                  par <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <quote>Python-fu</quote> è diventato ora lo standard
                  per l'interfaccia di scripting esterna di
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2. Ciò significa che ora è
                  possibile usare le funzioni di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  negli script <acronym>Python</acronym> o, viceversa, usare
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> per scrivere plug-in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. <acronym>Python</acronym> è
                  relativamente facile da capire anche per un principiante,
                  specialmente se confrontato con il linguaggio tipo
                  <acronym>Lisp</acronym> <acronym>Scheme</acronym> che
                  veniva usato per <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. I bindings
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> sono
                  potenziati da un insieme di classi per le operazioni più
                  comuni in maniera da evitare di dover consultare tutto il
                  database procedurale di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> per
                  eseguire alcune operazioni di base. Inoltre,
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> ha integrato l'ambiente di
                  sviluppo
                  e una gigantesca libreria che funziona non solo su
                  <acronym>Linux</acronym> ma
                  anche su Microsoft Windows e Mac OS X. Il più grosso difetto
                  di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 è che l'interfaccia utente
                  standard offerta da Python-fu non può usare completamente
                  la potenza del linguaggio <acronym>Python</acronym>.
                  L'interfaccia è attualmente studiata per
                  supportare script molto semplici ma una versione più
                  sofisticata è in progetto per gli sviluppi futuri.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  `Python-fu' is de standaard externe scripting taal van
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> geworden. Dit betekent dat u
                  makkelijk <acronym>GIMP</acronym> -functies in
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> kunt gebruiken of
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> kunt gebruiken om
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> -plug-ins te maken.
                  <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  is redelijk makkelijk te begrijpen, zelfs voor beginners in
                  ieder geval is het makkelijker te leren dan het
                  <acronym>Lisp</acronym>-gebaseerde `Script-fu' van
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1
                  De verwantschap met <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  komt mog sterker tot uitdrukking door een collectie klassen
                  voor gemeenschappelijke functies, dus u hoeft niet door de
                  hele <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-functies
                  beschrijving te ploegen om elementaire bewerkingen
                  uit te voeren. Sterker nog; <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  heeft de hele ontwikkelingsomgeving in een enorme
                  bibliotheek gegoten die niet alleen onder
                  <acronym>Linux</acronym> maar ook op Microsoft Windows en
                  Macintosh <acronym>OS X</acronym> werkt. Het grootste
                  nadeel hiervan voor <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.0
                  is dat de gebruikerslaag die `Python-fu' biedt, niet
                  over alle mogelijkheden van <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  beschikt. De huidige laag is ontworpen om eenvoudige
                  recepten uit te voeren, maar een geavanceerder versie is een
                  verder ontwikkelingsdoel.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Språket <emphasis>Python-fu</emphasis> er nå standardspråket
                  for å lage skript i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Dette betyr at du
                  kan bruke funksjonar frå <acronym>GIMP</acronym> i skript laga
                  i Python og nytte Python for å lage tilleggsprogram (Plug ins)
                  for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Dersom du tidlegare har laga
                  skript med det Lisp-liknande språket Scheme, som blei brukt i
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1, vil du sjå at Python-fu er mykje
                  enklare. T.d. er Python-fu sett opp med mange klassar for dei
                  vanlegaste operasjonane slik at du slepp leite gjennom heile
                  databasen for prosedyrar i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Python-fu
                  har også eit integrert utviklingsområde og eit stort bibliotek
                  med ulike prosedyrar og nødvendige programbitar. Python-fu kan
                  også brukast både på Linux, Windows og Macintosh OS X. Den
                  største ulempa for <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 er at Python-Fu
                  ikkje utnyttar all krafta som ligg i Python. Førebels kan du
                  difor bare lage enkle skript. Her er ei oppgåve for
                  vidareutvikling.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> is no longer distributed with
                  the standard <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2
                  distribution, but is available as a separate package.
                  Currently, <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> is supported only
                  on <acronym>Unix</acronym>-like
                  operating systems. It includes both a simple scripting
                  language, and the ability to code more polished interfaces
                  using the <acronym>Gtk2</acronym> perl module. Direct
                  pixel manipulation is
                  available through the use of <acronym>PDL</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> ist nicht länger Bestandteil
                  der Standardauslieferung von <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, kann
                  aber nach wie vor als separates Installationspaket
                  eingebunden werden. <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> ist
                  jedoch, im Gegensatz zu <acronym>Python</acronym>, nur auf
                  <acronym>Unix</acronym> basierten Systemen verfügbar.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> n'est plus livré avec la
                  distribution standard de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2, mais
                  il reste disponible dans un paquetage à part.
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> n'est accepté que par les
                  systèmes <acronym>Unix</acronym>. Il inclut à la fois un
                  langage d'écriture simple et la possibilité de
                  coder des interfaces plus polies grâce au module perl
                  <acronym>Gtk2</acronym>.
                  La manipulation directe des pixels est disponible à travers
                  <acronym>PDL</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> non viene più distribuito con
                  la distribuzione standard di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 ma
                  è dispobile come pacchetto separato. Attualmente
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> è supportato solo su sistemi
                  di tipo <acronym>Unix</acronym>. Include un semplice
                  linguaggio di scripting e la
                  possibilità di codificare interfacce più pulite usando il
                  modulo perl <acronym>Gtk2</acronym>. La manipolazione
                  diretta dei pixel è
                  disponibile attraverso l'uso di <acronym>PDL</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym>
                  wordt niet langer met de standaard pakket van
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2
                  meegeleverd, maar moet als afzonderlijk pakket
                  geinstalleerd worden. Op dit moment kan
                  <acronym>GIMP-Perl</acronym> alleen op
                  <acronym>Unix</acronym>-achtige
                  besturingssystemen gebruikt worden. Hierbij zijn
                  ook een eenvoudige receptuur-taal en de mogelijkheid om
                  beter gestoomlijnde interactielagen met de
                  <acronym>Gtk2-Perl</acronym>
                  module te schrijven. Met behulp van <acronym>PDL</acronym>
                  kunnen beeldpunten rechtstreeks worden bewerkt.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Gimp-Perl blir nå ikkje distribuert saman med
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, men er tilgjengeleg for Unix-liknande
                  system som ekstrapakke. Det inneheld både eit enkelt
                  skriptspråk og høve til å lage betre grensesnitt ved hjelp
                  av Perlmodulen Gtk2. Du kan bruke PDL for direkte
                  pikselmanipulering.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  Script-fu, based on <quote>Scheme</quote>, has the same
                  drawbacks as
                  before: not intuitive, hard to use and lacking a real
                  development environment. It does, however, have one major
                  advantage compared to Python-fu: Script-fu scripts are
                  directly interpreted by <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and do not
                  require any
                  additional software installation. Python-fu requires that
                  you install a package for the <acronym>Python</acronym>
                  language.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Script-fu, basé sur <quote>Scheme</quote>, a les mêmes
                  inconvénients
                  qu'avant: peu intuitif, difficile à utiliser et manquant
                  d'un environnement de développement véritable. Il a
                  néanmoins un avantage majeur par rapport à Python-fu: Les
                  scripts Script-fu sont interprétés directement par
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sans
                  avoir besoin d'installer un logiciel complémentaire.
                  Python-fu, lui, necessite l'installation d'un paquetage pour
                  le langage <acronym>Python</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Script-fu, basato su <quote>Scheme</quote>, ha le stesse
                  controindicazioni
                  di sempre: non intuitivo, difficile da usare e mancante di
                  un vero ambiente di sviluppo. Comunque ha anche dei vantaggi
                  in confronto a Python-fu: gli script Script-fu sono
                  direttamente interpretati da <acronym>GIMP</acronym> e non
                  richiedono nessuna
                  installazione di software aggiuntivo. Python-fu richiede che
                  si installi un pacchetto per il linguaggio
                  <acronym>Python</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  `Script-fu', dat vaar het voorbeeld van `Scheme' ontwikkeld
                  is, heeft dezelfde oude nadelen: Niet intuitief, moeilijk te
                  gebruiken en gebrek aan een echte ontwikkelomgeving. Het
                  heeft echter een voordeel ten opzichte van `Python-fu':
                  `Script-fu' recepten kunnen rechtstreeks door
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  gebruikt worden en hebben geen extra software nodig. Voor
                  `Python-fu' moet een pakket voor de
                  <acronym>Python</acronym> taal installeren.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Script-Fu basert på Scheme har dei same ulempene som
                  tidlegare, dvs. lite intuitivt og vanskeleg å bruke. Fordelen
                  er at skript laga med Script-Fu kan leggjast direkte inn i
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> utan vidare. Python-Fu krev her ei
                  tilleggspakke.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Nástroj Text</term>
              <term lang="en">The Text Tool</term>
              <term lang="de">Das Werkzeug <quote>Text</quote></term>
              <term lang="fr">L'Outil Texte</term>
              <term lang="it">Lo strumento di testo</term>
              <term lang="nl">Het tekst gereedschap</term>
              <term lang="no">Tekstverktøyet</term>

              <listitem>
                <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The big problem with the standard text tool in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 was
                  that text could not be modified after it was rendered. If
                  you wanted to change anything about the text, all you could
                  do was <quote>undo</quote> and try again (if you were
                  lucky enough to
                  have sufficient undo history available, and then of course
                  you would also undo any other work you had done in the
                  meantime). In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2 there was also a
                  <quote>dynamic text</quote>
                  plug-in that allowed you to create special text layers and
                  keep them around indefinitely, in a modifiable form, but it
                  was buggy and awkward to use. The second generation Text
                  tool is an enhanced combination of the old Text tool and the
                  Dynamic Text plugin. Now all options are available in the
                  <quote>Tool Options</quote>: font, font size, text color,
                  justify,
                  antialiasing, indent, spacing. To create a new text item,
                  click in the image and a little editor pops up. Text appears
                  on the image while you are editing (and carriage returns are
                  handled properly!). A new dedicated layer is created; this
                  layer resizes dynamically to match the text you key in. You
                  can import plain text from a file, and you can even do
                  things like writing from right to left in Arabic. If you
                  select a text layer, clicking on it opens the editor, and
                  you can then modify your text.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die wohl größte Einschränkung des alten Textwerkezeuges in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 war, dass einmal gezeichneter
                  Text nicht mehr
                  verändert werden konnte. Wenn irgendeine Einstellung oder
                  auch nur ein einzelner Buchstabe geändert werden sollte, so
                  mußte bisher die gesamte den Text beinhaltende Ebene
                  gelöscht, und komplett neu angelegt werden. Diese
                  Einschränkungen wurden mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 beseitigt.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Le grand problème avec l'outil Texte dans
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 était que
                  le texte ne plus être modifié un fois produit. Dans
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1
                  il y avait aussi un greffon <quote>Texte dynamique</quote>
                  qui permettait
                  de créer des calques texte spéciaux que vous pouviez
                  conserver pour les modifier, mais il était bogué et affreux
                  à utiliser.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Un grande problema con lo strumento di testo standard di
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 era che il testo non poteva più
                  essere modificato dopo che era stato
                  <quote>disegnato</quote>. Se si voleva cambiare
                  qualsiasi particolare del testo bisognava eseguire un
                  <quote>annullamento</quote> e riprovare (se si era
                  abbastanza fortunati
                  da avere memoria per gli annullamenti a sufficienza e
                  naturalmente era necessario annullare anche qualsiasi altro
                  lavoro fatto nel frattempo). In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  1.2 c'era anche un plug-in di <quote>testo dinamico</quote>
                  che permetteva di creare
                  speciali livelli di testo e mantenerli indefinitivamente in
                  una forma modificabile ma era bacato e di difficile uso. La
                  seconda generazione dello strumento di testo è una
                  combinazione avanzata del vecchio strumento e del plug-in di
                  testo dinamico. Ora tutte le opzioni sono disponibili nelle
                  <quote>opzioni dello strumento</quote>: carattere,
                  grandezza carattere,
                  colore carattere, giustificazione, aliasing, indentazione,
                  spaziatura. Per creare un nuovo elemento di testo, basta
                  fare clic sull'immagine e appare una piccolo editor. Il
                  testo appare sull'immagine mentre la si sta modificando (e i
                  ritorni a capo sono gestiti in modo corretto!). Viene creato
                  un nuovo livello di testo dedicato; questo livello si
                  ridimensione dinamicamente per corrispondere con il testo
                  che si è appena inserito. È possibile importare del testo
                  semplice da un file e si può persino scrivere da destra a
                  sinistra in Arabo. Se si seleziona un livello di testo,
                  facendo clic su di esso si apre l'editor ed è possibile
                  modificarne il contenuto.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Het grote probleem met het standaard tekstgereedschap in
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1
                  was dat de tekst niet meer gewijzigd kon worden nadat ze
                  getekend was. Indien er iets gewijzigd moest worden kon de
                  tekst alleen ongedaan gemaakt worden en moest ze weer
                  helemaal opnieuw ingevoerd worden. (Als u genoeg geheugen
                  had om genoeg van de wijzigingsgeschiedenis op te slaan en
                  alle andere tussentijdse wijzigingen werden natuurlijk ook
                  ongedaan gemaakt.) In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1.2
                  was er ook een dynamische tekst-plugin beschikbaar
                  waardoor u speciale tekstlagen kon aanmaken die latere
                  wijzigingen toestonden, maar de werking van deze plugin was
                  niet geheel triviaal en feilloos te noemen. De tweede
                  generatie tekstgereedschap is een vernuftige combinatie van
                  de eigenschappen van het oude en de dynamische tekst-plugin.
                  Alle opties zijn beschikbaar in het gereedschapsopties-vak:
                  Lettertype, grootte, kleur, uitlijning, Anti-aliasing,
                  inspring, spatie-ering. Om een nieuw tekstvoorwerp te maken,
                  dient u in de tekening te klikken. Er verschijnt dan een
                  klein invoervenster. De tekst verschijnt in de afbeelding
                  terwijl u het in het venster invoert (en regelafbrekingen
                  worden op correcte wijze doorgevoerd!). Er wordt voor de
                  tekst speciaal een nieuwe laag gevormd die met de grootte
                  van de tekst meegroeit of krimpt. U kunt platte tekst uit
                  een bestand inlezen, en het is ook mogelijk om bijvoorbeeld
                  van rechts naar links te schrijven zoals in het arabisch.
                  Als u een tekstlaag selecteerd kunt u het invoervenster met
                  de tekst weer oproepen door erop te klikken.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 kan du ikkje forandra ein tekst
                  etter at han er teikna inn i biletet. Den einaste måten er å
                  <emphasis>angre</emphasis> og deretter skrive inn ny tekst.
                  Rett nok kom det i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2 eit
                  tilleggsprogram som kunne lage spesielle tekstlag, men dette
                  var tungvindt i bruk. Frå <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 og utover,
                  er dette sterkt forbetra. Nå kan du justera teksten etter
                  ønskje i <emphasis>Verktøyinnstillingane</emphasis>, både
                  skrifttype, storleik, farge og mykje meir. For å skriva inn
                  ein tekst, vel du tekstmodus og klikkar på biletet. Det dukkar
                  då opp eit lite redigeringsvindauge der du kan skrive og
                  redigere teksten. Endåtil enter-tasten verkar som han skal. Du
                  kan også importera tekst frå andre kjelder. Teksten blir lagt
                  i eit eige tekstlag, og kan behandlast som andre lag. Du kan
                  seinare opna dette laget og redigera teksten om du har behov
                  for det, utan å gjere andre forandringar i biletet.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Nástroj Cesty</term>
              <term lang="en">The Path Tool</term>
              <term lang="de">Das Pfadwerkzeug</term>
              <term lang="fr">L'outil Chemins</term>
              <term lang="it">Lo strumento tracciato</term>
              <term lang="nl">Het pad gereedschap</term>
              <term lang="no">Baneverktøyet</term>

              <listitem>
                <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The second generation Path tool has a completely new
                  interface. The first major difference you notice is that
                  paths are no longer required to be closed. A path can be
                  made up of a number of disjoint curve segments. The next
                  major difference is that now the path tool has three
                  different modes, Design, Edit and Move.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Das neue Pfadwerkzeug hat eine komplett neue
                  Benutzeroberfläche. Der erste große Unterschied, den Sie
                  bei der Arbeit mit Pfaden bemerken werden ist, dass Pfade
                  nicht mehr geschlossen sein müssen. Die zweite Neuerung
                  ist, dass das Werkzeug jetzt über drei Modi (Design,
                  Bearbeiten, Verschieben) verfügt.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Le nouvel outil Chemins a une interface entièrement
                  nouvelle. Les chemins n'ont plus besoin d'être fermés. Un
                  chemin peut être formés de plusieurs composants distincts.
                  Trois modes différents sont possibles: Tracer, Édition,
                  Déplacer.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Lo strumento tracciato di seconda generazione possiede
                  un'interfaccia completamente nuova. La prima differenza che
                  si nota è che non è più necessario chiudere i tracciati. Un
                  tracciato può essere costituito da un numero di segmenti di
                  curva disgiunti. Altra grossa differenza è che ora lo
                  strumento ha tre differenti modalità: Progetta, Modifica e
                  Sposta.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Het pad-gereedschap heeft in haar tweede generatie een
                  volledig nieuwe bedieningsorganen gekregen. De eerste grote
                  verandering die u kunt opmerken is dat paden niet langer
                  gesloten hoeven te zijn. Een pad kan opgebouwd zijn uit
                  verschillende, niet-verbonden delen. Het volgende grote
                  verschil zijn de drie werktoestanden: Ontwerpen, wijzigen en
                  verplaatsen.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Andregenerasjons baneverktøy har ein heilt ny utsjånad i høve
                  til tidlegare. Noe av det første du merkar, er kanskje at
                  banane ikkje treng vere lukka. Du kan bygge opp ein bane av
                  mindre sirkelsegment eller andre korte strekar. Den andre
                  store skilnaden er at baneverktøyet nå har tre ulike modus:
                  Design (Lag ny), Rediger og Flytt
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  In Design mode, you can create a path, add nodes to an


                  existing path and modify the shape of a curve either by
                  dragging edges of the curve or dragging the
                  <quote>handles</quote> of a node.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  En mode Tracer, vous pouvez créer un chemin, ajouter des
                  nœuds à un chemin existant et modifier la forme de la courbe
                  en glissant les segments ou en glissant les poignées d'un
                  nœud.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  In modalità Progetta, è possibile creare un tracciato,
                  aggiungere nodi ad un tracciato esistente e modificare la
                  forma della curva sia spostando i bordi di essa che
                  spostandone gli <quote>appigli</quote> dei nodi.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  In de Ontwerptoestand kunt u een pad aanmaken, knopen aan
                  een bestaand pad toevoegen en de vorm erva veranderen door
                  de uiteinden of de knopen van plaats te veranderen.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  I designmodus kan du lage nye baner, legge til noder eller
                  endre utsjånaden til eksisterande baner ved å dra i kantane
                  på ei kurve eller dra i <quote>handtaka</quote> til ein node.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  In Edit mode, you can add nodes in the middle of curve
                  edges, and remove nodes or edges, as well as change the
                  shape of the curve. You can also connect two path
                  components.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  En mode Éditer, vous pouvez ajouter ou supprimer un nœud sur
                  un segment, changer la forme de la courbe ou raccorder deux
                  composants.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  In modalità modifica, è possibile aggiungere nodi nel mezzo
                  della curva e rimuovere nodi o estremità come modificarne la
                  forma. È anche possibile unire due componenti del tracciato.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  In de wijzigingstoestand kunt u knopen op het midden tussen
                  de uiteinden toevoegen, knopen of eindpunten verwijderen en
                  de vorm van het pad veranderen. Ook kunt u twee delen van
                  een pad met elkaar verbinden
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  I redigeringsmodus kan du legge til eller fjerne noder kvar
                  som helst på kurvene. Du kan også binde saman banekomponentar.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  The third mode, Move, is, as you might expect, used to move
                  path components. If your path has several components, you
                  can move each path component separately. To move all
                  components at once, use the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  En mode Déplacer, vous pouvez déplacer les composants du
                  chemin, ensemble ou séparément.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  La terza modalità, Sposta, è come prevedibile, usata per
                  spostare i componenti del tracciato. Se il tracciato
                  possiede più componenti, è possibile spostarli tutti insieme
                  usando il tasto <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  De derde, verplaats-toestand kan een pad verplaatsen, als
                  een pad uit verschillende delen bestaat kunt u die
                  afzonderlijk verplaatsen, als u ze allemaal tegelijk wilt
                  verplaatsen dient u de <keycap>Shift</keycap> toets te
                  gebruiken.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Modus Flytt er vel eigentleg sjølvforklarande. Du kan anten
                  flytta kvar enkel komponent for seg, eller alle komponentane
                  samstundes ved å halde nede Shift-tasten.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  Two other path-related features are new in the
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0. The <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  can not only import an SVG image as a raster image, but
                  can also keep SVG paths intact as <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  paths. This means that the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is now
                  more able than ever to complement your
                  favorite vector drawing tool. The other feature which has
                  made the path tool much better is the introduction of
                  vector-based stroking. In previous versions, stroking paths
                  and selections was a matter of drawing a brush-stroke along
                  the path. This mode is still available, but it is now
                  possible to stroke a curve accurately, using the vector
                  library <acronym>libart</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Zwei weitere neue Funktionen, die mit Pfaden in Zusammenhang
                  stehen sind das Laden von SVG Dateien als Pfad und die Art
                  wie Sie Pfade zeichnen können.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  L'outil chemin comporte deux autres nouveautés. Non
                  seulement <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 peut importer les
                  images SVG mais il peut aussi garder les chemins SVG
                  intacts comme chemins <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Cela
                  signifie que <acronym>GIMP</acronym> peut collaborer avec
                  votre outil de dessin vectoriel favori. L'autre nouveauté
                  qui a amélioré l'outil Chemins est la possibilité de
                  <quote>tracer</quote>
                  automatiquement un chemin avec la brosse de votre choix.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Ci sono altre due nuove caratteristiche riguardanti i
                  tracciati in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0. Ora
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> non solo può importare
                  immagini SVG come raster ma può anche mentenere intatti i
                  tracciati SVG come tracciati <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                  Perciò ora <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è molto
                  più utile come complemento di un qualsiasi programma di
                  grafica vettoriale. L'altra importante caratteristica che
                  rende lo strumento del tracciato più utile che mai è
                  l'introduzione dei tracciati basati su vettori. Nelle
                  versioni precedenti, i tracciati e le selezioni erano basati
                  sul disegno di un tracciato con uno strumento tipo pennello.
                  Questa modalità è ancora disponibile ma ora è anche
                  possibile tracciare una curva accuratamente usando la
                  libreria di vettori <acronym>libart</acronym>.
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  Er zijn nog twee andere nieuwe, pad gerelateerde
                  toevoegingen aan de mogelijkheden van
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> -2.0. Een SVG afbeelding kan nu niet
                  alleen meer als rasterafbeelding geimporteerd worden, maar
                  SVG-paden kunnen nu ook omgezet worden naar
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-paden. Dit betekent dat
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                  een nog betere aanvulling op vector-tekenprogramma's is. De
                  andere belangrijke verbetering van het pad-gereedschap is
                  het gebruik van vectorgebaseerde penseelstreken. In vorige
                  versies, panseel-gestroken paden en selecties werden gevormd
                  door penseelstreken over het pad te tekenen, deze werkwijze
                  is nog steeds mogelijk, maar het is nu ook mogelijk een
                  kromme nauwkeurig aan te strijken door gebruik te maken van
                  de vectorbibliotheek <acronym>libart</acronym>
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Frå og med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 blei det innført to
                  nye eigenskapar. I tillegg til å importera eit SVG-bilete
                  som eit rasterbilete, kan du nå importera SVG-banar som
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-banar. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er
                  altså nå betre eigna som tilleggsprogram til
                  favorittprogrammet ditt for å laga vektorgrafikk.
                  Den andre forbetringa er at <acronym>GIMP</acronym> nå
                  kan lage vektorbasert oppstreking av banane. Tidlegare blei
                  banane streka opp ved å dra ein pensel langs banen. Dette
                  er framleis mogleg, men til vanleg vil du nå streke opp
                  banen ved hjelp av vektorbiblioteket.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>


            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="cs">Ostatní vylepšení</term>
              <term lang="en">Other improvements</term>
              <term lang="de">Weitere Neuerungen</term>
              <term lang="fr">Autres améliorations</term>
              <term lang="it">Altri miglioramenti</term>
              <term lang="nl">Andere verbeteringen</term>
              <term lang="no">Andre forbetringar</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="cs">Některá další vylepšení:</para>
                <para lang="en">Some other improvements in brief:</para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Außerdem wurden Verbesserungenn in folgenden Bereichen
                  vorgenommen:
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">Quelques autres améliorations, en bref:</para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Ecco brevemente alcuni altri miglioramenti:
                </para>
                <para lang="nl">
                  In het kort enkele andere verbeteringen:
                </para>
                <para lang="no">Noen andre forbetringar som bør nemnast:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para lang="cs">
                      Kvalitnější vyhlazování v některých situacích, zejména
                      při použití textového nástroje.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      Higher-quality antialiasing in some places — most
                      notibly in the Text tool.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Die Qualität des Anti-Aliasing wurde an verschiedenen
                      Stellen (zum Beispiel im Textwerkzeug) verbessert.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Haute qualité de lissage, surtout dans l'outil Texte.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      In alcune situazioni la qualità dell'antialias è stata
                      migliorata notevolmente — principalmente nello
                      strumento di testo.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Op enkele plaatsen is het anti-aliasing (gladstrijking
                      van gekartelde schuine lijnen) verbeterd — Dit is het
                      beste merkbaar bij het tekst-gereedschap.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Betre kantutjamning, spesielt i tekstverktøyet.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      Icons and menus are skinnable. You can create your own
                      icon set and apply it to the toolbox using the
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Preference</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Interface</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>
                      menu option. A theme called <quote>small</quote> is
                      included with the standard distribution.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Symbole und Menüs können über Themen geändert werden.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      On peut changer le décor des icônes et des menus. Vous
                      pouvez créer votre propre lot d'icônes et l'appliquer à
                      la Boîte à outils en utilisant l'option Interface du
                      menu Préférences. Un thème <quote>small</quote>
                      (petit) est inclus dans la distribution standard.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Icone e menu ora possono avere un tema. È possibile
                      creare un proprio insieme di icone ed applicarlo alla
                      barra degli strumenti usando l'opzione di menu
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Preferenze</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Interfaccia</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                      È stato incluso un tema <quote>small</quote> (trad.:
                      <quote>piccolo</quote>) nella distribuzione standard.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Om de iconen en menu's kunnen eigen omvattingen gelegd
                      worden. U kunt nu uw eigen iconenverzameling maken en in
                      het gereedschapsvenster gebruiken door gebruik te maken
                      van de
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Voorkeuren</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Bediening</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>-menuoptie. Bij de
                      standaarduitgave zit al een alternatief standaard-thema,
                      genaamd <quote>Small</quote>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Utskiftelege ikon og menyar. Du kan endre utsjånaden
                      til <acronym>GIMP</acronym> med menyvala
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Innstillingar</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Tema</guimenuitem>
                      </menuchoice> i hovudmenyen.
                      Originalt finn du, utanom normaloppsettet, også eit
                      valfritt oppsett kalla <quote>small</quote>.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      An image can be saved as a template and used to create
                      new images.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Ein Bild kann als Vorlage gespeichert und für die
                      Anlage neuer Bilder verwendet werden.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Une image peut être enregistrée comme modèle et être
                      utilisée à créer de nouvelles images.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Un'immagine può essere salvata come modello e usata per
                      creare nuove immagini.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Een afbeelding kan als sjabloon opgeslagen worden en
                      gebruikt worden om nieuwe afbeeldingen te genereren.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Du kan lagra eit bilete som eit mønster og bruke det som
                      grunnlag for andre bilete.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      There are four new combination modes for layers that lie
                      one on top of another within an image:
                      <quote>Hard Light</quote>, <quote>Soft Light</quote>,
                      <quote>Grain Extract</quote> and
                      <quote>Grain Merge</quote>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Es wurden vier neue Modi zur Verknüpfung von Ebenen
                      hinzugefügt: <quote>Hartes Licht</quote>,
                      <quote>Weiches Licht</quote>,
                      <quote>Faser extrahieren</quote>
                      sowie <quote>Faser mischen</quote>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Il y a quatre nouveaux modes de fusion des calques qui
                      gisent l'un au dessus de l'autre:
                      <quote>Lumière dure</quote>,
                      <quote>Lumière douce</quote>,
                      <quote>Extraction de grain</quote>,
                      <quote>Fusion de grain</quote>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Ci sono quattro nuove combinazioni di modalità per i
                      livelli che giacciono sopra un'altro in un'immagine:
                      <quote>Luce forte</quote>, <quote>Luce debole</quote>,
                      <quote>Estrazione grana</quote> e
                      <quote>Fusione grana</quote>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Er zijn vier nieuwe combinatie modi voor lagen die op
                      elkaar liggen in een afbeelding:
                      <quote>Hard Licht</quote>, <quote>Zacht licht</quote>,

                      <quote>Grain extract</quote> (Korrel aftrekken) en
                      <quote>Grain Merge</quote> (Korrel samenvoegen).
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Det er lagt til fire nye modus for å kombinera ulike
                      lag: <quote>Hardt lys</quote>, <quote>Mjukt
                        lys</quote>, <quote>Trekk frå korn</quote> og
                      <quote>Flett korn</quote>.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      If there is an active selection, you can crop the image
                      directly to the selection size using image menu
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Crop</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Wenn es im Bild eine Auswahl gibt, so können Sie mit
                      einem neuen Kommando das Bild auf die Auswahl
                      beschneiden.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      S'il y a une sélection active, vous pouvez découper
                      l'image à la taille de cette sélection par l'option
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Découper</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Se c'è una selezione attiva, è possibile ritagliare
                      l'immagine direttamente alla selezione usando il menu
                      immagine
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Immagine</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Ritaglia immagine</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Als er iets geselecteerd is kunt u de afmetingen van de
                      afbeeldinge reduceren tot de afmetingen van de selectie
                      door het gebruik van de menukoppeling:
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Afbeelding</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Afbeelding snijden</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Dersom du har ei aktiv markering, kan du krympe biletet
                      direkte til same storleik som markeringa med kommandoen
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Bilete</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Beskjer biletet</guimenuitem>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>

                  </listitem>


                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      As well as being able to create guides, there's
                      now a grid functionality in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                      It is complementary to the guides functionality and
                      makes it easier to position objects so that they
                      align perfectly.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Neben der Möglichkeit der Hilfslinien können Sie jetzt
                      auch ein Gitter über das Bild legen, um präziser zu
                      arbeiten.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> a maintenant une grille,
                      complémentaire des
                      guides, rendant plus facile le positionnement des
                      objets.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Oltre a essere possibile la creazione di guide, ora in
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> c'è anche una griglia. È
                      complementare alle guide e
                      rende più facile il posizionamento allineato degli
                      oggetti.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Als verder aanvulling op de verbeterde werking van de
                      hulplijnen kunt u in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                      nu een raster gebruiken om voorwerpen makkelijker
                      perfect ten opzichte van elkaar te plaatsen en uit te
                      lijnen.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      I tillegg til at du kan setje opp hjelpelinjer (Bm.:
                      <quote>innrettingslinjer</quote>), er det nå også eit
                      rutenett tilgjengeleg for å tilpassa komponentar
                      (nesten) perfekt.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The Layers dialog is more coherent, in that there are no
                      more hidden functions accessed only with right click on
                      the miniature image of the layer that appears there. You
                      can now handle layer operations directly from the image
                      menu: Layer Mask, Transparency, Transformation and Layer
                      Color operations are directly in the Layer submenu.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Die Benutzerfläche des Ebenendialoges wurde
                      überarbeitet. Damit werden einige Funktionen leichter
                      zugänglich. Ausserdem sind wichtige, ebenenbezogene
                      Funktionen jetzt über ein Menü im Bildfenster
                      zugänglich.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Le dialogue des Calques est plus cohérent, en ce qu'il
                      n'y a plus de fonctions cachées, accessibles uniquement
                      par le menu local. Toutes les fonctions concernant les
                      calques sont accessibles par le sous-menu Calque.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      La finestra di dialogo livelli è più coerente, nel senso
                      che non ci sono più funzioni nascoste accessibili solo
                      con il tasto destro del mouse sulla miniatura del
                      livello. Ora è possibile gestire le operazioni sui
                      livelli direttamente dal menu immagine: le operazioni di
                      Maschera, Trasparenza, Trasforma e Colori sono ora
                      direttamente nel sottomenu livelli.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Het lagen dialoogvenster duidelijker opgebouwd doordat
                      het verwijderen van de verborgen functies alleen met een
                      rechter muisklik op het icoon van de laag, gebruikt
                      konden worden: Laag-bewerkingen zijn nu direkt vanaf de
                      menubalk in het afbeeldingsvenster toegankelijk:
                      Laagmasker-, Transparantie-, Transformatie- en
                      Kleurbewerkingen staan nu in het `Lagen'-submenu
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Lagdialogen er nå fullstendig. Det er ingen usynlege
                      funksjonar som bare er tilgjengelege ved høgreklikk på
                      miniatyrbiletet. Alle operasjonane er også tilgjengelege
                      frå menyen, så som lagmaske, dekningsevne, transformasjon
                      og manipulering av lagfargane.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      Color display filters are now available from the image
                      menu
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Display Filters</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                      Using them, you can
                      simulate different gamma values, different contrasts, or
                      even color deficient vision, without altering your
                      original image. This actually has been a feature of the
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developer versions for a long
                      time, but it has never been stable enough to appear in
                      a stable version of the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> before.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Mit Hilfe der neuen Ansichtsfilter können Sie ein Bild,
                      ohne es verändern zu müssen unter verschiedenen
                      Farbfiltern betrachten. Damit können beispielsweise
                      verschiedene Gammawerte simuliert werden.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Les filtres d'affichage couleur sont maintenant
                      disponibles via le menu
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Affichage</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Filtres d'affichage</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>:
                      ils vous permmettent de modifier l'affichage des
                      couleurs sur votre écran, sans modifier l'image
                      elle-même. Cela est utile aux personnes ayant un
                      problème de vision des couleurs.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      I filtri di colore del video sono ora disponibili dal
                      menu immagine
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Visualizza</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Mostra filtri</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>. Usandoli è
                      possibile simulare differenti valori di gamma, contrasti
                      o addirittura una deficienza di colore senza alterare
                      l'immagine originale. Questa è stata una caratteristica
                      della versione di sviluppo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                      per molto tempo e fino a ora non era stata mai
                      abbastanza stabile da poter essere inclusa nella
                      versione ufficiale di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Er zijn nu kleurweergavefilters beschikbaar in het
                      afbeeldingsmenu
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Beeld</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Weergavefilers</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                      Hiermee kunt u
                      verschillende gamma waarden, contrasten, en zelfs
                      kleurenblindheids effecten simuleren zonder daarvoor de
                      afbeelding te wijzigen. Dit zat eigenlijk al een lange
                      tijd in de ontwikkelingsversie maar was nog niet eerder
                      stabiel genoeg om in de stabiele versie van
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> toegelaten te worden.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Fargefiltra er nå tilgjengelege direkte frå menyen
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Vis</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Vis filtra</guimenuitem>
                      </menuchoice>.
                      Ved å bruke desse filtra, kan du gjere ein heil del
                      endringar på biletet utan å endra sjølve biletet. Dette er
                      første gongen dette er med i ein stabil versjon av
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The color selection dialog has a new CMYK mode,
                      associated with the printer icon.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Der Dialog zur Farbauswahl verfügt über einen neuen
                      CMYK Modus.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Le dialogue de sélection des couleurs possède un mode
                      CMJN associé à l'onglet représentant une imprimante.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      La finestra di dialogo della selezione del colore ora ha
                      una nuova modalità CMYK, associata all'icona stampante.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Het kleurselectie dialoogvenster heeft een nieuwe CMYK
                      werkmodus die met het printericoon verbonden is.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Dialogen for fargeval har nå også ein CMYK-modus som er
                      tilordna ikonet for skriv ut.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      Data stored in <acronym>EXIF</acronym> tags by digital
                      cameras are now
                      handled in read and write mode for JPEG files.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Bildaten die in <acronym>EXIF</acronym> Tags enthalten
                      sind, bleiben beim
                      Lesen und Speichern von JPEG Bildern erhalten.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Les méta-données <acronym>EXIF</acronym> des appareils
                      photo numériques
                      sont maintenant gérées en mode lecture et écriture pour
                      les fichiers JPEG.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      I dati memorizzati come campi <acronym>EXIF</acronym>
                      dalle macchine
                      fotografiche digitali ora sono gestiti e possono esser
                      letti e scritti nei file JPEG.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Gegevens die als <acronym>EXIF</acronym> etiketten aan
                      <acronym>JPEG</acronym>
                      bestanden zijn toegevoegd door digitale camera's worden
                      nu ook gelijk met de afbeelding bewerkt.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Data som ulike digitalkamera lagrar som EXIF-data knytt
                      til bileta, blir nå tatt med ved lasting og lagring av
                      JPEG-filer. (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan førebels ikkje
                      gjere seg nytte av EXIF).
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      MNG animations are now supported. The MNG file format
                      can be considered as animated PNG. It has all the
                      advantages of PNG over GIF, such as more colors, 256
                      levels of transparency, and perhaps most importantly,
                      lack of patent encumbrance. The format is a web standard
                      and all recent popular web browsers support it.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      MNG Animationen werden unterstützt. Das MNG Dateiformat
                      kann als eine Art animiertes PNG betrachtet werden. Es
                      hat all die Vorteile von PNG (gegenüber GIF), als da
                      wären hohe Farbtiefe, 256 Transparenzstufen und fast
                      das Wichtigste — es ist frei von Patenten.

                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Les animations MNG sont maintenant gérées. le format MNG
                      peut être considéré comme un PNG animé. Il a tous les
                      avantages du PNG sur le GIF, tels le nombre plus grand
                      de couleurs, 256 niveaux de transparence, et, peut-être
                      plus important, l'absence de problème de licence. C'est
                      un standard Web, et les navigateurs les plus répandus
                      l'acceptent.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Ora le animazioni MNG sono supportate. Il formato file
                      MNG può essere considerato come un PNG animato. Possiede
                      tutti i vantaggi del PNG sul GIF, come il fatto di avere
                      molti più colori, 256 livelli di trasparenza e, forse la
                      cosa più importante di tutte, la mancanza di un brevetto
                      su di esso. Il formato è uno standard web e tutti i più
                      recenti e diffusi software di navigazione web lo
                      supportano.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      <acronym>MNG</acronym> -filmpjes worden nu ook
                      ondersteund. Het <acronym>MNG</acronym>
                      bestandsformaat wordt behandeld als bewogen
                      <acronym>PNG</acronym> daardoor heeft het alle extra's
                      die <acronym>PNG</acronym> over <acronym>GIF</acronym>
                      heeft: Meer kleuren, 256 transparantieniveau's en -nog
                      belangrijker- geen last van patent-beperkingen. Het is
                      een Web-standaard die alle niet al te oude, populaire
                      web browsers kunnen lezen.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> støtter nå MNG-animasjonar.
                      (Animert PNG). Fordelen med MNG-formatet i høve til det
                      meir vanlege GIF-formatet, er større fargerikdom, 256
                      nivå av gjennomsikt, og ikkje minst, ingen patentrettar
                      slik GIF-formatet har. MNG blir støtta av alle nyare
                      nettlesarar.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para lang="cs">
                      GAP (
                      <foreignphrase>GIMP Animation package</foreignphrase>
                      ), což je rozšíření Gimpu pro práci s animacemi, nyní
                      podporuje zvuk, funkci modré obrazovky a metodu
                      <foreignphrase>onion skinning</foreignphrase>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Animation package now does
                      onion-skinning, a
                      bluescreen feature was added as well as audio support.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Das <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Animationspaket kann jetzt
                      <quote>onion-skinning</quote>, außerdem wurde eine
                      <quote>bluescreen</quote> Funktion hinzugefügt.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">Je n'ai pas su traduire. Désolé!</para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Il pacchetto di animazione di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                      ora possiede anche la
                      gestione delle cartaveline, del bluscreen (trad.
                      <quote>schermoblu</quote>) e il supporto per l'audio.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Het <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                      Animatie pakket kan nu ook met verschillende lagen
                      werken. Verder zijn er blauwscherm functionaliteit en
                      geluidsondersteuning aan toegevoegd.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Animasjonspakka til <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har nå
                      <quote>onion-skinning</quote>. I tillegg også
                      ei form for <quote>bluescreen</quote> og dessutan støtte
                      for lyd.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <!--  FIXME: cs content missing -->
                    <para lang="cs">FIXME</para>
                    <para lang="en">
                      A channel mixer filter, previously available from the
                      web as an add-on, appears in
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Colors</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="de">
                      Der Kanalmixer, zuvor als Erweiterung verfügbar, ist
                      jetzt im Menü
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Farben</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>
                      zu finden.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="fr">
                      Un mixeur de canaux est apparu dans
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Couleurs</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="it">
                      Un filtro mescolatore di canali, un tempo disponibile
                      solo via web, ora lo si trova in
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Filtri</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Colori</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="nl">
                      Een kanalen mengfilter, voorheen alleen als een extra
                      toevoeging beschikbaar vanaf het web is nu beschikbaar
                      via
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Kleuren</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="no">
                      Eit filter for kanalmiksing er lagt til og tilgjengeleg
                      frå
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Fargar</guimenuitem>
                        <guimenuitem>Kanalmiksar</guimenuitem>
                      </menuchoice>
                      i biletmenyen.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
