<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-04-12 j.h: update to v-2.10
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-select">
  <title>Common Features</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selections</primary>
    <secondary>Common Features</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Selection tools are designed to select regions from the active layer so
    you can work on them without affecting the unselected areas. Each tool has
    its own individual properties, but the selection tools also share a number
    of options and features in common. These common features are described
    here; the variations are explained in the following sections for each tool
    specifically. If you need help with what a <quote>selection</quote>
    is in GIMP, and how it works, see
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Selection</link>.
  </para>
  <para>This category includes the following tools:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the <link linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select">Rectangle Select</link>;
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the <link linkend="gimp-tool-ellipse-select">Ellipse Select</link>;
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-free-select">Free Select (the Lasso)</link>;
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-foreground-select">Foreground Select</link>;
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the <link linkend="gimp-tool-fuzzy-select">
        Fuzzy Select (Select Contiguous Regions)</link>;
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the <link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">By Color Select</link> and
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        the <link linkend="gimp-tool-iscissors">
        Scissors Select (Select Shapes from Image)</link>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    In some ways the Path tool can also be thought of as a selection tool: any
    closed path can be converted into a selection. It also can do a great deal
    more, though, and does not share the same set of options with the other
    selection tools.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gimp-tools-select-modifiers">
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <para>
      The behavior of selection tools is modified if you hold down the
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>, and/or
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> keys while you use them.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Advanced users find the modifier keys very valuable, but novice users
        often find them confusing. Fortunately, it is possible for most
        purposes to use the Mode buttons (described below) instead of modifier
        keys.
      </para>
    </note>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When creating a selection, holding down the
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key can have two different actions
            according to the way you use it:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Holding down the key <emphasis>while drawing</emphasis>
                the selection toggles the <quote>Expand from center</quote>
                option.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you hold down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key
                <emphasis>before drawing a selection</emphasis>, this new
                selection switches to the Subtract mode. So, this new
                selection will be subtracted from an existing one as soon as
                you release the click, as far as they have common pixels.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Holding <keycap>Alt</keycap> will allow movement of the
            current selection (only its frame, not its content). If the
            whole image is moved instead of the selection only, try
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>.
            Note that the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is sometimes intercepted by
            the windowing system (meaning that GIMP never knows that it was
            pressed), so this may not work for everybody.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When creating a selection, holding down the
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> key can have two different actions
            according to the way you use it:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you hold down the key <emphasis>before
                clicking</emphasis> to start the selection, this
                selection will be in <emphasis>Addition</emphasis>
                mode as long as you press the key.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key
                <emphasis>after clicking</emphasis> to start the selection,
                the effect will depend on the tool you are using: for
                example, the selection will be a square with the
                Rectangle Select tool.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Using
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            together can do a variety of things, depending on which tool is
            used. Common to all selection tools is that the selection mode
            will be switched to intersection, so that after the operation is
            finished, the selection will consist of the intersection of the
            region traced out with the pre-existing selection. It is an
            exercise for the reader to play with the various combinations
            available when performing selections while holding
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            and releasing either both or either prior to releasing the mouse 
            <mousebutton>Left&nbsp;Button</mousebutton>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Key modifiers to move selections</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <mousebutton>Left-click-and-drag</mousebutton>
            </keycombo> and
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
              <mousebutton>Left-click-and-drag</mousebutton>
            </keycombo>
            are used to move selections.
            See <xref linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Space bar</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Pressing the <keycap>Space</keycap> bar while using a selection
            tool transforms this tool into the Navigation cross as long as
            you press the bar, allowing you to pan around the image instead
            of using the scroll-bars when your image is bigger than the
            canvas. This is the default option: in the
            <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window">Image Windows preferences</link>
            you can toggle the Space bar to the Move tool.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-tool-select-options">
    <title>Options</title>
    <para>
      Here we describe the tool options that apply to all selection tools:
      options that apply only to some tools, or that affect each tool
      differently, are described in the sections devoted to the individual
      tools. The current settings for these options can be seen in the Tool
      Options dialog, which you should always have visible when you are using
      tools. To make
      the interface consistent, the same options are presented for all
      selection tools, even though some of them don't have any effect for some
      of the tools.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Selection</primary>
            <secondary>Modes</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            This determines the way that the selection you create is combined
            with any pre-existing selection. Note that the functions performed
            by these buttons can be duplicated using modifier keys, as
            described above. For the most part, advanced users use the
            modifier keys; novice users find the mode buttons easier.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
               <guiicon>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                      fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection-replace.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
               </guiicon>
               <phrase>Replace</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Replace mode will cause any existing selection to be
                  destroyed or replaced when the new selection is created.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
               <guiicon>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                      fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection-add.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
               </guiicon>
               <phrase>Add</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Add mode will cause the new selection to be added to any
                  existing selection regions.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
               <guiicon>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                      fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection-subtract.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
               </guiicon>
               <phrase>Subtract</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Subtract mode will remove the new selection area from any
                  existing selection regions.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>
               <guiicon>
                <inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                      fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection-intersect.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject>
               </guiicon>
               <phrase>Intersect</phrase>
              </term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Intersection mode will make a new selection from the area
                  where the existing selection region and the new selection
                  region overlap.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Antialiasing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option only affects some selection tools: it causes
            the boundary of the selection to be drawn more smoothly.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Feather Edges</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Edge feathering (Selections)</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            This options allows the boundary of the selection to be blurred,
            so that points near the boundary are only partially selected. For
            further information regarding feathering, see the glossary entry
            <link linkend="glossary-feathering">Feathering</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            When this option is checked, a <guilabel>Radius</guilabel> option 
            appears. Default value is 10 pixels: higher image resolution, 
            higher radius.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
