<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-04-12 j.h: update to v-2.10
     -->
<sect2 
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-foreground-select">
  <title>Foreground Select</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Foreground Select</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selection</primary>
    <secondary>Foreground Select</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Foreground Select</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    This tool lets you extract the foreground from the active layer or from a
    selection. After the selection is made, with its
    <link linkend="glossary-marching-ants">marching ants</link>, you can
    copy-paste or click-and-drag it to another image used as background, and,
    inverting the selection, you can make changes in background.
  </para>

  
  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Foreground Select</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-foreground-select.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This tool has no shortcut, but you can set one using
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Keyboard Shortcuts</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>, open the <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> group on the left,
          select <guilabel>Foreground Select</guilabel> and then press the
          keys you want to use as shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

   <sect3 id="tool-fg-select-usage">
    <title>Directions for use</title>
    <para>
      Let us start with an object that is easy to distinguish from the
      background and doesn't need to be refined.
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>
        The foreground select tool needs a lot of memory for its processing,
        depending on the size of the image. It is known to crash or slow down
        when using larger images.
      </para>
      <para>
        One way to improve this is to use <guilabel>Matting Global</guilabel>
        instead of <guilabel>Matting Levin</guilabel>. The slow processing
        speed can be improved by increasing the number of downsampled
        <guilabel>Levels</guilabel>, at the cost of using more memory. Both of
        these options also come with the disadvantage of being less accurate.
      </para>
    </warning>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          The way it works is similar to the
          <link linkend="gimp-tool-free-select">Free Select tool</link>.
          Roughly select the object you want to extract, with a little bit of
          background around it.
          To get a more accurate outline, keep the mouse button pressed while
          moving. To use straight lines for parts of your selection, click
          and release the button between the start and end points of the
          straight section.
        </para>
        <para>
          As soon you click to start drawing the selection, a small window pops
          up:
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-pop-up.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Before the selection is finished, only the button to close the dialog
          is active, allowing you to cancel and return to the original image
          (this can also be done by pressing the <keycap>Esc</keycap> key).
        </para>
        <para>
          To finish the initial selection, it needs to be closed. When the mouse
          cursor hovers over the dot where you started the selection, it turns
          yellow. Click this to close the selection. Instead of doing that,
          you can also double-click to close the selection.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-select.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              The selection is closed.
            </para>
          </caption>
         </mediaobject>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To create the mask from your selection, press <keycap>Enter</keycap>,
          or double-click inside the selection:
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-mask.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>
          The mouse pointer now changes into a Paintbrush icon with a circle.
          The dark blue area (this color can be changed) shows the background.
          The lighter area covers the zone you have selected as foreground and
          a small part of background.
          Outside the selected area, the dark blue area is called the
          <quote>Unknown pixels area</quote>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The options in the small window on top of the image become active:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A <guilabel>Preview mask</guilabel> checkbox that toggles
                displaying a preview of the foreground extraction status.
                The same can also be done by pressing the
                <keycap>Enter</keycap> key.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button that will be used to 
                create the extraction after marking the foreground.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Now we start the actual foreground extraction process: draw a line
          through the foreground. The size of the brush can be changed in the
          Tool Options area. Draw a continuous line over the selected foreground
          area moving over colors which will be kept for the extraction. The
          color used to draw the line is not important, but not using the same
          color as the foreground makes it easier to see. Be careful not to
          paint background pixels.
        </para>
        <para>
          With this one-color object, that is easy to distinguish from the
          background, a few strokes are enough:
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-draw.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Toggle the preview</emphasis> button, or press
          <keycap>Enter</keycap> to verify the result.
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-result.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            You can draw directly on this <guilabel>Preview mask</guilabel> and
            see the result immediately.
          </para>
        </note>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          When you are satisfied with the result, click the
          <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button, or press <keycap>Enter</keycap>
          to finalize the selection and finish the foreground selection
          operation. You can cancel the operation by pressing
          <keycap>Esc</keycap>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect3>
          
  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-foreground-select.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="../about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode</term>
        <term>Feather edges</term>
        <listitem>
          <xi:include href="about-common-select-options.xml"/>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Draw mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Draw foreground</guilabel>: when selecting with a brush,
            what you draw will be considered part of the foreground, i.e.
            included in the selection.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Draw background</guilabel>: when selecting with a brush,
            what you draw will be considered part of the background, i.e. it
            will be excluded from the selection.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Draw unknown</guilabel>: When drawing on the background,
            outside the initial selection, it marks the drawn pixels as
            belonging to the foreground.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stroke width</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           The size of the brush to select with.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Preview mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Color</guilabel> (default): the color of the selection
                preview mask; the current color is shown in the color swatch.
                You can change the color by clicking on it.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Grayscale</guilabel>: allows you to see the resulting
                mask in black and white. This preview is similar to a layer
                mask. It can be useful in images where foreground and background
                color are similar and difficult to distinguish.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry> 
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Engine</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the method that will be used to select the foreground.
            The default is <guilabel>Matting Levin</guilabel>, which usually
            gives the best results, but you can also try
            <guilabel>Matting global</guilabel>, especially if processing is
            slow and you are using larger images.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Levels (Matting Levin only)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The number of downsampled levels to use. Higher numbers can
            improve processing speed at the cost of using more memory.
            The default is 2 levels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Active levels (Matting Levin only)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The number of levels to perform solving. Higher numbers can increase
            the selection a bit at the cost of slowing down processing. Setting
            this number higher than <guilabel>Levels</guilabel> has no effect.
            The default is 2 active levels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Iterations (Matting Global only)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Higher values may improve the result at the cost of being slower.
            The default is 2 iterations.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Refining Foreground Extraction</title>
    <para>
      In a lot of images, distinguishing what is foreground or background can be
      difficult. Refining the selection allows you to extract these foregrounds.
      The procedure steps are the same as above, but, while drawing the
      foreground, you will often toggle Preview, use Zoom (<keycap>+</keycap>
      key), switch to <guilabel>Draw background</guilabel> to delete unwanted
      background areas, and switch between <guilabel>Grayscale</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Color</guilabel> preview mode.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Draw background</quote> Example</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-draw-bg.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            On the left: drawing foreground by mistake went over the background
            area: a part of the background will be included in the foreground
            selection!
          </para>
          <para>
            In the middle: <guilabel>Draw background</guilabel> option is
            checked: draw on the unwanted background pixels.
          </para>
          <para>
            On the right: unwanted selected pixels in the background are no
            longer in the foreground selection.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Draw unknown</quote> Example</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/FG-select-unknown.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            On the left: the selection left a small part of the foreground
            unselected, in the unknown pixels area.
          </para>
          <para>
            On the right: with <guilabel>Draw unknown</guilabel> option
            checked, draw on the unselected pixels to select them. This shows
            that they are now selected.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
