<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2015-12-27 j.h rewrite auto-shrink 
  2008-03-19 JPL rewiewed & modified en
  2006-06-12 changed Ctrl+Shift section by j.h
  2005-12-06 replaced simplesect by sect3 by lexa
  2005-12-06 replaced informalfigure by figure by lexa
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-rect-select">
  <title>Rectangle Selection</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Rectangle Selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selection</primary>
    <secondary>Rectangle selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The Rectangle Selection tool is designed to select rectangular regions of
    the active layer: it is the most basic of the selection tools, but very
    commonly used. For information on selections and how they are used in GIMP
    see <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Selections</link>;
    for information on features common to all selection tools see
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Selection Tools</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    This tool is also used for rendering a rectangle on an image. To render a
    filled rectangle, create a rectangular selection, and then fill it using
    the <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket Fill tool</link>.
    To create a rectangular outline, the simplest and most flexible approach
    is to create a rectangular selection and then
    <link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">stroke</link> it.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Rectangle Select</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-rect-select.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the <keycap>R</keycap> keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <xi:include href="about-common-select-modifiers.xml"/>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Pressing the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key after starting
            your selection, and holding it down until you are finished,
            causes your starting point to be used as the center of the
            selected rectangle, instead of a corner.  Note that if you
            press the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key <emphasis>before</emphasis>
            starting to make the selection, the resulting selection will be
            subtracted from the existing selection. The cursor becomes
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-modifier-minus.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you press the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key
            <emphasis>before</emphasis> starting the selection, the
            resulting selection will be added to the existing one. The cursor
            becomes
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-modifier-plus.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
          <para>
            Pressing the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key <emphasis>after
            </emphasis> starting your selection, toggles the <guilabel>Fixed
            </guilabel> option, and holding it down until you are finished,
            will constrain the selection to a square, if it is your first
            selection. Later, with the default <guilabel>Aspect Ratio
            </guilabel>, your selection will respect the aspect ratio of the
            previous selection.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Pressing both keys after starting your selection
            combines the two effects, giving you a square selection centered
            on your starting point. Note that pressing these keys before
            starting your selection intersects the resulting selection with
            the existing one and the pointer change shape accordingly:
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-modifier-intersect.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="tool-rect-select-manip">
    <title>Tool manipulation</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example of Rectangle Selection.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/rectangle-selection.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      When this tool is selected the mouse pointer is displayed like this:
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-mode-tool-crosshair.png"/>
           </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      as soon as it is over the image. A drag and drop allows to get a
      rectangular (or square) shape. When the mouse button is relaxed, a
      dotted line
      (<link linkend="glossary-marching-ants"><quote>marching ants</quote></link>)
      outlines the selection. It's not necessary to adjust the selection with
      care; you can resize it easily later.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the pointer is moving on the canvas, the pointer and selection
      aspects change:
    </para>
    <para>
      - outside the selection it looks like previously; this allows to design
      a new selection but will erase the existing one if this isn't combined
      with an action on the relevant key to add or subtract another selection
      as described in the previous paragraph.
    </para>
    <para>
      - within selection peripheral parts, the mouse pointer changes into
      various shapes when overflying rectangular sensitive and clearly marked
      areas. These <emphasis>handles</emphasis> allow you to resize the
      selection. In selection corners the pointer changes into a shape
      according to the context; for instance in the low right corner it
      becomes:
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-corner-bottom-right.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
      So, by click-and-dragging these areas, you can magnify or shrink the
      selection size. Over median selection parts, lateral, low or up,
      pointer is changed into appropriate shapes according to the context.
      For instance, when the mouse pointer is over the median right side, the
      pointer looks like:
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-side-right.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
      So you can click-and-drag to magnify or to shrink the selection size by
      moving the chosen boundary.
    </para>
    <para>
      - inside selection central area the mouse pointer looks like usual for
      object manipulation, i.e.:
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-rect-select-modifier-move.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
      So you can move the whole selection by a click-and-drag.
    </para>
    <para>
      Moreover, if you have not unchecked the <guilabel>Highlight</guilabel>
      option, your work will be easier because what is out the selection will be
      darkest than what is in the selection, and then the selection seems
      highlighted.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        If you use moving keys you can move the selection or modify its size
        by one pixel step. If you use it in combination with
        <keycap>Shift</keycap> you can move it by a 25 pixel step.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <figure>
      <title>Sensitive selection areas</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/select-area.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
          Display of all possible pointers in function of their localization
          with respect to the selection area.
        </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      After creating and modifying the selection, you will have to exit this
      editing mode (and commit any changes). You can do this with a single
      click inside the selection or by pressing the <keycap>Enter</keycap>
      key. Or you can just use a non-selection tool and, for example, fill or
      paint the selection.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="tool-rect-select-options">
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-rectangle-select.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="../about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode</term>
        <term>Antialiasing</term>
        <term>Feather edges</term>
        <listitem>
          <xi:include href="about-common-select-options.xml"/>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rounded corners</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you enable this option, a slider appears. You can use this to
            adjust the radius that is used to round the corners of the
            selection.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Expand from center</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you enable this option, the point the selection is started by
            pressing the mouse button is used as center of the selected area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fixed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This menu allows you the option of constraining the shape of
            the rectangle in different ways.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Aspect ratio</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This option allows you to design and resize the selection
                  while keeping the aspect ratio fixed and written within the
                  relevant box. By default the ratio is 1:1 (so we have a
                  square) but it can be changed. With the two little landscape
                  and picture icons, you can invert this ratio.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Width</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  With this choice you can fix the width of the selection.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Height</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  With this choice you can fix the height of the selection.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Size</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  With this choice you can fix the width and height of the
                  selection.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Position</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These two text fields contain the current horizontal and vertical
            coordinates of the upper left corner of the selection. You can use
            these fields to adjust the selection position precisely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These two text fields contain the current width and height of
            the selection. You can use these fields to adjust the selection
            size precisely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Highlight</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you enable this option, the selected area is emphasized by a
            surrounding mask to make visual selection much easier.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="composition-guides">
        <term>Guides</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Guides</primary>
            <secondary>Selection guides</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Composition guides</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            With this menu you can select the type of guides that is shown
            within the selection to make the creation of a selection easier,
            respecting <emphasis>Photo composition rules</emphasis>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Six options are available:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>No Guides</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Center lines</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Rule of thirds</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Rule of fifths</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Golden sections</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Diagonal lines</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Auto Shrink</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option is active when a rectangle selection is drawn.
            Clicking on the <guibutton>Auto Shrink Selection</guibutton> 
            button will make the selection automatically shrink to the 
            nearest rectangular shape including elements in the selection. 
            The algorithm for finding the best rectangle to shrink to is
            <quote>intelligent</quote>, which in this case means that it
            sometimes does surprisingly sophisticated things, and sometimes
            does surprisingly strange things. In any case, if the region
            that you want to select has a solid-colored surround,
            auto-shrinking will always pick it out correctly. Note that
            the resulting selection does not need to have the
            same shape as the one you sweep out.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Auto Shrink example</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/autoshrink-1.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Image with two distinct elements selected
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/autoshrink-2.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Auto Shrink applied
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>             
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shrink merged</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If <guilabel>Sample Merged</guilabel>
            is also enabled, then Auto Shrink will use the pixel information
            from the visible display of the image, rather than just from the
            active layer.
          </para>
          <para>
            For more information, see the
            <link linkend="glossary-samplemerge">Glossary entry</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
