<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--section history:
  2018-09-18 j.h Created
-->

<sect2 id="gimp-filter-shadows-highlights">
  <title>Shadows-Highlights</title>
  
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Colors</primary>
    <secondary>Shadows and Highlights</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Shadows and Highlights</primary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <para>
    This filter allows adjusting shadows and highlights in the image 
    separately. The implementation closely follow its counterpart in the 
    Darktable photography software 
<ulink url="https://docs.darktable.org/usermanual/development/en/module-reference/processing-modules/shadows-and-highlights/">Shadows and Highlights</ulink>.
  </para>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <para>
      You can access this command from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Shadows-Highlights…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Shadows-Highlights Options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata 
fileref="images/menus/colors/shadows-highlights-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Presets</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <quote>Presets</quote> are a common feature for
            several Colors commands. You can find its description in
            <xref linkend="colors-common-features"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <!--This description closely follows the Darktable manual-->
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Three options groups:</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role= "bold">Shadows</emphasis>: options for shadows:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Shadows</guilabel>: This slider controls the effect on 
                shadows; positive values lighten shadows while negative 
                values darken them.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Shadows color adjustment</guilabel>: This slider 
                controls the color saturation adjustment made to shadows; high 
                values cause saturation enhancements on lightened shadows; low 
                values cause desaturation on lightened shadows. It is normally 
                safe to leave this at its default of 100%. This gives a natural 
                saturation boost on shadows&mdash;similar to the one you would also 
                expect in nature if shadows received more light.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          
          <para>
            <emphasis role= "bold">Highlights</emphasis>: options for 
            highlights:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Highlights</guilabel>: This slider controls the effect 
                on highlights; negative values darken highlights while 
                positive values lighten them. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Highlights color adjustment</guilabel>: This slider 
                controls the color saturation adjustment made to highlights; 
                high values cause saturation enhancements on darkened 
                highlights; low values cause desaturation on darkened 
                highlights. Often highlights do not contain enough color 
                information to give convincing colors when darkened. You might 
                need to play a bit with this parameter in order to find the best 
                fitting value depending on your specific image; but be aware 
                that sometimes results still might not be fully satisfying.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>
            <emphasis role= "bold">Common</emphasis>: options common to shadows 
            and highlights:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>White point adjustment</guilabel>: By default the
                algorithm of this module leaves black point and white point
                untouched. In some cases an image might contain tonal
                variations beyond the white point, i.e. above a luminance value
                of 100. A negative shift in the white point adjustment slider
                allows to bring these values down into the proper range so that
                further details in the highlights get visible.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Radius</guilabel>: This slider controls the radius of 
                the involved blurring filter. Higher values give softer 
                transitions between shadows and highlights but might introduce 
                halos. Lower values reduce the size of halos but may lead 
                to an artificial look. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Compress</guilabel>: This slider controls how strong 
                the effect extends to mid-tones; high values reduce the effect 
                to the extreme shadows and highlights; low values cause strong 
                adjustments also to mid-tones. You normally only need to touch 
                this parameter if you want to limit the effects to the extreme 
                shadows and highlights; increase the value in this case. At 100% 
                this module has no visible effect any longer as only absolute 
                black and absolute white are affected.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Blending Options</term>
        <term>Preview</term>
        <term>Merge filter</term>
        <term>Split view</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These are common features described in
            <xref linkend="colors-common-features"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
