<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-11-14 AntI: Added "es"
  2007-05-18 KoSt: added 'no'
  2007-05-10 lexa: added warning: the filter does not work for large images
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-09-19 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-flame">
  <title>Flame</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Render</secondary>
    <tertiary>Flame</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Flame</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example of a rendered Flame</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/flame1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/render-taj-flame.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>Flame</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      With the Flame filter, you can create stunning, randomly
      generated fractal patterns. You can't control the fractals as
      you can with the <link linkend="plug-in-ifsfractal">Ifs
      Compose</link> filter, but you can steer the
      random generator in a certain direction, and choose from
      variations of a theme you like.
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>
        Unfortunately it turned out, that this filter is not working properly
        for large images. Even more unfortunate is, that its developer is
        currently not undertaking any actions with that plug-in at all, so
        there seems no quick fix in sight. Although we can give you the exact
        numbers, the plug-in worked in a quick test for a 1024x768 pixel
        image, but didn't do it for a 2500x2500 pixel image.
      </para>
    </warning>
    <note>
      <para>
        This plug-in was given to GIMP by Scott Draves in 1997. He also holds
        the copyright for the plug-in. An descriptive page for the plug-in,
        provided by the author can be found in the internet
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-flames"/>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the filter</title>
    <para>
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Render</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Nature</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Flame</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Flame</quote> filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/filters-render-flame.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      In the main window, you can set Rendering and Camera
      parameters. The first three parameters in the Render display are
      Brightness, Contrast and Gamma. The result of these options is
      visible in the Preview window, but it's generally better to
      stick to the default values, and correct the rendered image
      later with Image/Colors.
    </para>
    <para>
      The other three parameters affect the rendering process and
      don't show in the preview window. Sample Density, which controls
      the resolution of the rendered pattern, is the most important of
      these. The Camera parameters allow
      you to zoom and offset the flame pattern, until you're happy
      with what you see in the preview window. Flame also offers the
      possibility to store and load your favorite patterns.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edit</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title>The Edit Flame dialog</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/filters/filters-render-flame-edit.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            Pressing this button brings up the Edit dialog.  The
            dialog shows nine different windows. The pattern displayed
            in the center is the current pattern, and the eight
            windows surrounding it are random variations of that
            pattern.  Clicking on the central image creates eight new
            variations, which can be adjusted with the Speed
            control. You select a variation by clicking on it, and it
            instantly replaces the image in the middle. To pick a
            certain character or theme for the variations, you can
            choose from nine different themes in the Variations
            menu. You can also use Randomize, which replaces the
            current pattern with a new random pattern.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Open</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This button brings up a file selector that allows you to
            open a previously saved Flame settings file.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This button brings up a file save dialog that allows you
            to save the current settings for the plug-in, so that you
            can recreate them later.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rendering tab</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Brightness</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Controls the brightness of the flame object.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Contrast</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Controls the contrast between brighter and dimmer parts of
                  the flame.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Gamma</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Sets a gamma correction for parts with intermediate
                  brightness.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Sample Density</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Controls the resolution of the rendered pattern.  (Does
                  not have any effect on the preview.)  A high sample
                  density results in soft and smooth
                  rendering (like a spider's web), whereas low density
                  rendering resembles spray or particle clouds.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Spatial Oversample</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  What does this do?
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Spatial Filter Radius</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  What does this do?
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Colormap</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This menu gives you several options to set the color blend
                  in the flame pattern:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      The current gradient as shown in the Toolbox.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      A number of preset colormaps.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      The colors from images that are presently open in
                      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Camera tab</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Zoom</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Allows you to zoom the flame in or out.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>X, Y</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Allows you to move the flame around in the image area.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
