<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-grid' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Grid</title>
  <title lang="cs">Mřížka</title>
  <title lang="fr">Grille</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">网格</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Render</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Grid</tertiary>

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Vykreslení</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">Mřížka</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Rendu</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Grille</tertiary>

    <primary lang="zh_CN">滤镜</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">绘制</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="zh_CN">网格</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject lang="en">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-render-grid.png' format='PNG'/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject lang="cs">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-render-grid.png' format='PNG'/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject lang="de">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-render-grid.png' format='PNG'/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject lang="fr">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-render-grid.png' format='PNG'/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/zh_CN/filters-render-grid.png' format='PNG'/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="de">Allgemeines</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>

    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Render</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Pattern</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>rid</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Vykreslení</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Vzorek</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Mřížka</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Rendu</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Motif</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>rille...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该滤镜在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;滤镜/绘制/图案/网格</guimenuitem>。
    </para>

    <para lang="en"><!-- updated 2005/06/20 - default color -->
      It renders a Cartesian grid in the active layer, on top of the existing
      contents. The width, spacing, offsets, and colors of the grid lines can
      all be set by the user. By default, the lines are with the Gimp's
      foreground color. (Note: this plugin was used to create demonstration
      images for many of the other plugins.)
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr vykreslí v aktivní vrstvě, přes její existující obsah,
      pravoúhlou mřížku. Rozestupy mezi čarami, jejich tloušťka, barva
      a posun vůči levému hornímu rohu obrázku lze nastavit podle libosti.
      Jako výchozí používá barvu popředí Gimpu. (Tento filtr byl použit k
      vytvoření mnoha ukázkových obrázků použitých pro ostatní zásuvné moduly
      v této příručce.)
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre crée une grille cartésienne dans le calque actif par dessus
      le contenu existant. La largeur, l'espacement, les décalages et les
      couleurs des lignes de grille sont réglables par l'utilisateur. Par
      défaut les lignes utilisent la couleur de premier plan (ce filtre était
      utilisé pour créer des images de démonstration pour d'autres filtres).
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      它在活动图层上绘制笛卡尔网格。用户可以设置网格线的宽度，间距，位移和颜色。线默认是深蓝色的。(注意：该滤镜用作生成其它滤镜使用的范例图像。)
    </para>

    <tip lang="en">
      <para>
        If you set the grid line widths to 0, then only the intersections
        will be drawn, as plus-marks.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <tip lang="cs">
      <para>
        Pokud se tloušťka čar nastaví na nulu, budou vykresleny pouze
        jejich průniky v podobě křížků. <!-- FIXME CS nutno rozvést-->
      </para>
    </tip>
    <tip lang="fr">
      <para>
        Si vous réglez la largeur des lignes à 0, alors seules les
        intersections seront tracées, avec des +.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <tip lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        当网格线宽度为 0 时，就只会勾出交叉点，其为加号符号。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <para lang="en">
      There are separate options for controlling the horizontal grid
      lines, vertical grid lines, and intersections.  By default, the
      horizontal and vertical settings are locked together, so that
      all changes are applied symmetrically.  If you want to change
      just one of them, click on the "chain" symbol below it to unlock
      them.  The results of changing the "intersection" parameters are
      rather complex.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr poskytuje možnost nezávislého nastavení vodorovných a svislých čar
      mřížky a jejich průniků. Implicitně je nastavení vodorovných a svislých
      čar svázáno, takže změna jednoho ovlivní i druhé. Toto provázání lze
      vypnout kliknutím na ikonu řetězu a jejím rozpojením. Nastavení průniků
      je poměrně složité.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il y a des options séparées pour contrôler les lignes verticales,
      horizontales et les intersections. Par défaut, les réglages
      horizontaux et verticaux sont communs. Si vous souhaitez
      changer seulement l'un des deux cliquez sur l'icone en forme de
      chaîne pour les rendre indépendants. Les résultats des paramètres
      d'intersection sont par contre plus complexes.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      其中有控制水平网格线，垂直网格线和交叉点的单独选项。水平和垂直设置默认是锁在一起的，因此所有的变化都是同步的。如果要单独改变其中一个，需要点击下面的“锁链”标志将它们解锁。改变“虚线”的参数则相对要复些。
    </para>
    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Width</term>
        <term lang="cs">Šířka</term>
        <term lang="fr">Largeur</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">宽度</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Sets the widths of the horizontal or vertical grid
            lines, or of the symbols drawn at their intersections. 
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Nastavuje tloušťku čar. ať už vodorovných, svislých, nebo
            čar tvořících křížky označující průniky.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Règle l'épaisseur des lignes horizontales et verticales
            ou des symboles d'intersection.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            设置水平网格线，垂直网格线和交叉点标志的宽度。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Spacing</term>
        <term lang="cs">Rozestup</term>
        <term lang="fr">Espacement</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">间距</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Sets the distance between grid lines.  For intersections,
            sets the distance from the intersection point for the
            starting points of the line segments that are drawn.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Nastavuje vzdálenost mezi sousedními čarami. V případě průniků
            nasatvuje vzdálenost od skutečného místa průniku k počátkům
            vykreslených čar.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Règle la distance entre les lignes. Pour les intersections,
            règle la distance entre l'intersection réelle et les
            départs des segments tracés.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            设置网格线间的距离。对于虚线，则是设置交叉点到虚线中线段起始点的距离。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Offset</term>
        <term lang="cs">Posun</term>
        <term lang="fr">Décalage</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">位移</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Sets the offset for grid lines with respect to the upper left
            corner. For intersections, sets the distance from the intersection
            point to the ending points of the line segments that are drawn.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Učuje posun čar mřížky vzhledem k levému hornímu rohu obrázku.
            V případě průniků určuje vzdálenost od skutečného místa průniku po
            konec vykreslených čar.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Règle le décalage des lignes par rapport au coin haut gauche.
            Pour les intersections, règle la distance entre l'intersection
            réelle et les extrémités des segments tracés.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            设置网格线相对于左上角的位移。对于虚线，则是设置交叉点到虚线中线段结束点的距离。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Color Selectors</term>
        <term lang="cs">Voliče barev</term>
        <term lang="fr">Sélecteurs de couleurs</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">颜色选择器</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            These allow you to set the colors of the grid lines and
            intersection marks.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tři voliče barev v dolní části dialogu umožňují zvolit barvy
            vodorovných a svislých čar a jejich průniků.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ceci permet de régler les couleurs affectées aux lignes de
            la grille et aux symboles d'intersection.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            它设置网格线和交叉虚线的颜色。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
