<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='filters-render-introduction' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Render filters introduction</title>
  <title lang="cs">Úvod od filtrů vykreslení</title>
  <title lang="fr">Introduction aux filtres de rendu</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">绘制滤镜简介</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Render</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Introduction</tertiary>   

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">vykreslení</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">úvod</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Rendu</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Introduction</tertiary>

    <primary lang="zh_CN">滤镜</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">绘制</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="zh_CN">简介</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <para lang="en">
    Most Gimp filters act on a layer by transforming its contents, but
    the filters in the "Render" group are a bit different.  They
    create patterns from scratch, in most cases obliterating anything
    that was previously in the layer.  Some create random or noisy
    patterns, others regular of fractal patterns, and one (Gfig) is a
    general-purpose (but rather limited) vector graphics tool.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Většina gimpích filtrů peřměňuje obsah vrstvy, ale filtry kategorie
    „Vykreslení“ se tomuto pravidlu poněkud vymykají. Vytvářejí totiž
    obrazce a textury zcela od základu a většinou zcela překryjí původní obsah
    vrstvy. Některé tvoří náhodné či zašuměné vzorky, jiné pravidelné či
    fraktální vzory a jeden z nich (Gfig) je univerzální (byť značně omezený)
    vektorový grafický nástroj.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La plupart des filtres Gimp agissent sur un calque en modifiant son 
    contenu mais les filtres de la catégorie «Rendu» sont un peu différents.
    Ils créent des motifs et dessins en partant de zéro, la plupart du
    temps en écrasant ce qui se trouvait précédemment dans le calque.
    Certains créent des dessins aléatoires et bruités, d'autres des motifs
    jointifs, et un dernier GFig est un outil vectoriel général (mais 
    limité). 
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    大部分 GIMP 中的滤镜都是通过变换图层内容来对图层进行操作，绘制滤镜则有些不同。在大多数情况下，它们会移除图层中哦功能原来的内容，然后重新产生图案。有些产生随机或噪音的图案，有些则是普通或分形的图案，还有一个 (Gfig) 可以作为一般用途(比较有限)的矢量图形工具。
  </para> 
</sect2>
