<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="script-fu-line-nova">
  <title>Line Nova</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Render</secondary>
    <tertiary>Line Nova</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Line Nova</primary></indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <figure>
      <title>Example for the <quote>Line Nova</quote> filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/render/taj-line-nova.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para><quote>Line Nova</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      <guimenuitem>Line Nova</guimenuitem> command is a script which fills
      a layer with rays emanating outward from its center using the foreground
      color shown in the Toolbox.  All lines radiates from the near center of
      the layer, and get broader to join both neighboring lines into outer
      solid field filled with the foreground color.  Rendered lines are
      cropped on the every edge of the image to be fit inside of it.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        This filter does not provide any option which allow you to set the
        center point of lines.  If you need adjust the place of the radial
        lines where you want, create another transparent image and apply this
        filter on it, then add it on your image.  Setting large size for the
        new nova image may help you not to break lines inside of your image.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the image window menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Render</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Line Nova</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Line Nova</quote> options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/render/line-nova.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Number of lines</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By using this slider you can set the number of lines between 40
            to 1000. The default is 200.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sharpness (degrees)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Every transparent chink between lines is tapering off toward the
            outer direction.  To see the base image more wider, set this
            degree more shorter so that the chick spaces stretch longer.
            Allowed range is between 0.0 and 10.0, but note that 0.0 makes
            nothing drawn.  The default is 1.0.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Offset radius</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Almost lines don't reach the center point if this value is set
            over 0.  By this option, you can set radius (between 0 to 2000
            pixels) of the transparent space around the center point. The
            default value is 100 pixels.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Randomness</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Set this value more larger (up to 2000) to get more distoted
            radiation.  Regular star shape is given by setting this value
            to 1.  The default is 30.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
