<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-05-15 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-12-08 <simplesect> replaced by <sect3> by lexa
  2005/09/21 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-solid-noise">
  <title>Solid Noise</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Render</secondary>
    <tertiary>Solid Noise</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Solid noise</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example of turbulent solid noise</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/render-taj-solidnoise.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>Solid noise</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Solid Noise is a great texture maker. Note that this noise is
      always gray, even if you applied it to a very colorful image (it
      doesn't matter what the original image looks like -- this filter
      completely overwrites any existing background in the layer it is
      applied to). This is also a good tool to create displacement maps for
      the <link linkend="plug-in-warp">Warp</link> plug-in or for the
      <link linkend="plug-in-bump-map">Bump Map</link> plug-in. With the
      "turbulence" setting active, the results look quite a bit like real
      clouds.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the image window menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Render</guisubmenu>
        <guisubmenu>Clouds</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Solid noise</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Solid Noise</quote> filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/solid-noise-options.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Random Seed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Random Seed</guilabel> controls random behaviour of the
            filter. If the same random seed in the same situation is used, the
            filter produces exactly the same results. A different random seed
            produces different results. Random seed can be entered manually or
            generated randomly by pressing <guibutton>New Seed</guibutton>
            button.
          </para>
          <para>
            When the <guilabel>Randomize</guilabel> option is checked, random
            seed cannot be entered manually, but is randomly generated each
            time the filter is run. If it is not checked, the filter remembers
            the last random seed used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Turbulent</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you check this, you'll get very interesting effects,
            often something that looks much like oil on water, or
            clouds of smoke, or living tissue, or a Rorschach blot.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Detail</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This controls the amount of detail in the noise
            texture. Higher values give a higher level of detail, and
            the noise seems to be made of spray or small particles,
            which makes it feel hard. A low value makes it more soft
            and cloudy.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Tileable</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you check Tileable, you'll get a noise which can be
            used as tiles. For example, you can use it as a background
            in an HTML page, and the tile edges will be joined
            seamlessly.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>X and Y Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These control the size and proportion of the noise shapes
            in X (horizontal) and Y (vertical) directions (range 0.1
            to 16.0).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
