<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-concepts-brushes' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Stopy</title>
  <title lang="en">Brushes</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">画笔</title>
  <title lang="fr">Brosses</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">Stopy</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Brushes</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">画笔</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Brosses</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/brush-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
           Řada příkladů tahů vytvořených různými stopami z kolekce stop
           dodáváné spolu s Gimpem. Všechny byly namalovány pomocí nástroje
           Štětec.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
           A number of examples of brushstrokes painted using different
           brushes from the set supplied with GIMP.  All were painted
           using the Paintbrush tool.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
           下面是一些使用 GIMP 提供的一系列不同画笔所产生的笔划的范例。全都是使用画笔工具来进行涂画的。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
           Plusieurs exemples de tracés peints avec différentes brosses 
           provenant du lot fourni avec GIMP. Ils ont tous été peints avec 
           l'outil Pinceau.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='cs'>
    <emphasis>Stopa</emphasis> je bitová mapa nebo sada bitmap používaná
    k malování. Gimp obsahuje 10 kreslících nástrojů, které neprovádí pouze
    běžné kreslení, ale i operace jako mazání, kopírování, rozmazávání,
    zesvětlování či zmavování. Všechny, kromě nástroje Inkoust, používají
    stejnou sadu stop. Tyto bitmapy představují stopu, kterou v obrázku
    zanechá jeden dotyk nástrojem, napříkald štětcem. Tah štětcem nebo 
    jiným nástrojem tohoto typu vytvoří v obrázku řadu stop za sebou.
    Způsob jakým to udělá zavisí na použití stopě a konkrétním nástroji.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>brush</emphasis> is a pixmap or set of pixmaps used for
    painting.  GIMP includes a set of 10 "paint tools, which not
    only perform operations that you would think of as painting, but
    also operations such as erasing, copying, smudging, lightening or
    darkening, etc.  All of the paint tools, except the ink tool, use
    the same set of brushes.  The brush pixmaps represent the
    marks that are made by single "touches" of the brush to the image. 
    A brush stroke, usually made by moving the pointer across the image with 
    the mouse button held down, produces a series of marks spaced along the
    trajectory, in a way specified by the characteristics of the brush
    and the paint tool being used.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
   一个<emphasis>画笔</emphasis>是一个或一系列点阵图 (pixmap) 用做涂画。GIMP 包含一套 10 个涂画工具，它们不光完成您想象中的涂画操作，还包括擦除，拷贝，涂抹，减淡或加深等。除了墨水工具外的所以涂画工具都使用同一套画笔。这些画笔点阵图由该画笔在图像上的一个“压痕”的标志来表示。一个画笔笔划，通常是由按住鼠标键同时在图像上拖动光标产生，它根据使用的涂画工具其选取的画笔特性产生一系列随着轨迹间排列的一个一个斑点。
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Une <emphasis>brosse</emphasis> est une collection de pixels utilisée 
    pour peindre. GIMP comprend un lot de 10 brosses qui non seulement 
    réalisent les opérations attendues d'une brosse de peinture, mais aussi 
    des opérations de gommage, de copie, de mélange, d'éclaircissement ou 
    d'assombrissement...etc. Tous les outils, à l'exception de l'outil 
    Stylo-plume, utilisent ces mêmes brosses. Les brosses fonctionnent en 
    fait comme des tampons: un trait est composé de coups de tampons, de 
    touches de brosses successives. Si elles sont rapprochées le trait sera
    continu. Si elles sont espacées, le trait sera composé de touches 
    successives isolées.
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Stopy lze vybrat kliknutím na ijejich ikonu v <link
    linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>dialogu Stopy</link>. <emphasis>Aktuální
    stopa</emphasis> je vždy zobrazena v indikační oblasti panelu nástrojů.
    Kliknutí na tuto ikonu stopy v panelu nástrojů je jedním z možných způsobů
    vyvolání dialogu Stopy.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Brushes can be selected by clicking on an icon in the <link
    linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>Brushes dialog</link>.  GIMP's
    <emphasis>current brush</emphasis> is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the brush
    symbol there is one way of activating the Brushes dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    画笔能够在<link linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>画笔对话框</link>中通过点击一个其中图标来选取。GIMP <emphasis>当前画笔</emphasis>显示在工具箱的 画笔/图案/渐变 区域。点击画笔标志是开启画笔对话框的一种方式。
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Les brosses peuvent être sélectionnées par un clic simple sur une des 
    icônes dans la <link linkend='gimp-brush-dialog'>Boîte de dialogue des 
    brosses</link>. La brosse en cours est représentée dans l'aire 
    Brosses/Motifs/Dégradés de la Boîte à outils. Vous pouvez cliquer dessus 
    pour également ouvrir le Dialogue des brosses.
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Gimp je již při instalaci vybaven základní sadou stop včetně několika
    prazvláštních stop sloužících pro inspiraci (patří mezi ně i světoznámá
    zelená paprika). Můžete vytvořit další štětce, nebo si je stáhnout z
    Internetu a nainstalovat tak, aby o nich Gimp vědel.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a number of basic
    brushes, plus a few bizarre ones that serve mainly to give you
    examples of what is possible (i. e., the "green pepper" brush in
    the illustration).  You can also create new brushes, or
    download them and install them so that GIMP will recognize them.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    安装 GIMP 时，它自带了一系列基本的画笔外加一些主要提供当例子的怪异画笔(比如“绿色青椒”画笔)。您也能够新建画笔，或下载它们并安装，这样 GIMP 就会加载它们。
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Quand vous installez GIMP, plusieurs brosses sont installées en même 
    temps. Certaines, qui peuvent paraître bizarres, servent surtout 
    d'exemple sur les possibilités de GIMP (par exemple le «poivron vert»). 
    Mais vous pouvez aussi créer vos propres brosses ou en installer que 
    vous aurez téléchargées sur la Toile.
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Gimp umí používat řadu různých typů stop. Všechny se ale používají stejným
    způsobem a ve většině případů mezi nimi uživatel nemusí rozlišovat.
    Dostupné typy stop jsou následující:
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP can use several different types of brushes.  All of them,
    however, are used in the same way, and for most purposes you don't
    need to be aware of the differences when you paint with them.
    Here are the available types of brushes:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 可以使用许多不同类型的画笔。尽管如此，所以这些画笔使用方法都相同，对大部分目的，没有必要在用它们进行涂画时意识到这些不同。下面时可用的画笔类型：
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    GIMP peut utiliser différents types de brosses. La plupart s'emploient 
    de la même façon et vous n'avez pas à vous préoccuper de leur mode de 
    fonctionnement. Voici les divers types de brosses:  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='cs'>Obyčejné stopy</term>
      <term lang='en'>Ordinary brushes</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">普通画笔</term>
      <term lang='fr'> Les Brosses ordinaires</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Do této skupiny patří většina stop dodávaných s Gimpem. V dialogu
          Stopy jsou zobrazeny jako bitmapy v šedé škále. Při jejich použití
          aktuální barva popředí (zobrazená v oblasti barev panelu
          nástrojů) nahradí černou barvu v bitmapě stopy zobrazené v dialogu.
          Její tvar odpovídá tvaru značky, kterou za sebou jeden dotyk
          nástroje zanechá v obrázku.
        </para>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Chcete-li vytvořit stopu tohoto typu, namalujte ji jako malý obrázek
          ve stupních šedi (pracujte s přibloížením), který uložíte jako
          soubor s příponou .gbr. Pomocí tlačítka aktualizovat lze do sialogu
          Stopy načíst nové stopy, aniž by bylo nutné restartovat Gimp.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          Most of the brushes supplied with GIMP fall into this
          category.  They are represented in the Brushes dialog by
          grayscale pixmaps.  When you paint using them, the current
          foreground color (as shown in the Color Area of the Toolbox)
          is substituted for black, and the pixmap shown in the brushes
          dialog represents the mark that the brush makes on the image.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          To create such a brush: 
          Create a small image in gray levels using zoom. Save it with the 
          .gbr extension. Click on Refresh button in the Brush Dialog to get 
          it in preview without it being necessary to restart GIMP.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
        大部分 GIMP 自带的画笔属于这类，它们在画笔对话框中表现为灰度点阵图。当您使用它们时，当前前景色(在工具箱颜色区域显示)被换成黑色，而在画笔对话框中显示的点阵图表示画笔将在图像上产生的印记行踪。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Les brosses simples sont de petites images en niveaux de gris 
          utilisées comme brosses. Leur couleur ne peut pas être modifiée, 
          mais elles adoptent la couleur du Premier-Plan de la Boîte à outils 
          quand on les utilise. Elles ont l'extension 
          <emphasis>.gbr</emphasis>.  
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Pour créer ce type de brosse, créez une petite image en 
          niveaux de gris avec Arrière-Plan comme type de remplissage en 
          utilisant le zoom. Enregistrez-la avec l'extension .gbr selon le 
          chemin indiqué plus haut. Puis cliquez sur le bouton 
          <emphasis>Rafraîchir</emphasis> dans le dialogue des brosses pour 
          que la nouvelle brosse soit prise en compte sans qu'il soit 
          besoin de redémarrer Gimp.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='cs'>Barevné stopy</term>
      <term lang='en'>Color brushes</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">彩色画笔</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Les brosses figurées</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Stopy této skupiny jsou v dialogu reprezentovány barevnými obrázky.
          Když se s nimi maluje, nebere se aktuální barva popředí vůbec v
          úvahu, ale používají se barvy se stopy. Jinak fungují stejně jako
          obyčejné stopy.
        </para>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Chcete-li vytvořit takovouto stopu, namalujte malý RGBA obrázek
          (vytvořte nový obrázek v režimu RGB a jako pozadí zvolte
          průhlednost). Namalujte obrázek a nejprve ho uložte do .xcf souboru,
          abyste zachovali jeho vlastnosti. Pak ho uložte do .gbr formátu.
          Tlačítkem <emphasis>Aktualizovat</emphasis> pak stopu nahrajete do
          dialogu Stopy bez nutnosti restartovat Gimp.
        </para>
        <tip lang='cs'>
          <para>
            Stopu můžete vytvořit i z výběru pomocí script-fu
            Výběr/Do stopy.
          </para>
        </tip>
        <para lang='en'>
          Brushes in this category are represented by colored images in
          the Brushes dialog. They can be a text. When you paint with them, 
          the colors are used as shown; the current foreground color does 
          not come into play.  Otherwise they work the same way as ordinary 
          brushes.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          To create such a brush, create a small RGBA image. For this, open 
          New Image, select RGB for image type and Transparent for fill type. 
          Draw your image and save it first to .xcf file to keep its 
          properties. Then save it to .gbr format. Click on 
          <emphasis>Refresh</emphasis> button in Brush Dialog to get your 
          brush without it being necessary to restart Gimp.
        </para>
        <tip lang='en'>
          <para>
            You can transform a selection to a brush by using the 
            Selection/To Brush script-fu.
          </para>
        </tip>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          属于这类的画笔在画笔对话框中表现为彩色图像。使用它们涂画时，将使用其显示的颜色；当前前景色就不起作用，其它地方都和普通画笔一样。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Une brosse figurée est une brosse représentant une image souvent 
          en couleur ou un texte. Elle porte aussi l'extension .gbr, mais 
          ses couleurs peuvent être modifiées alors qu'elles sont 
          indépendantes de la couleur de Premier-Plan de la Boîte à outils. 
          Dans le dialogue Brosses, le Poivron («pepper») en est un exemple.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Pour créer ce type de brosse, créez une petite image RVBA. Pour 
          cela choisissez RVB comme type d'image et Transparent comme type 
          de remplissage. Dessinez votre image et faites une première 
          sauvegarde au format .xcf pour en conserver les propriétés, puis 
          enregistrez-la au format .gbr. Puis cliquez sur le bouton 
          <emphasis>Rafraîchir</emphasis> pour que la nouvelle brosse soit 
          prise en compte par le dialogue Brosses sans qu'il soit besoin de 
          redémarrer Gimp.
        </para> 
        <tip lang='fr'>
          <para>
            Vous pouvez transformer une sélection en brosse grâce au 
            script-fu Sélection/Vers Brosse.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='cs'>Animovaná stopa</term>
      <term lang='en'>Image hoses / Image pipes</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">图像管 (Image hoses) / (Image pipes)</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Brosses animées</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Stopy této skupiny mohou do obrázku dělar několik různých značek.
          V dialogu Stopy jsou tyto stopy vpravo dole označeny červeným
          trojúhelníčkem. Říká se jim animované, protože během malování
          tahu štětcem či jiným nástrojem se značky, které zanechávají v
          obrzáku, mění. Animované stopy mohou být velmi složité, zvláště
          ve spojení s tabletem. Tvar lze totiž měnit podle tlaku či sklonu
          stylusu a podobně. Tyto možnosti však nebyly nikdy plně využity a
          animované stopy dodávané s Gimpem jsou poměrně jednoduché (ale stále
          užitečné).
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          Brushes in this category can make more than one kind of mark
          on an image.  They are indicated by small red triangles at th
          lower right corner of the brush symbol in the Brushes dialog.
          They are sometimes called "animated brushes" 
          because the marks change as you trace out a brushstroke. In
          principle, image hose brushes can be very sophisticated,
          especially if you use a tablet, changing shape as a function
          of pressure, angle, etc.  These possibilities have never
          really been exploited, however; and the ones supplied with
          GIMP are relatively simple (but still quite useful). 
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
        属于这类的画笔能在一个图像上产生一种以上类型的印记。它们在画笔对话框的画笔标志右下方显示一个红色小三角。由于它们随着您勾画笔划时其印记也在改变，因此有时也把它们被叫作“动画画笔”。原则上，图像管会非常复杂，特别是使用一个平面板，在压力，角度等方面改变其形状。尽管如此，这些可能性并没有真正被挖掘；GIMP 自带的图像管就相对简单(不过仍然非常有用)。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Une brosse animée est une brosse dont la forme, l'orientation  et 
          la couleur peuvent varier au cours du tracé. Elle est composée de 
          plusieurs calques, un pour chacun des mouvements et/ou couleurs et 
          possède un canal alpha. Son extension est <emphasis>.gih</emphasis>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='cs'>Parametrické stopy</term>
      <term lang='en'>Parametric brushes</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">参数画笔</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Brosses paramétriques</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='cs'> 
          Tato skupina zahrnuje stopy vytvořené pomocí <link
          linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Editoru stop</link>, který
          pomocí jednoduchého rozhraní umožňuje vytvářet řadu různých tvarů
          stop. Příjemnou vlastností parametrických stop je, že <emphasis>lze
          měnit jejich velikost</emphasis>. V Gimpu 2.2 je možné v dialogu
          Předvolby nastavit ovládání velikosti takovýchto stop pomocí
          kolčka myši nebo klávesových zkratek.
        </para> 
        <para lang='en'>
          These are brushes created using the <link
          linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Brush Editor</link>, which
          allows you to generate a wide variety of brush shapes by
          using a simple graphical interface.  A nice feature of
          parametric brushes is that they are
          <emphasis>resizable</emphasis>.  In GIMP 2.2, it is possible,
          using the Preferences dialog, to make key presses or mouse
          wheel rotations cause the current brush to become larger or
          smaller, if it is a parametric brush.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN"> 
        它们是用<link linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>画笔编辑器</link>创建，允许您使用一个简单的图形界面产生大量不通的画笔形状。参数画笔的一个很好的特性就是其<emphasis>可缩放性</emphasis>。在 GIMP 2.2 中，在首选项对话框中使通过按键或滚动鼠标滑轮让参数画笔变大变小成为可能。
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Ces sont des brosses créées avec l'
          <link linkend='gimp-brush-editor-dialog'>Éditeur de brosse</link> 
          qui vous permet de générer des brosses de forme géométrique grâce à 
          une interface graphique simple. Ce qui est intéressant, c'est 
          que leur taille est modifiable. Dans GIMP 2.2 il est possible, en 
          utilisant le dialogue Préférences, de faire que la pression sur une 
          touche ou la rotation de la roue de la souris rende la brosse plus 
          large ou plus petite. Leur extension est <emphasis>.vbr</emphasis>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Gimpu chybí plnohodnotné <emphasis>procedurální</emphasis> stopy: stopy,
    jejichž tvar se během kreslení počítá, nikoliv kopíruje z předem dané
    bitmapy. Popravdě náznak takových stop používá v Gimpu nástroj Inkoust,
    ale ten je jedinou výjimkou. Lepší podpora procedurálních stop je jedním
    z cílů pro další zdokonalování Gimpu.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    One category that GIMP does not have is full-fledged
    <emphasis>procedural</emphasis> brushes:  brushes whose marks are
    calculated procedurally, instead of being taken from a fixed
    pixmap.  (Actually this is not quite correct:  the Ink tool uses a
    procedural brush, but it is the only one available in GIMP.)  A
    more extensive implementation of procedural brushes is a goal of
    future development for GIMP.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 中没有成熟的<emphasis>过程</emphasis>画笔：其印记是根据过程计算的，而不是使用是个固定的点阵图。(实际上这么说也不正确：墨水工具是 GIMP 中唯一可以使用过程画笔的工具。)对过程画笔更进一步的实现是 GIMP 将来发展的一个目标。
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Une catégorie de brosses que GIMP ne gère pas encore: les brosses 
    «procédurales». Ce sont des brosses dont la touche, la marque, est 
    calculée au lieu d'être simplement la reproduction d'une image 
    comme avec les autre brosses. L'insertion de ce type de brosses dans 
    GIMP est en vue. 
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Kromě bitmapy má každá stopa druhou důležitou vlastnost –
    <emphasis>rozestup</emphasis>. To je vzdálenost mezi jednotlivými otisky
    stopy při plynulém tahu štětcem (či jiným nástrojem). Každá stopa má svůj
    vlastní výchozí rozestup, který však lze v dialogu Stopy změnit.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    In addition to the brush pixmap, each GIMP brush has one other
    important property:  the brush <emphasis>Spacing</emphasis>. This
    represents the distance between consecutive brush-marks when a
    continuous brushstroke is painted.  Each brush has an assigned
    default value for this, which can be modified using the Brushes
    dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    每个 GIMP 画笔除了画笔点阵图还有另外一个重要属性：画笔<emphasis>间隔</emphasis>。它表示画一个连续笔划时相邻画笔印记间的距离。每个画笔都有一个给定的默认间距值，它可以通过画笔对话框修改。
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Outre son dessin, chaque brosse possède une autre propriété importante:
    son <emphasis>Espacement</emphasis>. C'est la distance entre deux 
    marques de la brosse: elle est réglable dans la boîte de dialogue des 
    Brosses.
  </para>

  <figure lang="en;de">
    <title lang='en'>
      The dialog to describe the animated brush.
    </title>
    <title lang='de'>
      Der Dialog um eine animierte Pinselform zu beschreiben.
    </title>
    <mediaobject lang="en;de">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/file-gih-save.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <simplesect id='gimp-GIH-dialog'>            <!--added 040927-->
    <title lang="cs">The GIH dialog box</title>
    <title lang="en">The GIH dialog box</title>
    <title lang="fr">Enregistrement de brosse animée</title>    
    <title lang="zh_CN">GIF 对话框</title>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento dialog obsahuje řadu obtížněji pochopitelných voleb.
      Umožňují nastavit způsob animace stopy.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This dialog box has several options not easy to understand. They 
      allow you to determine the way your brush is animated. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cette fenêtre de dialogue comporte de nombreuses options pas toujours 
      faciles à comprendre. Elles vous permettent de régler l'animation de 
      votre brosse.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该对话框中有许多不太容易理解的选项。它们决定画笔动画的方式。
    </para>

    <variablelist lang="en;fr">

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang= "en">Spacing (Percent)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Espacement (%)</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            "Spacing" is the distance between consecutive brush marks when you 
            trace out a brushstroke with the pointer. You must consider 
            drawing with a brush, whatever the paint tool, like stamping. If 
            Spacing is low, stamps will be very close and stroke look 
            continuous. If spacing is high, stamps will be separated: that's 
            interesting with a color brush (like "green pepper" for instance).
            Value varies from 1 to 200 and this percentage refers to brush 
            "diameter": 100% is one diameter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            L'Espacement est la distance entre deux marques de la brosse quand 
            vous tracez un trait avec le pointeur. Vous devez considérer que 
            dessiner avec une brosse est comme donner des coups de tampon. Si 
            l'espacement est faible, les coups de tampon seront très rapprochés 
            et le trait paraîtra continu. Si l'espacement est grand, les coups de 
            tampon seront séparés: c'est intéressant avec les brosses figurées, 
            comme le «poivron vert». La valeur varie de 1 à 200 et ce pourcentage 
            correspond au «diamètre» de la brosse: 100% est 1 diamètre.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Description</term>
        <term lang="fr">Description</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            It's the brush name that will appear at the top of Brush Dialog 
            (grid mode) when the brush is selected.
          </para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            C'est le nom donné à la brosse, qui apparaîtra en haut de la fenêtre 
            de sélection des brosses (en mode grille) quand la brosse sera 
            sélectionnée.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Cell Size</term>
        <term lang="fr">Taille des cases</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            That's size of cells you will cut up in layers... Default 
            is one cell per layer and size is that of the layer. Then there is 
            only one brush aspect per layer
          </para>
          <para>
            We could have only one big layer and cut up in it the cells that 
            will be used for the different aspects of the animated brush.
          </para>
          <para>
            For instance, we want a 100x100 pixels brush with 8 different 
            aspects. We can take these 8 aspects from a 400x200 pixels layer, or 
            from a 300x300 pixels layer but with one cell unused.
          </para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            C'est la dimension des cases que vous voulez découper dans les 
            calques... Par défaut, il n'y a qu'une case par calque et les 
            dimensions indiquées sont celles du calque. Il n'y a alors qu'un 
            aspect de la brosse par calque.
          </para>
          <para>
            Nous pourrions très bien n'avoir qu'un seul grand calque et découper 
            à l'intérieur les cases qui serviront pour les différents aspects de 
            la brosse animée.
          </para>
          <para>
            Par exemple, nous voulons une brosse de 100x100 pixels avec 8 aspects 
            différents. Nous pouvons prélever ces 8 aspects dans un calque de
            400x200 pixels, ou dans un calque de 300x300 mais alors avec une 
            case vide inutilisée.
          </para>  
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Number of cells</term>
        <term lang="fr">Nombre de cases</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            That's the number of cells (one cell per aspect) that will be cut in 
            every layer. Default is the number of layers as there is only one 
            layer per aspect. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            C'est le nombre de cases (une case par aspect) à découper dans 
            chaque calque. Par défaut, c'est le nombre de calques puisqu'il n'y 
            a qu'un calque par aspect.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Display as:</term>
        <term lang="fr">Afficher comme</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            This tells how cells have been arranged in layers. If, for example, 
            you have placed height cells at the rate of two cells per layer on 
            four layers, GIMP will display: "1 rows of 2 columns on each layer".
          </para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            C'est l'expression de la façon dont vous avez arrangé les cases sur 
            les calques. Si par exemple vous avez placé huit cases à raison de 
            deux cases par calque sur quatre calques, Gimp affichera: 
            «1 rangée(s) de 2 colonne(s) par calque».
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
  
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Dimension, Ranks, Selection</term>
        <term lang="fr">Dimension, Rangs, Sélection</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            There things are getting complicated! Explanations are necessary to 
            understand how to arrange cell and layers.
          </para>
          <para>
            GIMP starts retrieving cells from each layer and stacks them into a 
            FIFO stack (First In First Out: the first in is at the top of the 
            stack and so can be first out). In our example 4 layers with 2 cells 
            in each, we'll have, from top to bottom: first cell of first layer, 
            second cell of first layer, first cell of second layer, second cell 
            of second layer..., second cell of fourth layer. With one cell per 
            layer or with several cells per layer, result is the same. You can 
            see this stack in the Layer Dialog of the resulting .gih image file.
            </para>
            <para>
            Then GIMP creates a computer array from this stack with the 
            <guilabel>Dimensions</guilabel> you have set. You can use four 
            dimensions.  
          </para>  
          <para>
            In computer science an array has a "myarray(x,y,z)" form for a 3 
            dimensions array (3D). It's easy to imagine a 2D array: on a paper 
            it's an array with rows and columns
            <mediaobject lang="en">
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/array2D.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            With a 3d array we don't talk rows and columns but 
            <guilabel>Dimensions</guilabel> and <guilabel>Ranks</guilabel>. The 
            first dimension is along x axis, the second dimension along y axis, 
            the third along z axis. Each dimension has ranks of cells. 
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/array3D.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </para>
          <para>
            To fill up this array, GIMP starts retrieving cells from the top of 
            stack. The way it fills the array reminds that of an odometer: right 
            rank digits turn first and, when they reach their maximum, left rank 
            digits start running. If you have some memories of Basic programming 
            you will have, with an array(4,2,2), the following succession:
            (1,1,1),(1,1,2),(1,2,1),(1,2,2),(2,1,1),(2,1,2),(2,2,2),(3,1,1)....
            (4,2,2). We will see this later in an example.
          </para>
          <para> 
            Besides the rank number that you can give to each dimension, you can 
            also give them a <guilabel>Selection</guilabel> mode. You have 
            several modes that will be applyed when drawing:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Incremental</emphasis>: GIMP selects a rank from the 
                  concerned dimension according to the order ranks have in that 
                  dimension
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Random</emphasis>: GIMP selects a rank at random 
                  from the concerned dimension.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Angular</emphasis>: GIMP selects a rank in the 
                  concerned dimension according to the moving angle of the brush.
                </para>
                <para>
                  The first rank is for the direction 0°, upwards. The other 
                  ranks are affected, counter clockwise, to an angle whose value 
                  is 360/number of ranks. So, with 4 ranks in the concerned 
                  dimension, the angle will move 90° counterclockwise for each 
                  direction change: second rank will be affected to 270° (-90°) 
                  (leftwards), third rank to 180° (downwards) and fourth rank to 
                  90° (rightwards).
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Speed</emphasis>,
                  <emphasis>Pressure</emphasis>,
                  <emphasis>x tilt</emphasis> and 
                  <emphasis>y tilt</emphasis> are options for sophisticated 
                  drawing tablets.
               </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
  
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            C'est là que les choses se compliquent! Des explications sont 
            nécessaires pour comprendre comment arranger les cases et les 
            calques.
          </para>
          <para>
            Gimp commence par récupérer les cases dans chaque calque et à les 
            empiler dans une pile FIFO (First In first Out: Premier entré, 
            Premier sorti et donc premier entré en haut de la pile pour pouvoir 
            sortir le premier et dernier entré en bas de la pile). Dans notre 
            exemple 4 calques de 2 cases chacun, on aura, de haut en bas, la 
            première case du premier calque, la deuxième case du premier calque, 
            la première case du deuxième calque, la deuxième case du deuxième 
            calque..., la deuxième case du quatrième calque. Que vous ayez placé 
            une case par calque ou plusieurs cases par calque, le résultat sera 
            le même: toutes les cases seront récupérées ainsi et empilées dans 
            une seule pile. Vous pourrez voir cette pile dans le dialogue calque 
            du fichier .gih résultant.
            </para>
            <para>
            Dans un deuxième temps, Gimp crée, à partir de cette pile, un 
            tableau informatique ayant les <guilabel>Dimensions</guilabel> que 
            vous aurez indiquées. Vous disposez de quatre dimensions. 
          </para>
          <para>
            En informatique, un tableau se présente sous la forme 
            tableau(x,y,z) pour un tableau à 3 dimensions. Il est facile de se 
            représenter un tableau à 2 dimensions: sur une feuille de papier, 
            c'est un tableau avec des lignes et des colonnes 
            <mediaobject lang="fr">
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/array2D.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </para>
          <para>
            Avec un tableau 3D, on ne parle pas de lignes ni de colonnes, mais 
            de <guilabel>Dimension</guilabel> et de <guilabel>Rangs</guilabel>. 
            La première dimension est sur l'axe x, la deuxième sur l'axe y et la 
            troisième sur l'axe des z. Chaque dimension possède un certain nombre 
            de rangs de cases. 
            <mediaobject lang="fr">
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/array3D.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </para>
          <para>
            Pour remplir le tableau, Gimp va récupérer les cases sur la pile en 
            commençant par le haut. Sa façon de remplir le tableau évoque le 
            fonctionnement d'un compteur kilométrique: les chiffres du rang de 
            droite tournent jusqu'à leur maximum et alors ceux à gauche 
            commencent à tourner. Si vous avez des souvenirs de programmation 
            Basic, vous aurez, avec un tableau(4,2,2) la succession suivante:
            (1,1,1),(1,1,2),(1,2,1),(1,2,2),(2,1,1),(2,1,2),(2,2,2),(3,1,1)....
            (4,2,2). Nous verrons ça plus loin dans un exemple.
          </para>
          <para> 
            Outre le nombre de rangs que vous pouvez attribuer à chaque 
            dimension, vous pouvez lui donner un mode de <emphasis>Sélection</emphasis>.
            Vous disposez de différents modes de sélection qui s'appliqueront 
            lors du dessin:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Incrémentiel</emphasis>: Gimp sélectionnera un rang 
                  dans la dimension concernée dans l'ordre des rangs de cette 
                  dimension. 
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Au hasard</emphasis>: Gimp sélectionnera au hasard 
                  un rang dans la dimension concernée.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Angulaire</emphasis>: Gimp sélectionnera un rang de la 
                  dimension concernée en fonction de l'angle de déplacement de la 
                  brosse.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Le premier rang est pour la direction 0°, vers le haut. Les autres 
                  rangs sont affectés, dans le sens antihoraire, à un angle dont la 
                  valeur est 360°/nombre de rangs. Ainsi, avec 4 rangs dans la 
                  dimension concernée, l'angle se décalera de 90° à chaque changement 
                  de direction. Le deuxième rang sera affecté à la direction 
                  270° (-90°), vers la gauche. Le troisième rang sera affecté à 180°, 
                  vers le bas, et le quatrième rang à 90°, vers la droite.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Vitesse</emphasis>,
                  <emphasis>Pression</emphasis>,
                  <emphasis>Inclinaison x</emphasis> et 
                  <emphasis>Inclinaison y</emphasis> sont des options pour des 
                  tablettes graphiques perfectionnées
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  
    <variablelist lang="en;fr">
      <title lang="en">Examples</title>
      <title lang="fr">Exemples</title> 
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">A one dimension image pipe</term>
        <term lang="fr">Une brosse animée à une dimension></term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Well! What is all this useful for? We'll see that gradually with 
            examples. You can actually place in each dimension cases that will 
            give your brush a particular action.   
          </para>
          <para>
            Let us start with a 1D brush which will allow us to study selection 
            modes action. We can imagine it like this:
            <mediaobject lang="en">
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/array1D.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Follow these steps:
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Open a new 30x30 pixels image, RGB with Transparent fill type. 
                  Using the Text tool create 4 layers "1", "2", "3", "4". Delete 
                  the "background" layer.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem> 
                <para>
                  Save this image first with .xcf extension to keep its 
                  properties then save it as .gih.
                </para>
                <para>
                  The Save As Dialog is opened: select a destination for your 
                  image. OK. The GIH dialog is opened:
                  Choose Spacing 100, give a name in Description box, 30x30 for 
                  Cell Size, 1 dimension, 1 rank and choose "Incremental" in 
                  Selection box. OK.
                </para>
                <para>
                  You may have difficulties to save directly in the GIMP Brush 
                  directory. In that case, save the .gih file manually into the 
                  /usr/share/gimp/gimp 2.0/brushes directory. Then come back 
                  into the Toolbox, clic on the brush icon to open the Brush 
                  Dialog then click on "Refresh". Your new brush appears in the 
                  Brush window. Select it. Select pencil tool for instance and 
                  click and hold with it on a new image
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/1234incr.png' format='PNG'/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                  You see 1, 2, 3, 4 digits following one another in order.
                </para>
                <para> 
                  Take your .xcf image file back and save it as .gih setting 
                  Selection to "Random": digits will be displayed at random 
                  order:
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/1234rand.png' format='PNG'/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </para>
                <para> 
                  Now select "Angular" Selection:
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/1234angl.png' format='PNG'/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </para>           
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>  
  
          </para> 
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            Tout ça c'est bien joli, mais à quoi ça sert? Nous allons voir ça 
            progressivement. En fait, vous pouvez placer dans chaque dimension 
            les cases qui donneront une action particulière à votre brosse 
            animée. 
          </para>
          <para>
            Commençons par une brosse à 1 dimension qui nous permettra d'étudier 
            l'action des modes de Sélection . Nous pouvons la représenter 
            ainsi:
            <mediaobject lang="fr">
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/array1D.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Pour cela, suivez les étapes suivantes:
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Ouvrez une nouvelle image de 30x30 pixels, RVB avec un 
                  Type de remplissage transparent. Avec l'outil Texte, créez 
                  4 calques représentant respectivement 1,2,3,4. Vous pouvez 
                  effacer le calque «Arrière-plan».
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem> 
                <para>
                  Enregistrez cette image d'abord au format .xcf pour 
                  sauvegarder vos calques puis enregistrez-la sous le format 
                  .gih. 
                </para>
                <para>
                  Le dialogue d'enregistrement s'ouvre d'abord: choisissez le 
                  répertoire de destination de votre image. Validez.
                  La fenêtre de dialogue GIH s'ouvre: 
                  Choisissez un espacement de 100, donnez un nom, une taille de 
                  case de 30x30, 1 dimension, 1 rang et indiquez «incrémentielle» 
                  pour sélection. Validez.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Vous pouvez avoir des difficultés à enregistrer directement 
                  dans le répertoire des brosses de Gimp. Dans ce cas, placez 
                  manuellement le fichier .gih dans le répertoire 
                  /usr/share/gimp/gimp 2.0/brushes. Revenez dans la Boîte à 
                  outils. Cliquez sur l'icône des brosses pour ouvrir le 
                  dialogue des brosses et cliquez sur «Rafraîchir». Votre 
                  nouvelle brosse apparaît dans la fenêtre des brosses et vous 
                  pouvez la sélectionner pour dessiner. Faites un cliquer-glisser 
                  sur une nouvelle image:
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/1234incr.png' format='PNG'/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                  Vous voyez que les chiffres 1,2,3,4 se suivent dans l'ordre.
                </para>
                <para> 
                  Reprenez votre image .xcf et enregistrez-la en .gih en 
                  choisissant cette fois la sélection «Au hasard»: les chiffres 
                  se suivent dans un ordre aléatoire:
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/1234rand.png' format='PNG'/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </para>
                <para> 
                  Choisissez la sélection «angulaire»:
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/1234angl.png' format='PNG'/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </para>           
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>  
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
      </varlistentry> 
  
      <varlistentry> 
        <term lang="en">A 3 dimensions image hose</term>
        <term lang="fr">Une brosse animée à 3 dimensions</term>  
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            We are now going to create a 3D animated brush: its orientation will 
            vary according to brush direction, it will alternate Left/Right 
            hands regularly and its color will vary at random between black and 
            blue. 
          </para>
          <para>
            The first question we have to answer to is the number of images that 
            is necessary. We reserve the first dimension (x) to the brush 
            direction (4 directions). The second dimension (y) is for Left/Right 
            alternation and the third dimension (z) for color variation. Such a 
            brush is represented in a 3D array "myarray(4,2,2)": 
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/3Dnum.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            There are 4 ranks in first dimension (x), 2 ranks in second 
            dimension (y) and 2 ranks in third dimension (z). We see that there 
            are 4x2x2 = 16 cells. We need 16 images.
          </para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Creating images of dimension 1 (x)</emphasis>: 
                Open a new 30x30 pixels image, RGB with Transparent Fill Type. 
                Using the zoom draw a left hand with fingers upwards. Save it as 
                handL0k.xcf (hand Left O° Black).
              </para>
              <para>
                Open the Layer Dialog. Double click on the layer to open the 
                Layer Attributes Dialog and rename it to handL0k.
              </para>
              <para>
                Duplicate the layer. Let visible only the duplicated layer, 
                select it and apply a 90° rotation (Layer/Transform/ 90° 
                rotation counter-clockwise). Rename it to handL-90k.
              </para>
              <para>
                Repeat the same operations to create handL180k and handL90k.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Creating images of dimension 2 (y)</emphasis>:
                This dimension in our example has two ranks, one for left hand 
                and the other for right hand. The left hand rank exists yet. We 
                shall build right hand images by flipping it horisontally.
              </para>
              <para>
                Duplicate the handL0k layer. Let it visible only and select it. 
                Rename it to handR0K. Apply Layer/Transform/Flip Horizontally.
              </para>
              <para>
                Repeat the same operation on the other left hand layers to 
                create their right hand equivalent.
              </para>
              <para>
                Re-order layers to have a counter-clockwise rotation from top to 
                bottom, alternating Left and Right: handL0k, handR0k, handL-90k,
                handR-90k, ..., handR90k.
              </para> 
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Creating images of dimension 3 (z)</emphasis>:
                The third dimension has two ranks, one for black color and the 
                other for blue color. The first rank, black, exists yet. We well 
                see that images of dimension 3 will be a copy, in blue, of the 
                images of dimension 2. So we will have our 16 images. But a row 
                of 16 layers is not easy to manage: we will use layers with two 
                images.
              </para>
              <para>
                Select the handL0k layer and let it visible only. Using 
                Image/Canvas Size change canvas size to 60x30 pixels.
              </para>
              <para>
                Duplicate hand0k layer. On the copy, fill the hand with blue 
                using Bucket Fill tool.
              </para>
              <para>
                Now, select the Move tool. Double click on it to accede to its 
                properties: check "Move the Current Layer" option. Move the blue 
                hand into the right part of the layer precisely with the help of 
                Zoom.
              </para>
              <para>
                Make sure only handL0k and its blue copy are visible. Right click 
                on the Layer Dialog: Apply the "Merge Visible Layers" command 
                with the option "Expand as Necessary". You get a 60x30 pixels 
                layer with the black hand on the left and the blue hand on the 
                right. Rename it to "handL0".
              </para>
              <para>
                Repeat the same operations on the other layers.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Set layers in order</emphasis>: Layers must be set in 
                order so that GIMP can find the required image at some point 
                of using the brush. Our layers are yet in order but we must 
                understand more generally how to have them in order.There are 
                two ways to imagine this setting in order. The first method is 
                mathematical: GIMP divides the 16 layers first by 4; that gives 
                4 groups of 4 layers for the first dimension. Each group 
                represents a direction of the brush. Then, it divides each group 
                by 2; that gives 8 groups of 2 layers for the second dimension: 
                each group represents a L/R alternation. Then another division 
                by 2 for the third dimension to represent a color at random 
                between black and blue.
              </para> 
              <para>
                The other method is visual, by using the array representation. 
                Correlation between two methods is represented in next image:
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='../images/using/correlation-en.png' format='PNG'/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Voilà. Your brush is ready. Save it as .xcf first then as .gih 
                with the following parameters:
                Spacing:100    Description:Hands      Cell Size: 30x30
                Number of cells:16    Dimensions: 3
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para> 
                    Dimension 1: 4 ranks  Selection: Angular
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                    Dimension 2: 2 ranks  Selection: Incremental
                    </para>
                  </listitem> 
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                    Dimension 3: 2 ranks  Sélection: Random
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </para> 
              <para>
                Place your .gih file into GIMP brush directory and refresh the 
                brush box. You can now use your brush. Unfortunately GIMP 2.0 is 
                bug-ridden and you may have some difficulties with brush 
                orientation.
              </para>
              <para>
                Here is the result by stroking an elliptical selection with the 
                brush: 
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/using/hands_stroke.png' format='PNG'/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                This brush alternates right hand and left hand regularly, 
                black and blue color at random, according to four brush 
                directions.
              </para>
            </listitem>   
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>  
  
        <listitem lang="fr"> 
          <para>
            Nous allons maintenant créer une brosse à 3 dimensions permettant de 
            dessiner une main dont l'orientation change suivant la direction de 
            la brosse (4 directions), alternant régulièrement main droite et 
            main gauche, et changeant de couleur de façon aléatoire.
          </para>  
          <para> 
            La première question qui se pose est le nombre d'images nécessaires.
            Nous réserverons la première dimension aux 4 orientations de la main. 
            La deuxième dimension sera pour l'alternance Gauche/Droite et la 
            troisième pour la variation entre deux couleurs. Une telle brosse 
            aura besoin d'un tableau semblable au tableau 3D que nous avons 
            utilisé comme exemple:
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/using/3Dnum.png' format='PNG'/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            Il y a 4 rangs dans la première dimension (x), 2 rangs dans la 
            deuxième dimension (y) et 2 rangs dans la troisième dimension (z).
            Nous voyons que le nombre de cases, qui correspond au nombre 
            d'images, est de 4 x 2 x 2 = 16.
          </para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Création des images de la dimension 1 (x)</emphasis>: 
                Ouvrez une nouvelle image 30x30 pixels, RVB, avec Type de 
                remplissage Transparent. En vous aidant du zoom, dessinez 
                l'image d'une main gauche les doigts vers le haut. Enregistrez-la 
                sous le nom mainG0n.xcf pour "main gauche 0° noire".
              </para>
              <para>
                Ouvrez le dialogue Calques. Double Clic² sur le calque pour 
                ouvrir le dialogue Attributs du Calque et le renommer en 
                «mainG0n».
              </para>
              <para>
                Dupliquez le calque. Laissez uniquement le calque dupliqué 
                visible, sélectionnez-le et appliquez-lui une rotation de 90° 
                (Calque/Transformations/Rotation 90° sens anti-horaire). 
                Renommez-le en mainG-90n.
              </para>
              <para>
                Effectuez les mêmes opérations pour créer mainG180n et mainG90n.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Création des images de la dimension 2 (y)</emphasis>:  
                Cette dimension possède 2 rangs, un pour la main Gauche et 
                l'autre pour la main droite. Le rang main gauche existe déjà.
                Nous allons créer les images de la main Droite par un simple 
                retournement horizontal.
              </para>
              <para>
                Dupliquez le calque mainG0n. Rendez-le seul visible et 
                sélectionnez-le. Renommez-le en mainD0n 
                Appliquez Calque/Transformations/Retournement Horizontal. 
              </para>
              <para>
                Agissez de la même façon sur les autres calques main gauche pour 
                créer leur équivalent main droite.
              </para> 
              <para>
                Ré-ordonnez les calques pour avoir une rotation anti-horaire de 
                haut en bas alternant Gauche et Droite: mainG0n, MainD0n,
                mainG-90, mainD-90n, ..., mainD90n. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Création des images de la dimension 3 (z)</emphasis>:
                La dimension 3 possède 2 rangs, un pour la couleur noire et 
                l'autre pour la couleur bleue. Le premier rang, noir, existe 
                déjà. On voit bien que les images de la dimension 3 vont être 
                une duplication, en bleu, des images de la dimension 2. Nous 
                aurons ainsi nos 16 images. Mais un alignement de 16 calques est 
                difficile à gérer. Nous allons donc utiliser des calques à deux 
                images.
              </para>
              <para>
                Sélectionnons le calque maing0n et rendons-le seul visible. 
                Avec Image/Taille du Canevas, changeons la taille du canevas de 
                ce calque en 60x30.
              </para>
              <para>
                Dupliquez le calque maing0n. Sur la copie, utilisez l'outil 
                Remplissage pour remplir la main de bleu.
              </para>
              <para>
                Sélectionnez l'outil Déplacement. Double clic dessus pour 
                accéder à ses propriétés. Cochez l'option «Déplacer le calque 
                courant». Déplacez l'image dans la partie droite du calque avec 
                précision en vous aidant du zoom. 
                </para> 
                <para>
                Assurez-vous que seuls le calque maing0n et sa copie sont 
                visibles. Clic droit sur la fenêtre des calques: appliquez la 
                commande «Fusionner les calques visibles» avec l'option «Étendre 
                autant que nécessaire». Vous obtenez ainsi un calque 
                avec une main gauche noire à gauche et une main gauche bleue à 
                droite. Renommez-le en mainG0.
              </para>
              <para>
                Agissez de même sur les autres calques.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Mise en ordre des calques</emphasis>: Les calques 
                doivent être rangés dans un ordre particulier pour que Gimp 
                puisse retrouver l'image voulue à un moment donné de 
                l'utilisation de la brosse. Nos calques sont déjà en ordre, mais 
                nous devons comprendre plus généralement comment les avoir dans 
                le bon ordre. La première méthode est mathématique: GIMP divise 
                d'abord les 16 calques de la pile en 4, ce qui donne 4 groupes 
                de 4 calques pour la première dimension. Chaque groupe 
                représente une direction de la brosse. Puis il divise chaque 
                groupe en 2, ce qui donne 8 groupes de 2 calques pour la 
                deuxième dimension, chaque groupe représentant l'alternance G/D. 
                Enfin une autre division par deux pour représenter une couleur 
                au hasard entre noir et bleu.
              </para>
              <para>
                L'autre méthode est visuelle, basée sur la représentation du 
                tableau 3D. La corrélation entre ces deux méthodes est donnée 
                dans l'image suivante:
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='../images/using/correlation-fr.png' format='PNG'/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para> 
                <emphasis>Comment GIMP lira-t-il ce tableau?</emphasis>
                GIMP commence par la première dimension qui est programmée pour 
                un choix «angulaire», par exemple -90°. Dans ce rang -90°, en 
                jaune, il choisit, dans la deuxième dimension, de façon 
                «incrémentielle» une alternance G/D. Puis, dans la troisième 
                dimension, sur un mode aléatoire, il choisit une couleur.
                Finalement, nos calques doivent avoir la disposition suivante:
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fr/mains_gih.png' format='PNG'/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
   
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Voilà. Votre brosse est prête. Enregistrez-la d'abord au format 
                .xcf puis au format .gih avec les paramètres suivants: 
                Espacement:100   Description: mains    Taille des cellules: 30x30 
                Nombre de cellules: 16   Dimensions: 3
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para> 
                      Dimension 1: 4 rangs  Sélection: angulaire
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      Dimension 2: 2 rangs  Sélection: incrémentielle
                    </para>
                  </listitem> 
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      Dimension 3: 2 rangs  Sélection: Au hasard
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </para>
              <para>
                Placez la brosse dans le répertoire des brosses de Gimp, 
                rafraîchissez la boîte des brosses. Votre brosse est 
                utilisable.
                Malheureusement, à l'heure de la rédaction de ce texte, 
                la version 2.0 de Gimp est boguée: l'orientation des mains 
                peut avoir des ratés.
                </para>
                <para>
                Et voici le résultat en «traçant» une sélection elliptique 
                avec la brosse:  
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref='../images/using/hands_stroke.png' format='PNG'/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                Cette brosse alterne les mains droite et gauche 
                régulièrement, les couleurs bleue et noire au hasard , selon 
                quatre directions de la brosse.
              </para>
  
            </listitem>   
          </orderedlist> 
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  
</sect2>
