<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-07-15 KoSt: added 'no'
  2008-04-05 Mr.Dust : added 'ko' contents
  2007-12-26 lexa: initial version for en and de
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-color-management">
  <title>Color Management in GIMP</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Color</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>ICC profile</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Many devices you use in your design or photography workflow, like digital
    photo cameras, scanners, displays, printers etc., have their own color
    reproduction characteristics. If those are not taken into account during
    opening, editing and saving, harmful adjustments can be done to images.
    With <acronym>GIMP</acronym> you can have reliable output for both Web
    and print.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Image Processing Workflow</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/using/colormanagement-workflow1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Workflow without Color management</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/using/colormanagement-workflow2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Process with Color management</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2>
    <title>Problems of a non Color Managed Workflow</title>
    <para>
      The basic problem of image manipulation without color management is that
      you do simply not see what you do. This affects two different areas:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There are differences in Colors caused by different color
          characteristics of different devices like cameras, scanners,
          displays or printers
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There are differences in Colors caused by the limitations of the
          colorspace a specific device is able to handle
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      The main purpose of color management is to avoid such problems. The
      approach taken to do so involves the addition of a description of the
      color characteristic to an image or devices.
    </para>
    <para>
      These descriptions are called <emphasis>color profile</emphasis>. A
      color profile is basically a look-up table to translate the specific
      color characteristic of a device to a device-independent color space -
      the so called working-space. All the image manipulation is then done to
      images in the working-space. In addition to that the color profile of a
      device can be used to simulate how colors would look on that device.
    </para>
    <para>
      The creation of color profiles is most often done by the manufacturer
      of the devices themselves. To make these profiles usable independent of
      platform and operating system, the ICC (International Color Consortium)
      created a standard called ICC-profile that describes how color profiles
      are stored to files and embedded into images.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="plug-in-icc-profile-set">
    <title>Introduction to a Color Managed Workflow</title>
    <tip>
      <para>
        Most of the parameters and profiles described here can be set in the
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> preferences. Please see
        <xref linkend="gimp-prefs-color-management"/> for details.
      </para>
    </tip>

    <sect3 id="plug-in-icc-profile-apply">
      <title>Input</title>
      <para>
        Most digital cameras embed a color profile to individual photo files
        without user interaction. Digital scanners usually come with a color
        profile, which they also attach to the scanned images.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Applying the ICC-profile</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/using/icc-apply-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        When opening an image with an embedded color profile,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> offers to
        convert the file to the RGB working color space. This is sRGB by
        default and it is recommended that all work is done in that color
        space. Should you however decide to keep the embedded color profile,
        the image will however still be displayed correctly.
      </para>
      <para>
        In case for some reason a color profile is not embedded in the image
        and you know (or have a good guess) which one it should be, you can
        manually assign it to that image.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-concepts-cm-display">
      <title>Display</title>
      <para>
        For the best results, you need a color profile for your monitor. If a
        monitor profile is configured, either system-wide or in the Color
        Management section of the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Preferences dialog,
        the image colors will be displayed most accurately.
      </para>
      <para>
        One of the most important <acronym>GIMP</acronym> commands to work
        with color management is described in
        <xref linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you do not have a color profile for your monitor, you can
        create it using hardware calibration and measurement tools. On
        UNIX systems you will need
        <productname>Argyll Color Management System</productname>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-argyllcms"/> and/or
        <productname>LProf</productname>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-lprof"/>
        to create color profiles.
      </para>

      <sect4 id="gimp-concepts-cm-display-profiling">
        <title>Display Calibration and Profiling</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Color management</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Color profile</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
          For displays there are two steps involved. One is called calibration
          and the other is called profiling. Also, calibration generally
          involves two steps. The first involves adjusting external monitor
          controls such as Contrast, Brightness, Color Temperature, etc, and
          it is highly dependent on the specific monitor. In addition there
          are further adjustments that are loaded into the video card memory
          to bring the monitor as close to a standard state as possible. This
          information is stored in the monitor profile in the so-called vcgt
          tag. Probably under Windows XP or Mac OS, the operating system loads
          this information (LUT) in the video card in the process of starting
          your computer. Under Linux, at present you have to use an external
          program such as xcalib or dispwin. (If one just does a simple visual
          calibration using a web site such as that of Norman Koren, one might
          only use xgamma to load a gamma value.)
        </para>
        <para>
          The second step, profiling, derives a set of rules which allow
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          to translate RGB values in the image file into appropriate colors on
          the screen. This is also stored in the monitor profile. It doesn't
          change the RGB values in the image, but it does change which values
          are sent to the video card (which already contains the vcgt LUT).
        </para>
      </sect4>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Print Simulation</title>
      <para>
        Using <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you can easily get a preview of what
        your image will look
        like on paper. Given a color profile for your printer, the display can
        be switched into Soft Proof mode. In such a simulated printout, colors
        that cannot be reproduced will optionally be marked with neutral gray
        color, allowing you to correct such mistakes before sending your
        images to the printer.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
