<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2011-02-26 Michael added "resolution" and improved "layers"
  2009-03-20 j.h: fixed bug #557343
  2007-02-27 lexa: reorganized concepts
  2006-01-07 HdJ: Added quote and acronym tags, added English and Dutch
             version of layers explanation
  2005-12-18 Lexa: reviewed and added de translation-->

<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-concepts-basic">
  <title>Basic Concepts</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Concepts</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Wilber, the GIMP mascot</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/using/wilber.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          The Wilber Construction Kit
          (<ulink url="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help/-/blob/master/src/images/Wilber_Construction_Kit_original.xcf?ref_type=heads">
          src/images/Wilber_Construction_Kit_original.xcf</ulink>)
          allows you to give <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s mascot named Wilber a
          different appearance. It is the work of Tuomas Kuosmanen (tigert).
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    This section provides a brief introduction to the basic concepts and
    terminology used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. The concepts presented here
    are explained in
    much greater depth elsewhere. With a few exceptions, we have avoided
    cluttering this section with a lot of links and cross-references:
    everything mentioned here is so high-level that you can easily
    locate it in the index.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Images</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Images are the basic entities used by <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          Roughly speaking, an <quote>image</quote> corresponds to a single
          file, such as a TIFF or JPEG file. You can also think of an image
          as corresponding to a single display window (although in truth it
          is possible to have multiple windows all displaying the same image).
          It is not possible to have a single window display more than one
          image, though, or for an image to have no window displaying it.
        </para>
        <para>
          A <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image may be quite a complicated thing.
          Instead of thinking of it as a sheet of paper with a
          picture on it, think of it as more like a stack of sheets, called
          <quote>layers</quote>. In addition to a stack of layers, a
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image may contain a selection mask, a set of
          channels, and a set of paths. In fact, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          provides a mechanism for attaching arbitrary pieces of data, called
          <quote>parasites</quote>, to an image.
        </para>
        <para>
          In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it is possible to have many images open
          at the same time. Although large images may use many megabytes of
          memory, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses a sophisticated
          tile-based memory management system that allows
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to handle very large images gracefully.
          There are limits, however, and having more memory available
          may improve system performance.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layers</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a simple image can be compared to a single sheet of paper, an
          image with layers is likened to a sheaf of transparent papers
          stacked one on top of the other. You can draw on each paper, but
          still see the content of the other sheets through the transparent
          areas. You can also move one sheet in relation to the others.
          Sophisticated <acronym>GIMP</acronym> users often deal with images
          containing many layers, even dozens of them. Layers need not be
          opaque, and they need not cover the entire extent of an image, so
          when you look at an image's display, you may see more than just the
          top layer: you may see elements of many layers.
          For more info see <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layers">Introduction
          to Layers</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <phrase>Resolution</phrase>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Resolution</primary>
        </indexterm>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Digital images consist of a grid of square pixels.
          Each image has a size measured in two dimensions, such as 900
          pixels wide by 600 pixels high. But pixels don't have a set size in
          physical space. To set up an image for printing, we use a value
          called resolution, defined as the ratio between an image's size in
          pixels and its physical size (usually in inches) when it is printed
          on paper. Most file formats (but not all) can save this value, which
          is expressed as ppi&mdash;pixels per inch.
        </para>
        <para>
          When printing a file,
          the resolution determines the size the image will have on
          paper, and as a result, the physical size of the pixels. The same
          900×600 pixel image may be printed as a small 3×2" card with barely
          noticeable pixels&mdash;or as a large poster with large, chunky
          pixels.
        </para>
        <para>
          Images imported from cameras and mobile devices tend to
          have a resolution attached to the file. The resolution is usually
          72 or 96 ppi. It is important to realize that this resolution is arbitrary
          and was chosen for historic reasons. You can always change the
          resolution with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>&mdash;this has no
          effect on the actual image pixels. Furthermore, for uses such as
          displaying images online, on mobile devices, television or video
          games&mdash;in short, any use that is not print&mdash;the
          resolution value is meaningless and is ignored. Instead, the
          image is usually displayed so that each image pixel conforms to one
          screen pixel.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry id="gimp-concepts-channels" xreflabel="Channels">
      <term>
        <phrase>Channels</phrase>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Channel</primary>
        </indexterm>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <!--TRANSLATORS: this is the modified text from glossary.xml, so
        you should check po/LANG/glossary.po for an old translation-->
        <para>
          A Channel is a single component of a pixel's color. For a colored
          pixel in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, these components are usually Red,
          Green, Blue and sometimes transparency (Alpha). For a
          <link linkend="glossary-graylevel">Grayscale</link> image, they are
          Gray and Alpha and for an
          <link linkend="glossary-indexedcolors">Indexed</link> color image,
          they are Indexed and Alpha.
        </para>
        <para>
          The entire rectangular array of any one of the color components for
          all of the pixels in an image is also referred to as a Channel. You
          can see these color channels with the
          <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">Channels Dialog</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
          When the image is displayed, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puts these
          components together to form the pixel colors for the screen,
          printer, or other output device. Some output devices may use
          different channels from Red, Green and Blue. If they do,
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s channels are converted into the
          appropriate ones for the device when the image is displayed.
        </para>
        <para>
          Channels can be useful when you are working on an image which needs
          adjustment in one particular color. For example, if you want to
          remove <quote>red eye</quote> from a photograph, you might work on
          the Red channel.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can look at channels as masks which allow or restrict the output
          of the color that the channel represents. By using Filters on the
          channel information, you can create many varied and subtle effects
          on an image. A simple example of using a Filter on the color
          channels is the
          <link linkend="gimp-filter-channel-mixer">Channel Mixer</link>
          filter.
        </para>
        <para>
          In addition to these channels, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also allows
          you to create other channels (or more correctly, Channel Masks),
          which are displayed in the lower part of the Channels dialog. You
          can create a <link linkend="gimp-channel-new">New Channel</link> or
          save a <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">selection to a
          channel (mask)</link>.
          See the glossary entry on
          <link linkend="glossary-masks">Masks</link> for more information
          about Channel Masks.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Selections</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Often when modifying an image, you only want a part of the image
          to be affected. The <quote>selection</quote>
          mechanism makes this possible. Each image has its own selection,
          which you normally see as a moving dashed line separating the
          selected parts from the unselected parts (the so-called
          <link linkend="glossary-marching-ants"><quote>marching ants</quote></link>).
          Actually this is a bit misleading: selection in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          is graded, not all-or-nothing, and really the selection is
          represented by a full-fledged grayscale channel. The dashed line
          that you normally see is simply a contour line at the 50&percnt;-selected
          level. At any time, though, you can visualize the selection channel
          in all its glorious detail by toggling the
          <link linkend="gimp-image-window-quick-mask-button">Quick Mask</link>
          button.
        </para>
        <para>
          A large component of learning how to use <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          effectively is acquiring the art of making good
          selections—selections that contain exactly what you need and nothing
          more. Because selection-handling is so centrally important,
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> provides many tools for doing
          it: an assortment of selection-making tools, a menu of selection
          operations, and the ability to switch to Quick Mask mode, in which
          you can treat the selection channel as though it were a color
          channel, thereby <quote>painting the selection</quote>.
          For more information, see also
          <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">The Selection</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Undoing</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When you make mistakes, you can undo them. Nearly everything you can
          do to an image is undoable. In fact, you can usually undo a
          substantial number of the most recent things you did, if you decide
          that they were misguided. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes this
          possible by keeping a history of your actions. This history consumes
          memory, though, so undoability is not infinite. Some actions use
          very little undo memory, so that you can do dozens of them before
          the earliest ones are deleted from this history; other types of
          actions require massive amounts of undo memory.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can configure
          the amount of memory <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows for the undo
          history of each image, but in any situation, you should always be
          able to undo at least your 2-3 most recent actions. The most
          important action that is not undoable is closing an image. For this
          reason, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> asks you to confirm that you really
          want to close the image if you have made any changes to it.
          For more information, see also
          <link linkend="gimp-concepts-undo">Undoing</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Plug-ins</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A lot of the things that you do to an image in
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> are done by <acronym>GIMP</acronym> itself.
          However, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also makes
          extensive use of <quote>plug-ins</quote>, which are external programs
          that interact very closely with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, and are
          capable of manipulating images and other <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          objects in very sophisticated ways. Many important plug-ins are
          bundled with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but there are also
          many available by other means. In fact, writing
          plug-ins (and scripts) is the easiest way for people not on the
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> development team to add new capabilities to
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
        </para>
        <para>
          All of the commands in the Filters menu, and a substantial number of
          commands in other menus, are actually implemented as plug-ins.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Scripts</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In addition to plug-ins, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can also make use of
          scripts. Scripts are written in a language called Script-Fu, which
          is unique to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (for those who care, it is a
          dialect of the Lisp-like language called Scheme).
          In the past there was a clear distinction between scripts and
          plug-ins, but that is disappearing. Depending on which Script-Fu
          interpreter you use, Scheme scripts can also be installed as
          plug-ins.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>
