<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-05-28 Fixed Auto Follow Active Image by j.h
  2005-12-18 reviewed by lexa
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-concepts-docks">
  <title>Dialogs and Docking</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Docking</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Docking</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dockable-dock-bars">
    <title>Organizing Dialogs</title>

    <!-- It's not clear whether these two anchors are still being used,
         but for now let's just add them to this general part of the
         docks documentation.
    -->
    <anchor id="gimp-dock"/>
    <anchor id="gimp-dock-close"/>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has great flexibility for arranging dialogs on
      your screen. A <quote>dialog</quote> is a moving window which
      contains options for a tool or is dedicated to a special task. A
      <quote>dock</quote> is a container which can hold a collection of
      persistent dialogs, such as the Tool Options dialog, Brushes dialog,
      Palette dialog, etc. Docks cannot, however, hold non-persistent dialogs
      such as the Preferences dialog or the image window.
    </para>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has three default docks:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            the Tool Options, Device Status, Undo History and Images dock
            under the Toolbox in the left panel,
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            the Brushes, Patterns, Fonts and Document History dock in the upper part of the
            right panel,
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            the Layers, Channels and Paths dock in the lower part of the
            right panel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      In these docks, each dialog is in its own tab.
    </para>
    <para>
      In multi-window mode, the Toolbox is a <emphasis>utility
      window</emphasis> and not a dock. In single-window mode, it belongs to
      the single window.
    </para>
    <para>
      Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      to view a list of dockable dialogs. Select a dockable dialog from
      the list to view the dialog. If the dialog is available in a dock,
      then it is made visible. If the dialog is not in a dock, the behavior
      is different in multi and single window modes:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In multi-window mode, a new window, containing the dialog, appears
            on the screen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In single-window mode, the dialog is automatically docked to the
            Brushes-Document History dock as a tab.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      You can click-and-drag a tab and drop it in the wanted place:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            either in the tab bar of a dock, to integrate it in the dialog
            group,
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            or on a docking bar that appears as a blue line when the mouse     
            pointer goes over a dock border, to anchor the dialog to the dock.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      In multi-window mode, you can also click on the dialog title and drag it
      to the wanted place.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>Integrating a new dialog in a dialog group</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/dock-integrate-dialog.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Here, in multi-window mode, the Histogram dialog was dragged to the
            tab bar of the Layers-Undo dock.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      More simple: the <command>Add tab</command> command in the Tab menu <xref
      linkend="gimp-dockable-menu"/>.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>Anchoring a dialog to a dock border</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/dock-anchor-dialog.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The Histogram dialog dragged to the left vertical docking bar of
            the right panel and the result: the dialog anchored to
            the left border of the right panel. This dialog now belongs to the
            right panel.
          </para>
          <para>
            So, you can arrange dialogs in a <emphasis>multi-column</emphasis>
            display, interesting if you work with two screens, one for dialogs,
            the other for images.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <tip>
      <para>
        Press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key in the image window to toggle the
        visibility of the docks. This is useful if the docks hide a portion
        of the image window. You can quickly hide all the docks,
        do your work, then display all the docks again.
        Press the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key inside a dock to navigate
        through the dock.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dockable-menu">
    <title>Tab Menu</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Docks</primary>
      <secondary>Tab menu</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-menu"/>
    <para>
      In each dialog, you can access a special menu of tab-related operations by
      pressing the Tab Menu button
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-menu-left.svg"
              contentwidth="16px"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
      The exact commands shown in the menu depend on the active dialog, but
      they always include operations for creating new tabs, closing or
      detaching tabs.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The Tab menu of the Layers dialog.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/tab-menu.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Multi-window mode</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/tab-menu-single-window-mode.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Single-window mode</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The Tab menu gives you access to the following commands:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Context Menu</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Context Menu</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            At the top of each Tab menu, an entry opens the
            dialog's context menu, which contains operations specific to that
            particular type of dialog. For example, the context menu for the
            Layers tab is <guilabel>Layers Menu</guilabel>, which contains
            a set of operations for manipulating layers.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-add">
        <term>Add Tab</term>
        <listitem>
          <!--anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-add"/-->
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Add Tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Add Tab</guilabel> opens into a submenu allowing you to
            add a large variety of dockable dialogs as new tabs.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title><quote>Add tab</quote> submenu</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/using/tab-menu-add-tab.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-close">
        <term>Close Tab</term>
        <listitem>
          <!--anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-close"/-->
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Close tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Close the dockable dialog. Closing the last dialog in a dock
            causes the dock itself to close.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-detach">
        <term>Detach Tab</term>
        <listitem>
          <!--anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-detach"/-->
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Detach tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Detach the dialog from the dock, creating a new dock
            with the detached dialog as its only member. It has the same
            effect as dragging the tab out of the dock and releasing it at a
            location where it cannot be docked.
          </para>
          <para>
            It's a way to create a paradoxical new window in single-window mode!
          </para>
          <para>
            If the tab is <link linkend="gimp-dock-tab-lock">locked</link>,
            this menu item is disabled.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-lock">
        <term>Lock Tab to Dock</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Lock tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Prevent the dialog from being moved or detached. When activated,
            <guimenuitem>Detach Tab</guimenuitem> is disabled.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-preview-size">
        <term>Preview Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Previews</primary>
            <secondary>Tab preview size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Layer</primary>
            <secondary>Preview size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Preview size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Many, but not all, dialogs have Tab menus containing a
            <guilabel>Preview Size</guilabel>
            option, which opens a submenu giving a list of sizes for the
            items in the dialog, from small to large.
            For example, the Brushes dialog shows pictures of all available
            brushes: the Preview Size determines how large the pictures are.
            The default is <guilabel>Medium</guilabel> size.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-style">
        <term>Tab Style</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Tab style</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Tab Style</guilabel> opens a submenu allowing you to
            choose the appearance of the tabs at the top. There are five
            choices, but not all are enabled for every dialog:
          </para>
          <para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Icon</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Use an icon to represent the dialog type.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Current Status</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Is only available for dialogs that allows you
                    to select something, such as a brush, pattern,
                    gradient, etc. <guilabel>Current Status</guilabel>
                    shows a representation of the currently selected
                    item in the tab top.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Text</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Use text to display the dialog type.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Icon and Text</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Using both an icon and text results in wider tabs.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Status and Text</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Show the currently selected item and text with the dialog
                    type.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-view-as-list">
        <term>View as List</term>
        <term>View as Grid</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-dock-view-as-grid" xreflabel="View as Grid"/>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>View as List/Grid</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm><primary>List search field</primary></indexterm>
          <para>
            These entries are shown in dialogs that allow you to select an
            item from a set: brushes, patterns, fonts, etc. You can choose
            to view the items as a vertical list, with the name of
            each beside it, or as a grid, with representations of the items
            but no names. Each has its advantages: viewing as a list gives you
            more information, but viewing as a grid allows you to see
            more possibilities at once. The default for this varies across
            dialogs: for brushes and patterns, the default is a grid; for most
            other things, the default is a list.
          </para>

          <para>
            When the tree-view is <guilabel>View as List</guilabel>, you can
            use tags. Please see <xref linkend="gimp-tagging"/>.
          </para>
          
          <para>
            You can also use a list search field:
            <figure>
              <title>The list search field.</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                            fileref="images/using/list-search-field.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    Press
                    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo>
                    to open the list search field, displayed at the bottom.
                    An item must be selected for this command to be effective.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </para>
          <para>
            The list search field automatically closes after five seconds
            if you do nothing.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              The search field shortcut is also available for the tree-view you
              get in the <quote>Brush</quote>, <quote>Font</quote> or
              <quote>Pattern</quote> option of several tools.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-show-button-bar">
        <term>Show Button Bar</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Some dialogs display a button bar on the bottom of the dialog; for
            example, the Patterns, Brushes, Gradients, and Images dialogs.
            This is a toggle. If it is checked, then the Button Bar is
            displayed.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Button Bar on the Brushes dialog.</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                            fileref="images/using/dialog-button-bar.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-image-menu">
        <term>Show Image Selection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option is available in multi-window mode only.
            This is a toggle. If it is checked, then the active image is shown
            at the top of the dock:
            <figure id="figure-highlight-imagemenu">
              <title>A dock with the Image Menu highlighted.</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/dialog-highlight-imagemenu.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            It is not available for dialogs docked below the Toolbox. This
            option is interesting only if you have several open images on your
            screen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-auto-button">
        <term>Auto Follow Active Image</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option is available in multi-window mode only.
            This option is also interesting only if you have several images
            open on your screen. Then, the information displayed in a dock
            is always that of the selected image in the Image Selection
            drop-down list. If the <guilabel>Auto Follow Active Image
            </guilabel> is disabled, the image can be selected only in the
            Image Selection. If enabled, you  can also select it by
            activating the image directly (clicking on its title bar).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

<!-- DOCUMENTATION WRITERS: Compare with gimp-view-change-screen -->
      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-change-screen">
        <term>Move to Screen</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The option <guimenuitem>Open Display…</guimenuitem> is an
            experimental functionality to choose a different display.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
