<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	            "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-01-28 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-08-13 added norwegian translation by KoSt 
  2006-07-24 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-12 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-05 lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant
  2006-01-06 HdJ: Added dutch translation, replaced some " by " 
                  and added empty lines between the markup tags of
                  succesive translations.   
  2005-11-28 lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-concepts-text" lang="cs;de;es;en;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="de;es;fr;ko;nl;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-04</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-28</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision : 1.23 $</revnumber>
        <date>2006-04-02</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-05-12</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="nl">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-04-30</date>
        <authorinitials>HdJ</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-09-04</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Text and Fonts</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Text a písma</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Text und Schriftarten</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Texto y tipografías</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Texte et Polices</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Testo e caratteri</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">텍스트와 폰트</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Tekst en lettertype's</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Tekst og teikn</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">文字和字体</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Текст и шрифты</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Fonts and Texts</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>obrázek</primary>
    <secondary>text</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Textos y tipografías</primary>
    <secondary>Generalidades</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Textes et Polices</primary>
    <secondary>Généralités</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>폰트와 텍스트</primary>
    <secondary>개략</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Caratteri e testo</primary>
    <secondary>Panoramica</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>Afbeelding</primary>
    <secondary>Tekst</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Bilete</primary>
    <secondary>Tekst</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Текст и шрифты</primary>
    <secondary>Обзор</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>图像</primary>
    <secondary>文字</secondary>
  </indexterm>  

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">Example of a text item</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Beispiel eines Textelementes</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo de un elemento de texto</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Exemple d'un élément Texte</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Esempio di testo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">텍스트 아이템 예제</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Voorbeeld van een tektvoorwerp</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på bruk av tekstelement</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Пример текста</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/text-example.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Example of a text item, showing the boundary of the text layer.
          (Font: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Ukázka textové položky se zobrazenou hranicí textové vrstvy. (Písmo:
          Utopia Bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Ein Beispieltext mit gut sichtbarer Textebene (die Schriftart ist
          Utopia fett)
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Aquí se pueden ver los contornos de la capa de texto (tipografía
          empleada: Utopia Bold).
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Exemple de Texte, montrant les limites du calque de texte. (Police :
          Utopia bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Esempio di una voce di testo che mostra il bordo del livello testo
          (tipo di carattere: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="ko"> 
          텍스트 레이어의 경계가 표시된 텍스트 아이템 예제이다.(폰트: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="nl">
          Voorbeeld van een tekst onderdeel met daaromheen de grens van de
          tekstlaag aangegeven (Lettertype: "Utopia Bold" (Bold=Vet))
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Tekst med synlege kantar rundt tekstlaget. (Skrifttype: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Пример текста, показана граница текстового слоя. (Шрифт: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">一个文本例子，显示文字图层的边缘。(字体：Utopia Bold)</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    One of the greatest improvements of GIMP 2.0 over GIMP 1.2 is in the
    handling of text. In GIMP 2.0 and 2.2, each text item goes in a separate
    Text layer, and you can come back later to the layer and edit the text in
    it. You can also move the text around in the image, or change the font, or
    the font size. You can use any font available on your system. You can
    control justification, indentation, and line spacing.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Jedno z největších vylepšení GIMPu řady 2 oproti předchozím verzím se
    týkalo práce s textem. V GIMPu 2.0 a 2.2 je každá textová položka umístěna
    v samostatné textové vrstvě, ke které se kdykoliv můžete vrátit a
    upravovat ji. Text můžete v obrázku libovolně přesouvat, měnit řez písma
    nebo jeho velikost. Použít můžete libovolný řez písma dostupný ve vašem
    systému. Můžete nastavit zarovnání textu, odsazení a rozestup řádků.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Eine der wichtigsten Weiterentwicklungen von GIMP Version 1.2 zu GIMP2 ist
    die Arbeit mit Text. Jedes Textelement in GIMP wird in einer Ebene
    abgelegt, und Sie können den Text einer solchen Ebene auch später noch
    ändern. Sie können den Text im Bild herumschieben, die Schriftart und die
    Schriftgröße ändern. Sie können jede auf Ihrem Computer vorhandene
    Schriftart verwenden und darüber hinaus sowohl die Textausrichtung als
    auch den Zeilenabstand einstellen.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Una de las mejoras más importantes de la versión 2.0 del GIMP con respecto
    a la versión 1.0 es la gestión de texto.  En el GIMP 2.0 y 2.2, cada
    elemento de texto va por separado en una capa especial de texto.  Luego de
    haber sido creada, su texto se puede volver a editar.  Además, puede
    desplazar el texto por la imagen, cambiar su tipografía, o su tamaño.
    Puede emplear cualquier tipografía disponible en su sistema, y dispone de
    controles para la justificación, el sangrado, y el espaciado de línea.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Une des plus importantes améliorations de GIMP-2.0 par rapport à GIMP-1.2
    est sa façon de gérer les textes. Maintenant, chaque texte va dans un
    calque séparé, et vous pouvez revenir au calque par la suite pour en
    éditer le texte. Vous pouvez aussi déplacer le texte dans l'image, ou
    changer de police ou de taille de police. Vous pouvez utiliser toutes les
    polices présentes sur votre système. Vous pouvez contrôler la
    justification, l'indentation et l'espacement des lignes.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Uno dei più grandi miglioramenti di GIMP 2.0 rispetto a GIMP 1.2 è
    nella gestione del testo. Da GIMP 2.0 in poi, ogni elemento di testo
    finisce in un livello di testo separato, sul quale è possibile
    ritornare a modificare il testo immasso. È possibile anche spostare il
    testo rispetto all'immagine o cambiarne il tipo di carattere o la
    dimensione. È possibile usare qualsiasi tipo di carattere disponibile
    sul proprio sistema oltre che impostare la giustificazione,
    l'indentazione e la spaziatura delle righe di testo.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    김프가 1.2에서 2.0으로 업데이트되면서 가장 크게 달라진 부분은 텍스트에
    관한 부분이다. 김프 2.0 과 2.2 에서 텍스트 아이템은 각기 독립적인 
    레이어에 위치하게 된다. 그리고 그 레이어 위에서 텍스트를 편집하거나,
    움직이거나, 폰트나 폰트 사이즈를 변경하는 등의 작업을 하게 된다.
    시스템에 있는 폰트는 전부 사용할 수 있으며, 좌우맞추기, 들여쓰기, 줄간격
    조정 등도 할 수 있다.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    Een van de voornaamste verbeteringen die er bij de overgang van
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-1.2 naar <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.0 hebben
    plaatsgevonden is hoe het prgramma met tekst omgaat. In
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.x wordt er voor ieder tekstobject een eigen
    laag gemaakt. Later kunt u in deze laag ook nog wijzigingen in de tekst
    aanbrengen of de grootte veranderen, verplaatsen, lettertype veranderen.
    U kunt ieder lettertype die in uw systeem beschikbaar is gebruiken en ook
    de uitlijning, inspringen en de regelafstanden instellen.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Ei av dei store forbetringane som kom med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 er
    handteringa av tekst. Frå <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 og utover blir kvar
    tekst lagt i eit eige tekstlag slik at du kan kome tilbake seinare for å
    redigera det du har skrive. Du kan også flytte rundt på teksten, forandra
    storleik, skrifttype eller oppfylle andre typografiske innfall du måtte
    få.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Одно из наибольших улучшений GIMP 2.0 в сравнении с GIMP 1.2 заключается 
    в обработке текста. В GIMP 2.0 и GIMP 2.2 каждый текстовый элемент 
    находится в отдельном текстовом слое, и вернувшись к с обработке слоя 
    позже, вы можете изменить текст в нём. Также вы можете перемещать 
    текст по изображению, или изменять шрифт, или размер шрифта. Вы 
    можете использовать любой шрифт, доступный в вашей системе. 
    Вы можете контролировать выравнивание, отступ, и межстрочный интервал.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    从 GIMP 1.2 到 GIMP 2.0，一个最大的进步就在处理文字。GIMP 2.0 和 2.2 中，
    每个文本都有自己独立的文字图层，以后可以通过该图层来编辑其中的文字，还可
    以在图像中移动文字，改变字体及其大小。您可以使用系统中可用的任何字体，控
    制其对齐，缩进和行距。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    Actually, you can operate on a text layer in the same ways as any other
    layer, but doing so often means giving up the ability to edit the text
    without losing the results of your work.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    S textovou vrstvou můžete provádět stejné operace jako s kteroukoliv jinou
    vrstvou, některé takové operace však znemožňují další úpravy textu
    (respektive je umožňují jen za cenu ztráty výsledků těchto operací).
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Sie können Textebenen auch in ganz normale Ebenen überführen, dann ist es
    jedoch nicht mehr möglich, den Text als solches zu verändern. Sie müssten
    dann alle Veränderungen auf Pixelebene vornehmen.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    En realidad, puede operar sobre una capa de texto de la misma forma en que
    opera sobre cualquier otra capa, pero al hacerlo es posible que pierda la
    capacidad de editar su texto sin que se pierdan las modificaciones que ha
    efectuado.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    En fait, vous pouvez opérer sur un calque de texte comme vous le faites
    avec les autres calques, mais au risque d'abandonner la possibilité
    d'éditer le texte sans perdre le résultat de votre travail.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Actually, you can operate on a text layer in the same ways as any other
    layer, but doing so often means giving up the ability to edit the text
    without losing the results of your work.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    사실 텍스트 레이어도 다른 레이어와 똑같다. 다만 기존의 작업들에 영향을
    주지 않는 상태로 텍스트를 편집할 수 있다라는 것뿐이다.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    U kunt ook iedere andere bewerking die u op andere lagen uit kunt voeren
    op een tekst uitvoeren, maar vaak betekent dit dat u daarna de tekst zelf
    niet meer kunt wijzigen.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Du kan gjere det same med eit tekstlag som du kan gjere med andre
    lag, men mister i noen tilfelle høvet til å kunna redigera vidare på
    teksten. 
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Фактически вы можете производить такие же операции на текстовом слое, 
    как и на любых других слоях, но поступая таким образом, вы теряете 
    возможность редактирования текста без потери результатов вашей работы. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    实际上，您能像其它图层一样操作文字图层，不过这样做通常意谓着放弃编辑文字
    的能力而不会丢失您所工作的结果。
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">GIMP text editor</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Der GIMP-Texteditor</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">El editor de textos del GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">L'Éditeur de texte GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">L'editor dei testi di GIMP</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">김프 텍스트 편집기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">De GIMP tekstbewerker</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Tekstbehandlaren</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Редактор текста в GIMP</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;es;ru;zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ko">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ko/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="nl">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/nl/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-dialog-text.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    To understand some of the idiosyncrasies of text handling, it may help for
    you to realize that a text layer contains more information than the pixel
    data that you see: it also contains a representation of the text in a
    text-editor format. You can see this in the text-editor window that pops
    up while you are using the Text tool. Every time you alter the text, the
    image layer is redrawn to reflect your changes.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    K pochopení specifik manipulace s textem je dobré si uvědomit, že textová
    vrstva obsahuje více informací, než pouhé údaje o viditelných pixelech:
    obsahuje text ve formátu čitelném textovým editorem. Vidíte to v okně
    textového editoru, které se otevře při práci s textovým nástrojem.
    Kdykoliv text změníte, vrstva se podle jeho nového znění překreslí.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Um die Eigenheiten des Umganges mit Text in GIMP besser zu verstehen,
    hilft es möglicherweise sich vor Augen zu halten, dass Textebenen ganz
    andere Informationen beinhalten als normale Ebenen, welche ausschließlich
    aus Pixeln zusammengesetzt sind. In Textebenen muss zusätzlich der Text in
    Textformat, zusammen mit all den Informationen über Schriftart, Größe,
    Ausrichtung und so weiter, verwaltet werden. Sie können dies im Texteditor
    sehen, welcher sich öffnet, wenn Sie das Textwerkzeug benutzen. Jedes Mal,
    wenn Sie den Text verändern, wird die Bildebene neu gezeichnet, um Ihre
    Änderungen widerzuspiegeln. Weitere Informationen zum Textwerkzeug finden
    Sie im <xref linkend="gimp-tool-text" />.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Para comprender algunas de las idiosincracias de la manipulación de texto,
    puede ayudar saber que una capa de texto contiene más información que los
    datos de píxeles que muestra.  Además contiene una representación en forma
    de texto.  Puede verla en la ventana del editor de texto, que aparece
    cuando emplea esta herramienta.  Cada vez que altere el texto, la capa de
    la imagen que lo contiene se vuelve a dibujar para reflejar los cambios.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Pour comprendre certaines des particularités de la gestion des textes,
    vous devez savoir qu'un calque de texte contient plus d'information que sa
    simple composition en pixels : il contient aussi une représentation du
    texte comme dans un éditeur de texte. Vous pouvez vous en rendre compte
    dans la fenêtre d'édition du texte qui apparaît quand vous utilisez
    l'outil Texte : chaque fois que vous modifiez le texte, l'image du calque
    est redessinée pour refléter vos changements.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Per aiutare a capire alcune delle idiosincrasie della gestione del
    testo è necessario comprendere che un livello di testo contiene molte
    più informazioni di quelle che mostrano i dati del pixel visualizzati:
    vi è contenuta anche una rappresentazione del testo che normalmente
    viene memorizzata in un formato dati di testo. È facile comprendere
    questo fatto osservando attentamente la finestra di modifica del testo
    che salta in primo piano quando si usa lo strumento di
    testo. Ogniqualvolta si altera il testo, il livello immagine viene
    ridisegnato per riflettere i cambiamenti effettuati.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    텍스트 처리의 특징에 대해 이해하려면, 텍스트 레이어에 눈에 보이는 픽셀외의
    다른 정보가 상당수 포함되어 있음을 이해하면 된다. 또 텍스트 편집기에서의
    텍스트 표현에 관한 정보도 포함하고 있는데, 이것은 텍스트 도구를 사용할 때
    뜨는 텍스트 편집기에서 볼 수 있다. 그리고 텍스트를 고치는 매순간 이미지
    레이어는 그 변한 값을 반영한다.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    Enkele eigenaardigheden in de omgang met teksten komen voort uit het feit
    dat een tekstlaag meer informatie bevat dan er wordt gegeven door de
    beeldpunten die u in de afbeelding, op het scherm ziet. Een laag bevat ook
    de tekst informatie als letters die met een tekstbewerker te veranderen
    zijn. De teksteweergave verschijnt in een apart bewerkingsschermpje dat
    verschijnt als u met het tekstgereedschap bezig bent. Telkens als u iets
    aan de tekst wijzigt wordt de afbeeldingslaag opnieuw getekend on het
    effect van de verandering te tonen.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    For å forstå noe av det særeigne med tekstbehandlinga, kan det vere til
    litt hjelp å hugsa på at tekstlaget inneheld meir informasjon enn bare
    det du kan sjå. Laget inneheld også ei utgåve av teksten i eit format
    som kan høve til redigering. Dette blir synleg i redigeringsvindauget
    som dukkar opp når du bruker tekstverktøyet. Kvar gong du gjer endringar
    i teksten, blir tekstlaget teikna om for å vise endringane dine. 
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Понимание некоторых особенностей управления текстом дает вам представление 
    о том, что текстовый слой содержит больше информации, чем просто набор 
    пикселей, которые вы видите: также он содержит представление текста 
    в формате текстового редактора. Вы можете это видеть в всплывающем 
    окне редактирования текста, которое появляется при выборе инструмента 
    "Текст". Каждый раз при изменении текста, изображение слоя перерисовывается 
    для отражения сделанных вами изменений. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    要理解文字处理的一些特性，先要认识到一个文字图层比您所看到的像素数据要包
    含更多的信息：它还包括表现为文本编辑器格式的文字，在使用文字工具弹出的文
    本编辑器窗口中可以看到。每当您修改文本时，图像图层都重画并反映出这些变化。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    Now suppose you create a text layer, and then operate on it in some way
    that does not involve the Text tool: rotate it, for example. Suppose you
    then come back and try to edit it using the Text tool. As soon as you edit
    the text, the Text tool will redraw the layer, wiping out the results of
    the operations you performed in the meantime.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Nyní si představte, že vytvoříte textovou vrstvu, ale pak s ní provedete
    operaci jinak, než pomocí textového nástroje, například ji otočíte.
    Jakmile pak text upravíte, textový nástroj vrstvu překreslí, čímž zahodí
    výsledky všech operací, které jste s vrstvou v mezičase provedli.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Nehmen wir einmal an, Sie erzeugen eine Textebene und bearbeiten die Ebene
    dann auf eine Weise, die nichts mit dem Text zu tun hat. Beispielsweise
    könnten Sie die Ebene drehen. Wenn Sie nun wiederum den Text der Ebene
    bearbeiten, so wird dieser neu in die Ebene gezeichnet und zerstört das
    Ergebnis der in der Zwischenzeit durchgeführten Bearbeitungsschritte.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Ahora suponga que crea una capa de texto, y luego realiza operaciones
    sobre ella que no implican a esta herramienta, como por ejemplo rotarla.
    Si vuelve a editarla con la herramienta de texto, la capa se vuelve a
    dibujar, reemplazando las modificaciones que ha hecho entremedio.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Maintenant, supposons que vous créiez un calque de texte, puis que vous
    agissiez sur lui autrement qu'avec l'outil Texte, en appliquant une
    rotation par exemple. Si vous essayez alors d'éditer à nouveau ce texte
    avec l'outil Texte, cet outil redessinera le calque, effaçant le résultat
    des opérations que vous avez effectuées entre temps.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Ora supponiamo che si crei un livello di testo e che si voglia operare
    su di esso senza passare attraverso lo strumento di testo, ruotando il
    testo ad esempio... Supponiamo che in seguito si voglia tornare sul
    testo e modificarlo con lo strumento di testo. Non appena si tenta di
    modificare il testo, lo strumento di testo ridisegnerà il livello,
    eliminando il risultato delle operazioni effettuate successivemente
    all'ultimo uso dello strumento testo.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    이제 텍스트 레이어를 하나 만들었다고 가정하고, 텍스트 도구 외의 다른 
    작업을 해보자. 예를 들어 회전시키기. 그런 후에 다시  텍스트 도구로 
    텍스트를 수정하면 그 전에 작업한 결과들을 무시하고 새롭게 고쳐진 텍스트가
    텍스트 레이어에 기록되게 된다.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">

    Als u een tekstlaag gemaakt hebt en er een bewerking op uitvoert die niet
    met het tekst gereedschap te doen is; roteren bijvoorbeeld. Als u daarna
    een verandering in de tekst maakt met het tekstgereedschap, wordt de tekst
    van daar uit weer opnieuw getekend en het resultaat van de rotatie wordt
    dan teniet gedaan.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Dersom du gjer endringar i tekstlaget med andre verktøy enn
    tekstbehandlaren, for eksempel at du roterer laget, vil desse endringane
    forsvinna dersom du redigerer teksten igjen. Difor dukkar det opp ei
    åtvaring om dette dersom det er aktuelt slik at du kan velja anten å
    redigere teksten likevel, eller å la det vere. Dessutan får du tilbod om
    å lage eit nytt tekstlag for den nye teksten.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Теперь предположим, что вы создали текстовый слой и затем произвели 
    над ним некоторые операции, не включающее в себя использование инструмента 
    "Текст": к примеру, поворот слоя. Предположим, затем вы вернулись обратно 
    к редактированию слоя с помощью инструмента "Текст". После того, как 
    вы завершите редактировать текст, инструмент перерисует слой, удалив 
    результат предыдущего действия.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    现在假设新建一个文字图层，然后用文字工具外的操作对它进行处理：比如旋转它。
    然后打算再用文字工具编辑它。一旦您编辑了文本，文字工具就会重画图层，清除
    此间所作的所有操作。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    Because this danger is not obvious, the Text tool tries to protect you
    from it. If you operate on a text layer, and then later try to edit the
    text, a message pops up, warning you that your alterations will be undone,
    and giving you three options: (1) edit the text anyway; (2) cancel; (3)
    create a new text layer with the same text as the existing layer, leaving
    the existing layer unchanged.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Protože toto nebezpečí není zcela samozřejmé, snaží se vás na něj textový
    nástroj upozornit. Pokud provedete na vrstvě úpravy a pak se snažíte
    editovat text, objeví se varovná zpráva upozorňující na hrozící ztrátu
    provedených změn a nabízející tři možnosti: (1) Úpravy – upravovat text i
    za cenu ztráty úprav ve vrstvě; (2) Zrušit; (3) Nový – vytvořit novou
    textovou vrstvu se stejným textem, jako má vrstva stávající, a ponechat
    stávající vrstvu beze změn.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Da diese Gefahr nicht offensichtlich ist, versucht das Textwerkzeug, Sie
    davor zur beschützen. Wenn Sie auf einer Textebene arbeiten und später
    versuchen, den Text weiter zu bearbeiten, wird ein Dialogfenster angezeigt,
    welches Sie warnt und Ihnen anbietet, entweder den Text trotzdem zu
    bearbeiten, die Aktion abzubrechen oder eine neue Textebene mit dem Text
    der bereits vorhandenen Textebene anzulegen und diese unverändert zu
    belassen.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Dado que este peligro no es aparentemente obvio, la herramienta de texto
    le advierte de lo que va a suceder.  Si Ud. modifica la capa de texto y
    luego vuelve a editarla con esta herramienta, surje un mensaje, pidiéndole
    la confirmación de su acción.  Hay tres opciones: (1) editar el texto; (2)
    cancelar; (3) crear una nueva capa que contenga el mismo texto que la capa
    existente, conservando la capa existente como está.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Parce que ce danger n'est pas évident, l'outil Texte cherche à vous en
    protéger. Si vous essayez de travailler sur un calque de texte et
    qu'ensuite vous essayez d'éditer le texte, un message apparaît,vous
    avertissant que vos modifications vont être annulées, et vous offrant
    trois options : (1) éditer le texte de toute façon ; (2) annuler ; (3) créer

    un nouveau calque de texte avec le même texte que celui sur lequel vous
    avez travaillé.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Dato che la pericolosità dell'operazione non è ovvia, lo strumento di
    testo cerca di proteggerci da essa. Se si lavora su un livello di testo
    e successivamente si tenta di modificare il testo, un messaggio salta
    in primo piano avvertendo l'utente che le alterazioni verranno
    eliminate dandoci tre possibilità: (1) modificare comunque il testo;
    (2) annullare; (3) creare un nuovo livello di testo con lo stesso testo
    come nel livello esistente, lasciando il livello esistente immodificato.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    하지만 이러한 위험은 드러나있지 않기 때문에 텍스트 도구에서는 경고창을
    내보내며 세 가지 선택을 보여준다. (1)무시하고 편집하기; (2)취소; 
    (3)기존 레이어를 바꾸지 않고, 기존 레이어에 있는 텍스트와 똑같은 텍스트
    새로만들기
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    Omdat dit risico niet zo duidelijk is probeert het tekstgereedschap u te
    behoeden voor dit soort fouten. Als u een bewerking op een tekstlaag
    uitvoert en later de tekst wilt wijzigen, verschijnt er eerst een
    berichtscherm dat met het wijzigen van de tekst alle voorgaande
    bewerkingen teniet gedaan worden. Het scherm geeft u drie mogelijkheden om
    op dit risico te reageren: (1) De tekst tòch wijzigen, (2) Annuleren, (3)
    een nieuwe laag met dezelfde tekst aanmaken en de huidige ongewijzigd
    laten.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Поскольку эта опасность неочевидна, инструмент "Текст" пытается 
    защитить вас от неё. Если вы проводите операции на текстовом слое, 
    и затем позже пытаетесь редактировать текст, возникнет всплывающее 
    сообщение, предупреждающее о том, изменения будут отменены, и вам 
    будет предложено три варианта: (1) создать новый текстовый слой с 
    текстом существующего слоя, оставив существующий слой неизмененным. 
    (2) отмена; (3) всё равно редактировать текст; <!--поменял местами 
    п. 1 и 3 в соотв. с интерфейсом-->
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    由于这种危险不明显，文字工具避免您这样做。对文字图层操作后再尝试编辑它时，
    会弹出一条警告信息，告诉您所作的修改会被恢复原状，并给您三个选项：(1)强
    行编辑;(2)取消;(3)新建一个与现有图层有相同文本的文字图层，而保持现有图层
    不变。
  </para>

</sect2>
