<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-01-28 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-08-13 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-24 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-12 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-05 lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant
  2006-01-06 HdJ: Added dutch translation, replaced some " by "
                  and added empty lines between the markup tags of
                  succesive translations.
  2005-11-28 lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-text">
  <title>Text and Fonts</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Fonts and Texts</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Example of a text item</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/text-example.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Example of a text item, showing the boundary of the text layer.
          (Font: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Text tool is progressively improved.
    One of the greatest improvements of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 over
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2 is in the
    handling of text. In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 and 2.2, each text item
    goes in a separate
    Text layer, and you can come back later to the layer and edit the text in
    it. You can also move the text around in the image, or change the font, or
    the font size. You can use any font available on your system. You can
    control justification, indentation, and line spacing.
  </para>
  <para>
    With <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.6, you can draw a bounding box (a
    rectangular frame) for the text on your image and you can adjust this
    rectangle in the same way as a rectangular selection. The text goes on
    being edited in the Text Editor, but it is automatically wrapped within
    this box.
  </para>
  <para>
    Actually, you can operate on a text layer in the same ways as any other
    layer, but doing so often means giving up the ability to edit the text
    without losing the results of your work.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>GIMP text editor</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/toolbox/tool-dialog-text.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    To understand some of the idiosyncrasies of text handling, it may help for
    you to realize that a text layer contains more information than the pixel
    data that you see: it also contains a representation of the text in a
    text-editor format. You can see this in the text-editor window that pops
    up while you are using the Text tool. Every time you alter the text, the
    image layer is redrawn to reflect your changes.
  </para>
  <para>
    Now suppose you create a text layer, and then operate on it in some way
    that does not involve the Text tool: rotate it, for example. Suppose you
    then come back and try to edit it using the Text tool. As soon as you edit
    the text, the Text tool will redraw the layer, wiping out the results of
    the operations you performed in the meantime.
  </para>
  <para>
    Because this danger is not obvious, the Text tool tries to protect you
    from it. If you operate on a text layer, and then later try to edit the
    text, a message pops up, warning you that your alterations will be undone,
    and giving you three options:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>edit the text anyway;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>cancel;</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        create a new text layer with the same text as the existing layer,
        leaving the existing layer unchanged.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <figure>
    <title>Warning lose modifications</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/text-warning.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</sect1>
