<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-concepts-gradients' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Přechody</title>
  <title lang="en">Gradients</title>
  <title lang="fr">Dégradés</title>  <!--050508-->
  <title lang="zh_CN">渐变</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="cs">Obrázek</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Přechody</secondary>
    <secondary lang="en">Gradients</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Dégradés</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">渐变</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Několik příkladů gimpích přechodů.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          Some examples of GIMP gradients.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Quelques exemples de dégradés Gimp.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          一些 GIMP 渐变的范例。
       </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='cs'>
    <emphasis>Přechod</emphasis> je sada barev uspořádaná za sebou.
    Nejtypičtějším využitím přechodů je použití nástroje <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Mísení</link>, též známého jako
    „Vyplňování přechodem“, který vyplní vybranou oblast barvami
    z přechodu. Nad způsobem použití barev z přechodu máte značnou
    kontrolu. Existují i další sůležité způsoby využití přechodů,
    například:
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>gradient</emphasis> is a set of colors arranged in a
    linear order.  The most basic use of gradients is by the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Blend tool</link>, sometimes known as
    the "gradient tool" or "gradient fill tool":  it works by filling
    the selection with colors from a gradient.  You have many options
    to choose from for controlling the way the gradient colors are
    arranged within the selection.   There are also other
    important ways to use gradients, including:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Un <emphasis>dégradé</emphasis> est un groupe de couleurs placées 
    dans un ordre linéaire. L'utilisation la plus simple des dégradés 
    est celle de l'outil <link linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>Blend tool
    </link> qui remplit une sélection avec un dégradé choisi et qui 
    possède de nombreuses options. Il y aussi deux autres façons 
    importantes d'utiliser les dégradés: 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一个<emphasis>渐变</emphasis>就是一系列线性排列的颜色。渐变最基本的使用是<link linkend='gimp-tool-blend'>渐变工具</link>，也被叫作“渐变填充工具”：它将一个渐变中的颜色填充的选区，有很多控制渐变颜色与选区排列方式的很多选项。还有其它多种使用渐变的方式，包括：
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="cs">Malování přechodem</term>
      <term lang="en">Painting with a gradient</term>
      <term lang="fr">Peindre avec un dégradé</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">用渐变涂画</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="cs">
          Každý ze základních kreslících nástrojů Gimpu umožňuje používat
          barvy z přechodu. Lze tak tvořit tahy štětcem, které mají na začátku
          jinou barvu, než na konci.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Each of GIMP's basic painting tools allows you the option of
          using colors from a gradient.  This enables you to create
          brushstrokes that change color from one end to the other.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Tous les outils de peinture possèdent l'option «Dégradé»: le 
          coup de pinceau changera de couleur tout au long de son tracé.
        </para> 
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          GIMP 中每个基本的涂画工具提供使用一个渐变中颜色的选项。这使您可以画出从一端到另一端改变颜色的笔划。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang='cs'>Filtr Mapování z přechodu</term>
      <term lang='en'>The Gradient Map filter</term>
      <term lang='fr'>Le filtre Application de dégradé</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">渐变映射滤镜</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento filtr umožňuje „obarvit“ obrázek v odstínech šedi nahrazením
          jednotlivých šedých tónů barvami z přechodu. Více se dozvíte v části
          <link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>Mapování z přechodu</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          This filter allows you to "colorize" a grayscale image, by
          replacing each shade of gray with the corresponding color from a
          gradient. See the <link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>Gradient
          Map</link> section for more information.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Ce filtre vous permet de colorier une image qui est en niveaux 
          de gris, en remplaçant chaque nuance de gris par la couleur 
          correspondante dans le dégradé choisi. Voyez la section 
          <link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>Application de dégradé</link>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该插件通过一个渐变中相应的颜色来替代每个灰色色度，允许您“单色化”一个灰度图像，请看<!--<link linkend='plug-in-gradmap'>渐变映射</link>-->以便获取更多信息。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Instalace Gimpu obsahuje velké množství pěkných a zajímavých přechodů,
    další si můžete sami vytvořit nebo stáhnout z Internetu. Všechny v Gimpu
    dostupné přechody se zobrazují v dokovatelném <link
    linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>dialogu Přechody</link>, který můžete
    otevírat pouze v případě potřeby nebo mít stále připravený jako odrážku v
    doku. Aktivní přechod používaný ve většině operací souvisejících s
    přechody se zobrazuje v indikační oblasti Panelu nástrojů. Kliknutím na
    ikonu přechodu v této části se otevře zmíněný dialog Přechody.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a large number of
    interesting gradients, and you can add new ones that you create or
    download from other sources.  You can access the full set of
    available gradients using the <link
    linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>Gradients dialog</link>, a dockable
    dialog that you can either activate when you need it, or keep
    around as a tab in a dock.  The "current gradient", used in most
    gradient-related operations, is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox.  Clicking on the
    gradient symbol in the Toolbox is an alternative way of bringing
    up the Gradients dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Quand vous installez Gimp, il est fourni avec un grand nombre de 
    dégradés intéressants, et vous pouvez en ajouter de nouveaux que 
    vous aurez créés ou téléchargés. Vous pouvez accéder aux dégradés 
    disponibles par le <link
    linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>Dialogue des dégradés</link>, un 
    dialogue attachable que vous pouvez appeler quand vous en avez 
    besoin ou que vous gardez à disposition en l'attachant sous forme 
    d'onglet à une fenêtre. Le «dégradé actif» est affiché dans l'aire 
    Brosse/Motif/Dégradé de la Boîte à outils. Cliquer sur le symbole 
    du dégradé actif dans la Boîte à outils est une autre façon 
    d'ouvrir la fenêtre du Dialogue des dégradés.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当您安装 Gimp 时，它已经自带了大量有趣的渐变，并且您可以自己创建或从其它地方下载来添加新的。可以用<link linkend='gimp-gradient-dialog'>渐变对话框</link>来显示所有可用的渐变，它是一个可停靠的对话框，您可以需要它是来打开它或放置它为一个停靠栏上的页签。显示在工具箱的画笔/图案/渐变区域的“当前渐变”在大多数有关渐变的操作中使用。点击工具箱的渐变标志则是另外一种唤出渐变对话框的方法。
  </para>   

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/gradient-usage.png'
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Čtyři způsoby použití přechodu Tropical colors (Tropické barvy):
          vyplnění lineárním přechodem, tvarovaným přechodem, tah nakreslený
          barvami z přechodu a tah nakreslený měkkým štětcem a pak vybarvený
          filtrem Mapování z přechodu.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          Four ways of using the Tropical Colors gradient:  a linear
          gradient fill, a 
          shaped gradient fill, a stroke painted using colors from
          a gradient, and a stroke painted with a fuzzy brush then
          colored using the Gradient Map filter.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Quatre manières d'utiliser le dégradé Tropical colors: un 
          remplissage linéaire par le dégradé, un remplissage en forme, 
          un coup de pinceau utilisant les couleurs du dégradé, un coup 
          de pinceau avec une brosse floue colorée ensuite en utilisant 
          le filtre Application de Dégradé. 
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          四种使用 Tropical Colors 渐变的方法：线性渐变填充，形状渐变填充，用模糊画笔涂画和使用渐变映射滤镜着色。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Užitečné poznatky o přechodech v Gimpu.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    A few useful things to know about GIMP's gradients:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Quelques points utiles à connaître à propos des dégradés Gimp:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一些对了解 GIMP 渐变有用的东西：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang='cs'>
        První čtyřui přechody zobrazené v dailogu Přechody jsou zvláštní,
        protože používají aktuální barvu popředí a pozadí. Proto, pouhou
        změnou barvy popředí a pozadí můžete vytvořit plynulý přechod mezi
        dvěma libovolnými barvami. Ostatní přechody v seznamu a všechny
        přechody, které vytvoříte sami, mají barvy pěvně dané.
      </para>
      <para lang='en'>  <!--Changed 050515-->
        The first four gradients in the list are special:  they use the
        Foreground and Background colors from the Toolbox Color Area, 
        instead of being fixed. <guilabel>FG to BG (RGB)</guilabel> is the 
        RGB representation of the gradient from the Foreground color to the 
        Background color in Toolbox. <guilabel>FG to BG (HSV 
        counter-clockwise) </guilabel> represents the hue succession in 
        Color Circle from the selected hue to 360°. <guilabel>FG to BG 
        (HSV clockwise</guilabel> represents the hue succession in Color 
        Circle from the selected hue to 0°. With <guilabel>FG to transparent
        </guilabel>, the selected hue becomes more and more transparent. You 
        can modify these colors by using the Color Selector. Thus, by 
        altering the foreground and background colors, you can make these 
        gradients transition smoothly between any two colors you want. 
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Ces dégradés sont particuliers. <guilabel>PP vers AP (RVB)</guilabel>
        est la représentation RVB du dégradé entre la couleur de Premier-Plan 
        et la couleur d'Arrière-Plan de la Boîte à outils. <guilabel>PP vers 
        AP (TSV sens antihoraire)</guilabel> représente la succession des teintes 
        dans le cercle colorimétrique depuis la teinte sélectionnée jusqu'à 
        360°. <guilabel>PP vers AP (TSV horaire)</guilabel> représente la 
        succession des teintes dans le cercle colorimétrique depuis la teinte 
        sélectionnée jusqu'à 0°. Avec <guilabel>PP vers Transparent</guilabel> 
        la teinte sélectionnée devient de plus en plus transparente. Vous les 
        modifiez en utilisant le Sélecteur de couleur. Vous pouvez ainsi 
        adoucir une transition entre deux couleurs de votre choix.
      </para> 
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        渐变对话框顶部四个渐变比较特别，因为它们使用 GIMP 当前的前景和背景色，将前景色置换为黑色和将背景色置换为白色。这样通过交换前景和背景色，您能使这些渐变在想要的任何两种颜色间平滑地过渡。其它渐变在列表中，任何您自建的渐变有其固定的颜色。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Přechody nemusí zahrnovat pouze změny v barvě, ale i změny v její
        průhlednosti. Některé přechody jsou zcela neprůhledné, jiné obsahují
        průsvitné nebo zcela průhledné části. Pokud vyplňujete nebo malujete
        přechodem, který není zcela neprůhledný, bude zpoza něj prosvítat
        stávající obsah vrstvy.
      </para>
      <para lang='en'>
        Gradients can involve not just color changes, but also changes
        in opacity.  Some of the gradients are completely opaque;
        others include transparent or translucent parts.  When you
        fill or paint with a non-opaque gradient, the existing
        contents of the layer will show through behind it.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les dégradés incluent une variation de couleurs, mais aussi 
        des variations d'opacité. Certains dégradés sont complètement 
        opaques; d'autres incluent des parties plus ou moins 
        transparentes. Quand vous peignez avec un dégradé non opaque,
        les zones du calque sur lequel vous peignez transparaîtront  
        dans les zones transparentes du dégradé.
      </para> 
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        渐变并不仅仅导致颜色改变，而且改变不透明度。一些渐变完全不透明；而一些包括透明或半透明部分。当您用一个非不透明的渐变填充或涂画时，图层的已存在内容会从下面透出来。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='cs'>
        Své <emphasis>vlastní</emphasis> přechody můžete vytvářet pomocí
        <!--FIXCS<link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>-->Editoru
        přechodů<!--</link>-->.
        Nemůžete upravovat přechody dodávané přímo s Gimpem, ale můžete
        upravovat jejich kopie nebo vytvořit zcela nové přechody.
      </para>
      <para lang='en'>
        You can create new <emphasis>custom</emphasis> gradients,
        using the <link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>Gradient
        Editor</link>.  You cannot modify the gradients that are
        supplied with GIMP, but you can duplicate them or create new
        ones, and then edit those.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Vous pouvez créer de nouveaux <emphasis>dégradés sur mesure
        </emphasis> grâce à l'<link 
    linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>Éditeur de dégradés</link>.
        Vous ne pouvez modifier un dégradé existant, mais vous pouvez 
        le dupliquer et le modifier à votre gré.
      </para> 
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您能使用<link linkend='gimp-gradient-editor-dialog'>渐变编辑器</link>来创建<emphasis>自定义</emphasis>渐变。您不能修改 GIMP 自带的渐变，但可以复制或创建一个新的，然后再编辑它们。
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Přechody dodávané přímo s Gimpem jsou uložené v systémovém adresáři
    <filename>gradients</filename>. Ve výchozím nastavení jsou vaše vlastní
    přechody ukládané do adresáře <filename>gradients</filename> ve vašem
    osobním Gimp adresáři. Všechny tam uložené přechody (jejichž soubory končí
    příponou <filename>.ggr</filename>) se při spuštění Gimpu automaticky
    načtou. Více adresářů do cesty pro vyhledávání přechodů můžete přidat v
    v kartě Přechody části <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Adresáře</link> dialogu Předvolby.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    The gradients that are supplied with GIMP are stored in a system
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder.  By default, gradients that
    you create are stored in a folder called
    <filename>gradients</filename> in your personal GIMP directory.
    Any gradient files (ending with the extension
    <filename>.ggr</filename>) will automatically be loaded when you
    start GIMP.  You can add more directories to the gradient search
    path, if you want to, in the Gradients tab of the <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Data Folders</link> pages of the
    Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les dégradés fournis avec Gimp sont stockés dans un dossier 
    «gradients» du système. Par défaut, les dégradés que vous créez 
    sont stockés dans votre répertoire Utilisateur avec l'extension 
    <filename>.ggr</filename>. Tous les dégradés seront chargés par 
    Gimp au démarrage, à condition que leur chemin soit indiqué et
    coché dans l'onglet Dégradés de la page <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Dossiers/Dégradés</link> des 
    Préférences.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 自带的渐变放在系统的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹。而您创建的渐变默认保存在个人 GIMP 文件夹的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹中。任何渐变文件(扩展名为 <filename>.ggr</filename>) 将在每次启动 GIMP 时自动加载。您可以根据需要添加更多的文件夹到渐变搜索路径，在首选项对话框的<link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>文件夹</link>页的渐变标签中。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Gimp 2.2 má novou schopnost – nahrávat přechody uložené ve formátu SVG,
    který používá řada vektorových grafických programů. Jediné co musíte
    udělat, je umístit soubor se SVG přechodem do adresáře
    <filename>gradients</filename> ve vašem osobním adresáři Gimpu nebo jiného
    adresáře, ve kterém jsou přechody vyhledávány.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    New in GIMP 2.2 is the ability to load gradient files in SVG
    format, used by many vector graphics programs.  To make GIMP load
    an SVG gradient file, all you need to do is place it in the
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your personal GIMP
    directory, or any other folder in your gradient search path.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Nouvelle dans Gimp 2.2 est la possibilité de charger des fichiers 
    de dégradés au format SVG utilisé dans de nombreux programmes de 
    dessin vectoriel. Tout ce que vous avez à faire est de le mettre 
    dans votre répertoire de dégradés personnels.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 2.2 中允许读取在许多矢量图形程序中使用的 SVG 格式的渐变文件。要使 GIMP 读取一个 SVG 渐变文件，需要做的就是将它放在您个人 GIMP 目录的 <filename>gradients</filename> 文件夹中，或任何渐变搜索路径的其它文件夹中。
  </para> 

  <para lang='cs'>
    Velké množství zajímavých SVG přechodů najdete na webu, zejména na stránce
    <ulink
    url='http://openclipart.org/cgi-bin/navigate/Gradients'>OpenClipArt</ulink>
    (anglicky). Pokud váš webový prohlížeč nepodporuje SVG, můžete si přechody
    prohlédnout až po jejich stáhnutí.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You can find a large number of interesting SVG gradients on the
    web, in particular at <ulink
    url='http://openclipart.org/cgi-bin/navigate/Gradients'>OpenClipArt
    Gradients</ulink>.  You won't be able to see what these gradients
    look like unless your browser supports SVG, but that won't prevent
    you from downloading them.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Vous trouverez de nombreux dégradés intéressants sur le Web, en 
    particulier à l'adresse <ulink
    url='http://openclipart.org/cgi-bin/navigate/Gradients'>OpenClipArt
    Gradients</ulink>. Vous ne pourrez pas voir ces dégradés si votre 
    navigateur n'accepte pas le format SVG, mais cela ne vous 
    empêchera pas de les télécharger.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    网上有大量有趣的 SVG 渐变，特别是 <ulink url='http://openclipart.org/cgi-bin/navigate/Gradients'>OpenClipArt Gradients</ulink>。只有当您的浏览器支持 SVG 时才能看到这些渐变，不过下载它们是没问题的。
  </para>
  
</sect2>
