<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6. No change
  2006-03-04 made docbook compliant.
  2005-11-28 Lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures.
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-gradients">
  <title>Gradients</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Gradient</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title>Some examples of GIMP gradients. </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/gradient-examples.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Gradients from top to bottom: FG to BG (RGB);
          Full Saturation Spectrum CCW;
          Nauseating Headache; Browns; Four Bars
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    A <emphasis>gradient</emphasis>
    is a set of colors arranged in a linear order. The most basic use of
    gradients is by the <link linkend="gimp-tool-gradient">Gradient tool</link>,
    sometimes known as <quote>gradient fill tool</quote>: it works
    by filling the selection with colors from a gradient. You have many
    options to choose from for controlling the way the gradient colors are
    arranged within the selection. There are also other important ways to use
    gradients, including:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Painting with a gradient</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Each of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s basic painting tools allows you
          the option of using
          colors from a gradient. This enables you to create brushstrokes that
          change color from one end to the other.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>The Gradient Map filter</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
           This filter is in the Colors menu, and allows you to
           <quote>colorize</quote>
           an image, using the color intensity of each point with the
           corresponding color from the active gradient (the intensity 0, very
           dark, is replaced by the color at most left end of the gradient,
           progressively until the intensity is 255, very light, replaced by
           the most right color of the gradient. See
           <xref linkend="plug-in-gradmap"/> for more information.
         </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> comes presupplied with a large number of
    gradients. You can also add new gradients that you create or
    download from other sources. You can access the full set of available
    gradients using the
    <link linkend="gimp-gradient-dialog">Gradients dialog</link>,
    a dockable dialog that you can either activate when you need it, or keep
    around as a tab in a dock. The <quote>current gradient</quote>, used in
    most gradient-related operations, is shown in the Brush/Pattern/Gradient
    area of the Toolbox. Clicking on the gradient symbol in the Toolbox is an
    alternative way of bringing up the Gradients dialog.
  </para>
  <para>
    Some quick examples of working with gradients (for more information
    see <link linkend="gimp-tool-gradient">Gradient Tool</link>) are:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Put a gradient in a selection:</para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Choose a gradient.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            With the Blend Tool click and drag with the mouse between
            two points of a selection.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Colors will distributed perpendicularly to the direction
            of the drag of the mouse and according to the length
            of it.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <figure>
        <title>How to use rapidly a gradient in a selection</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/using/gradient-draw.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Painting with a gradient:</para>
      <para>
        You can also use a gradient with one of the drawing tools (e.g. Pencil,
        Paintbrush or Airbrush) if you switch on
        <guilabel>Enable dynamics</guilabel> and set
        <guilabel>Dynamics</guilabel> to
        <guilabel>Color From Gradient</guilabel>. In the next step, set the
        gradients length and the <guilabel>Repeat</guilabel> style in the
        <guilabel>Fade Options</guilabel> section, and select a suitable
        gradient in the <guilabel>Color Options</guilabel> section.
        <xref linkend="gimp-tool-dynamic-options"/> describes these
        parameters in more detail.
        </para>
        <para>
        The following example shows the impact on the Pencil tool.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>How to use a gradient with a drawing tool</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/color-gradient-pencil-dialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Tool settings</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/color-gradient-pencil-example.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Resulting succession of the gradients colors</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Different productions with the same gradient:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Gradient usage</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/using/gradient-usage.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Four ways of using the Tropical Colors gradient: a linear gradient
              fill, a shaped gradient fill, a stroke painted using colors from a
              gradient, and a stroke painted with a fuzzy brush then colored
              using the <link linkend="plug-in-gradmap">Gradient Map</link>
              filter.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>A few useful things to know about <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
  gradients:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The first gradients in the list are special: They use the colors from
        the <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-color-area">Foreground/Background
        Colors Area in the Toolbox</link>, instead of being fixed.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>FG to BG (HSV Counter-Clockwise)</guilabel> represents
            the hue succession in a color wheel from the selected hue to 360°.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
        <guilabel>FG to BG (HSV Clockwise)</guilabel> represents the hue
        succession in a color wheel from the selected hue to 0°.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
        <guilabel>FG to BG (RGB)</guilabel> is the
        RGB representation of the gradient from the Foreground color to the
        Background color in Toolbox.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
          The<guilabel>FG to BG (Hard Edge)</guilabel> gradient
          generates a gradient from the foreground color to the background color,
          with hard-edged transitions in between.
      </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
        With <guilabel>FG to Transparent</guilabel>, the selected hue becomes
        more and more transparent. You
        can modify these colors by using the Color Selector. Thus, by
        altering the foreground and background colors, you can make these
        gradients transition smoothly between any two colors you want.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <guilabel>FG to Transparent (Hard Edge)</guilabel> gradient
            generates a gradient from the foreground color to transparency,
            with hard-edged transitions in between.
          </para>
          <para>
            Using this gradient, you can generate patterns very quickly with the
            <quote>Repeat</quote> option, alternating repetitive colored shapes
            with full transparency over a given background. Does works best
            with shapes like spiral, radial, square and linear.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Gradients can involve not just color changes, but also changes in
        opacity. Some of the gradients are completely opaque; others include
        transparent or translucent parts. When you fill or paint with a
        non-opaque gradient, the existing contents of the layer will show
        through behind it.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        You can create new <emphasis>custom</emphasis> gradients,
        using the <link linkend="gimp-gradient-editor-dialog">Gradient
        Editor</link>.  You cannot modify the gradients that are
        supplied with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but you can duplicate them or
        create new ones, and then edit those.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    The gradients that are supplied with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> are stored in
    a system <filename>gradients</filename> folder.
  </para>
  <para>
    Gradients that you create are automatically saved in the
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your personal
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory. Any gradient files (ending with
    the extension <filename>.ggr</filename>) found in one of these
    folders, will automatically be loaded when you start
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You can add more directories to the
    gradient search path, if you want to, in the Gradients tab of the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Data Folders</link>
    section of the Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can also load gradient files in SVG format, used
    by many vector graphics programs. To make <acronym>GIMP</acronym> load an
    SVG gradient file, place it in the
    <filename>gradients</filename> folder of your personal
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory, or any other folder in your gradient
    search path.
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      You can find a large number of interesting SVG gradients on the web, in
      particular at OpenClipArt Gradients
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-openclipart-gradients"/>.
    </para>
  </tip>
</sect1>
