<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2006-09-17 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-02-28 Added italian translation and fixed 'Shift' key meaning for
             guide move (en,it) by ciampix
  2006-01-06 Activated dutch translation and replaces some
             ' by " by HdJ
  2005-12-18 reviewed and added de translation by lexa
  2005-11-28 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-image-grid">
  <title>
    <phrase>Grids and Guides</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Grid and guides</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Grid</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Guides</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    You will probably have it happen many times that you need to place
    something in an image very precisely, and find that it is not easy to do
    using a mouse. Often you can get better results by using the arrow keys on
    the keyboard (which move the affected object one pixel at a time, or 25
    pixels if you hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
    key), but GIMP also provides you with two other aids to make positioning
    easier: grids and guides.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase>Image used for examples below</phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-nogrid.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase>The Image Grid</phrase>
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>Image with default grid</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-defaultgrid.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Each image has a grid. It is always present, but by default it is not
      visible until you activate it by toggling
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Show Grid</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      in the image menu. If you want grids to be present more often than not,
      you can change the default behavior by checking "Show grid" in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-appearance">
        Image Window Appearance
      </link>
      page of the Preferences dialog. (Note that there are separate settings
      for Normal Mode and Fullscreen Mode.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The default grid appearance, set up when you install GIMP, consists of
      plus-shaped black crosshairs at the grid line intersections, with grid
      lines spaced every 10 pixels both vertically and horizontally. You can
      customize the default grid using the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-default-grid">Default Image Grid</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog. If you only want to change the grid
      appearance for the current image, you can do so by choosing
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Configure Grid</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      from the image menu: this brings up the
      <link linkend="gimp-configure-grid-dialog">Configure Grid</link> dialog.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>A different grid style</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-othergrid.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Not only can a grid be helpful for judging distances and spatial
      relationships, it can also permit you to align things exactly with
      the grid, if you toggle
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Snap to Grid</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      in the image menu:  this causes the pointer to "warp" perfectly to
      any grid line located within a certain distance.  You can
      customize the snap distance threshold by setting "Snap distance"
      in the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Tool Options</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog, but most people seem to be happy
      with the default value of 8 pixels.  (Note that it is perfectly
      possible to snap to the grid even if the grid is not visible.  It
      isn't easy to imagine why you might want to do this, though.)
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase>Guides</phrase>
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase>Image with four guides</phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-guides.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      In addition to the image grid, GIMP also gives you a more flexible
      type of positioning aid: <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.  These are
      horizontal or vertical lines that you create by clicking on one of
      the rulers and dragging into the image.  You can create as many
      guides as you like, positioned wherever you like.  To move a guide
      after you have created it, activate the Move tool in the Toolbox (or
      press the <keycap>M</keycap> key), you can then click and drag a
      guide. To delete a guide, simply drag it outside the image. Holding
      down the Shift key, you can move everything but a guide, using the
      guides as an effective alignment aid.
    </para>
    <para>
      As with the grid, you can cause the pointer to snap to nearby
      guides, by toggling
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Snap to Guides</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      in the image menu.  If you have a number of guides and they are
      making it difficult for you to judge the image properly, you can
      hide them by toggling
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Show Guides</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      It is suggested that you only do this momentarily, otherwise you
      may get confused the next time you try to create a guide and
      don't see anything happening.
    </para>
    <para>
      If it makes things easier for you, you can change the default behavior
      for guides in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-appearance">Image Window
      Appearance</link> page of the Preferences dialog. Disabling "Show
      guides" is probably a bad idea, though, for the reason just given.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Another use for guides:  the <link linkend="plug-in-guillotine">Guillotine</link> plugin can use guides
        to slice an image into a set of sub-images.
      </para>
    </note>
    <note>
      <para>
        See also <link linkend="glossary-guides">Guides</link> in Glossary.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
