<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-07-08 j.h: add moving guides intersection
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-image-grid-and-guides">
  <title>Grids and Guides</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Grid and guides</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Grid</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Guides</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    You will probably have it happen many times that you need to place
    something in an image very precisely, and find that it is not easy to do
    using a mouse. Often you can get better results by using the arrow keys on
    the keyboard (which move the affected object one pixel at a time, or 25
    pixels if you hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
    key), but <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also provides you with two other aids to
    make positioning easier: grids and guides.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Image used for examples below</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-nogrid.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="gimp-concepts-image-grid">
    <title>The Image Grid</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Image with default grid</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-defaultgrid.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Each image has a grid. It is always present, but by default it is not
      visible until you activate it by toggling
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Show Grid</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      in the main menu. If you want grids to be present more often than not,
      you can change the default behavior by checking <guilabel>Show grid</guilabel> in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-appearance">Image Windows Appearance</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog. (Note that there are separate settings
      for Normal Mode and Fullscreen Mode.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The default grid appearance, set up when you install
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, consists of solid lines,
      spaced every 10 pixels both vertically and horizontally. You can
      customize the default grid using the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-default-grid">Default Image Grid</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog. If you only want to change the grid
      appearance for the current image, you can do so by choosing
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Configure Grid…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      from the main menu: this brings up the
      <link linkend="gimp-configure-grid-dialog">Configure Grid</link> dialog.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>A different grid style</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-othergrid.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Not only can a grid be helpful for judging distances and spatial
      relationships, it can also permit you to align things exactly with
      the grid, if you toggle
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Snap to Grid</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      in the main menu:  this causes the pointer to "warp" perfectly to
      any grid line located within a certain distance.  You can
      customize the snap distance threshold by setting "Snap distance"
      in the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-snapping">Snapping Behavior</link>
      page of the Preferences dialog, but most people seem to be happy
      with the default value of 8 pixels.  (Note that it is perfectly
      possible to snap to the grid even if the grid is not visible.)
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        To create a grid that is actually part of the image, use the
        <link linkend="gimp-filter-grid">Grid</link> plug-in.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-concepts-image-guides">
    <title>Guides</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Image with four guides</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/wilber-simple-guides.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      In addition to the image grid, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also gives you a
      more flexible type of positioning aid: <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.
      These are horizontal or vertical lines you can temporarily display on an
      image while you are working on it.
    </para>
    <para>
      To create a guide, simply click on one of the rulers in the image window
      and pull out a guide, while holding the mouse
      <mousebutton>Left&nbsp;Button</mousebutton> pressed. The guide is then
      displayed as a blue, dashed line, which follows the pointer. As soon as
      you create a guide, the <quote>Move</quote> tool is activated and the
      mouse pointer changes to the Move icon.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also create a guide with the
      <link linkend="script-fu-guide-new">New Guide</link> command, which
      allows you to precisely place the guide on the image, the
      <link linkend="script-fu-guide-new-percent">New Guide (by
      Percent)</link> command, or the
      <link linkend="script-fu-guides-from-selection">New Guides from
      Selection</link> command.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can create as many guides as you like, positioned wherever you like.
      To <emphasis>move a guide</emphasis> after you have created it, activate
      the Move tool in the Toolbox (or press the <keycap>M</keycap> key), you
      can then click and drag a guide; click-and-drag the intersection of
      two guides to move them together. To <emphasis>delete a guide</emphasis>,
      simply drag it outside the image. Holding down the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
      key, you can move everything but a guide, using the guides as an
      effective alignment aid.
    </para>

    <para>
      The behavior of the guides depends upon the <guilabel>Move</guilabel>
      (Affect) mode of the <quote>Move</quote> tool. When
      <emphasis>Layer</emphasis> mode is selected, the mouse pointer turns
      into a small hand as soon as it gets close to a guide. Then the guide is
      activated and it turns red, and you can move the guide or delete it by
      moving it back into the ruler. If <emphasis>Selection</emphasis> mode is
      selected, you can position a guide, but you cannot move it after that.
    </para>
    <para>
      As with the grid, you can cause the pointer to snap to nearby
      guides, by toggling
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Snap to Guides</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      in the main menu. If you have a number of guides and they are
      making it difficult for you to judge the image properly, you can
      hide them by toggling
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Show Guides</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      It is suggested that you only do this momentarily, otherwise you
      may get confused the next time you try to create a guide and
      don't see anything happening.
    </para>
    <para>
      If it makes things easier for you, you can change the default behavior
      for guides in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-appearance">Image Windows
      Appearance</link> page of the Preferences dialog. Disabling
      <guilabel>Show&nbsp;guides</guilabel> is probably a bad idea, though,
      for the reason just given.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can remove the guides with the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Guides</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Remove all Guides</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      command.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Another use for guides: the
        <link linkend="plug-in-guillotine">Slice Using Guides</link> plug-in
        can use guides to slice an image into a set of sub-images.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
