<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-08-07 ude: moved ghostscript instructions here from File/Print
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-03-14 lexa: split out from another file
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-fileformats-opening">
  <title>Opening Files</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Files</primary>
    <secondary>Open</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    There are several ways of opening an existing image in
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>:
  </para>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-open-file">
    <title>Open File</title>
    <para>
      The most obvious way to open an existing image is the <guilabel>Open
      Image</guilabel> dialog.
      Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      or <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>
      to open the <link linkend="gimp-open-dialog">Open Image</link> dialog.
      For details on how to use this dialog, see the link in the previous
      sentence.
      This dialog allows you to navigate to the image you want to use, select
      its name, and then use the <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button to load the
      image.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Open Image</guilabel> dialog provides several features to
      help you navigate quickly to a file. Perhaps the most important is the
      ability to create <quote>bookmarks</quote>, for folders that you use
      often.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-open-location">
    <title>Open Location</title>
    <para>
      If instead of a file name, you have a <acronym>URI</acronym>
      (i.e., a web address) for the image, select
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Open Location…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      from the image menu. In the dialog,
      enter (or paste) the <acronym>URI</acronym>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-open-recent">
    <title>Open Recent</title>
    <para>
      To open an image that was recently open in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, select
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Open Recent</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> from the image menu.
      This displays a submenu of the most recently opened images that you can
      click to open the desired image. At the bottom of this submenu is the
      <link linkend="gimp-document-dialog">Document History</link> command if
      you need to reopen an image from longer ago.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-external-programs">
    <title>Using External Programs</title>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses plugins for reading and writing all
      file formats except XCF. These plugins may use external libraries or
      programs. For example, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> does not directly support
      <link linkend="glossary-pdf">PDF</link> and
      <link linkend="glossary-postscript">PostScript</link>. Instead,
      for reading (or writing) PDF (file extension
      <filename class="extension">.pdf</filename>) and PostScript files
      (file extension <filename class="extension">.ps</filename> or
      <filename class="extension">.eps</filename>), <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      requires a powerful free software program called
      <application>Ghostscript</application>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Linux distributions almost always come with Ghostscript already
      installed (not necessarily the most recent version). On Windows
      Ghostscript<xref linkend="bibliography-online-ghostscript"/> is
      included in the installer so you don't need to install it
      separately.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-file-manager">
    <title>File Manager</title>
    <para>
      If you have associated an image file type with
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      either when you installed <acronym>GIMP</acronym> or later, then you
      can navigate to the file using a file manager (such as Nautilus or
      Konqueror in Linux, or Windows Explorer in Windows), and once you
      have found it, double-click on the file.  If properly configured,
      the image will open in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-drag-and-drop">
    <title>Drag and Drop</title>
    <para>
      Drag and drop a file onto the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-toolbox">Toolbox</link>
      to open the file.
    </para>
    <para>
      Drag an image into an open <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image to add the
      dropped file as a new layer, or set of layers, to the already open image.
    </para>
    <para>
      Many applications support dragging and dropping an image into
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>; for example, drag an image from
      <application>Firefox</application> and drop it onto
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s toolbox.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-open-copy-and-paste">
    <title>Copy and Paste</title>
    <para>
      Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Create</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>From Clipboard</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      to create a new image from the clipboard; alternatively, you can use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Paste as</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Paste as New Image</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Many applications support copying an image to the clipboard that can
      then be pasted into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Many operating systems
      support copying screen content to the clipboard.
      <keycap>Print Screen</keycap> typically copies the screen content to
      the clipboard. Print screen is not universally
      supported, and just because your operating system can copy an image to
      the clipboard, does not mean that <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can use
      the image from the clipboard. Your best bet is to try it and see
      if it works.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2  id="gimp-using-image-browser">
    <title>Image Browser</title>
    <para>
      Linux supports an image-management application named
      <application>gThumb</application>. Besides being an excellent
      image browser, you can right click an image, choose
      <guilabel>Open with</guilabel>, then select
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> from the list of options. You can also
      drag an image from <application>gThumb</application> onto the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> toolbox.
      See the gThumb home page <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gthumb"/>
      for more information. Other similar application is Geeqie
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-geeqie"/>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
