<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-08-28 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-12-18 reviewed and added rewrote de image explenation by lexa
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-images" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="de;es;fr;ko;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-13</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-06</date>
        <authorinitials>manuelq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision : 1.32 $</revnumber>
        <date>2006-03-27</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-05-02</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-28</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Práce s obrázky</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Working with Images</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Mit Bildern arbeiten</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Trabajar con imágenes</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Travailler avec des Images</phrase>  <!--050508-->
    <phrase lang="it">Lavorare con le immagini</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">이미지 편집하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Het werken met afbeeldingen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Å arbeide med bilete</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">了解图像</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Работа с изображениями</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Bild</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The GIMP is an image manipulation program. At the most sweeping level,
    using GIMP involves three basic steps: (1) opening images or creating new
    ones; (2) altering those images; (3) saving the results.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    GIMP je program pro úpravu obrázků. V nejzákladnější rovině lze práci s
    Gimpem popsat ve třech krocích: (1) otevření nebo vytvoření nového
    obrázku; (2) úprava obrázku; (3) uložení obrázku.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    <application>GIMP</application>
    ist ein Bildbearbeitungsprogramm. Salopp gesprochen sind dies drei
    Schritte: (1) Bild laden oder neu anlegen; (2) Bild verändern; (3)
    Ergebnis speichern.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    El GIMP es un programa de manipulación de imágenes. A grandes rasgos, su
    uso implica tres pasos básicos: (1) abrir o crear imágenes; (2) modificar
    dichas imágenes; (3) guardar los resultados.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    <application>GIMP</application>
    est un programme de manipulation d'image. Au niveau le plus bas,
    l'utilisation de <application>GIMP</application>
    implique trois étapes de base : (1) ouvrir une image ou en créer une
    nouvelle ; (2) modifier cette image ; (3) enregistrer le résultat.
  </para>
  <para lang="hr">
    GIMP je aplikacija za obradu slike. U svojem najjednostavnijem nivou,
    korištenje Gimpa podrazumijeva tri osnovne etape : (1) otvoriti sliku ili
    kreirati novu sliku; (2) obraditi tu istu sliku; (3) pohraniti rezultat.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    GIMP è un programma di fotoritocco. Ridotto al minimo, l'uso di GIMP può
    essere sintetizzato nei tre passi seguenti: (1) apertura delle immagini o
    creazione di nuove; (2) modifica delle immagini; (3) salvataggio dei
    risultati.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    김프는 이미지 편집 프로그램이다. 그리고 대부분의 프로그램들처럼 다음 세 가지 기본 단계를 가진다. (1) 이미지를 열거나 새 이미지
    만들기. (2) 이미지 편집하기. (3) 결과 저장하기.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    <application>GIMP</application>
    is een beeld bewerkingsprogramma, globaal gezien bestaat het gebruik ervan
    uit drie basis stappen: (1) Openen of creëren van afbeeldinsbestanden; (2)
    bewerken van de afbeelding; (3) Opslaan van het resultaat.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    er eit biletbehandlingsprogram. Den mest overflatiske bruken involverer
    likevel tre grunnleggjande steg: 1. Opne eller kreere eit bilete. 2. Endre
    biletet. 3. Lagre resultatet.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    GIMP это программа для манипуляции изображениями. Говоря очень обобщенно,
    использование GIMP включает в себя три основных шага: (1) открытие
    изображений или создание новых; (2) редактирование этих изображений; (3)
    сохранение результатов.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 是图像处理程序。概括地说，使用 GIMP 有三个基本步骤：(1)打开图像或新建；(2)修改这些图像；(3)保存结果。
  </para>


  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Opening Images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Otevírání obrázků</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bilder laden</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Apertura de imágenes</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Ouvrir des images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="hr">Otvoriti sliku</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Apertura delle immagini</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">이미지 열기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Openen van Afbeeldingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å opna bilete</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Открытие изображений</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">打开图像</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      Depending on how GIMP was started, there may already be one or more
      images open when you begin. You can open new images from files using the
      <link linkend="gimp-file-open">Open</link>
      command from the File menu. GIMP is capable of opening a large variety
      of graphics file formats; see
      <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Files</link>
      for more information. Depending on how your system is set up, you may
      also be able to open images by clicking on icons in a file manager, or
      by drag-and-drop from other programs. If you aren't sure whether you can
      do this, just try it. The worst thing that can happen is that your
      computer could explode.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      V závislosti na způsobu spuštění Gimpu může být otevřen jeden nebo i
      více obrázků již na počátku práce s programem. Další obrázky můžete
      otevřít ze souboru pomocí položky (FIXLINK)Otevřít v menu
      <guimenu>Soubor</guimenu>. GIMP umí otevřít velké množství
      nejrůznějších grafických formátů, viz kapitolu
      <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Souborové formáty</link>.
      V závislosti na nastavení systému možná můžete obrázky otevírat i
      poklepáním na ikonu ve správci souborů, nebo přetažením z jiných
      aplikací. Pokud nevíte, zda to váš systém umí, prostě to vyzkoušejte.
      Nemůže se stát nic horšího, než že to nebude fungovat.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Je nachdem, wie Sie <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      gestartet haben, wurden möglicherweise ein oder mehrere Bilder bereits
      beim Starten geladen. Dies geschieht zum Beispiel, wenn Sie Bilddateien
      mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> assoziiert haben und diese Bilder dann per
      Doppelklick öffnen. Ein anderer Weg, Bilddateien in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zu öffnen, ist das Kommando
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>D</accel>atei</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ö<accel>f</accel>fnen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      (<xref linkend="gimp-file-open" />
      ). Dabei ist GIMP in der Lage, Bilder in den verschiedensten
      Dateiformaten zu lesen. Eine, vermutlich unvollständige, Liste finden
      Sie im <xref linkend="gimp-using-fileformats" />.
      Auf einigen Betriebssystemen unterstützt GIMP darüber hinaus auch
      <quote>Drag'n'Drop</quote>.
      Als Benutzer laden sie mit dieser Technik die Dateien, indem Sie sie
      einfach auf das Werkzeug fallen lassen. Wenn Sie nicht sicher sind, ob
      das bei Ihnen funktioniert, probieren Sie es einfach aus.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Dependiendo de la forma en que GIMP fue iniciado, puede haber una o más
      imágenes ya abiertas al comienzo. Puede abrir imágenes nuevas desde
      archivos usando el comando
      <!-- <link linkend="gimp-file-open">Open</link> -->
      Abrir desde el menú Archivo. El GIMP es capaz de abrir una gran variedad
      de formatos de archivos.
      <!-- Vea <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Archivos</link> para
        más información. -->
      Dependiendo de cómo esté configurado su sistema, también puede abrir una
      imagen clicando en su icono en el administrador de archivos, o mediante
      arrastrar y soltar (drag-and-drop) desde otros programas. Si no está
      seguro si puede o no hacer esto, sólo pruebe. Lo peor que puede pasar es
      que tu computadora explote.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      En fonction du mode de lancement de GIMP, il peut y avoir une ou
      plusieurs images ouvertes lorsque vous commencez. Vous pouvez ouvrir de
      nouvelles images depuis le fichier en utilisant la commande
      <link linkend="gimp-file-open">Ouvrir</link>
      du menu Fichier. GIMP sait ouvrir une grande variété de formats
      graphiques de fichier : voyez
      <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Fichiers</link>
      pour plus d'informations. En fonction des paramètres de votre système,
      vous pouvez aussi ouvrir des images en cliquant sur les icônes du
      gestionnaire de fichiers, ou en cliquant-glissant depuis d'autres
      programmes. Si vous ne savez pas si telle ou telle méthode peut
      fonctionner, essayez-la. Dans le pire des cas votre ordinateur
      explosera.
    </para>

    <para lang="hr">
      Ovisno o tome kako je GIMP pokrenut, moguće je imati jednu ili više
      otvorenih slika prilkom samog lansiranja programa. Nove slike možete
      otvoriti iz same datoteke koristeći komandu
      <!--<link linkend="gimp-file-open">-->Open<!--</link>-->
      izbornika File. GIMP može otvoriti veliki broj grafičkih formata:
      pogledajte<!--<link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">-->
      Files<!--</link>-->
      za više informacija. Ovisno o tome kako je postavljen vaš sistem, možete
      također otvoriti datoteke ukoliko kliknete na ikone u upravljaču
      datoteki, ili ako kliknite i povučite sliku iz nekog drugog programa.
      Ukoliko ne znate funkcionira li ili ne određeni metoda, jednostavno ju
      isprobajte. U najgorem slučaju vaše će računalo jednostavo explodirati.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      A seconda di come GIMP è stato eseguito, può esserci già una o più
      immagini aperte alla partenza. È comunque possibile caricare nuove
      immagini da file usando il comando
      <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="gimp-file-open" -->Apri<!-- /link-->
      dal menu File. GIMP è in grado di aprire una grande varietà di formati
      grafici; vedere
      <!-- FIXME it link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats"
      -->File<!-- /link-->
      per ulteriori informazioni. Se il sistema in uso è stato predisposto, è
      possibile anche aprire le immagini facendo clic sulle icone delle stesse
      in un file manager o trascinandone le icone da questo o da altri
      programmi. Se non si è sicuri se questo comportamento sia stato
      impostato, basta provare per verificarlo. Non vi preoccupate, se non
      funziona non succede niente di male!
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      김프는 시작과 동시에 한 개 내지는 여러 개의 이미지를 열 수 있다. 또는 파일 메뉴의
      <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-file-open">열기</link> -->
      열기 명령을 통해서 새로운 이미지를 열 수도 있다. 김프는 굉장히 다양한 형태의 파일을 지원하는데 이에 대한 자세한 내용은
      <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">파일</link> -->
      파일 섹션을 참고하기 바란다. 그리고 사용하고 있는 운영체제에 따라 다르긴 하겠지만 파일 관리자에서 아이콘을 클릭하거나 다른
      프로그램에서 김프로 드래그앤드롭해서 이미지를 열 수도 있다. 위 방법들 중 어떠한 방법들로 사용할 수 있는지 알고 싶다면, 일단
      시도해봐라. 뭐 기껏해야 컴퓨터가 폭발하는 정도가 아니겠는가?!
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Na het starten van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      kunnen er, afhankelijk van de manier waarop <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      opgestart is, een of meerdere afbeeldingen open staan. Nieuwe
      afbeeldingen kunt u openen door gebruik te maken van het
      <!--link linkend="gimp-file-open"-->Openen<!--/link-->
      commando van het Bestand-menu. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      kan een behoorlijke verscheidenheid van afbeeldingsbestandsformaten aan.
      zie <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Bestanden</link>
      voor meer informatie hierover. Afhankelijk van de instellingen van uw
      computer, kunt u misschien afbeeldingsbestanden openen door met de
      muiscursor op een icoon te klikken in een bestandsbeheerprogramma. Als u
      niet zeker weet of dit kan, moet u het gewoon eens proberen; Het ergste
      dat er kan gebeuren is dat uw computer onder uw neus explodeert.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Avhengig av måten <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      blei opna på, kan det vere ingen eller fleire bilete framme når du
      startar <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      . Du kan også opne nye bilete ved å klikka på
      <!-- PENDING:no (src/menus -> file-open.xml)
        <link linkend="gimp-file-open"-->Opna<!--/link--> i filmenyen. I
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      kan du bruke mange ulike filformat, sjå nærare om desse formata under
      <!-- PENDING:no (src/using -> fileformats.xml )
        link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats"-->Filer<!--/link-->
      . Dersom maskinen din er sett opp slik, kan du også opne bilete ved å
      klikke på ikonet til biletet i filbehandlingssystemet, eller ved
      dra-og-slepp frå andre program. Er du i tvil om dette lar seg gjere,
      prøv det.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В зависимости от того, каким образом GIMP был запущен, в начале работы
      уже могут быть открытыми одно или несколько изображений. Изображения в
      GIMP открываются при помощи функции
      <!-- PENDING: ru link linkend="gimp-file-open"-->
      Открыть<!--/link-->,
      находящейся в меню "Файл". GIMP поддерживает множество графических
      форматов файлов, их список можно посмотреть в разделе<!-- PENDING: ru link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats"-->
      Файлы<!--/link-->.
      В зависимости от настроек системы, изображение можно открыть щелчком
      по пиктограмме в файловом менеджере или перетаскиванием с помощью
      drag-and-drop из другой программы. Если вы не уверены, поддерживаются ли
      эти функции в вашей системе, просто попробуйте. Наихудшее, что может
      случиться, это взрыв компьютера.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      由于 GIMP 不同的启动方式，启动时可能已经打开了一个或多个图像。您可以使用文件菜单中的
      <link linkend="gimp-file-open">打开</link>
      命令。GIMP 能读取大量的图形文件格式，请看
      <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">文件</link>
      。由于系统的不同设置，您也许可以通过在文件管理器中点击图标，或从其它程序拖放到 GIMP
      中来打开图像。当您不确定是否能够这样时，可以尝试下，最坏也不过是电脑爆炸而已。
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Altering Images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Úprava obrázků</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bilder verändern</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Modificación de imágenes</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Modifier des images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="hr">Obraditi sliku</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Modifica delle immagini</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">이미지 편집하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Bewerken van afbeeldingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Endre biletet</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Редактирование изображений</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">修改图像</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      provides you with an enormous number of ways of acting on images:
      painting tools, color manipulation tools, transformation tools, filters,
      etc. The bulk of this manual is devoted to describing these tools and
      how to work with them.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      K úpravě obrázků nabízí GIMP nesmírné množství možností: kreslící
      nástroje, transformační nástroje, filtry atd. Většina této příručky
      popisuje právě tyto nástroje a způsob práce s nimi.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      verfügt über unendlich viele Wege, um ein Bild zu verändern:
      Malwerkzeuge, Werkzeuge zur Farbkorrektur, Transformationswerkzeuge,
      Filter und so weiter. Der größte Teil dieses Handbuches beschäftigt sich
      damit, Ihnen diese Werkzeuge zu erklären und zu zeigen, was Sie damit
      anstellen können.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      proporciona una enorme cantidad de maneras de accionar sobre imágenes:
      herramientas de pintura, herramientas de manipulación de color,
      herramientas de transformación, filtros, etc. Gran parte de este manual
      está dedicada a describir esas herramientas y la manera de trabajar con
      ellas.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      GIMP vous apporte énormément de moyens de modifier des images : des
      outils pour peindre, manipuler des couleurs, tranformer, filtrer, etc.
      Le but de ce manuel est de décrire ces outils et leur fonctionnement.
    </para>
    <para lang="hr">
      GIMP vam pruža brojne mogućnosti za obradu slike: alate za slikanje,
      manipulaciju boja, transformaciju, filtere, itd. Cilj ovog priručnika je
      opsati sve te alate i njihovo funkcioniranje.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      fornisce un'enorme numero di modi di elaborare le immagini: strumenti di
      disegno, strumenti di modifica dei colori, strumenti di trasformazion,
      filtri, ecc. Questo grosso manuale è dedicato alla descrizione di questi
      strumenti e a come utilizzarli con profitto.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym>
      에서는 페인팅 도구, 색상 편집 도구, 변형 도구, 필터 등 수 없이 많은 편집 방법들을 제공한다. 사실 이 메뉴얼의 대부분은
      이러한 도구들과 그것들의 사용 방법에 관한 것이다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Met <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      kunt u op veel manieren afbeeldingen bewerken: schilder-werktuigen,
      kleurbewerkings gereedschappen, vervormings instrumenten, filters,
      enzovoorts. Het grootste deel van deze handleiding beschrijft al deze
      instrumenten en het gebruik ervan.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      er det utruleg mange måtar å behandla bilete på. Det finst vanleg
      maleverktøy, verktøy for å manipulere fargar, ulike filter osv.
      Mestedelen av denne rettleiinga handlar nettopp om desse verktøya og
      korleis du kan bruke dei.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В GIMP существует множество инструментов для работы с изображениями:
      инструменты рисования, управления цветом, инструменты преобразования,
      фильтры, и т.д. В этом руководстве описываются и сами инструменты, и
      способы работы с ними.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      GIMP 提供大量操作图像的方式：涂画工具，颜色处理工具，变换工具和滤镜等。该手册中大部分都是描述这些工具以及如何使用它们。
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Saving Images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ukládání obrázků</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bilder speichern</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Guardado de imágenes</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Enregistrer des images</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">opslaan van afbeeldingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Salvataggio delle immagini</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">이미지 저장하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Lagra bilete</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Сохранение изображений</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">保存图像</phrase>
      <phrase lang="hr">Pohraniti sliku</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      When you are finished working with an image, you will want to save the
      results. (In fact, it is often a good idea to save at intermediate
      stages too: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is a pretty robust program, but we have heard rumors, possibly
      apocryphal, that it may have been known on rare and mysterious occasions
      to crash.) Most of the file formats that <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      can open, can also be used for saving. There is one file format that is
      special, though: XCF is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s native format, and is
      useful because it stores <emphasis>everything</emphasis> about an image
      (well, almost everything; it does not store <quote>undo</quote>
      information). Thus, the XCF format is especially suitable for saving
      intermediate results, and for saving images to be re-opened later in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      XCF files are not readable by most other programs that display images,
      so once you have finished, you will probably also want to save the image
      in a more widely used format, such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Když skončíte s úpravou obrázku, obvykle si budete chtít výsledek svého
      snažení uložit. (Ve skutečnosti se vyplatí ukládat i během práce. GIMP
      je sice velmi stabilní program, ale program, který nemůže spadnout za
      žádných okolností, skutečně neexistuje. Ani GIMP není výjimka.) Většinu
      formátů, které umí GIMP otevřít, lze použít i k ukládání obrázků.
      Nicméně jeden z formátů je obzvláště významný. Je to XCF, nativní formát
      Gimpu, který ukládá <emphasis>všechny informace</emphasis>
      o obrázku (s výjimkou dat pro funkci zpět/znovu a historii). XCF se
      proto výborně hodí zejména pro ukládání během práce nebo pro obrázky,
      které budou v budoucnu v Gimpu dále upravovány. Většina ostatních
      programů ale neumí soubory XCF otevřít, proto je vhodné po dokončení
      práce obrázek uložit také v některém rozšířenějším formátu, např. JPEG,
      PNG, TIFF a podobně.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie mit der Arbeit an einem Bild fertig sind, werden Sie Ihre
      Änderungen in der Regel speichern wollen. (Genaugenommen ist es eine
      gute Idee, auch während der Arbeit an dem Bild gelegentlich die
      Zwischenergebnisse zu speichern.) Die meisten der Dateiformate, welche
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      lesen kann, können Sie auch zum Speichern Ihrer Bilder verwenden.
      Allerdings sollten Sie auf jeden Fall beachten, welche speziellen
      Eigenschaften und Effekte das von Ihnen gewählte Dateiformat speichern
      kann. Es gibt nur genau ein Format in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, welches
      alle Funktionen und Effekte, die <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      Ihnen zur Verfügung stellt, auch in einer Datei speichern kann:
      <emphasis>XCF</emphasis>. Allerdings hat auch XCF einen Nachteil: Es
      gibt nicht allzuviele Programme außer <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      die XCF-Dateien lesen können. Es ist also eine gute Idee, Dateien,
      welche Sie weitergeben möchten, zusätzlich in einem anderen Dateiformat
      wie JPEG oder TIFF zu speichern.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Cuando haya terminado de trabajar con una imagen, querrá guardar los
      resultados. (de hecho, es a menudo una buena idea guardar también en
      etapas intermedias: <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      es un programa completo y robusto, pero hemos escuchado algunos rumores,
      posiblemente apócrifos, de que en raras y misteriosas ocasiones se lo ha
      visto fallar). La mayoría de los formatos de archivo que el
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      puede abrir, también pueden ser usados para guardar. Hay, sin embargo,
      un formato de archivo que es especial: XCF es el formato nativo del
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      y es útil porque guarda todo lo que hay en una imagen (bueno, casi
      todo, no guarda la información de <quote>deshacer</quote>
      ). Por eso, el formato XCF es especialmente útil para guardar resultados
      intermedios de trabajos que van a volver a ser abiertos en el
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      Los archivos XCF no pueden ser leídos por la mayoría de otros
      programas que muestran imágenes, así que una vez que haya terminado,
      probablemente también querrá guardar la imagen en un formato usado más
      ampliamente, como JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Quand vous aurez fini votre travail sur une image vous voudrez
      sauvegarder le résultat (en fait, c'est une bonne habitude de
      sauvegarder durant les étapes intermédiaires : GIMP est un programme
      plutôt robuste, mais nous avons entendu des rumeurs, sans doute
      apocryphes, qu'il lui serait arrivé, dans de rares et mystérieuses
      occasions, de planter). La plupart des formats de fichier que GIMP sait
      ouvrir peuvent être utilisés pour l'enregistrement. L'un d'eux est
      spécial : XCF est le format natif de GIMP, et il est très utile
      puisqu'il sauvegarde <emphasis>tout</emphasis>
      d'une image (enfin, presque tout, les informations d'annulation ne sont
      pas enregistrées). Ainsi, le format XCF est parfait pour enregistrer les
      résultats intermédiaires, et pour enregistrer des images destinées à
      être réouvertes par le GIMP. Le format XCF n'étant pas exploité par la
      plupart des autres programmes qui affichent des images, vous voudrez
      probablement enregistrer vos images dans un format plus répandu, comme
      JPEG, PNG, TIFF, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="hr">
      Kad završite s radom na jednoj slici sigurno ćete poželjeti sačuvati
      rezultat (u stvari pohranjivanje u tijeku same obrade slike, između
      određenih faza rada, jedna je jako dobra navika: iako je GIMP jedan vrlo
      otporan program, načuli smo od, zasigurno nevjerodostojnih izvora, da mu
      se ponekad zna dogoditi, u rijetkim i čudnim okolnostima, da padne).
      Većina tipova formata slika koje GIMP otvora mogu biti korišteni i za
      njihovo pohranjivanje. Jedan od tih formata je međutim poseban : XCF je
      format Gimpa i neizmjerno je koristan jer čuva <emphasis>sve</emphasis>
      informacije koje nosi jedna slika (ili gotovo sve, informacije o
      poništavanju nisu pohranjene). Format XCF je idealan za pohranjivanje
      <quote>među-rezultata</quote>
      onih slika koje su predviđene za rad jedino u Gimpu. Budući de se format
      XCF ne koristi u većini drugih programa za obradu slike, trebali bi ste
      pohraniti vaše slike i u jenom drugom korištenijem, formatu kao što je
      JPEG, PNG, TIFF, itd.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Quando si ha finito di lavorare su di un'immagine, in genere si desidera
      salvarla. In effetti è sempre una buona idea fare molti salvataggi
      intermedi, dato che, non si sa mai, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      potrebbe anche andare in crash (raro ma non impossibile) o potrebbe
      mancare la corrente. La maggior parte dei formati di file che
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      può aprire, possono essere usati anche per salvare. C'è un formato file
      che è speciale: l'XCF, il formato nativo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      molto utile perché memorizza
      <emphasis>quasi ogni informazione</emphasis>
      relativa all'immagine (non memorizza le modifiche intermedie per gli
      <quote>annullamenti</quote>
      ). Perciò il formato XCF è particolarmente interessante per i salvataggi
      delle versioni intermedie di lavoro e per salvare immagini che devono
      successivamente essere riaperte in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      I file XCF non sono leggibili dalla gran parte dei programmi di
      visualizzazione delle immagini perciò, una volta finito il lavoro, è
      conveniente salvare l'immagine in un formato di uso più diffuso come
      JPEG, PNG, TIFF, ecc.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이미지 편집을 완료했으면, 이제 결과를 저장해야 한다(사실 작업
      중간중간에 저장을 해두는 것이 좋다. <acronym>김프</acronym>는
      상당히 안정적인 프로그램이지만, 떠도는 말에 따르면 간혹 충돌을
      일으킬 수도 있다고 한다). 저장가능한 파일 포맷은
      <acronym>김프</acronym>로 열 수 있는 모든 포맷이다. 이 중에서
      XCF 파일은 조금 특별한데, 이것은 <acronym>김프</acronym> 고유의
      포맷이다. 이 포맷을 이용하면 이미지에 대한
      <emphasis>모든 정보</emphasis>를 저장할 수 있어 굉장히 유용하다
      (단, <quote>되돌리기</quote> 정보는 저장할 수 없다). 따라서
      이 XCF 포맷은 작업 중간에 저장하기에 적당한 포맷이고,
      또 나중에 <acronym>김프</acronym>로 다시 열어보기에도 좋다.
      하지만 대부분의 그래픽 뷰어에서는 이 포맷을 읽을 수 없으므로
      최종적인 결과물은 널리 사용되는 JPEG, PNG, TIFF 등의 포맷으로
      저장하는 것이 좋다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Wanneer u klaar bent met het bewerken van een afbeelding zult u het
      resultaat ervan op willen slaan. (Het is sowieso een goed idee om
      tijdens het bewerken regelmatig de tussenresultaten op te slaan.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is een behoorlijk robuust programma, maar we hebben geruchten gehoord,
      mogelijk nog uit de pre-historie, dat het in zeldzame en mysterieuze
      omstandigheden wel eens is vastgelopen of afgestort.) De meeste
      bestandsformaten die <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      kan lezen zijn ook de formaten waarin iets opgeslagen kan worden. Het
      <quote>eXperimental Computing Facility</quote>-formaat (XCF) neemt
      echter een speciale plaats in: XCF is het eigen formaat van
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en erg nuttig omdat hier
      <emphasis>alles</emphasis>
      over de afbeelding in opgeslagen wordt (behalve de de lijst van recente
      wijzigingen helaas). Het XCF-formaat is daarom bij uitstek geschikt om
      tussentijdse resultaten op te slaan van plaatjes die later nog met
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      verder bewerkt moeten worden. Veel andere grafische programma's kunnen
      het XCF-bestanden echter niet lezen. Dus als u afbeeldingen buiten
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      wilt gebruiken kunt u ze beter ook volgens een algemener gebruikt
      formaat als JPEG, PNG, TIFF , enz. opslaan.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Når du er ferdig med eit bilete, ønskjer du til vanleg å lagre dette.
      (Det er forresten ein god idé å lagre bilete innimellom også.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      er eit nokså robust program, men vi har høyrt rykte om at det ved
      sjeldne og mystiske tilfelle har krasja.) Som regel vil du lagra bileta
      i same formatet som dei blei opna i. Det kan likevel vere ein god regel
      å lagra i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      sitt eige filformat XCF medan du arbeider med biletet. Dette fordi
      nesten alle opplysningane om biletet og arbeidsgangen blir lagra
      samstundes. Einaste viktige som ikkje blir lagra samstundes er
      angrehistoria. XCF-filene kan, etter det vi kjenner til, ikkje lesast av
      andre program, så når biletet er ferdig, bør du lagra det i eit meir
      vanleg format som t.d. JPEG, PNG, TIFF, osv.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      По окончании работы вам нужно будет сохранить результат. (Кроме того,
      неплохо было бы сохранять изображение и на промежуточных стадиях: GIMP,
      конечно, весьма устойчивая программа, но ходят слухи, возможно
      недостоверные, что и у него случаются фатальные сбои.) Большинство
      форматов файлов, которые открываются с помощью GIMP, можно использовать
      и для сохранения. Обратите внимание на формат XCF: это родной формат
      GIMP, он полезен тем, что сохраняет <emphasis>всю</emphasis>
      информацию о изображении (ну, почти всю; он не сохраняет информацию
      "истории отмен"). Поэтому формат XCF особенно удобен для сохранения
      промежуточных результатов, и для тех изображений, которые позднее будут
      открыты в GIMP вновь. Файлы формата XCF не поддерживаются большинством
      программ для просмотра изображений, поэтому после окончания работы вам
      понадобится сохранить изображение в более распространенном формате,
      таком, как JPEG, PNG, TIFF, и т.д.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当修改完图像时，您想要保存其结果。(实际上，保存一些中间步骤常常是个好主意：GIMP 是非常健壮的程序，不过我们听说，也许是不可信的：发生罕见和难以解释的崩溃。)大部分 GIMP 能打开的文件格式，也能够保存。不过有一个特殊个文件格式：XCF 是 GIMP 内建的文件格式， 它非常有用因为它保存一个图像的所有信息(实际是几乎所有信息，它不保存“撤销”信息)。因此 XCF 特别适合保存中间步骤，以后再在 GIMP 中打开。不过 XCF 不能被大多数其它显示图像的程序读取，所有完成后，最好保存为更广泛使用的格式如 JPEG，PNG，TIFF等。
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
