<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--  section history:
  2008-01-14 alex falappa: fixed outstanding TODOs for 'it'
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-02-27 fixed Korean translation by Dust
  2006-10-16 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-09-17 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-24 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-07-15 fixed spelling errors in german
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-01-11 note added by j.h line 744
  2006-01-06 HdJ: Revised dutch text.
 -->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-window" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;nl;no;sv;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="de;es;fr;ko;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2006-07-15</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="es">2006-10-16</date>
        <authorinitials lang="es">manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="fr">2006-03-27</date>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="ko">2007-02-27</date>
        <authorinitials lang="ko">Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="no">2006-09-17</date>
        <authorinitials lang="no">KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Image Window</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Okno obrázku</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Das Bildfenster</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">La ventana de la imagen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Fenêtre d'image</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Finestra immagine</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">이미지 창</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Het Afbeeldingsvenster</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Biletvindauget</phrase>
    <phrase lang="sv">Bildfönstret</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">图像窗口</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Окно изображения</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image Windows</primary><secondary>Description</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Status bar</primary><secondary>In image window</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Navigation preview</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Preview</primary><secondary>Navigation preview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Okno obrázku</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Ventana de la imagen</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Fenêtres d'image</primary><secondary>Description</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Barre d'état</primary>
    <secondary>Dans la fenêtre d'image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Navigation</primary><secondary>Aperçu de navigation</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Aperçu</primary><secondary>Aperçu de Navigation</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Biletvindauget</primary><secondary>Beskriving</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Statuslinje</primary><secondary>I biletvindauget</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Navigasjon, førehandsvising</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Førehandsvising</primary><secondary>Navigasjon</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Окна изображения</primary><secondary>Описание</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Планка статуса</primary><secondary>В окно изображения</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Просмотр навигации</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Просмотр</primary><secondary>Просмотр навигации</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Finestra immagine</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>이미지 창</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl"><primary>Afbeeldingsvenster</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="sv"><primary>Bildfönstret</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Окно изображения</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>图像窗口</primary></indexterm>

  <figure lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Das Bildfenster mit seinen wichtigsten Komponenten
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">
        A screenshot of the image window illustrating the important components
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Důležité součásti okna obrázku</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        Captura de pantalla que muestra los componentes principales de una
        ventana de imagen.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        Capture de la fenêtre d'image illustrant ses principaux composants.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        La cattura di una finestra immagine che ne illustra i componenti
        principali.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">주요 구성 요소들이 표시된 이미지 창의 모습</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">
        Het afbeeldingsvenster met de belangrijkste elementen.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Biletvindauget med dei viktigaste komponentane
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Главные компоненты окна изображения</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">一个图像窗口的屏幕截图包含了其重要元素</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/de/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="es">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/it/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ko">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/ko/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="nl">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/nl/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref="../images/using/zh_CN/imagewindow-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <orderedlist>
    <para lang="en">
      In GIMP, each image that you have open is displayed in its own separate
      window. (In some cases, multiple windows may all display the same image,
      but this is unusual.) We will begin with a brief description of the
      components that are present by default in an ordinary image window. Some
      of these, in fact, can be made to disappear using commands in the
      <link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">View</link>
      menu; but you will probably find that you don't want to do that.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="cs">
      V Gimpu je každý otevřený obrázek zobrazen v samostatném okně. (V
      některých případech může více oken zobrazovat obrázek jeden, ale není to
      obvyklé.) Nejprve popíšeme prvky, které jsou ve výchozím nastavení
      přítomné v běžném okně obrázku. Některé z nich mohou být odstraněny pomocí
      příkazů v nabídce <!--FIXCS<link
        linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">-->Zobrazení<!--</link>-->,
      ale pravděpodobně to udělat chtít nebudete.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="de">
      In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      wird jedes Bild in einem eigenen Fenster geöffnet. Die folgenden
      Abschnitte beschreiben die wichtigsten Elemente des Bildfensters, welche
      in den Standardeinstellungen sichtbar sind. Einige dieser Elemente können
      über Kommandos im Menü
      <link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">Ansicht</link>
      ausgeblendet werden.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="es">
      En el GIMP, cada una de las imágenes que se abren se representan en su
      ventana propia (en algunos casos, múltiples ventanas pueden mostrar la
      misma imagen, pero esto es inusual).  Empezaremos con una descripción
      básica de los componentes presentes por defecto en una ventana de imagen
      ordinaria.  Algunos de estos, de hecho, se pueden ocultar usando comandos
      del menú <link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">Ver</link>; pero en
      general no necesitará hacer esto.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans GIMP, chaque image ouverte est affichée dans sa propre fenêtre (dans
      certain cas la même image peut être affichée dans plusieurs fenêtres, mais
      c'est inhabituel). Nous commencerons par une brève description des
      composants présents dans une fenêtre image ordinaire. En fait, certains
      peuvent disparaître lors de l'utilisation de commandes dans le menu
      <link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">Affichage</link> ;
      mais sans doute n'est-ce pas ce que vous voulez faire.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="it">
      In GIMP ogni immagine che si aperta viene visualizzata in una finestra
      a separata (in alcuni casi più finestre possono mostrare la stessa
      immagine ma non è un uso comune). Cominceremo con una breve descrizione
      dei componenti predefinitivamente visualizzati in una normale finestra
      immagine. Alcuni di questi possono essere fatti sparire usando i
      comandi presenti nel menu <link
      linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">Mostra</link> ma è improbabile
      che si desideri effettuare quest'operazione, almeno all'inizio.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="ko">
      김프에서는 각각의 이미지들이 독립된 창으로 열립니다(혹 복수의 창에 같은
      이미지를 열 수도 있지만, 그리 흔한 일은 아닙니다). 이제 일반적인 이미지
      창에 기본적으로 나타나는 구성 요소들에 대해 설명할 것입니다. 이들 중 몇
      개는 <!-- PENDING: ko <link
      linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">보기</link> --> 보기 메뉴를 통해
      없앨 수도 있지만 아마도 굳이 그럴 필요는 없을 것입니다.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="nl">
      In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> wordt iedere afbeelding die u geopend heeft in
      zijn eigen, afzonderlijke venster weergegeven. (In sommige gevallen kunnen
      er meerdere vensters dezelfde afbeelding weergeven, maar dit is vrij
      ongewoon.) We geven een korte beschrijving van de elementen die standaard
      in dit afbeeldingsvenster aanwezig zijn. Enkele hiervan kunt u verbergen
      met behulp van comando's in het <!--link
      linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view"XXX_NL-->Beeld<!--/link-->menu; maar
      dat wilt u waarschijnlijk niet.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="no">
      I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> blir kvart bilete opna i eitt, eller i noen få
      tilfelle i fleire, separate vindauge. Vi byrjar med å presentere dei
      komponentane som blir sette automatisk i eit ordinært biletvindauge. Noen
      av desse kan rett nok fjernast med kommandoar i
      <link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">Vis</link>-menyen, men du
      finn kanskje ut at det er like greitt å ha dei på plass.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="ru">
      Каждое открытое вами изображение в GIMP отображается в своём
      собственном отдельном окне. (В некоторых случаях, несколько окон
      могут отображать одно изображение, но это  редкость). Мы начнём с
      краткого описания компонентов, представленных по умолчанию в
      обычном окне изображения.  Некоторые из них могут быть убраны с
      помощью команд  в меню <!--link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view"-->
      Просмотр<!--/link-->; но по всей вероятности вы решите, что вы не хотите
      делать этого.
    </para>
  
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 中，打开的各个图像都在自己独立的窗口显示。(有
      时多个窗口都显示同一个图像，但这不常见。)我们在这将对默认普通图像窗口的
      组件一个简单的介绍。事实上，您可以
      用<link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">查看</link>菜单使其中的一
      些不显示;但是可能会发现您并不想这么干。
    </para>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Title Bar:</emphasis>
        At the top of the image window you will probably see a emphasis bar,
        showing the name of the image and some basic information about it. The
        emphasis bar is actually provided by the windowing system, not by GIMP
        itself, so its appearance may vary with different operating systems,
        window managers, and/or themes. In the
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Preferences dialog</link>
        you can customize the information that appears here, if you want to.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Záhlaví okna:</emphasis>
        Na vrchu okna obrázku pravděpodobně vidíte jeho záhlaví, které
        zobrazuje jméno obrázku a další informace o něm. Záhlaví okna
        nevytváří přímo GIMP, ale správce oken, takže se jeho vlastnosti mohou
        měnit v závislosti na používaném operačním systému, správci oken nebo
        motivu vzhledu. V <!--FIXCS<link
          linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">-->dialogu Předvolby<!--</link>-->
        můžete nastavit, jaké informace se v záhlaví zobrazují.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Titelzeile:</emphasis>
        Im oberen Bereich des Fensters befindet sich die Titelzeile, in
        welcher verschiedene Informationen angezeigt werden. Da dieser Bereich
        des Fensters nicht von GIMP selbst, sondern vom Betriebssystem bzw.
        Desktopsystem Ihres Computers verwaltet wird, kann sich das Aussehen
        von dem hier gezeigten unterscheiden. Die dargestellten Informationen
        bleiben jedoch gleich. Wie Sie die angezeigten Informationen nach
        Ihren eigenen Bedürfnissen anpassen können erfahren Sie im <xref
        linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Barra de título:</emphasis> En la parte superior de la
        ventana de la imagen probablemente se encuentre el nombre de la imagen
        y alguna información adicional como título de la ventana.  Esta barra
        la dispone el gestor de ventanas del sistema, no GIMP, por lo que su
        apariencia puede variar con el sistema operativo.  En el <link
        linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">diálogo de preferencias</link> puede
        personalizar la información que aparece en el título, si así lo desea.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Barre de titre</emphasis> :
        En haut de la fenêtre image se trouve probablement la barre de titre
        dans laquelle s'affiche le nom de l'image et quelques informations de
        base. La barre de titre est en fait générée par le gestionnaire de
        fenêtre du système et non par GIMP, aussi son apparence peut changer
        selon le système d'exploitation, le gestionnaire de fenêtre et/ou le
        thème. Dans le
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Dialogue des préférences</link>
        vous pouvez personnaliser les informations qui y apparaîssent.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Barra del titolo:</emphasis>
        in cima alla finestra immagine è presente e in evidenza una barra che
        mostra il titolo dell'immagine e alcune informazioni di base su di
        essa. La barra del titolo viene "costruita" dal gestore delle
        finestre, non da GIMP, per cui la sua resa varia da sistema a sistema
        a seconda del gestore di finestre, del sistema operativo, dal tema in
        uso, ecc. Nella
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">finestra delle preferenze</link>
        è possibile personalizzare le informazioni da mostrare in questa
        barra.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>제목 표시줄:</emphasis> 이미지 창의 상단을 보면 강조된
        줄을 볼수 있는데, 이곳에는 이미지의 이름과 간단한 기본정보가
        표시됩니다. 이 제목 표시줄은 사실 김프가 아닌, 윈도우 시스템(역자
        주 : MS 사의 Windows가 아닌 GUI를 의미함)에서 제공되는 것입니다.
        따라서 운영체제나, 윈도우 관리자, 혹은 테마 등에 따라 다르게 보일
        수 있습니다.  그리고
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">기본 설정
             대화상자</link> -->
        기본 설정 대화상자에서 이곳에 나타나는 정보의 종류를 변경할 수
        있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>TitelBalk:</emphasis>
        Aan de bovenkant van het venster ziet u hoogstwaarschijnlijk de
        titelbalk. Deze toont de naam van de afbeelding en wat korte
        informatie over haar eigenschappen. Deze balk wordt verzorgd door het
        venstersysteem en niet door <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
        dus de vorm ervan is afhankelijk van welk besturing-, venstersysteem
        en mogelijk thema u gekozen heeft. In het
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Voorkeuren venster</link>
        kunt u de getoonde informatie aanpassen als u dat wenst.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Tittellinja:</emphasis> Øvst i biletvindauget finn du eit
        lite område som viser namnet på biletet og noen andre opplysningar
        om det. Tittellinja blir eigentleg laga av datamaskinen, og ikkje
        av <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Difor kan utsjånaden skifte etter kva
        operativsystem du nyttar og korleis dette er sett opp. Du kan
        tilpassa ein del av innstillingane for tittellinja i 
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">brukarinnstillingane</link> dersom 
        du ønskjer det.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Сверху окна изображения вы вероятно увидите заголовок,
        отображающий название изображения и некоторую  основную
        информацию о нём. На самом деле заголовок  предоставляется
        оконной системой, а не самим GIMP'ом, поэтому его внешний вид
        может различаться на разных  операционных системах, оконных
        менеджерах, и/или  темах. Если желаете, в разделе  <link
        linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Настройки</link> вы можете
        изменить отображаемую здесь информацию.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>标题栏：</emphasis> 在图像窗口最上面是标题栏，显示图像的名
        字和一些基本信息。标题栏其实是由窗口系统而不是 GIMP 自身提供的，因此
        在不同操作系统，窗口管理器和主题中表现也不尽相同。如果您愿意，可以在
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">首选项对话框</link>
        中定制您想显示的信息。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Image Menu:</emphasis>
        Directly below the emphasis bar appears the Image Menu (unless it has
        been suppressed). This menu gives you access to nearly every operation
        you can perform on an image. (There are some <quote>global</quote>
        actions that can only be accessed via the Toolbox menu.) You can
        also get the Image Menu by right-clicking inside the image
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Users with an Apple Macintosh and a one button mouse can use
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>mousebutton</mousebutton>
            </keycombo> instead.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        , or by left-clicking on the little <quote>arrow</quote> symbol in
        the upper left corner, if for some reason you find one of these more
        convenient.
        More: most menu operations can also be activated from the keyboard,
        using Alt plus an <quote>accelerator</quote> key underlined in the
        menu emphasis.
        More: you can define your own custom shortcuts for menu actions, if
        you enable <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface"> Use Dynamic Keyboard
        Shortcuts</link> in the Preferences dialog.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Nabídka obrázku:</emphasis>
        Přímo pod záhlavím okna je zobrazena nabídka obrázku (pokud nebyla
        vypnuta). Poskytuje přístup v podstatě ke všem možným operacím s
        obrázkem (existuje několik „globálních“ operací dostupných jen z
        nabídky panelu nástrojů). Nabídku obrázku můžete otevřít také
        kliknutím pravým tlačítkem myši kamkoliv do obrázku
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Na počítačích Macintosh lze použít
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> a levé tlačítko myši.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        , nebo kliknutím levým tlačítkem myši na malou ikonu „šipky“ v levém
        horním rohu okna obrázku. Vyberte si způsob, který vám nejlépe
        vyhovuje. Většina operací z této nabídky může být navíc vyvolána přímo
        z klávesnice pomocí klávesy Alt spolu s mnemonickou klávesou
        (podtrženou v názvu nabídky) či pomocí klávesových zkratek,
        pokud povolíte <!--FIXME: cs <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">-->
        Používat dynamické klávesové zkratky<!--</link>--> v dialogu Předvolby.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Bildmenü:</emphasis>
        Genau unter der Titelzeile befindet sich die Menüzeile des
        Bildfensters. Dieses Menü erlaubt Ihnen einen Zugriff auf fast alle
        Operationen und Werkzeuge, welche in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        zur Verfügung stellt. Das Bildmenü ist außerdem mit einem rechten
        Mausklick
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Benutzer eines Apple-Computers mit einer Eintastenmaus können
            das Kontextmenü durch Drücken von
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Strg</keycap><mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton>
            </keycombo>
            erreichen.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        auf das Bild zu erreichen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Menú de la imagen:</emphasis> Directamente por debajo de la
        barra de título se encuentra el menú de la imagen (a menos que haya
        sido ocultado).  Este menú brinda acceso a casi todas las operaciones
        que pueden efectuarse sobre una imagen (hay algunas acciones
        <quote>globales</quote> que sólo pueden ser accedidas por el menú de
        la caja de herramientas).  Además puede obtener este mismo menú
        haciendo clic derecho dentro de la imagen
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Los usuarios de una Apple Macintosh o de ratones con sólo un botón
            pueden hacer <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> clic en su lugar.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        , o haciendo clic izquierdo sobre la pequeña <quote>flecha</quote> de
        la esquina superior izquierda, si por alguna razón lo encuentra más
        conveniente.  Es más: la mayoría de las operaciones del menú pueden
        activarse desde el teclado, usando Alt mas una tecla
        <quote>aceleradora</quote> que se encuentra subrayada en el menú.  Y
        más: puede definir sus propios atajos de teclado para las acciones del
        menú, si activa <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface"> Usar
        combinaciones de teclas dinámicas </link> en el diálogo de
        preferencias.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Barre des Menus :</emphasis>
        Juste en dessous de la barre de titre se trouve le <quote>Menu
        d'image</quote> (à moins qu'il n'ait été désactivé). Ce menu vous
        permet d'accéder à presque toutes les opérations réalisables sur une
        image (Il y a des actions <quote>globales</quote> qui ne sont
        accessibles que par le menu de la boîte à outil). Vous pouvez aussi
        dérouler le menu image en cliquant avec le bouton droit sur l'image
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Les utilisateurs de Mac peuvent utiliser
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>bouton</mousebutton>
            </keycombo>.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        , ou bien en cliquant sur la flèche dans le coin supérieur gauche, si
        l'une de ces méthodes vous convient mieux. De plus, la plupart des
        opérations du menu peuvent aussi être activées depuis le clavier, en
        utilisant Alt et une touche <quote>accélératrice</quote> soulignée
        dans le texte du menu. Enfin, vous pouvez définir vos propres
        raccourcis clavier pour les actions du menu, si vous avez autorisé
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">
          Utiliser les raccourcis clavier dynamiques
        </link>
        dans le dialogue des Préférences.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Menu immagine:</emphasis>
        direttamente sotto la barra del titolo appare il menu immagine (a meno
        che non sia stata disabilitata la sua visualizzazione). Da questo menu
        si può accedere a quasi tutte le operazioni effettuabili su
        un'immagine (ci sono alcune azioni <quote>globali</quote>
        che possono essere raggiunte solo tramite il menu degli strumenti). È
        possibile raggiungere il menu immagine anche tramite il tasto destro
        del mouse facendo clic all'interno dell'immagine
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Gli utenti Apple con mouse monotasto possono usare in alternativa
            il tasto della tastiera <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 
            insieme al tasto del mouse.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        , oppure facendo clic sulla piccolo simbolo a forma di
        <quote>freccia</quote>
        presente nell'angolo in alto a sinistra, se lo trovate più comodo.
        Inoltre: molte operazioni di menu possono essere attivate da tastiera,
        usando Alt più un tasto <quote>acceleratore</quote>
        che viene visualizzato sottolineato nelle voci di menu. E ancora: è
        possibile definire delle scorciatoie personalizzate per le azioni di
        menu abilitanto
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">
          Usa tasti scorciatoia dinamici
        </link> nella finestra delle preferenze.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>이미지 메뉴:</emphasis>
        이미지 메뉴는 (없애지 않는 한) 제목 표시줄 바로 아래에 위치합니다.
        이 메뉴를 통해 이미지 편집을 위한 거의 모든 작업들을 할 수
        있습니다(하지만 도구상자 메뉴를 통해서만 접근할 수 있는
        <quote>전역</quote> 명령어들도 있습니다). 이미지 안에서 오른쪽
        버튼을 클릭하거나
        <footnote>
          <para>
            애플 맥킨토시 사용자들과 원 버튼 마우스 사용자들은
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 마우스 버튼으로 대신할 수 있습니다.
          </para>
        </footnote>
        이미지 창의 왼쪽 상단 구석에 있는 <quote>화살표</quote> 를 클릭해서
        이미지 메뉴를 사용할 수도 있습니다.
        추가 : 대부분의 메뉴는 Alt 키와 메뉴 이름 옆에 있는
        <quote>단축키</quote>를 누름으로써 키보드로도 실행시킬 수 있습니다.
        추가 : 기본 설정 대화상자에서
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">동적 키보드
        단축키</link> --> 동적 키보드 단축키를 활성화시켰다면, 메뉴 동작에
        대한 단축키를 직접 설정할 수도 있습니다.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Afbeeldingsmenu:</emphasis>
        Meteen onder de titelbalk zit het afbeeldingsmenu (Tenzij dit
        onderdrukt is). De items in deze tweede balk geven u toegang tot bijna
        alle bewerkingen die u op een afbeelding kunt uitvoeren. (Er zijn
        enkele "algemene" bewerkingen die u alleen via het gereedschapsvenster
        kunt wijzigen.) Een andere manier om toegang te krijgen tot het
        afbeeldingsmenu is het rechtsklikken als de muiscursor in het
        afbeeldingsvenster zit
        <footnote>
          <para>
            Apple Macintosh-gebruikers kunnen ook de
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            +linker muisknop combinatie gebruiken
          </para>
        </footnote>
        , of u kunt links-klikken op het kleine pijl-symbool in de
        linkerbovenhoek. Verder krijgt u nog eenvoudiger toegang tot de meeste
        bewerkingen door een <keycap>Alt</keycap> +"Sneltoets" combinatie te
        gebruiken. In de menu's staat de letter
        onderstreept die u voor de betreffende functie moet gebruiken. U kunt
        ook uw eigen sneltoets-combinaties instellen als u het vakje voor `
        <!--link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface"XXX_NL-->
        use dynamic keyboard shortcuts<!--/link-->
        ' in het `Bediening'-tabblad van het
        <!--link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface"XXX_NL-->Voorkeuren<!--/link-->
        dialoogvenster aanvinkt.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Biletmenyen:</emphasis>
         Like under tittellinja finn du biletmenyen (dersom du ikkje har vald å
         gjere han usynleg). Denne menyen gir deg tilgang til det meste du kan
         gjere med eit bilete. (Det finst noen få globale settingar som bare er
         tilgjengelege frå hovudmenyen). Du kan også få tilgang til biletmenyen
         ved å høgreklikka på biletet
        <footnote>
          <para>
             På Apple Macintosh kan du bruke <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> +
             museknappen.
          </para>
        </footnote>,
        eller ved å venstreklikka på pilsymbolet i øvre, venstre hjørne
        dersom du av ein eller annan grunn finn dette enklare. Vidare: Dei
        fleste menyfunksjonane kan også nåast frå tastaturet med
        <keycap>Alt</keycap>-tasten pluss den bokstaven som er understreka i
        menyen. Endeleg kan du også definera dine eigne snartastar dersom du
        opnar <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">tastatursnarvegane</link>
        i hovudmenyen.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Прямо под заголовком находится меню изображения (до тех пор,
        пока оно не будет отключено).  С помощью этого меню вы можете
        получить доступ  ко всем операциям, применимым к изображению. (
        Некоторые "глобальные" действия, которые доступны  только через
        меню панели инструментов.) Вы также можете  вызвать меню
        изображение щелчком правой кнопкой мыши  на
        изображении<footnote><para> Пользователи  Apple Macintosh могут
        использовать  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+левая кнопка
        мыши.</para></footnote>,  или щелчком левой кнопкой мыши по
        небольшому значку- "стрелке" в левом верхнем углу, если вы
        считаете один из этих  методов более удобным.  И ещё:
        большинство доступных через меню операций может  быть
        активировано через клавиатуру с помощью клавиши <keycap>Alt</keycap>+
        <quote>клавиша быстрого доступа</quote>, подчёркнутую в пункте меню.
        Также вы можете назначить свои собственные клавиши быстрого  доступа
        для действий меню, если разрешите <link
        linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">Использовать клавиши быстрого доступа
        </link> в диалоге настроек.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>图像菜单：</emphasis> 标题栏正下方是图像菜单(除非它被挤压
        了)。该菜单提供几乎所有的可以在图像上操作的功能。(一些“全局”操作只能
        通过工具箱菜单实现。)您也能在图像菜单中点右键或在左上角左键点“箭头”
        标志来打开图像菜单，选择您觉得最方便的办法。另外：大部分操作也能通过
        键盘，用Alt+ 菜单标题旁带下划线的字母。如果您在首选项对话框勾选
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">使用动态快捷键</link>
        ，就可以自定义自己菜单动作的快捷键。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-image-window-origin">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Menu Button:</emphasis>
        Clicking on this little button gives you the Image Menu, except in a
        column instead of a row. Mnemonics users who don't want the menu bar
        visible can acces to this menu by pressing the
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
         key.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Tlačítko nabídky:</emphasis>
        Kliknutí na toto tlačítko se otevře nabídka obrázku, seřazená do
        sloupce místo do vodorovné řady. Uživatelé mnemonik, kteří nechtějí
        mít viditelnou nabídku v liště mohou tuto nabídku otevřít stisknutím
        klávesy
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de"><!-- fuzzy 10/10/2004 -->
        <emphasis>Menüschaltfläche:</emphasis>
        Durch Klicken auf die Menüschaltfläche erreichen Sie das Bildmenü.
        Um dieses per Tastatur aufzurufen, können Sie
        <keycombo><keycap>Umschalt</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
        verwenden.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Botón del menú:</emphasis> Hacer clic en este pequeño botón
        hace aparecer el menú de la imagen, en forma de columna en vez de
        fila.  Los usuarios mnemotécnicos que ocultan la barra del menú pueden
        acceder a éste presionando las teclas
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Bouton Menu :</emphasis>
        Cliquer sur ce petit bouton déroule le Menu d'image sur une colonne au
        lieu d'une ligne. Ceux qui utilisent les accélérateurs claviers
        et qui n'ont pas la barre des menus visible peuvent accéder au menu
        d'image par la touche
        <keycombo><keycap>Maj</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Pulsante menu:</emphasis> facendo clic su questo piccolo
        pulsante si ottiene il menu immagine. Gli utenti con buona memoria
        che non desiderano avere la barra dei menu sempre visibile, possono
        accedervi premendo in alternativa la combinazione di tasti
        <keycombo><keycap>Maiusc</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
       <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>메뉴 버튼:</emphasis>
        이 작은 버튼을 누르면 세로로된 이미지 메뉴를 사용할 수 있습니다.
        이미지 메뉴를 보이지 않게 설정하고,
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
        키를 눌러 이 메뉴를 사용할 수도 있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Menuknop:</emphasis>
        Als u op deze kleine knop drukt krijgt u het Afbeeldingsmenu in beeld
        in kolomvorm in plaats van in een rij. Geoefende sneltoets-gebruikers
        die de menubalk niet meer in beeld willen hebben, kunnen dit menu
        openen met de
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
        toetscombinatie.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Menyknappen:</emphasis>
        Klikk på denne knappen for å få fram menyen som eige menyfelt. Køyrer
        du av ein eller annan grunn med usynleg biletmeny, kan du få fram
        menyen når du treng han ved å trykke
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Щелчок по этой небольшой кнопке вызывает меню изображения,
        расположенное в столбец вместо строки. Мнемонические
        пользователи, которые не желают держать панель меню видимой,
        могут получить доступ к этому меню с помощью клавиш
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN"><!-- fuzzy 10/10/2004 -->
        <emphasis>菜单按钮：</emphasis>
        点击这个小按钮就出现竖向的图像菜单。这个按钮并不是特别有用。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-image-window-ruler">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Ruler:</emphasis>
        In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the left of the
        image, indicating coordinates within the image. You can control what
        type of coordinates are shown if you want to. By default, pixels are
        used, but you can change to other units, using the Units setting
        described below.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One of the most important uses of rulers is to create
        <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.
        If you click on a ruler and drag into the image display, a guideline
        will be created, which you can use to help you position things
        accurately. Guides can be moved by clicking on them and dragging, or
        deleted by dragging them out of the image display.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Pravítko:</emphasis>
        Ve výchozím uspořádání okna jsou pravítka umístěna nalevo a nad
        obrázkem a zobrazují souřadnice v obrázku. Jaké souřadnice se
        zobrazují, můžete nastavit. Ve výchozím nastavení se používají pixely,
        ale můžete nastavit i jiné jednotky, jak je popsáno dále.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pravítka slouží také k vytváření <emphasis>vodítek</emphasis>.
        Pokud na pravítko kliknete a potáhnete myší do obrázku, vytvoří se
        vodítko, které lze použít k přesnému umisťování objektů v obrázku.
        Vodítka lze přesouvat kliknutím a tažením. Odstranit je lze přetažením
        mimo obrázek.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Lineal:</emphasis>
        In der üblichen Anordnung des Bildfensters erscheinen Lineale an der
        oberen und linken Kante. Diese Lineale beschreiben die aktuellen
        Koordinaten des Bildes. In der Standardeinstellung wird als Maßeinheit
        für die Lineale <quote>Pixel</quote>
        verwendet. Dies können Sie jedoch ganz einfach über das Einheitenmenü
        am unteren Bildrand ändern.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Eine der wichtigsten Eigenschaften der Lineale ist, dass Sie aus ihnen
        die Hilfslinien <quote>herausziehen</quote> können. Probieren Sie es
        einfach einmal aus: Klicken Sie auf ein Lineal und ziehen Sie bei
        gedrückter Maustaste eine Hilfslinie in das Bild. Sehr einfach - sehr
        hilfreich!
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Regla:</emphasis> En la configuración predeterminada, las
        reglas se muestran en la parte superior y en la parte izquierda de la
        imagen, e indican las coordenadas dentro de la misma.  Puede controlar
        el tipo de coordenadas que se muestran si así lo desea.  Por defecto,
        se emplean píxeles, pero puede cambiar a otras unidades, mediante la
        opción Unidades que se describe debajo.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Uno de los usos más importantes de las reglas es el de crear
        <emphasis>guías</emphasis>. Si hace clic sobre una regla y arrastra
        el ratón hacia adentro de la imagen, se crea una línea guía, la que
        puede usarse para posicionar objetos con precisión.  Las guías pueden
        moverse haciendo clic sobre ellas y arrastrando el ratón, y pueden
        borrarse arrastrándolas fuera de la imagen.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Les règles :</emphasis>
        Dans la configuration par défaut, les règles sont affichées en haut et
        à gauche de l'image, elles indiquent les coordonnées dans l'image.
        Vous pouvez choisir le type de coordonnées affiché. Par défaut,
        l'unité de mesure est le pixel, mais vous pouvez choisir une autre
        unité en utilisant les paramètres d'unité décrits plus loin.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Un des usages majeur des règles est de créer des
        <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.
        Si vous cliquez sur une règle et que vous la glissez dans l'image
        affichée, un guide va être créé que vous pouvez dès lors utiliser pour
        vous positionner précisément dans l'image. Les guides sont déplaçables
        en cliquant dessus ; ramenez-les vers leur règle d'origine pour les
        ôter de l'image.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Righello:</emphasis> nella disposizione predefinita,
        vengono mostrati dei righelli sopra e a sinistra dell'immagine,
        indicanti le coordinate del puntatore nell'immagine. È possibile
        controllare il tipo di coordinare da mostrare: mentre
        l'impostazione predefinita mostra i pixel è possibile cambiare in
        altre unità usando le impostazioni descritte di seguito.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Uno degli usi principali dei righelli è per creare delle
        <emphasis>guide</emphasis>. Facendo clic su un righello e
        trascinando il puntatore del mouse sull'immagine, verrà creata una
        guida; essa può essere sfruttata per posizionare agevolmente e con
        precisione degli oggetti grafici sull'immagine. Le guide possono
        essere spostate facendo clic e trascinandole o cancellandole e
        creandone delle nuove in altre posizioni sull'immagine.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>눈금자:</emphasis>
        기본값으로 눈금자는 이미지의 상단과 왼쪽에 표시되며, 이미지 내의
        좌표를 나타냅니다. 수치 타입은 기본값으로 픽셀이 사용되지만,
        원한다면 아래에 있는 단위 설정법을 이용해 다른 타입으로 바꿀 수도
        있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        눈금자의 가장 중요한 기능 중에 하나는 <emphasis>안내선</emphasis>을
        만드는 것입니다. 눈금자를 클릭한 다음 이미지 내부로 드래그하면
        이미지의 정확한 배치에 도움이 되는 안내선을 생성할 수 있습니다.
        안내선의 이동은 안내선을 클릭한 후 드래그하면 되고, 이미지 밖으로
        드래그하면 삭제됩니다.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Lineaal:</emphasis>
        Als standaardinstelling worden er links en boven van de afbeeldig
        linealen getoond met daarin de coordinaten van de afbeelding. U kunt
        de eenheden die aangegeven worden aanpassen, de standaardweergave is
        in beeldpunten, verder onder kunt u vinden hoe u deze aanduiding kunt
        wijzigen.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Een van de belangrijkste functies van de linealen is de mogelijkheid
        om <emphasis>hulplijnen</emphasis>
        aan te maken. Als u op een lineaal de linker muistoets indrukt, dan de
        muis met ingedrukte toets de afbeelding insleept, neemt u een hulplijn
        mee die u vervolgens kan helpen om verschillende voorwerpen in uw
        afbeelding netjes ten opzichte van elkaar te rangschikken. De
        hulplijnen kunnen verplaatst worden door er op te gaan staan en ze
        weer met ingedrukte linkermuisknop te verslepen, Door ze de afbeelding
        uit te slepen verwijderd u ze tenslotte.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Linjal:</emphasis>
         I normaloppsettet er det synlege linjalar over og til venstra for
         biletet. Dette for å vise koordinata til musepeikaren inne i biletet.
         Til vanleg viser linjalane biletpunkt (pikslar), men dette kan du
         endre. Sjå nedafor.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Ein av dei viktige bruksmåtane for linjalane er å lage
        <emphasis>hjelpelinjer</emphasis> (også kalla 
        <quote>innrettingslinjer</quote>). Klikkar du på ein linjal og dreg
        musepeikaren inn på biletet, vil det bli laga ei hjelpelinje på
        biletet. Slike hjelpelinjer er nyttige når du ønskjer å plassera noe
        nøyaktig. Hjelpelinjene kan flyttast ved å klikka på dei og dra dei
        til ny posisjon, eller du kan flytta dei heilt ut av biletet for å
        bli kvitt dei.
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        В схеме по умолчанию линейки показаны сверху и слева от
        изображения, отображая координаты внутри изображения.  Если
        желаете, вы можете выбрать в каких единицах измерения
        отображаются координаты. По умолчанию используются пикселы,  но
        вы можете изменить их на другие единицы измерения  с помощью
        настроек, описанных ниже.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Одно из основных действий для использования линеек это  создание
        <emphasis>направляющих</emphasis>. Если вы щёлкните на линейке
        и перетащите на окно изображения, будет создана направляющая
        линия, которая поможет вам аккуратно располагать предметы.
        Направляющие могуть быть перемещены с помощью щелчка по
        направляющей и перетаскиванием, или они могут быть удалены
        перетаскиванием  за пределы изображения.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>标尺：</emphasis> 在默认布局中，标尺在图像的左边和上面，显
        示图像的坐标。您可以控制想显示何种类型的坐标。默认使用像素，但能够用
        下面提到的单位设置更换为其它单位。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-quick-mask-toggle">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>QuickMask Toggle:</emphasis>
        At the lower left corner of the image display is a small button that
        toggles on or off the Quick Mask, which is an alternate, and often
        extremely useful, way of viewing the selected area within the image.
        For more details see <link linkend="gimp-qmask">QuickMask</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Přepínač rychlé masky:</emphasis>
        V levém dolním rohu okna obrázku je malé tlačítko, které zapíná a
        vypíná režim rychlé masky, což je jiný, a často nesmírně užitečný,
        způsob zobrazení vybrané oblasti v obrázku. Více se dozvíte v části
        <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Rychlá maska</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Schaltfläche <emphasis>Schnellmaske:</emphasis>
        Mit dieser Schaltfläche können Sie die Schnellmaske aktivieren und
        deaktivieren. Die Maske selber ist eine alternative Ansicht, um
        Auswahlen zu bearbeiten. Detaillierte Informationen hierzu finden Sie
        im Abschnitt <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Schnellmaske</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Activador de la máscara rápida:</emphasis> En la esquina
        inferior izquierda de la ventana de la imagen hay un pequeño botón que
        activa o desactiva la máscara rápida, la cual es una forma
        alternativa, y a menudo muy útil, de visualizar el área seleccionada
        de la imagen.  Para más detalles diríjase a la sección sobre <link
        linkend="gimp-qmask">máscara rápida</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>(Dés)activer le masque rapide :</emphasis>
        En bas à gauche de la fenêtre image se trouve un petit bouton qui
        permet d'activer ou de désactiver le masque rapide qui est une manière
        alternative, et souvent très utile, de voir la partie sélectionnée
        d'une image. Pour plus d'information voyez la section
        <link linkend="gimp-image-window-qmask-button">Masque rapide</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Commutazione maschera veloce:</emphasis> nell'angolo in
        basso a sinistra della finestra immagine è mostrato un piccolo
        pulsante che serve ad abilitare e disabilitare la maschera veloce,
        la quale è semplicemente un modo alternativo, spesso molto utile,
        di vedere le aree selezionate in un'immagine. Per ulteriori
        dettagli sull'argomento, vedere la parte relativa
        alla <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Maschera veloce</link> di questo
        manuale.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>퀵마스크 전환:</emphasis>
        이미지 창의 좌하단에 있는 이 버튼은 퀵마스크를 실행하거나
        종료하는데 사용됩니다. 퀵마스크는 이미지 내의 선택 영역을 표시하는
        방법의 하나로 굉장히 유용한 기능입니다. 이에 대한 자세한 내용은
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-qmask">퀵마스크</link> -->
        퀵마스크에 있습니다.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Snelmasker knop:</emphasis>
        In de linkeronderhoek van de afbeeldingsvenster bevindt zich de kleine
        knop die het snelmasker uit of aan zet. Het uit- en aanzetten van dit
        masker is een uitermate handige manier om te zien welk deel van de
        afbeelding er nu eigenlijk en in welke mate, geselecteerd is. Voor
        meer informatie raadpleegt u
        <!--link linkend="gimp-qmask"XXX_NL-->Snelmasker<!--/link-->.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Snarmaske av/på:</emphasis>
        Nede i venstre hjørne av biletvindauget finn du knappen for å veksle
        mellom snarmaske av eller på. Snarmaska blir brukt for å syne
        markerte område av eit bilete. Sjå <xref linkend="gimp-qmask" />
        for nærare detaljar.
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        В левом нижнем углу окна изображения расположена  небольшая
        кнопка, которая включает или выключает  быструю маску, которая
        является альтернативным, и часто черезвычайно полезным методом
        просмотра  выделенной области внутри изображения. Для
        дополнительной информации смотрите раздел<link
        linkend="gimp-qmask">Быстрая маска</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>快速蒙板开关：</emphasis> 在图像显示的左下角有一个控制快速
        蒙板开启关闭的小按钮，这是非常有用的一种查看图像选区的方法。要了解更
        多，请看
        <link linkend="gimp-image-window-qmask-button">快速蒙板</link>。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Pointer Coordinates:</emphasis>
        In the lower left corner of the window is a rectangular area used to
        show the current pointer coordinates (that is, the mouse location, if
        you are using a mouse), whenever the pointer is within the image
        boundaries. The units are the same as for the rulers.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Souřadnice ukazatele:</emphasis>
        V levém dolním rohu okna obrázku, v levé části stavové lišty, je
        oblast zobrazující aktuální souřadnice ukazatele (kurzoru myši, pokud
        používáte myš), pokud je ukazatel umístěn nad obrázkem. Jednotky jsou
        tytéž, jako používají pravítka.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Mauszeigerkoordinaten:</emphasis>
        Die Koordinaten des Mauszeigers im aktuellen Bild werden in diesem
        Bereich eingeblendet. Die Einheiten der Koordinaten (x, y im
        Koordinatensystem des Bildes) können mit der angrenzenden Schaltfläche
        verändert werden.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Coordenadas del puntero:</emphasis> En la esquina inferior
        izquierda de la ventana hay un área rectangular en la que se muestran
        las coordenadas actuales del puntero (esto es, la ubicación del ratón
        u otro dispositivo de entrada), cuando el puntero se halla dentro de
        la imagen.  Las unidades empleadas son las mismas que las de las
        reglas.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Coordonnées du pointeur :</emphasis>
        Dans le coin inférieur gauche de la fenêtre image s'affiche les
        coordonnées du pointeur (c.-à-d. la position de la souris, si vous
        utilisez une souris), tant que le pointeur se trouve sur l'image.
        L'unité est la même que pour les règles.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Coordinate del puntatore:</emphasis> nell'angolo in basso
        a sinistra della finestra, sotto il tasto di maschera veloce, c'è
        un'area dedicata alla visualizzazione delle coordinate del
        puntatore (ergo la posizione della punta della freccetta del mouse)
        se il puntatore è all'interno dell'area immagine. L'unità di misura
        è la stessa usata per i righelli.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>커서 좌표:</emphasis>
        창의 왼쪽 아래 구석에 있는 사각형 부분에는 커서가 이미지 경계안에
        있을 경우 현재 커서의 좌표가 표시되며 단위는 눈금자와
        동일합니다(마우스를 사용한다면 마우스 커서의 현재 위치입니다).
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Cursorpositie:</emphasis>
        Het rechthoekige vlak in de linkeronderhoek toont op welke coordinaten
        de (muis-)cursor zich op dat moment precies bevindt als deze ergens
        binnen de randen van het afbeeldingsvenster zit. Deze coördinaten
        worden in dezelfde eenheden weergegeven als die van de linealen.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Peikarkoordinat:</emphasis>
         Nede til venstre finn du koordinata for peikaren. I praksis er dette
         som oftast koordinata for musepeikaren dersom du bruker mus. Dersom
         peikaren kjem utanfor biletet, blir koordinata viste i grått.
         Måleeiningane er dei same som du har sett for linjalane.
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        В левом нижнем углу окна расположена прямоугольная область
        используемая для отображения текущих координат указателя
        (положение мыши, если вы используете мышь), когда указатель
        расположен в пределах границ изображения. Используются те же
        единицы измерения, что и для линеек.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>指针坐标：</emphasis> 当您的指针在图像内部时，左下角的矩形
        窗口就会显示当前的指针坐标。(假如您使用鼠标，就是指鼠标指针所在位
        置。)改单位和标尺单位一样。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <!--TODO cs es fr ko nl ru zh_CN: remove "new in GIMP 2.2" remarks-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Units menu:</emphasis>
        By default, the units used for the rulers and several other purposes
        are pixels. You can change to inches, cm, or several other
        possibilities using this menu. (If you do, note that the setting of
        <quote>Dot for dot</quote> in the View menu affects how the display is
        scaled: see <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Dot for Dot</link>
        for more information.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Nabídka jednotek:</emphasis> (Tato vlastnost je nová v
        Gimpu verze 2.2; neexistuje v Gimpu 2.0). Ve výchozím nastavení se
        pro pravítka a další účely používají pixely.  Pomocí této nabídky
        můžete přepnout na používání palců, centimetrů či jiných
        jednotek. (Pokud tak učiníte, uvědomte si, že nastavení volby "Bod
        na bod" v nabídce Zobrazení ovlivňuje způsob, jakým se upraví
        velikost zobrazení: viz
        <!--FIXME cs <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">-->Bod na
        bod<!--</link>-->.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Einheitenmenü:</emphasis>
        Die voreingestellte Maßeinheit in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        ist Pixel. Diese Maßeinheit wird von Werkzeugen, Linealen und vielen
        anderen Dingen in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        benutzt. Durch Klicken auf die Schaltfläche können Sie die Maßeinheit
        auf cm, inch oder andere verändern.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Menú de unidades:</emphasis> (Esta característica se
        encuentra disponible desde la versión 2.2 del GIMP; no aparece en GIMP
        2.0). Por defecto, las unidades empleadas para las reglas y para la
        mayoría de los propósitos son los píxeles.  Puede cambiar a
        centímetros, pulgadas, o a varias otras usando este menú (si lo hace,
        note que colocar <quote>Punto por punto</quote> en el menú Ver afecta
        la forma en que el visor es escalado: vea <link
        linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Punto por punto</link> para más
        información.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Menu des unités</emphasis> :
        (fonctionnalité apparue dans GIMP 2.2). Par défaut, l'unité utilisée
        pour les règles et d'autres fonctions est le pixel. Vous pouvez la
        changer pour le centimètre, le pouce ou bien d'autres possibilités en
        utilisant ce menu (si vous le faites, sachez que le paramètre
        <quote>Point pour point</quote> du menu Affichage modifiera les
        dimensions d'affichage de l'écran : Voyez
        <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Point pour point</link>
        pour plus d'informations.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Menu unità di misura:</emphasis>  L'unità di misura
        predefinita per i righelli e per
        molti altri scopi sono i pixel. Usando questo menu è possibile
        cambiare l'unità di misura in pollici, centimetri o molte altre
        unità (se lo fate, notate che le impostazioni di <quote>punto per
        punto</quote> nel menu Mostra interessa come il display viene
        scalato: vedere <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Punto per
        punto</link> per informazioni aggiuntive.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>단위 메뉴:</emphasis> (김프 2.2의 새로운 기능으로 2.0
        이하에는 없습니다) 눈금자나 다른 여러 목적에 사용되는 기본 단위는
        픽셀입니다. 하지만 이 메뉴를 통해 인치나 cm 등 다른 단위로 바꿀
        수도 있습니다. 단위를 바꿀 경우 보여지는 비율이 바뀔 수 있으므로
        보기 메뉴의 <quote>점대점</quote> 설정을 확인해야 합니다.
        이에 대한 자세한 내용은
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">점대점</link> -->
        점대점에 있습니다.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Eenheden menu:</emphasis>
        (Dit is een nieuwe eigenschap in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.2 die niet in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.0 beschikbaar is.) Standaard gebruiken de
        linealen en enkele andere
        functies het aantal beeldpunten als eenheidsmaat U kunt dit in dit
        menu veranderen naar duimen, centimeters(cm) of enkele andere
        eenheden. (Als u dit doet, zult u zien dat de instelling van `punt
        voor punt' in het <guimenu>Beel<accel>d</accel></guimenu>-menu de
        manier waarop de afbeelding getoond wordt, beiinvloed: Zie
        <!--link
          linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot"XXX_NL -->punt voor punt<!--/link-->
        voor meer informatie.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Måleeining:</emphasis> I normalsettinga blir det brukt
        pikslar (px) som måleeining på linjalane, men det kan av og til
        vere behov for andre måleeiningar. Du kan velje etter behov med
        denne menyen. (Merk at innstillingane i <quote>Punkt for
        punkt</quote> i Vis-menyen kan påverke måten biletet blir skalert
        på. Sjå <xref linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot" /> for
        nærare detaljar).
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Меню единиц:</emphasis> По умолчанию, единицы измерения,
        используемые для линеек и других целей - точки. Их можно изменить на
        дюймы, сантиметры и другие единицы при помощи этого меню.
        (При изменении имейте ввиду, что установка режима <quote>Точка за
        точкой</quote> в меню изображения влияет на то, каким образом
        отображение масштабируется: для дополнительной информации
        смотрите <!--link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot"-->Точка за
        точкой<!--/link-->.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>单位菜单：</emphasis> (这是 GIMP 2.2 的新特性,在 GIMP 2.0
        中没有)。在标尺和许多其它操作中默认的单位是像素。您能在该菜单中将其
        单位变为英尺，厘米或其它可用的单位。(如果您要这么做，要注意在“查看”
        菜单中“点对点”的设置对显示刻度的影响：更详细的信息可以看
        <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">点对点</link>
        。)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-image-window-zoom">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Zoom button:</emphasis>
        There are a number of ways to zoom the image in or out, but this menu
        is perhaps the simplest.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Nabídka zvětšení:</emphasis>
        (Tato vlastnost je nová v Gimpu verze 2.2; neexistuje v Gimpu 2.0).
        Existuje řada způsobů pro přibližování a oddalování obrázku, ale
        použití této nabídky je asi nejjednodušší.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Zoom-Schaltfläche:</emphasis>
        Sie können die Zoom-Stufe durch Klicken auf diese Schaltfläche
        beliebig verändern.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Botón de ampliación:</emphasis> (Esta característica se
        encuentra disponible desde la versión 2.2 del GIMP; no aparece en GIMP
        2.0).  Hay varias maneras de apliar o reducir la imagen, pero este
        menú parece ser la más simple.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Bouton Zoom :</emphasis>
        (fonctionnalité apparue dans GIMP 2.2). Il y a plusieurs manières de
        zoomer plus ou moins dans l'image, mais ce menu est rapide d'accès et
        affiche la valeur courante du zoom.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Pulsante di zoom:</emphasis> (questa caratteristica è
        nuova in GIMP 2.2 e quindi non è presente in GIMP 2.0 o versioni
        inferiori). Ci sono diversi metodi per fare lo zoom di un'immagine
        e questo menu è forse il metodo più semplice e diretto.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>확대 버튼:</emphasis>
        (김프 2.2의 새로운 기능으로 2.0 이하에는 없습니다) 이미지를
        확대하거나 축소해 보는 방법에는 여러가지가 있지만 이 메뉴를
        이용하는 것이 가장 간단합니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Schaalknop:</emphasis>
        (Dit is wederom nieuw in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.2 en niet
        beschikbaar in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.0) Er zijn verschillende
        manieren om de Schaling van de afbeelding te vergroten of the
        verkleinen, maar met dit menu gaat het waarschijnlijk het makkelijkst.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Zoomknappen:</emphasis>
        (Frå og med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2). Det finst mange måtar å
        forstørre eller forminske visninga av biletet på (zoome biletet),
        men denne knappen er oftast den raskaste dersom dei valde intervalla
        passar.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        (Эта особенность является новинкой в GIMP 2.2; она отсутствует
        в GIMP 2.0). Есть несколько методов  увеличения или уменьшения
        масштаба изображения,  но это меню является наиболее простым.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>缩放按钮：</emphasis> (这是 GIMP 2.2 的新特性,在 GIMP 2.0
        中没有)。有许多方法放大缩小图像，但使用这个菜单可能是最简单的。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-image-window-status-bar">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Status Area:</emphasis>
        The Status Area appears below the image display. Most of the time, by
        default, it shows which part of the image is currently active, and the
        amount of system memory that the image is consuming. You can customize
        the information that appears here, by changing your Preferences. When
        you perform time-consuming operations, the status area changes
        temporarily to show what operation is being performed, and its state
        of progress.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Stavová oblast:</emphasis>
        Stavová oblast je v dolní části okna pod obrázkem. Ve výchozím
        nastavení po většinu času informuje o tom, jaká část obrázku je právě
        aktivní a kolik obrázek spotřebovává paměti. V předvolbách ale můžete
        zobrazované informace nastavit podle vlastního uvážení. Když provádíte
        časově náročnou operaci, informuje stavová oblast o tom, jaká operace
        se provádí a jak je daleko.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Statuszeile:</emphasis>
        Die Statuszeile zeigt die aktuelle Ebene, auf der gezeichnet wird,
        sowie die Größe des derzeit vom Bild benutzten Speichers. Bei
        zeitintensiven Operationen verändert sich die Statuszeile zu einer
        Fortschrittsanzeige.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Área de estado:</emphasis> El área de estado aparece debajo
        de la imagen.  La mayor parte del tiempo, por defecto, muestra qué
        parte de la imagen se encuentra actualmente activa, y la cantidad de
        memoria del sistema que está consumiendo.  Puede personalizar la
        información que aparece aquí cambiando sus preferencias.  Cuando
        performa operaciones que tardan cierto tiempo en realizarse, el área
        de estado cambia temporalmente a una barra que muestra el nombre de la
        operación y el estado del progreso.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Barre de statut :</emphasis>
        La barre de statut se trouve en bas de la fenêtre image. La plupart du
        temps, par défaut, elle affiche la partie de l'image actuellement
        active, et l'espace mémoire que l'image occupe. Vous pouvez
        personnaliser ces informations en changeant vos Préférences. Lorsque
        vous lancez des opérations consommatrices de temps, la barre de statut
        indique quelle est l'opération en cours et son état d'avancement.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Area di stato:</emphasis> l'area di stato appare appena
        sotto la finestra immagine. Il più delle volte e come
        preimpostazione, mostra la parte dell'immagine attiva e la quantità
        di memoria usata per l'immagine. Le informazioni che appaiono in
        questa barra sono personalizzabili dalla finestra delle
        preferenze. Quando si eseguono operazioni il cui completamento può
        impiegare del tempo, l'area di stato viene costantemente aggiornata
        per mostrare l'operazione in esecuzione ed il suo andamento
        progressivo.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>상태창:</emphasis>
        상태창은 이미지 아래에 위치하며, 여기에는 현재 활성화되어 있는
        부분이나 이미지가 차지하는 메모리 용량이 표시됩니다. 이곳에
        표시되는 정보의 종류는 기본 설정을 통해 변경할 수 있습니다. 또
        시간이 많이 걸리는 작업을 하고 있다면 상태창에는 해당 작업의 진행
        상황이 시시각각 보여질 것입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Statusvak:</emphasis>
        Het statusvak is onderin het afbeeldingsvenster zichtbaar. Meestal
        laat het zien welk deel van de afbeelding bewerkt wordt en de
        hoeveelheid systeemgeheugen dat hierbij gebruikt wordt. U kunt in de
        <guimenu>
          <accel>V</accel>oorkeursinstellingen
        </guimenu>
        zelf instellen welke informatie hier weergegeven wordt. Als u
        bewerkingen doet die veel tijd kosten laat het statusvak tijdelijk
        zien met welke bewerking
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        nu bezig is en welk deel er al van afgewerkt is.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Statusområdet</emphasis>
        Som oftast viser dette området kva del av biletet som for tida er
        aktivt, i tillegg til kor mykje minneplass biletet nyttar. Du kan
        tilpassa visinga etter eige ønskje ved å gå inn på
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Fil</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Brukarinnstillingar</guimenuitem>
          <guimenuitem>Biletvindauge</guimenuitem>
          <guimenuitem>Tittel og status</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> i hovudmenyen.
        Når du utfører tidkrevjande operasjonar vil innhaldet i dette
        vindauget fortelje kva for operasjon som blir utført akkurat nå, og
        kor langt prosessen er komen.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Область статуса расположена под изображением. По умолчанию, почти всё
        время она отображает активный слой изображения, и количество занятой
        изображением системной памяти. С помощью изменения настроек вы можете
        настроить представляемую здесь информацию. Когда вы выполняете
        занимающие время операции, область статуса временно изменяется для
        отображения выполняемой операции, и состояние прогресса.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>状态区：</emphasis> 状态区在图像显示下方。大部分时间，它默
        认显示图像当前活动部分和图像消耗的系统内存量。您可以改变首选项来定制
        择里显示的信息。当您运行很耗时的操作时，状态区就零时地显示当前进行地
        操作及其进程。
      </para>

      <note lang="en;es;fr;it;ko;no">
        <para lang="en">
          Note that the amount of memory consumed by the image is quite
          different from the image file size. For instance, a 69.7Kb .PNG
          image will occupy 246Kb in memory when displayed. Two reasons for
          that. First, image is reconstituted from the compressed .PNG file.
          Then, GIMP keeps a copy of the image in memory to be used by the
          Undo command.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Note que la cantidad de memoria que consume una imagen no es lo
          mismo que el tamaño del archivo que la contiene. Por ejemplo, un
          archivo PNG de 69.7Kb puede ocupar unos 246Kb de memoria cuando se
          abre. Hay dos razones para esto. Primero, la imagen se reconstruye
          desde el archivo PNG comprimido. Segundo, el GIMP mantiene una copia
          de la imagen en memoria para el comando Deshacer.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          C'est la place occupée en mémoire par l'image affichée qui est
          indiquée ici, et non pas la taille de l'image. Une image .PNG de
          69,7 Ko, par exemple, occupera 246 Ko en mémoire une fois affichée.
          Deux raisons à cela. D'abord, l'image est reconstituée à partir des
          données du fichier comprimé .PNG. Ensuite, GIMP garde en mémoire un
          double de l'image qui sera utilisé par la commande Refaire.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          L'ammontare della memoria usata dall'immagine è un concetto diverso
          dalla dimensionde del file immagine. Per esempio un file immagine di
          .png di 69.7Kb può occupare 246Kb in memoria quando viene mostrato.
          Due sono le ragioni di questo comportamento. La prima è che
          l'immagine mostrata viene decompressa quando viene estratta dal file
          .png. La seconda è che l'immagine in memoria viene almeno duplicata
          da GIMP per poter far funzionare il comando di annullamento delle
          operazioni.
        </para>
        <para lang="ko">
          이미지가 사용중인 메모리 총량은 이미지 파일 크기에 따라 다릅니다. 예를 들어 69.7Kb의 PNG 이미지는 246Kb
          메모리를 사용하는데, 이것은 .PNG 파일을 김프가 사용하는 파일 타입으로 재구성해야하고, 되돌리기 명령에 대비하여
          이미지의 복사본을 보관하기 때문입니다.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Mengda av minne som biletet bruker er som oftast mykje større
          enn filstorleiken. For eksempel vil eit 69,7 Kb .png-bilete
          bruke 256 Kb minneplass når det blir vist på skjermen. Dette kjem
          av at biletet er rekonstruert frå ei pakka fil. I tillegg lagar
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ein kopi av biletet slik at du eventuelt
          kan angra det du måtte gjere med biletet.
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Cancel Button:</emphasis>
        At the lower right corner of the window appears the Cancel button. If
        you start a complex, time-consuming operation (most commonly a
        plug-in), and then decide, while it is being computed, that you didn't
        really want to do it after all, this button will cancel it
        immediately.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Tlačítko zrušit:</emphasis>
        V pravém dolním rohu okna obrázku se nachází tlačítko Zrušit. Pokud
        probíhá složitá, časově náročná operace (obvykle prováděná zásuvným
        modulem), a vy se během výpočtu rozhodnete, že ji vlastně provádět
        nechcete, použijte toto tlačítko.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Abbrechen-Schaltfläche:</emphasis>
        Mit der Schaltfläche <quote>Abbrechen</quote> können
        zeitintensive Operationen abgebrochen werden.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Botón Cancelar:</emphasis> En la esquina inferior derecha de
        la ventana se encuentra el botón Cancelar.  Si inicia una operación
        compleja, que consume mucho tiempo (comúnmente un complemento,
        plug-in), y luego cambia de idea, este botón cancela la acción en
        curso inmediatamente.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Bouton Annuler :</emphasis>
        Dans le coin en bas à droite de la fenêtre image se trouve le bouton
        Annuler. Si vous commencez une opération complexe et consommatrice de
        temps (la plupart du temps un greffon), et décidez, alors qu'elle est
        en cours, que vous ne voulez plus vraiment l'effectuer, ce bouton
        l'arrêtera immédiatement.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Pulsante di annullamento:</emphasis> nell'angolo in basso
        a destra della finestra, appare il pulsante di annullamento. Se si
        comincia una complessa e lenta operazione (spesso è un plug-in) ed
        in seguito si decide, mentre l'operazione è in esecuzione, che non
        la si vuole eseguire o che si vuole cambiare qualche parametro,
        questo pulsante è in grado di annullarne l'esecuzione
        istantaneamente.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>취소 버튼:</emphasis>
        오른쪽 하단 구석에 있는 취소 버튼은 플러그인 적용과 같이 시간이
        걸리거나 복잡한 작업을 시작한 뒤, 실행하는 도중 전부 취소하고
        싶을때 사용하게 됩니다. 이 버튼을 누르면 즉시 모든 작업이
        취소됩니다.
      </para>


      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Annuleren knop:</emphasis>
        In de rechter onderhoek van het scherm staat de knop om te Annuleren.
        Als u een bewerking gestart heeft die nogal lang duurt en halverwege
        besluit dat dit toch niet is wat u wilde, kunt u met deze knop de
        bewerking direkt afbreken.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Avbrytknappen:</emphasis>
        Denne finn du nede i høgre hjørnet av biletvindauget. Dersom du
        byrjar ein tidkrevjande operasjon (som oftast eit programtillegg) og
        under utføringa av programmet kjem fram til at du eigentleg ikkje har
        bruk for dette, kan du avbryte programmet med denne knappen.
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        В нижнем правом углу окна расположена кнопка "Отмена". Если вы
        запустили сложную, занимающую время операцию(обычно плагин), и
        затем во время  вычеслений решите, что вам это не нужно, эта
        кнопка немедленно отменит операцию.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>取消按钮：</emphasis> 取消按钮在窗口的右下角。假如您启动一
        个复杂，耗时的操作(主要是插件)，当它正在计算时，您决定不这么干了，该
        按键就使其马上停止下来。
      </para>

      <note>
        <para lang="en">
          There are a few plug-ins that respond badly to being canceled,
          possibly leaving corrupted pieces of images behind.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Některé zásuvné moduly na použití tohoto tlačítka reagují špatně a
          zanechají za sebou poškozené části obrázku.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Einige GIMP-Erweiterungen reagieren sehr langsam auf die
          Schaltfläche <guibutton>Abbrechen</guibutton>.
          Das kann zu unerwünschten Resultaten führen.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Hay algunos complementos que responden mal a la cancelación, y
          posiblemente dejan piezas corruptas de imágenes.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Il y a quelques greffons qui répondent mal à l'arrêt et peuvent
          altérer des parties de l'image.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Alcuni plug-in non si comportano correttamente se annullati,
          rovinando parti dell'immagine.
        </para>
        <para lang="ko">
          몇몇 플러그인은 취소를 해도 응답이 없는 경우가 있는데, 이것은
          실행 중단으로 인해 쓸모없어진 이미지 조각들을 삭제하고 있기
          때문입니다.
        </para>
        <para lang="nl">
          Er zijn enkele `plug-ins' die zo'n abrupte afbraak niet goed
          afhandelen en delen van de afbeelding in de war achterlaten.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Noen av programtillegga likar dårleg å bli avbrotne og demonsterar
          dette ved å øydeleggja biletet. Kanskje like greitt å la programmet
          gjere seg ferdig, og så bruke
          <quote>angre</quote>
          etterpå.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Существует несколько плагинов, которые плохо реагируют на отмену,
          возможно оставляя за собой испорченные части изображения.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">有些插件对被取消无法及时响应，可能在图像上留下未 完成部分。</para>
      </note>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-image-window-nav-button">
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Navigation</primary>
        <secondary>Navigation button</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="fr">
        <primary>Navigation</primary>
        <secondary>Bouton de Navigation</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Navigation control:</emphasis>
        This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right corner of the
        image display. Clicking on it, and holding the left mouse button down,
        brings up a window showing a miniature view of the image (Navigation
        Preview), with the
        displayed area outlined. You can pan to a different part of the image
        by moving the mouse while keeping the button depressed. For large
        images of which only a small part is displayed, the navigation window
        is often the most convenient way of getting to the part of the image
        you are looking for. (See
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Navigation Dialog</link>
        for other ways to access the Navigation Window). (If your mouse has a
        middle-button, click-drag with it to span across the image).
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Navigační kříž:</emphasis>
        Malé tlačítko ve tvaru kříže poblíž pravého dolního rohu okna obrázku.
        Pokud na něj kliknete a podržíte tlačítko myši stlačené, objeví se
        miniatura obrázku s orámovanou oblastí, která je v okně obrázku právě
        zobrazena. Tažením myši se stále stlačeným tlačítkem můžete zobrazenou
        oblast přesouvat. V případě velkých obrázků, z nichž je najednou v
        okně zobrazena jen malá část, to bývá nejpohodlnější způsob navigace.
        (Další metody navigace v obrázku jsou popsány v části
        <!--FIXCS<link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">-->Dialog
        Navigace<!--</link>--> . (Pokud má vaše myš prostřední tlačítko,
        můžete se v obrázku pohybovat jeho stisknutím a tažením.)
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Navigationsschaltfläche:</emphasis>
        Diese kleine Schaltfläche blendet durch Klicken eine Miniaturansicht
        des aktuellen Bildes ein, in der navigiert werden kann. So können Sie
        die aktuelle Ansicht des Bildabschnitts beliebig verschieben. Für sehr
        große Bilder kann auch der
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Navigationsdialog</link>
        hilfreich sein.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Control de navegación:</emphasis>
        Éste es un pequeño botón con forma de cruz que se encuentra en la
        esquina inferior derecha del visor de la imagen. Si se hace clic sobre
        el mismo y se mantiene presionado el botón del ratón, aparece una
        ventana que tiene una vista en miniatura de la imagen, con el área
        visible delineada. Puede desplazarse a otra parte de la imagen
        moviendo el ratón mientras mantiene su botón presionado. La ventana de
        navegación es la forma más conveniente de desplazarse por imágenes muy
        grandes con una pequeña parte visible en la ventana. También vea el
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">diálogo de navegación</link>
        , que es otra forma de acceder a la ventana de navegación. Si su ratón
        tiene tres botones, haciendo clic con el botón del medio y arrastrando
        también se puede desplazar por la imagen.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Bouton Navigation :</emphasis>
        C'est un petit bouton avec une croix dont les bras sont des flèches
        situé en bas à droite de la fenêtre image. Cliquer dessus et maintenir
        le bouton gauche de la souris enfoncé fait apparaître une fenêtre
        montrant une vue miniature de l'image (Aperçu de Navigation) et la
        partie actuellement affichée encadrée. Vous pouvez vous déplacer dans
        l'image en bougeant la souris tout en maintenant le bouton pressé.
        Pour les images de grande taille, dont une petite partie seulement
        est affichée, la fenêtre de navigation est souvent la manière la plus
        simple d'afficher la partie qui vous intéresse (voir
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">dialogue de Navigation</link>
        pour les autres manières d'accèder à la fenêtre de navigation). (Si
        votre souris possède une molette, le fait de cliquer avec dans l'image
        vous permet de vous déplacer dans l'image).
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Controllo di navigazione:</emphasis>
        è un piccolo pulsante crociato presente nell'angolo in basso a destra
        della finestra immagine. Facendo clic su di esso, e tenendo premuto il
        tasto del mouse, viene portata in primo piano una finestra che mostra
        una vista in miniatura dell'immagine, con l'area visualizzata
        incorniciata. È possibile fare il pan (cioè spostare il riquadro di
        visualizzazione) in un'altra parte dell'immagine muovendo il mouse
        mentre si tiene premuto il tasto. Lavorando con immagini estese,
        normalmente si visualizza solo una piccola parte dell'immagine alla
        volta; la finestra di navigazione diventa quindi il modo più
        conveniente per spostarsi velocemente sulle parti interessanti
        dell'immagine (vedere la voce
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Finestra di navigazione</link>
        per cercare altri modi per accedere a questa finestra). Se il mouse ha
        un tasto centrale o lo può emulare con la pressione simultanea dei due
        tasti, facendo clic e trascinando con esso ci si può muovere
        velocemente sull'immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>네비게이션:</emphasis> 이미지 창의 오른쪽 아래 구석에
        있는 작은 십자가 모양의 버튼을 누르면 현재 보여지고 있는 부분이
        표시된 이미지의 축소판이 나타납니다. 마우스 버튼을 누른 채 움직이면
        이미지의 다른 부분으로 이동할 수가 있습니다. 일부분 밖에 표시되지
        않는 큰 이미지의 경우 네이게이션을 이용하면 손쉽게 원하는 부분으로
        이동할 수 있습니다(네비게이션 창을 다른 방법으로 열고 싶다면
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">네비게이션
        대화상자</link>
          -->
        네비게이션 대화상자를 보십시오). (또 마우스에 가운데 버튼이 있다면,
        이미지 위에서 가운데 버튼을 클릭한 후 드래그하여 원하는 부분으로
        이동할 수도 있습니다.)
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Positie controle</emphasis>
        Dit is een kleine knop met kruislingse pijlen in de rechteronderhoek.
        Als u hierop klikt verschijnt er een miniatuurafbeelding van de
        afbeelding. Als de afbeelding groter is dan het huidige
        vensterformaat, kunt u met ingedrukte muisknop in deze miniatuur het
        gewenste deel van de afbeelding naar het venstergebied verslepen; dit
        is vaak de handigste manier om snel naar het gewenste deel van de
        afbeelding te gaan (U kunt in het
        <!--link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog"XXX_NL-->
        Positie dialoogvenster<!--/link-->
        meer manieren vinden om bij het positie venster te komen. Indien uw
        muis een middelste knop heeft kunt u die ook gebruiken om de
        afbeelding onder het venster heen te schuiven.)
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Navigasjonskontroll:</emphasis>
        Denne knappen nede i høgre hjørnet gjer mest nytte for seg når du
        arbeider med store bilete eller store forstørringar. Klikkar du på
        denne, og held museknappen nede, vil du få fram ein miniatyr av det
        biletet du arbeider med. Dersom dette biletet er større enn skjermen,
        vil du også få fram ei ramme som viser det synlege utsnittet. Ved å
        flytte på ramma, kan du velje kva for eit biletutsnitt som skal synast
        i arbeidsvindauget. (Det finst også andre måtar å få fram
        navigasjonsvindauget på. Sjå 
        <xref linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog" />). Er maskinen din sett opp
        slik, kan du bruke den midtre museknappen eller musehjulet for å
        flytte deg rundt i biletet.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Панель навигации:</emphasis>
        Небольшая кнопка крестовидной формы расположена справа внизу под
        изображением. Щелчок по ней и удерживание левой кнопки мыши вызывает
        окно показывающее изображения в миниатюре, с выделенной видимой
        областью. Вы можете перемещаться к другим частям изображения двигая
        мышь при нажатой кнопке. Для больших изображений, где отображается
        только небольшая часть, окно навигации зачастую наиболее удобный метод
        получения необходимой части изображения. (Обратитесь к разделу
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Диалог навигации</link>
        для получения информации о других методах вызова диалога навигации)
        Если ваша мышь имеет среднюю кнопку, щелчком по ней и перетаскиванием
        вы можете перемещаться по изображению.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>导航控制：</emphasis> 这是一个在右下角地十字形按钮。点击它，
        然后按住右键不放，将出现图像的缩略图，轮廓线内表示显示区域。您可以按
        住按键移动鼠标让它在图像不同的区域上移动。对于只能显示一小部分的大图
        像来说，导航窗口常常是最方便地在图像上搜寻的方法。(要了解其它打开导
        航窗口的方法，请看
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">导航对话框</link>。)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Inactive Padding Area:</emphasis>
        This padding area seperates the active image display and the inactive
        padding area, so you're able to distinguish between them. You cannot
        apply any Filters or Operations in generall on the inactive area.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>neaktivní oblast okolo obrázku:</emphasis>
        Neaktivní oblast kolem obrázku. Nemůžete na ní aplikovat žádné filtry
        či jiné grafické operace.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Inaktiver Bildrahmen:</emphasis>
        Der inaktive Bildrahmen grenzt das eigentlich aktive Bild vom
        inaktiven Rahmen ab. Der Rahmen selber kann nur in seiner Farbe
        verändert werden, wird aber von Operationen oder Werkzeugen, die auf
        das Bild angewandt werden, nicht beeinflusst. Wenn Ebenen größer als
        das eigentliche Bild sind, sieht man den Ebenenrahmen im inaktiven
        Bildrahmen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Área de desplazamiento inactiva:</emphasis> Este área separa
        el visor de la imagen activa, para que sea posible distinguir entre
        ambas.  No se pueden aplicar filtros ni realizar ninguna operación
        sobre el área inactiva.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Partie inactive de la fenêtre image :</emphasis>
        Ce remplissage sépare, dans la fenêtre image, la partie active de
        l'image de la partie inactive, ainsi vous pouvez faire la distinction
        entre elles. Vous ne pouvez pas appliquer de filtres ni, plus
        généralement, faire d'opération sur la partie inactive.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Area inattiva di riempimento:</emphasis> quest'area di
        riempimento, come fa capire il nome, separa l'immagine attiva
        dall'area inattiva di riempimento in maniera da poterle
        distinguere. Non è possibile applicare filtri o in generale altre
        operazioni di trasformazione all'area inattiva.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>비활성화된 여백 공간:</emphasis>
        이 여백 공간은 활성화된 이미지와 그렇지 않은 공간을 구분합니다.
        이 공간에는 어떠한 필터나 작업도 적용시킬 수 없습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Passieve begrenzing:</emphasis>
        Deze begrenzingslijn geeft de scheiding tussen de actieve afbeelding
        en het onbewerkbare opvulgebied aan zodat het onderscheid duidelijk
        is. Op dit inactieve gebied kunt u natuurlijk geen bewerkingen
        uitvoeren aangezien het geen deel van de afbeelding uitmaakt.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Inaktiv ramme:</emphasis>
         Ubrukt skjermplass (lerret). Du kan ikkje gjere noe direkte med dette
         området.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Неактивная область заполнения:</emphasis>
        Эта область заполнения отделяет активное отображаемое изображение и
        неактивную область, поэтому вы видите различие между ними. Вы не
        можете применить вообще никаких фильтров или операций на неактивной
        области.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>非活动填充区域：</emphasis> 该填充区域将活动图像的显示和非
        活动填充区域区分开。您无法在非活动区域上进行任何滤镜和一般操作。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="imagewindow-display">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Image Display:</emphasis>
        The most important part of the image window is, of course, the image
        display or canvas. It occupies the central area of the window,
        surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image boundary, against
        a neutral gray background. You can change the zoom level of the image
        display in a variety of ways, including the Zoom setting described
        below.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Pohled na obrázek:</emphasis>
        Nejdůležitější část okna obrázku je samozřejmě samotný obrázek,
        respektive pohled na něj. <!-- FIXME: CS -->
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Bildanzeige:</emphasis>
        Der wohl wichtigste Teil des Bildfensters ist die Anzeige des Bildes.
        Um das Bild herum befindet sich eine gelb-schwarz gestrichelte Linie,
        welche die Grenzen einer Ebene kennzeichnet.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Visor de la imagen:</emphasis> La parte más importante de la
        ventana de la imagen es, por supuesto, el visor de la imagen o lienzo.
        Éste ocupa el área central de la ventana, y está rodeada por una línea
        de puntos amarilla que muestra los contornos de la imagen, contra un
        fondo gris neutro.  Puede cambiar el nivel de ampliación del visor de
        la imagen de varias formas, como el ajuste Ampliación descrito arriba.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Affichage de l'image :</emphasis>
        La partie la plus importante de la fenêtre image est, bien entendu,
        l'image elle-même. Elle occupe la partie centrale de la fenêtre,
        entourée d'un tireté jaune et noir montrant les limites de l'image,
        sur un fond gris neutre. Vous pouvez changer le niveau de zoom de la
        fenêtre image de diverses manières, y compris avec le paramètre du
        comportement du zoom décrit plus bas.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Riquadro immagine:</emphasis>
        la parte più importante della finestra immagine è, naturalmente, la
        parte che visualizza l'immagine. Occupa la parte centrale della
        finestra, circondata da una linea tratteggiata gialla che mostra il
        limiti dell'immagine su di uno sfondo grigio neutro. È possibile
        cambiare il livello di zoom dell'immagine mostrata in molti modi
        incluso il metodo di impostazione dello zoom descritto più avanti.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>이미지:</emphasis>
        이미지 창에서 가장 중요한 부분은 이미지나 캔버스입니다. 이미지는
        창의 중앙에 표시되며, 회색의 배경과 구분짓는 노란 점선으로 둘러
        싸여집니다. 아래에 설명된 확대 설정에 따라 다양한 방법으로 이미지를
        확대하거나 축소할 수 있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Afbeeldingsgebied:</emphasis>
        De weergave van de afbeelding of `het doek' is natuurlijk het
        belangrijkste deel van het afbeeldingsvenster. Het is het centrale
        deel van het venster en omgeven door een gele gestreepte lijn die de
        grens van de afbeelding aangeeft die zo op een neutrale grijze
        achtergrond staat. U kunt de afbeeldingsgrootte op verschillende
        manieren door middel van zoomen veranderen zoals bijvoorbeeld in de
        beschrijving van de schaal-instelling hieronder wordt vermeld.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Biletvisinga:</emphasis>
        Den viktigaste delen av biletvindauget er naturlegvis biletvisinga.
        Denne er plassert midt i vindauget, omgitt av ei prikkelinje som
        markerer yttergrensa for biletet. Resten av biletvindauget er nøytralt
        grått. Du kan endre storleiken på biletet på mange måtar, inklusive
        med zoom-knappen nemnd ovanfor.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Изображение:</emphasis>
        Наиболее важная часть окна изображения это конечно, само изображение.
        Оно занимает центральную область окна, окружённое жёлтой пунктирной
        линией, в отличие от нейтрального серого цвета фона. Вы можете
        изменять уровень масштабируемости несколькими способами, включая
        настройки масштабирования, описанные ниже.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>图像显示：</emphasis> 图像窗口中最重要的部分当然是图像显示。
        它由表示图像边界的黄色点划线围住，外围是中性灰色的背景，占据窗口的中
        间地带。由多种方式改变图像显示的大小，包括下面要提到的缩放设置。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem id="gimp-image-window-zoom-follow-button">
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Image Window Resize Toggle:</emphasis>
        If this button is pressed, the image itself will be resized if the
        image window is resized.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>přepínač změny velikosti obrázku:</emphasis>
        Je-li toto tlačítko zmáčknuto, změní se při změně velikosti okna i
        velikost pohledu na obrázek (jeho přiblížení, zoom).
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Schaltfläche zur Vergrößerung des Bildfensters:</emphasis>
        Wenn Sie diese Schaltfläche aktiviert haben, wird bei Vergrößerung
        oder Verkleinerung des Bildfensters die Darstellung des Bildes
        ebenfalls vergrößert oder verkleinert.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Botón de escalado de la ventana de la imagen:</emphasis> Si
        se presiona este botón, la imagen misma se escala cuando se escala la
        ventana que la contiene.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>
          (Dés)activer le redimensionnement de la fenêtre image :
        </emphasis>
        Si ce bouton est pressé, l'image est redimensionnée si la fenêtre
        image l'est aussi.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Commutazione del ridimensionamento immagine:</emphasis>
        se questo pulsante è premuto, l'immagine viene ridimensionata
        ogniqualvolta viene modificata la dimensione della finestra che la
        contiene.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>이미지 창 크기 전환:</emphasis>
        이 버튼이 눌르져 있으면, 이미지 창의 크기가 변할 때마다 그에 따라
        이미지가 자동적으로 축소되거나 확대됩니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Meeschaal schakelaar:</emphasis>
        Als deze schakelaar ingedrukt staat, verandert de schaal van de
        afbeelding mee met de grootte van het hele afbeeldingsvenster.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Kople biletvisinga og biletvindauget:</emphasis>
         Dersom denne knappen er aktivisert, vil storleiken på biletvisinga
         forandre seg etter storleiken på biletvindauge.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Изменение размера изображения:</emphasis>
        Если эта кнопка нажата, при изменении размера окна
        изображение будет изменять размер.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>图像窗口大小控制开关：</emphasis>
        如果按下该按钮，图像将随着图像窗口一起改变大小。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</sect2>
