<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2008-03-22 reviewed 'ko' contents by Mr.Dust
  2008-01-14 alex falappa: fixed outstanding TODOs for 'it'
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-02-27 fixed Korean translation by Dust
  2006-10-16 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-09-17 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-24 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-07-15 fixed spelling errors in german
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-01-11 note added by j.h line 744
  2006-01-06 HdJ: Revised dutch text.
 -->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-window">
  <title>Image Window</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image windows</primary>
    <secondary>Description</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Status bar</primary>
    <secondary>Image window</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Navigation preview</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Preview</primary>
    <secondary>Navigation preview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      A screenshot of the image window illustrating the important components
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/imagewindow-description.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <orderedlist>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> starts opening an empty window which is named
      <quote>GNU Image Manipulating Program</quote>. As soon as you open an
      image, it is displayed in the window and its specifications are
      displayed in the title bar according to the settings you defined in
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Preference Dialog</link>.
      Each image that you have open is displayed in its own separate
      window. (In some cases, multiple windows may all display the same image,
      but this is unusual.) We will begin with a brief description of the
      components that are present by default in an ordinary image window. Some
      of them can be removed by using commands in the
      <link linkend="gimp-imagewindow-menus-view">View</link>
      menu; but probably you don't want to do that.
    </para>
    <listitem>
      <!--1-->
      <para>
        <emphasis>Title Bar:</emphasis>
        At the top of the image window you will probably see a emphasis bar,
        showing the name of the image and some basic information about it. The
        emphasis bar is actually provided by the windowing system, not by GIMP
        itself, so its appearance may vary with different operating systems,
        window managers, and/or themes. In the
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Preferences dialog</link>
        you can customize the information that appears here, if you want to.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--2-->
      <para>
        <emphasis>Image Menu:</emphasis>
        Directly below the emphasis bar appears the Image Menu (unless it has
        been suppressed). This menu gives you access to nearly every operation
        you can perform on an image. (There are some <quote>global</quote>
        actions that can only be accessed via the Toolbox menu.) You can
        also get the Image Menu by right-clicking inside the image
        <footnote><para>
          Users with an Apple Macintosh and a one button mouse can use
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <mousebutton>mousebutton</mousebutton>
          </keycombo> instead.
        </para></footnote>,
        or by left-clicking on the little <quote>arrow</quote> symbol in
        the upper left corner, if for some reason you find one of these more
        convenient.
        More: most menu operations can also be activated from the keyboard,
        using Alt plus an <quote>accelerator</quote> key underlined in the
        menu emphasis.
        More: you can define your own custom shortcuts for menu actions, if
        you enable <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface"> Use Dynamic Keyboard
        Shortcuts</link> in the Preferences dialog.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--3-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-origin"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Menu Button:</emphasis>
        Clicking on this little button gives you the Image Menu, except in a
        column instead of a row. Mnemonics users who don't want the menu bar
        visible can access to this menu by pressing the
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
         key.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--4-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-ruler"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Ruler:</emphasis>
        In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the left of the
        image, indicating coordinates within the image. You can control what
        type of coordinates are shown if you want to. By default, pixels are
        used, but you can change to other units, using the Units setting
        described below.
      </para>
      <para>
        One of the most important uses of rulers is to create
        <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.
        If you click on a ruler and drag into the image display, a guideline
        will be created, which you can use to help you position things
        accurately. Guides can be moved by clicking on them and dragging, or
        deleted by dragging them out of the image display.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--5-->
      <anchor id="quick-mask-toggle"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>QuickMask Toggle:</emphasis>
        At the lower left corner of the image display is a small button that
        toggles on or off the Quick Mask, which is an alternate, and often
        extremely useful, way of viewing the selected area within the image.
        For more details see <link linkend="gimp-qmask">QuickMask</link>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--6-->
      <para>
        <emphasis>Pointer Coordinates:</emphasis>
        In the lower left corner of the window is a rectangular area used to
        show the current pointer coordinates (that is, the mouse location, if
        you are using a mouse), whenever the pointer is within the image
        boundaries. The units are the same as for the rulers.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--7-->
      <para>
        <emphasis>Units menu:</emphasis>
        By default, the units used for the rulers and several other purposes
        are pixels. You can change to inches, cm, or several other
        possibilities using this menu. (If you do, note that the setting of
        <quote>Dot for dot</quote> in the View menu affects how the display is
        scaled: see <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Dot for Dot</link>
        for more information.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--8-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-zoom"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Zoom button:</emphasis>
        There are a number of ways to zoom the image in or out, but this menu
        is perhaps the simplest. With GIMP-2.6 it is now possible to enter
        the zoom level you want in the text box.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--9-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-status-bar"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Status Area:</emphasis>
        The Status Area appears below the image display. Most of the time, by
        default, it shows which part of the image is currently active, and the
        amount of system memory that the image is consuming. You can customize
        the information that appears here, by changing your Preferences. When
        you perform time-consuming operations, the status area changes
        temporarily to show what operation is being performed, and its state
        of progress.
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          Note that the amount of memory consumed by the image is quite
          different from the image file size. For instance, a 69.7Kb .PNG
          image will occupy 246Kb in memory when displayed. Two reasons for
          that. First, image is reconstituted from the compressed .PNG file.
          Then, GIMP keeps a copy of the image in memory to be used by the
          Undo command.
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--10-->
      <para>
        <emphasis>Cancel Button:</emphasis>
        At the lower right corner of the window the Cancel button appears
        temporarily. If you start a complex, time-consuming operation (most
        commonly a plug-in), and then decide, while it is being computed,
        that you didn't really want to do it after all, this button, which
        appears then, will cancel it immediately.
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          There are a few plug-ins that respond badly to being canceled,
          possibly leaving corrupted pieces of images behind.
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--11-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-nav-button"/>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Navigation</primary>
        <secondary>Navigation button</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Navigation control:</emphasis>
        This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right corner of the
        image display. Clicking on it, and holding the left mouse button down,
        brings up a window showing a miniature view of the image (Navigation
        Preview), with the
        displayed area outlined. You can pan to a different part of the image
        by moving the mouse while keeping the button depressed. For large
        images of which only a small part is displayed, the navigation window
        is often the most convenient way of getting to the part of the image
        you are looking for. (See
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Navigation Dialog</link>
        for other ways to access the Navigation Window). (If your mouse has a
        middle-button, click-drag with it to span across the image).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Inactive Padding Area:</emphasis>
        This padding area separates the active image display and the inactive
        padding area, so you're able to distinguish between them. You cannot
        apply any Filters or Operations in general on the inactive area.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--12-->
      <anchor id="imagewindow-display"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Image Display:</emphasis>
        The most important part of the image window is, of course, the image
        display or canvas. It occupies the central area of the window,
        surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image boundary, against
        a neutral gray background. You can change the zoom level of the image
        display in a variety of ways, including the Zoom setting described
        below.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--13-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-zoom-follow-button"/>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Image Window Resize Toggle:</emphasis>
        If this button is pressed, the image itself will be resized if the
        image window is resized.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</sect2>
