<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--  section history:
  2007-09-30 lexa: reviewed en and de for GIMP 2.4
  2006-10-17: dust added/enhanced ko translation
  2006-02-17: added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-12-16: made valid docbook and reviewed by lexa
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-running" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect1info role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <!-- FIXME: cs nl ru zh_CN revision tag missing -->
      <revision lang="cs;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
        <revnumber>$Revision: 1881$</revnumber>
        <date>n.n.</date>
        <authorinitials>n.n.</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexA</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexA</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-23</date>
        <authorinitials>manuelq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-04-05</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="it">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-17</date>
        <authorinitials>ciampix</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$: 1881 </revnumber>
        <date>2006-10-27</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$: 1881 </revnumber>
        <date>2007-11-22</date>
        <authorinitials>kost</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Running GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Použití GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Starthilfen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Lanzamiento del GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Lancer GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Eseguire GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">김프 실행하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl"><acronym>GIMP</acronym> opstarten</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Starthjelp</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Запуск GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">运行 GIMP</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Running GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>použití</secondary><!--FIXME-CS-->
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Starthilfen</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Lanzamiento del GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Démarrage de GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Uso</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>김프</primary><secondary>사용하기</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Opstarten</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Start av GIMP</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>Использование</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>GIMP</primary><secondary>使用</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Most often, you start GIMP either by clicking on an icon (if your system
    is set up to provide you with one), or by typing <command>gimp</command>
    on a command line. If you have multiple versions of GIMP installed,
    you may need to type <command>gimp-2.4</command>
    to get the latest version. You can, if you want, give a list of image
    files on the command line after the program name, and they will
    automatically be opened by GIMP as it starts. It is also possible, though,
    to open files from within GIMP once it is running.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    GIMP se nejčastěji spouští poklepáním na ikonu (pokud ji váš systém
    obsahuje) nebo z příkazové řádky příkazem <command>gimp</command>.
    Máte-li v systému více verzí GIMPu, může být nutné pro spuštění
    nejnovější verze použít příkaz <command>gimp-2.4</command>. Pokud
    příkaz doplníte o seznam obrazových souborů, GIMP je při spuštění
    automaticky otevře. Soubory ale samozřejmě můžete otevírat i později
    z běžícího GIMPu.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Alle aktuellen Betriebssysteme stellen Ihnen eine Oberfläche zur
    Verfügung, wo Sie zum Starten von Programmen lediglich auf das zugehörige
    Symbol doppelklicken müssen. Dies ist auch für <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    der Fall. Alternativ können Sie es jedoch auch durch Eingabe von
    <command>gimp</command> auf der Kommandozeile starten. Sollten Sie mehrere
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Versionen installiert haben, wird es nötig sein,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> beispielsweise explizit mit dem Kommando
    <command>gimp-2.4</command>
    zu starten. Zusätzlich zu diesem Kommando können Sie verschiedene
    Parameter und Dateinamen angeben, um zum Beispiel mehrere Bilder
    gleichzeitig zu öffnen.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    A menudo, se inicia el GIMP clicando sobre un icono (si su sistema está
    configurado para proporcionar uno), o escribiendo <command>gimp</command>
    en la línea de comandos. Si tiene múltiples versiones del GIMP instaladas,
    podría necesitar escribir <command>gimp-2.4</command>
    para lanzar dicha versión. Si quiere, puede proporcionar una lista de
    imágenes en la línea de comandos, luego del nombre del programa, y
    automáticamente se abrirán al inicio. Una vez lanzado, es posible abrir
    archivos desde el interior del GIMP.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Le plus souvent vous lancez le GIMP en cliquant sur l'icône (si
    votre système est configuré pour vous en afficher une), ou en tapant
    <command>gimp</command> sur la ligne de commande. Si vous avez
    plusieurs versions de GIMP d'installées, vous devrez taper
    gimp-<emphasis>numéro_de_version</emphasis> pour lancer la dernière
    version. Vous pouvez, si vous le désirez, donner une liste de
    fichiers d'image dans la ligne de commande après le nom du programme,
    pour qu'ils soient automatiquement ouverts au démarrage de GIMP.
    On peut aussi, bien sûr, ouvrir des images une fois le programme
    démarré.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il modo più usato per eseguire GIMP è di fare clic sull'icona
    corrispondente (se il vostro sistema è predisposto per mostrarla) oppure
    potete anche eseguirlo battendo <command>gimp</command>
    a riga di comando. Se ci sono più versioni di GIMP installate, può essere
    necessario battere per es. <command>gimp-2.4</command>
    per eseguire la versione specificata. È possibile aggiungere alla riga di
    comando, dopo il nome di gimp, un'elenco di file immagine e questi saranno
    automaticamente aperti da GIMP alla partenza. Naturalmente è sempre
    possibile aprire altri file da GIMP una volta che questo è in esecuzione.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    대부분은 아이콘을 클릭함으로써 김프를 실행시킬 수 있습니다. 아니면
    명령줄에 <command>gimp</command> 를 치면 됩니다(만약 여러 버전의 김프를
    설치했다면 <command>gimp-2.4</command> 와 같이 최신 버전의 버전을
    입력해야 합니다). 그리고 프로그램명 뒤에 이미지 파일들의 이름을 덧붙여
    김프 시작과 동시에 해당 파일들을 열 수도 있습니다. 물론 김프를 실행한
    후에도 파일을 열 수 있습니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    Meestal start u <acronym>GIMP</acronym> op door op het icoon ervan te
    klikken (als uw systeem daarin voorziet) met de muis of door
    <command>gimp</command> op de opdrachtregel in te typen. Als u meerdere
    versies van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>  geinstalleerd heeft, kan het
    noodzakelijk zijn dat u <command>gimp-2.4</command> in moet toetsen om
    de meest recente versie op te starten. Op de oprachtregel kunt u achter
    het <command>gimp</command>-commando de namen van meerdere
    verschillende afbeeldingsbestanden intoetsen die dan allemaal ge-opend
    worden, maar u kunt ook afbeeldingen openen als u al bezig bent met
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Avhengig av operativsystemet du har, vil du som oftast starte
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ved å trykke på eit ikon på skrivebordet eller
    ved å skrive <command>gimp</command> på ei kommandolinje. Har du fleire
    utgåver av <acronym>GIMP</acronym> liggjande i maskinen din, må du kanskje
    skrive <command>gimp-2.4</command> eller noe liknande for å få opp den
    siste versjonen. Du kan, dersom det er ønskjeleg, skrive ei liste over
    biletfiler på kommandolinja etter programnamnet. Desse bileta vil så bli
    opna automatisk av <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Sjølvsagt kan du også opne
    filer frå <acronym>GIMP</acronym> medan programmet arbeider.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Наиболее часто вы запускаете <acronym>GIMP</acronym> или щелчком по иконке
    (если ваша система настроена соответствующим образом), или вводом
    <command>gimp</command> в командной строке. Если у вас установлено
    несколько версий <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, вы должны  ввести
    <command>gimp-2.4</command> для запуска последней версии. Если желаете, вы
    можете задать список файлов изображений в командной строке после имени
    программы, и они будут открыты автоматически при запуске GIMP. Также
    возможно открывать файлы из <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, когда он запущен.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一般，要启动 GIMP 您可以点击其图标(如果您的系统提供给您)，或再命令行下输
    入“gimp”。如果安装了多个版本的 GIMP,您要输入“gimp-2.4”来运行最新的版本。
    如果您原意，您可以再在命令行中程序后面输入一串图像文件名，这些文件将在
    GIMP 启动时自动打开。当然，您也可以在 GIMP 运行后一个个打开。
  </para>


  <para lang="en">
    In most operating systems, you can set things up so that various
    types of image files are <quote>associated</quote> with GIMP, and cause
    it to start automatically when icons for them are double-clicked.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Ve většině operačních systémů je možné obrazové soubory s GIMPem
    asociovat, takže se při poklepání automaticky otevírají právě v GIMPu.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Außerdem können Sie bei den meisten Betriebssystemen Bilddateien mit
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> assoziieren, so dass das Programm automatisch
    gestartet wird, wenn Sie eine Bilddatei <quote>doppelklicken</quote>.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    En la mayoría de los sistemas operativos, se pueden realizar
    configuraciones para que varios tipos de imágenes queden
    <quote>asociadas</quote>
    al GIMP. Esto causa que el GIMP se lance automáticamente cuando se realice
    doble clic sobre los iconos de las imágenes.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Dans la plupart des systèmes d'exploitation, vous pouvez faire en sorte
    que certains types de fichiers image soient <quote>associés</quote> avec
    GIMP et le lancent ainsi automatiquement lorsque l'icône de l'un d'entre
    eux est double-cliquée.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Molti sistemi operativi sono impostabili in modo tale da "associare" vari
    tipi di immagine a GIMP i maniera da farlo partire automaticamente quando
    si esegue un doppio clic sulle loro icone.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    대부분의 운영체제에서 다양한 포맷의 이미지 파일들을 김프와
    <quote>호환</quote>시킬 수 있습니다. 그러면 해당 포맷의 파일 아이콘을
    더블클릭하면 김프가 자동으로 시작되며 해당 파일이 열리게 됩니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    De meeste besturingssystemen bieden de mogelijkheid om de namen van
    verschikkende type's afbeeldingsbestanden met <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    te verbinden of te `associeren', <acronym>GIMP</acronym> wordt dan
    automatisch opgestart als u op het icoon van zo'n bestand klikt
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    I dei fleste operativsystema kan du tilordne biletfiler slik at dei
    blir opna i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> når du dobbeltklikkar fila eller
    filikonet.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    В большинстве операционных систем вы можете произвести настройки таким
    образом, чтобы разные типы файлов изображений были "ассоциированы" с GIMP,
    что позволяет запускать его автоматически при двойном щелчке по этому
    типу.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    在大多数操作系统中，您可以让各种图像文件和 GIMP 相关联，这样当您双击这些
    图像图标时，GIMP 就自动启动了。
  </para>


  <sect2 id="introduction-platforms">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Known Platforms</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Známé platformy</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Plattformverfügbarkeit</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Plataformas conocidas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Plateformes connues</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Piattaforme conosciute</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">지원하는 플랫폼</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Bekende besturingssystemen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Kjende plattformer</phrase>
      <phrase lang="sv">Kända plattformar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Известные платформы</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">适用平台</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is the most widely supported image
      manipulation available today. The platforms that The
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is known to work on include:
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> je rastrový editor s podporou největšího
      množství nejrůznějších platforem. Systémy, na kterých je úspěšně
      používán, zahrnují
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ist heutzutage eines der am weitesten
      verbreiteten Bildbearbeitungsprogramme und mindestens auf folgenden
      Plattformen verfügbar:
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El <acronym>GIMP</acronym> es el programa de
      manipulación de imágenes más ampliamente portado que hay a la
      fecha.  Las plataformas en que se conoce que funciona incluyen
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> est probablement le programme de
      manipulation d'images le mieux accepté par les différents systèmes
      d'exploitation.
      Les plateformes sur lesquelles <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      a été vu fonctionner
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      <application>김프</application>는 가장 많은 플랫폼을 지원하는 이미지
      편집 프로그램입니다. <application>김프</application>는
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è attualmente il programma di fotoritocco più
      ampiamente supportato esistente. Le piattaforme su cui
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è provato funzionare includono
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      De <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is vandaag de dag een van de meest
      gebruikte afbeeldingsmanipulatie programma's. De besturingssystemen
      waarvan bekend is dat <acronym>GIMP</acronym> erop draait zijn
      onder andere
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan brukast på fleire plattformer,
      operativsystem, enn noe anna biletbehandlingsprogram. Til nå er
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> prøvd ut på desse plattformene:
    </para>
    <para lang="sv">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> är troligen det bilmanipuleringsprogram
      som har mest stöd tillgängligt idag.
      De plattformar som <acronym>GIMP</acronym> är känt att kunna
      användas på är
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      На сегодняшний день, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> - наиболее
      поддерживаемое приложение по редактированию изображений. Платформы,
      на которых <acronym>GIMP</acronym> работает, включают:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 是当今对操作系统支持最全面的图像处理
      程序。已知能运行的平台有：
    </para>

    <para>
      <productname><acronym>GNU</acronym>/Linux</productname>,
      <productname>Apple Mac OS X</productname>,
      <productname>Microsoft Windows</productname>,
      <productname>OpenBSD</productname>, <productname>NetBSD</productname>,
      <productname>FreeBSD</productname>, <productname>Solaris</productname>,
      <productname>SunOS</productname>, <productname>AIX</productname>,
      <productname>HP-UX</productname>, <productname>Tru64</productname>,
      <productname>Digital UNIX</productname>,
      <productname>OSF/1</productname>, <productname>IRIX</productname>,
      <productname>OS/2</productname>

      <phrase lang="en">and</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">a</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">und</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">y</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">et</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">그리고</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">and</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">en</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">og</phrase>
      <phrase lang="sv">och</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">и</phrase>

      <productname>BeOS</productname>.

      <phrase lang="ko">에서 사용이 가능합니다</phrase>
    </para>


    <para lang="en">
      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can easily be ported to other
      operating systems because of its source code availability. For further
      information visit the GIMP developers homepage.
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Vzhledem k dostupnosti zdrojového kódu lze <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      v případě potřeby snadno portovat i na další operační systémy.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Durch den offengelegten Programmcode kann <acronym>GIMP</acronym> leicht
      auf andere Plattformen portiert werden. Besuchen Sie für weitere
      Informationen die GIMP-Entwicklerseite
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puede ser portado fácilmente
      a otros sistemas operativos por la disponibilidad de su código
      fuente.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> peut aisément être porté sur d'autres
      systèmes grâce à la disponibilité de son code source. Pour plus
      d'informations visitez la page web des développeurs du GIMP.
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> può essere facilmente portato su altri
      sistemi operativi grazie alla disponibilità del suo codice sorgente.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      <application>김프</application>는 소스 코드 차원의 지원으로 다른 운영
      체제에도 쉽게 이식될 수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      De <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan makkelijk overgezet worden naar
      andere besturingssystemen vanwege de beschikbaarheid van zijn broncode.
      Meer informatie hierover kunt u op de Ontwikkelaarssite
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev" /> vinden.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Sidan <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har opne kjeldekoder, er det
      enkelt å tilpassa programmet til andre operativsystem. Du kan finne meir
      om dette på denne Internettadressa:
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> можно легко переложить на другие
      операционные системы из-за доступности исходного кода.
    </para>
    <para lang="sv">
      Det är enkelt att porta <acronym>GIMP</acronym> till andra
      plattformar tack vare den öppna källkoden.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 由于其源代码是开放的，因而能够很容易的
      移植到其它的操作系统。
    </para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="gimp-concepts-running-language">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Language</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Jazykové verze</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">GIMP auf Deutsch</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Lenguaje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Langue</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Lingua</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">지원하는 언어</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Talen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Språk</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Язык</phrase>
      <phrase lang="sv">Språk</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">语言</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Languages</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Sprache</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Lenguajes</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Langues</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Lingue</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Språkinnstillingar</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Языки</primary></indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      All being well, GIMP detects the system language. This may fail on some
      machines and you may want use another language. It is possible to change
      the language:
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      GIMP je přeložen do několika desítek světových jazyků včetně češtiny a
      slovenštiny. Překlady jsou přímo součástí GIMPu, není je třeba dodatečně
      stahovat. Pokud je vše, jak má být, GIMP si sám zjistí jazyk systému
      a spustí se automaticky v příslušném jazyce, tedy v českém systému česky.
      Na některých počítačích to ale nemusí správně fungovat, nebo budete možná
      chtít spustit GIMP v jiném než v právě nastaveném systémovém jazyku. To
      lze udělat následujícím způsobem:
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      bietet unter anderem eine komplett deutsche Oberfläche. Die Sprache, in
      der Sie GIMP betreiben möchten, ist abhängig von den
      Systemeinstellungen. Sollte eine automatische Erkennung Ihrer
      gewünschten Sprache fehlschlagen, ist es möglich, GIMP manuell in Ihrer
      bevorzugten Sprache zu starten:
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Si está todo bien, el GIMP detecta el lenguaje del sistema. Esto puede
      fallar en algunas máquinas, o tal vez prefiera usar otro lenguaje. Es
      posible cambiar el lenguaje:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En principe, GIMP détecte la langue du système. Mais il peut échouer
      sur certaines machines et vous pouvez souhaiter utiliser une autre
      langue. Il est possible de changer de langue:
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se tutto va bene, GIMP rileva la lingua dal sistema. Questo meccanismo
      potrebbe non funzionare su alcune macchine o si potrebbe voler usare
      un'altra lingua. È comunque possibile cambiare lingua:
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      김프는 자동적으로 시스템의 언어를 인식합니다. 하지만 몇몇 시스템에선
      실패할 수도 있는데, 이럴때엔 다른 언어를 사용해야 합니다. 다음은
      언어를 변경하는 방법입니다. :
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Als alles goed gaat, detecteerd <acronym>GIMP</acronym> de
      systeemtaal. Dit kan mislukken op sommige machines. Het is
      mogelijk om de gebruikte taal te veranderen wanneer dit nodig zou
      zijn:
    </para>

    <!-- TODO: there is some additional content here, please translate to en -->
    <!-- It is spesific to Norwegian.
    Describes how to set up your computer to get help even if you are
    using a computer set to the other lang codes for Norwegian ('nn' or 'nb').
    than the 'no' generated by Help. Allso that the translation is used among
    others in KDE, GNOM, and OpenOffice.org.  Kolbjørn -->
    <para lang="no">
      Til vanleg vil <acronym>GIMP</acronym> automatisk finne ut kva
      språk systemet bruker og tilpassa seg dette. Dette stemmer ikkje
      heilt når det gjeld norsk. Generell språkkode for norsk er
      <quote>no</quote>. Bokmål har koden <quote>nb</quote> og
      nynorsk <quote>nn</quote>. Bokmålsversjonen er lagt inn på
      <quote>nb</quote> og <quote>no</quote>. Nynorsk vil bli lagt
      inn på <quote>nn</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Hjelpsidene finst bare på nynorsk, og har fått språkkoden
      <quote>no</quote>. (Dette etter diskusjon med
      dokumentasjonsteamet for GIMP). Dersom du ikkje får opp
      hjelp på norsk, vil det som oftast vere nok å døype om fila
      <filename class="directory">no</filename> i mappa <filename
      class="directory">GIMP-2.0/share/2.0/help/no</filename> til
      <filename class="directory">nb</filename> eller <filename
      class="directory">nn</filename> etter kva språk maskinen din er
      sett opp med. Skulle ikkje dette vere nok, må du be om hjelp eller
      kikke innom <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-no" />
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Det er noe av det same problemet som gjer at du finn
      ein del typiske bokmålsord i denne dokumentasjonen. Dette har eg
      ingen kontroll med. Årsak: Ein del standarduttrykk blir omsette
      automatisk. Ordlista som blir brukt er sett opp på bokmål for
      <quote>no</quote> og <quote>nb</quote>.  Så ikkje legg skulda
      på meg når du finn <quote>innholdsfortegnelse</quote> eller
      <quote>hjem</quote> i desse dokumenta. Kanskje noen i
      Linuxmiljøet kan gjere noe med dette?
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Sidan eg er inne på det, så er dei fleste faguttrykka etter tilråding
      frå <xref linkend="bibliography-online-18n-no" /> og etter
      diskusjonar på <xref linkend="bibliography-online-ordsmia-no" />.
      Dette for at språket i GIMP skal vere mest mogleg korrekt i høve
      til ulike fagtermar og i samsvar med andre program innan fri
      programvare (KDE, GNOME, OpenOffice.org osv).
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Ønskjer du å bruke <acronym>GIMP</acronym> på eit anna språk
      enn norsk, er det enkelt å skifte:
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Если всё хорошо, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> найдёт системный
      язык. Это может не сработать, и вы можете захотеть использовать другой
      язык. Поменять язык возможно:
    </para>
    <para lang="sv">
      Om allt går bra så hittar GIMP standard språket som systemet använder.
      Detta kan misslyckas på en del maskiner och du kanske vill använda ett
      annat språk. Det går att ändra språk:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      一般情况下，GIMP 自动检测您的系统语言。但是对某些机器可能会失败，或者
      您想使用其它的语言。这时您可以通过如下方式改变语言。
    </para>


    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Linux</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <emphasis>In LINUX</emphasis>: in console mode,
            type <userinput>LANGUAGE=en gimp</userinput> or
            <userinput>LANG=en gimp</userinput>
            replacing en by fr, de, ... according to the language you
            want. Background: By using <userinput>LANGUAGE=en</userinput>
            you're setting an environment variable for the executed
            program <userinput>gimp</userinput> here.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            <emphasis>V Linuxu</emphasis>: spusťte GIMP z konzole příkazem
            <command>LANGUAGE=<replaceable>cs</replaceable> gimp</command>
            nebo <command>LANG=<replaceable>cs_CZ</replaceable> gimp</command>.
            Pokud chcete spustit GIMP v jiném jazyce než češtině, můžete
            zaměnit řetězec <literal>cs</literal> za jiný, např.:
            <literal>en</literal> (angličtina),
            <literal>fr</literal> (francouzština),
            <literal>de</literal> (němčina),
            <literal>sk</literal> (slovenština) atd.;
            případně řetězec <literal>cs_CZ</literal> za např.:
            <literal>en_US</literal> (americká angličtina),
            <literal>fr_FR</literal> (francouzština),
            <literal>de_DE</literal> (němčina),
            <literal>sk_SK</literal> (slovenština) atd.
            Všimněte si, že v případě použití proměnné
            <option>LANGUAGE</option> stačí použít dvoupísmenný kód
            jazyka, zatímco v případě použití proměnné
            <option>LANG</option>, musíte použít celý název odpovídající
            locale.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            <emphasis>GNU/Linux</emphasis>
            : Öffnen Sie eine Konsole und geben Sie folgendes ein:
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=de_DE gimp</userinput> oder
            <userinput>LANG=de gimp</userinput>,
            um GIMP in Deutsch zu starten. Möchten Sie GIMP auf z.B. in
            Französisch starten, ersetzen Sie die Landesbezeichnung "de" durch
            "fr". Hintergrund: Durch <userinput>LANGUAGE=de_DE</userinput>
            setzen Sie eine Umgebungsvariable für das ausgeführte Programm
            <userinput>gimp</userinput>.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            <emphasis>En LINUX</emphasis>: en la línea de comandos, escriba
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=es gimp</userinput> o <userinput>LANG=es
              gimp</userinput> reemplazando "es" por el código de lenguaje que
            desee (fr, de, en, etc).  Al hacer
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=es</userinput> está estableciendo una variable
            de entorno para el programa en cuestión, en este caso
            <userinput>gimp</userinput>.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            <emphasis>Sous LINUX</emphasis> : en mode console, tapez
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=fr gimp</userinput> ou
            <userinput>LANG=fr gimp</userinput>
            en remplaçant fr par en, de, ...  selon la langue choisie. En utilisant
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=en</userinput> vous choisissez une
            variable d'environnement pour le programme <userinput>gimp</userinput>
            dans ce cas.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            <emphasis>In LINUX</emphasis>: in console, battere
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=it gimp</userinput> o <userinput>LANG=it
              gimp</userinput> sostituire it con en, de, ecc. a seconda della
            lingua che si desidera impostare.  Nota: con l'esecuzione del
            comando <userinput>LANGUAGE=it o LANG=it</userinput> si sta
            impostando una variabile ambiente per il programma eseguito
            successivamente, in questo caso <userinput>gimp</userinput>.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            <emphasis>LINUX</emphasis>: 콘솔모드에서
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=en gimp</userinput> 나
            <userinput>LANG=en gimp</userinput> 라고 입력하되 en 대신 원하는
            언어로 바꿔주면 됩니다. 즉,
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=ko gimp</userinput> 나
            <userinput>LANG=ko gimp</userinput> 라고 입력하면 됩니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            <emphasis>Onder LINUX</emphasis>: kunt u op de opdrachtregel type
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=nl gimp</userinput> of <userinput>LANG=nl
              gimp</userinput> intikken om <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in het
            nederlands te starten. Als u een ander tal wilt kunt u natuurlijk
            het "nl" door "en", "fr", "de" of een andere gewenste taal
            vervangen.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            <emphasis>I LINUX</emphasis>: i <quote>console mode</quote>,
            skriv du <userinput>LANGUAGE=xx GIMP</userinput> eller
            <userinput>LANG=xx GIMP</userinput>
            der du bytter ut <quote>xx</quote> med koden for det språket du
            ønskjer.
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            В <emphasis>LINUX</emphasis>: в консоли, наберите
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=ru gimp</userinput> или
            <userinput>LANG=ru gimp</userinput>. Если хотите использовать
            другой язык, замените "ru" на "en", "fr" или, например, "de".
            Таким образом перед запуском устанавливается переменная
            окружения <userinput>LANGUAGE</userinput> для
            программы <userinput>gimp</userinput>, определяющая
            язык пользовательского интерфейса.
          </para>

          <para lang="sv">
            <emphasis>Under Linux</emphasis>: i en terminal, skriv
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=en gimp</userinput> eller
            <userinput>LANG=en gimp</userinput> ersätt en med
            fr, de, ... beroende på vilket språk du vill använda.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis>LINUX 下</emphasis>：在控制台输入
            <userinput>LANGUAGE=zh_CN gimp</userinput>,或
            <userinput>LANG=zh_CN gimp</userinput>，或用您想要的语言替代
            zh_CN, 如 en、fr...
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
        <term>Windows XP</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Control Panel</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>System</guisubmenu>
              <guisubmenu>Advanced</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Environment</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            button in <quote>System Variables</quote> area:
            <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button: Enter LANG for Name and fr or
            de... for Value. Watch out! You have to click on three successive
            <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to validate your choice.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            If you often change language, you can create a batch file. Open
            NotePad. Type the following commands (for french for instance):
            <literallayout>
              set lang=fr
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Save this file as GIMP-FR.BAT (or another name, but always with a
            .BAT extension. Create shortcut and drag it to your desktop.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            <emphasis>Ve Windows XP</emphasis>: Ovládací
            panely/Systém/Upřesnit/Proměnné prostředí/Systémové
            proměnné/Nová -- Název proměnné
            <userinput>LANG</userinput>, Hodnota
            <userinput>cs</userinput> (či jiný jazykový kód).
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Linksklick auf das Symbol
            <guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem>, anschließend
            Rechtsklick auf den Eintrag Arbeitsplatz.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Im erscheinenden Kontextmenü den Eintrag
            <guimenu>Eigenschaften</guimenu> wählen.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Im jetzt erscheinenden Dialogfeld
            <guilabel>Systemeigenschaften</guilabel> die
            Registerkarte <guilabel>Erweitert</guilabel> auswählen,
            dann auf die Schaltfläche Umgebungsvariable klicken.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie sehen zwei Schaltflächen mit der Aufschrift
            <guibutton>Neu</guibutton>. Klicken Sie auf die untere und
            tragen folgendes ein: <emphasis>Name der Variablen</emphasis>:
            <userinput>LANG</userinput> und
            <emphasis>Wert der Variablen</emphasis>
            <userinput>de, fr, en, ...</userinput>
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie die Spracheinstellung häufig ändern, empfiehlt sich eine
            Automatisierung per Skriptdatei. Öffnen Sie
            <application>Notepad</application> und geben Sie die folgenden
            Kommandos ein:
            <literallayout>
              set lang=fr
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Speichern Sie die Datei mit der Änderung <quote>.bat</quote>,
            beispielsweise als <filename>GIMP-FR.BAT</filename>. Beim
            Ausführen wird die entsprechende Sprache aktiviert.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            <emphasis>En Windows XP</emphasis>: Panel de
            control/Sistema/Avanzado/botón "Entorno"/ En el área "Variables del
            sistema": botón "Agregar": Ingresar LANG en Nombre y el código del
            lenguaje (es, fr, de, en, etc) en Valor. Advertencia: necesita
            clicar sucesivamente en tres "Aceptar" para validar la opción. <!-->
            PENDING: es falta que alguien con plataforma Windows verifique<-->
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Si cambia de lenguaje a menudo, puede crear un archivo
            batch.  Abra el bloc de notas, y escriba los comandos que
            siguen (el ejemplo es para español):
            <literallayout>
              set lang=es
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Guarde este archivo como GIMP-ES.BAT (o cualquier otro
            nombre, pero siempre con la extensión .BAT. Cree un atajo y
            arrástrelo a su escritorio.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            <emphasis>Sous WINDOWS XP</emphasis> : allez sur
            <guimenuitem>Poste de
              travail</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>Propriétés</guimenuitem>/
            <guimenuitem>Onglet Avancé</guimenuitem>. Cliquez sur le Bouton
            <guibutton>Variables d'environnement</guibutton> puis sur le
            bouton <guibutton>Nouveau</guibutton> et entrez <userinput>
              LANG</userinput> pour Nom et <userinput>FR, EN, DE ...</userinput>
            pour Valeur. Attention ! vous devez cliquer sur trois
            <quote>OK</quote> successifs pour valider votre choix.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous changez souvent de langue, vous pouvez créer un fichier
            de commandes .BAT. Ouvrez le Bloc-Note. Tapez les commandes (pour
            avoir GIMP en anglais) :
            <literallayout>
              set lang=en
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Enregistrez ce fichier sous le nom GIMP-EN.BAT (ou tout autre nom
            mais toujours avec l'extension .BAT). Créez un raccourci pour ce
            fichier et faites-le glisser jusque sur votre bureau.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            <emphasis>In WINDOWS XP</emphasis>: Pannello di
            controllo / Sistema / Avanzato / tasto "Ambiente" / Nell'area
            "Variabili di sistema": Tasto "Aggiungi": inserire LANG come nome
            e it o de... come valore. Attenzione! È necessario fare clic sui
            tre "OK" successivi per confermare la scelta.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se si cambia spesso lingua, è possibile creare una procedura
            batch per automatizzare il processo.  Aprire il programma "Blocco
            note" e battere i seguenti comandi (per la lingua francese ad
            esempio):
            <literallayout>
              set lang=fr
              cd c:\Programmi\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Salvare questo file come GIMP-FR.BAT (o altro nome, basta che sia
            sempre con l'estensione .BAT. Creare un'icona per esso e
            trascinarla sul desktop o su un menu a piacere.
          </para>

          <para lang="ko">
            <emphasis>WINDOWS XP</emphasis>:
            제어판/ 시스템/ 고급/ "환경 변수" 버튼/ "시스템 변수" 영역에서 :
            "새로만들기" 버튼 : 변수이름에 LANG, 변수값에 원하는 언어
            이름(fr,de 등)을 넣습니다. 주의! 선택을 적용하려면 세번 연속
            "확인" 버튼을 눌러야 합니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            만약 언어를 자주 변경해야 한다면, 배치파일을 만들어 사용하면
            됩니다. 메모장을 열고 다음과 같이 입력합니다.
            <literallayout>
              set lang=ko
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            그리고 GIMP-KO.BAT 로 저장을 하고(다른 이름으로 저장해도
            관계없으나, 확장자는 .BAT 이어야 합니다), 바로 가기를 바탕화면에
            만듭니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            <emphasis>Onder WINDOWS XP</emphasis>: Configuratiescherm/Systeem/
            Geavanceerd/"Omgeving" knop/ in "Systeem Variabelen" dialoog:
            "Toevoegen" knop: voer LANG in als naam en fr or de... als waarde.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            <emphasis>I WINDOWS XP</emphasis>: Trykk på Start-knappen og
            vel Kontrollpanel. Derifrå går du til /Innstillinger for region
            og språk/Regionale innstillinger/. Vel språk frå
            nedtrekkslista. Dersom du har stilt inn oppgåvelinja til å vise
            språk, kan du også endre dette frå oppgåvelinja.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du ofte skifter språk, kan du lage ei batchfil. Opna
            Notisblokk og skriv inn følgjande (for fransk):
            <literallayout>
              set lang=fr
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Lagra fila som GIMP-FR.BAT (eller eit anna høveleg namn, men alltid
            med filutvidinga .BAT). Lag ein snarveg til fila på skrivebordet.
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Кнопка
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Контрольная панель</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Система</guisubmenu>
              <guisubmenu>Дополнительные</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Окружение</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            в разделе <quote>Системные переменные</quote>. Нажмите кнопку
            <quote>Добавить</quote>,
            введите LANG для названия и ru или любой другой язык для значения.
            Нажмите <quote>OK</quote> на всех окнах и закройте контрольную
            панель.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Если вы часто изменяете язык, вы можете создать коммандный файл.
            Откройте NotePad. Введите следующее (на пример, для русского):
            <literallayout>
              set lang=ru
              cd c:\Program Files\GIMP-2.0\bin
              GIMP-2.4.exe
            </literallayout>
            Сохраните файл как GIMP-RU.BAT (или под другим именем, но
            обязательно с расширением .BAT). Создайте ссылку на этот файл и
            установите её на рабочем столе.
          </para>

          <para lang="sv">
            <emphasis>Under Windows XP</emphasis>:
            Kontrollpanelen/System/Avancerat/ "Miljövariabler" knappen/ i
            "Systemvariabler" delen: "Ny" knappen: Skriv LANG som namn och fr
            eller de... som värde.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <emphasis>WINDOWS XP下</emphasis>：控制面板/系统/高级/环境变量/在
            “系统变量”栏中新建一个以“LANG”为变量名,语言为变量值的项，比如
            zh_CN。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <phrase>Apple Mac OS X</phrase>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Go to System Preferences, click on the International icon, and in
            the Language tab, the desired language should be the first in the
            list.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <interface>Předvolby systému</interface>,
            klepněte na ikonu <guiicon>Národní volby</guiicon>
            a v oddílu <guilabel>Jazyk</guilabel>
            nastavte požadovaný jazyk na první pozici v seznamu.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Öffnen Sie die Systemeinstellungen, klicken auf das Symbol
            <guilabel>Landeseinstellungen</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wählen Sie den Reiter <guilabel>Sprachen</guilabel>
            aus. Die Sprache, die Sie für GIMP bevorzugen, sollte in der Liste
            an erster Stelle stehen.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            Diríjase a Preferencias del sistema, haga clic sobre el icono
            Internacional, y en el apartado Lenguaje, el lenguaje que desee
            emplear debería ser el primero de la lista.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            allez dans les Préférences système, cliquez sur l'icône
            International et dans l'onglet Langue, la langue voulue doit être
            placée en premier dans la liste.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Andare alle preferenze di sistema, fare clic sull'icona
            internazionale, e nella linguetta Lingua, la lingua preferita
            dovrebbe essere la prima dell'elenco.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            시스템 설정에서 인터내셔널 아이콘을 클릭합니다. 그리고 언어 탭에서
            원하는 언어가 리스트의 상단에 오도록 설정합니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Ga naar Systeem Voorkeuren, klik op het Internationaal icoon en
            kies op het Talen tabblad de gewenste taal als eerste in de lijst.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Gå til System Preferences, klikk på ikonet
            <quote>International</quote> og  set det ønskte språket øvst på
            lista.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Системные настройки/пиктограмма Международные/закладка Язык.
            Выберите язык из списка.
          </para>
          <para lang="sv">
            Gå till Systeminställningar, klicka på Internationellt och inne i
            Språk tabben, det önskade språket ska vara överst på listan.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            打开[系统预置],然后点击[国际化]图标，在[语言]标签下把您想使用的语
            言放在列表的最前面。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="gimp-concepts-running-command-line">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Command Line Arguments</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Parametry na příkazové řádce</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Kommandozeilenparameter</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Argumentos de la línea de comandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Les arguments de la ligne de commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Argomenti della riga di comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">명령줄 인수</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Argumenten op de opdrachtregel</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Argument i kommandolinja</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Аргументы командной строки</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">命令行参数</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Command line Arguments</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Kommandozeilenparameter</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es">
      <primary>Línea de comandos</primary><secondary>Argumentos</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Ligne de commande</primary><secondary>Arguments</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>명령줄</primary><secondary>인수</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Kommandolinja</primary><secondary>Argument</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ru">
      <primary>Аргументы командной строки</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      Ordinarily you don't need to give any arguments when starting
      GIMP, but here is a list of some that may at one time or another be
      useful.  This is not a complete list; on Unix systems you can get
      a complete list by running <userinput>man gimp</userinput> in a
      terminal window.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Za běžných okolností není třeba GIMPu při startu předávat žádné
      parametry, ale některé parametry mohou být přeci jen občas užitečné.
      Následující seznam není úplný. Kompletní seznam můžete získat v
      terminálu na unixových systémech příkazem <command>man gimp</command>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Kommandozeilenparameter können sehr nützlich sein, sind aber optional.
      Die folgende Liste der Parameter ist abhängig vom verwendeten
      Betriebssystem und der verwendeten <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Version.
      Unter Unix-ähnlichen Betriebssystemen können Sie eine komplette Liste
      in der Manpage (<userinput>man gimp</userinput>) erfragen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      No necesita dar argumentos para lanzar el GIMP, pero aquí hay una lista
      de algunos que podrían ser útiles en ciertos momentos. Éste no es un
      listado completo; en sistemas Unix puede obtenerse escribiendo
      <userinput>man gimp</userinput> en la línea de comandos.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      D'habitude vous n'aurez pas besoin d'argument dans la ligne de commande
      de GIMP, mais voici la liste de ceux qui pourraient vous être utiles un
      jour ou l'autre. Elle n'est pas exhaustive ; sur les systèmes Unix vous
      pouvez obtenir une liste complète en lançant
      <userinput>man gimp</userinput> dans un terminal.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Normalmente non è necessario dare alcun argomento per far partire GIMP,
      comunque qui sotto sono elencati alcuni che potrebbero prima o poi
      tornare utili. Non è un'elenco completo; sui sistemi Unix puoi ottenere
      l'elenco completo eseguendo <userinput>man gimp</userinput>
      in una finestra di terminale.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      일반적으로 김프를 실행하는데 다른 인수를 추가할 필요는 없습니다.
      하지만 여기서는 때때로 유용한 몇가지 인수를 소개할 것입니다. 아래의
      리스트는 완전한 것이 아니며, Unix 시스템을 사용하고 있다면 터미널
      창에서 <userinput>man gimp</userinput> 를 실행하여 완전한 리스트를 볼
      수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Meestal hoeft u geen extra argumenten mee te geven als u
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opstart, maar hier volgt een lijst van
      argumenten die op sommige momenten best handig kan zijn. Deze lijst
      is niet compleet; op <acronym>Unix</acronym>-systemen kunt u een
      volledige lijst opvragen door <userinput>man gimp</userinput> in een
      invoerscherm in te toetsen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Normalt treng du ikkje skrive inn argument i kommandolinja når du
      startar <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Her er likevel ei liste over argument
      som frå tid til annan kan bli aktuelle. Lista er ikkje komplett.
      Køyrer du Unix kan du frå fram heile lista ved å køyre
      <userinput>man gimp</userinput> i eit terminalvindauge. Bruker du
      Windows, er det enklast å hoppe over heile lista og heller starte
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ved å klikke på GIMP-ikonet på skrivebordet.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Обычно нет необходимости задавать какие-либо агрументы при
      запуске GIMP, но вот список некоторых, которые иногда могут быть
      полезны. Это не полный список; в <acronym>Unix</acronym> системах
      вы можете получить полный список введя в окне  терминала
      <userinput>man gimp</userinput>.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      一般情况下，启动 GIMP 并不需要参数，这儿是一些列表，它们可能在一些情况
      下有用。下面列的并不完全;在 Unix 系统中通过在终端窗口中输入“man gimp”
      来获得完全的列表。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      To use the command line options, you have to put them in the command
      line which you use to start GIMP as
      <command>gimp-2.4 [OPTION...] [FILE|URI...]</command>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Um die Kommandozeilenparameter zu nutzen, müssen Sie diese beim Start
      von GIMP über die Kommandozeile in der folgenden Form angeben:
      <command>gimp-2.4 [OPTION...] [DATEI|URI...]</command>
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Per usare le opzioni da riga di comando, è necessario impostarle
      nella riga di comando usata per avviare GIMP nella forma:
      <command>gimp-2.4 [OPZIONI...] [FILE|URI...]</command>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Для использования параметров коммандной строки, их нужно ввести на
      коммандной строке, с которой вы запускаете GIMP в следующем формате:
      <command>gimp-2.4 [OPTION...] [FILE|URI...]</command>.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>-?, --help</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Display a list of all commandline options.</para>
          <para lang="cs">Zobrazí seznam možných parametrů.</para>
          <para lang="de">Eine Liste aller verfügbaren Parameter zeigen.</para>
          <para lang="es">
            Muestra un listado de todas las opciones de la línea de comandos.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Affiche la liste de toutes les options de la ligne de commande.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Mostra un'elenco di tutte le opzioni a riga di comando.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">모든 명령줄 옵션 보이기</para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Een lijst met alle opties voor de opdrachtregel
          </para>
          <para lang="no">Vis ei liste over alle kommandoane</para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Отображает список всех параметров командной строки.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">列出所以命令行选项。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--help-all</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Show all help options.</para>
          <para lang="de">Alle Hilfeoptionen anzeigen.</para>
          <para lang="it">Mostra tutte le opzioni di aiuto.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--help-gtk</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Show GTK+ Options.</para>
          <para lang="de">GTK+-Optionen anzeigen.</para>
          <para lang="it">Mostra le opzioni GTK+.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-v, --version</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Print the version of GIMP being used, and exit.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">Zobrazí verzi GIMPu.</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Versionsinformationen anzeigen und Programm beenden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Imprime la versión del GIMP en cuestión, y sale.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Affiche la version de GIMP utilisée et quitte.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">Stampa la versione di GIMP e esce.</para>
          <para lang="ko">현재 사용중인 김프 버전을 표시 후 종료</para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Laat de versie van de gebruikte <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-versie
            zien.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Skriv kva for versjon av GIMP som er i bruk, og slutt av
            programmet.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">Печатает используемую версию GIMP, и выходит.</para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">列出使用的 GIMP 版本，然后退出。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--license</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Show license information and exit</para>
          <para lang="de">Lizenzinformationen anzeigen und Programm beenden.</para>
          <para lang="it">Mostra le informazioni sulla licenza e esce.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--verbose</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Show detailed start-up messages.</para>
          <para lang="cs">Při startu GIMPu zobrazí podrobné informace.</para>
          <para lang="de">Detaillierte Meldungen auf der Konsole zeigen.</para>
          <para lang="es">Muestra mensajes detallados del inicio.</para>
          <para lang="fr">Affiche les messages de démarrage détaillés.</para>
          <para lang="it">Mostra i messaggi di partenza in maniera
          dettagliata.</para>
          <para lang="ko">시작 메세지를 자세히 보이기</para>
          <para lang="nl">Laat uitgebreidere opstartberichten zien.</para>
          <para lang="no">Vis detaljerte oppstartmeldingar.</para>
          <para lang="ru">Показывает подробные сообщения при запуске.</para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">显示详细启动信息。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>-n, --new-instance</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Start a new GIMP instance.</para>
          <para lang="de">Eine neue GIMP-Instanz starten.</para>
          <para lang="it">Esegue una nuova istanza di GIMP.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>-a, --as-new</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Open images as new.</para>
          <para lang="de">Bilder als neu öffnen.</para>
          <para lang="it">Apri le immagini come nuove.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>-i, --no-interface</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Run without a user interface.</para>
          <para lang="de">Ohne Benutzeroberfläche starten.</para>
          <para lang="it">Esegui senza interfaccia utente.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-d, --no-data</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Do not load patterns, gradients, palettes, or brushes. Often
            useful in non-interactive situations where start-up time is to be
            minimized.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Spustí GIMP, ale nenahraje vzorky, přechody, palety ani štětce. To
            je užitečné v neinteraktivních situacích, pokud je potřeba
            minimalizovat dobu nutnou ke spuštění GIMPu.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Keine Muster, Gradienten, Farbpaletten oder Pinsel öffnen. Dies
            ist in nicht-interaktiven Umgebungen sinnvoll, um die Startzeit zu
            minimieren.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            No carga patrones, gradientes, paletas, ni brochas. A menudo es
            útil cuando se quiere minimizar el tiempo de inicio, en
            situaciones de uso no interactivo.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ne charge ni motifs, ni dégradés, ni palettes, ni brosses. Souvent
            utile dans les situations non interactives quand le temps de
            démarrage doit être optimisé.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Non caricare motivi, gradienti, tavolozze, o pennelli. Spesso
            utile in ambiti non interattivi dove il tempo di esecuzione deve
            essere ottimizzato.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            무늬, 그라디언트, 색상표, 붓 등을 읽어 들이지 않기. 비대화식
            환경에서 시작 시간을 최소화할 때 유용합니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Dit voorkamt dat er allerlei patronen, verlooptinten,
            kleurschema's of penselen worden geladen en is handig als u gimp
            in commando-modus gebruikt of als de opstarttijd zo kort mogelijk
            gehouden moet worden.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Ikkje last inn mønsterelement, fargeovergangar, palettar eller
            penslar. Kan vere nyttig i ikkje-interaktive situasjonar der
            oppstarttida skal vere kortast råd.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Не загружать шаблоны, градиенты, палитры, или кисти. Чаще всего
            полезно в неинтерактивных ситуациях, где время загрузки должно
            быть минимизировано.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">不加载任何图案，渐变，色板和画笔。通常在需要最
          小化启动时间的非交互情况中使用。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>-f, --no-fonts</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Do not load any fonts. This option could be
          useful either for speeding up GIMP start-up for scripts that
          does not use fonts or to find malformed fonts related problems
          that could hang GIMP.</para>
          <para lang="de">Keine Schriften laden.</para>
          <para lang="it">Non caricare nessun carattere. Questa opzione può
          servire sia a velocizzare la partenza di GIMP per script che non
          usano i caratteri, sia a trovare i problemi relativi a font
          malformati che potrebbero bloccare la partenza di GIMP.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>-s, --no-splash</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Do not show the splash screen while starting.</para>
          <para lang="cs">Při startu GIMPu nezobrazí úvodní obrazovku.</para>
          <para lang="de">Keinen Startbildschirm zeigen.</para>
          <para lang="es">No muestra la pantalla de inicio al lanzarse.</para>
          <para lang="fr">N'affiche pas l'écran de démarrage.</para>
          <para lang="it">Non mostrare la schermata iniziale alla
          partenza.</para>
          <para lang="ko">시작시 스플래쉬 화면 보이지 않기</para>
          <para lang="nl">Laat het opstartscherm niet zien.</para>
          <para lang="no">Ikkje vis oppstartskjermen.</para>
          <para lang="ru">Не показывать заставку при запуске.</para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">启动不显示启动画面。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--no-shm</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Do not use shared memory between GIMP and
          plugins. <!-- maybe useful if you do not trust a plugin code? --></para>
          <para lang="de">
            Keinen gemeinsam genutzten Speicher zwischen GIMP und den Modulen
            verwenden.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">Non utilizzare la memoria condivisa tra GIMP e i
          plugin.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--no-cpu-accel</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Do not use special CPU acceleration
          functions. Useful for finding or disabling buggy accelerated
          hardware or functions.</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Keine speziellen Prozessorbeschleunigungen verwenden.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">Non utilizzare le speciali accelerazioni
          CPU. Utile per trovare e eventualmente disabilitare funzioni o
          hardware di accelerazione bacati.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--session=<replaceable>name</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Use a different <filename>sessionrc</filename> for this GIMP
            session. The given session name is appended to the default
            <filename>sessionrc</filename> filename.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pro relaci použije jiný <filename>sessionrc</filename> soubor.
            Zadané jméno (<replaceable>name</replaceable>) je připojeno k
            implicitnímu jménu <filename>sessionrc</filename>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Ein anderes Sitzungsprofil verwenden. Der angegebene Sitzungsname
            wird an den Standarddateinamen (<filename>sessionrc</filename>)
            angehängt.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Usa un archivo de configuración <filename>sessionrc</filename>
            alternativo para esta sesión.  El nombre de sesión (name)
            proporcionado se añade al final del nombre de archivo
            <filename>sessionrc</filename> por omisión.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Utilise un sessionrc différent pour cette session de GIMP. Le nom
            de session passé en paramètre est ajouté au nom du fichier
            sessionrc par défaut.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Usa un file <filename>sessionrc</filename> differente per la
            sessione GIMP. Il nome di sessione dato viene accodato al nome
            file <filename>sessionrc</filename> predefinito.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            김프 세션에 다른 sessionrc 사용하기. 새 세션 이름은 기본
            sessionrc 파일명에 덧붙여집니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Gebruik een alternatief <filename>sessionrc</filename>-bestand
            voor deze sessie van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. De
            <replaceable>name</replaceable> wordt aan de naam van het
            <filename>sessionrc</filename>-bestand van deze sessie geplakt.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Bruk eit anna <filename>sessionrc</filename> for denne
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-økta. Det gjevne <quote>session
              name</quote> blir lagt til det normale <quote>sessionrc
              filename</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Использовать другой файл sessionrc для сеанса работы GIMP.
            Предоставленное имя приставляется к имени файла по умолчанию
            <filename>sessionrc</filename>.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            GIMP 会话使用不同的 sessionrc，该会话的名字将添加到默认的
            sessionrc 文件名后。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--gimprc=<filename>filename</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Use an alternative <filename>gimprc</filename> instead of the
            default one. The <filename>gimprc</filename> file contains a
            record of your preferences.  Useful in cases where plugins paths
            or machine specs may be different.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Načte se alternativní soubor <filename>gimprc</filename>.
            se záznamy o předvolbách GIMPu. To je užitečné například v
            situacích, kdy se změnily cesty k zásuvným modulům či hardwarové
            specifikace.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Ein alternatives <filename>gimprc</filename>-Profil verwenden.
            (Die Datei <filename>gimprc</filename> enthält Ihre Präferenzen.)
            Nützlich in Fällen, wo sich Pluginpfade oder
            Maschinenspezifikationen unterscheiden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Utiliza un archivo de configuración <filename>gimprc</filename>
            alternativo en lugar del que existe por omisión. El archivo
            <filename>gimprc</filename> contiene un registro de las
            preferencias.  Es útil en los casos en que las rutas de los
            complementos (plug-ins) o las especificaciones del sistema pueden
            variar.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Utilise un gimprc de remplacement à la place de celui par défaut.
            Le fichier <quote>gimprc</quote> contient l'enregistrement de vos
            préférences.
            Utile dans les cas où le chemin des greffons ou les spécifications
            de machine sont différents.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Usa un gimprc alternativo invece del predefinito. Il file "gimprc"
            contiene la registrazione delle preferenze. Utile nel caso che il
            percorso dei plugin o le specifiche macchina siano differenti.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            기본값 외의 다른 gimprc 사용하기. <quote>gimprc</quote> 는 김프
            설정값을 담고 있는 파일입니다. 플러그인 위치나 시스템 사양이
            틀린 경우에 유용합니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Gebruik een ander <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            instellingenbestand dan het standaard bestand. Het
            "gimprc"-bestand bevat een opname van uw voorkeursinstellingen.
            Dit is handig als u op een andere plaats, met een andere computer,
            met andere instellingen werkt.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Bruk ei alternativ <quote>gimprc</quote>-fil i staden for den
            vanlege. <quote>gimprc</quote>-fila inneheld data om
            innstillingane dine. Kan vere nyttige når banane til
            programtillegga eller maskinoppsettet er endra.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Использовать альтернативный "gimprc" файл вместо используемого по
            умолчанию. Файл "gimprc" содержит записи ваших настроек. Полезно,
            если пути поиска плагинов или машинные требования могут
            отличаться.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            使用不同的 gimprc 文件。“gimprc”文件包括首选项记录。常用在插件路
            径或机器设置不同时指定。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--system-gimprc=<replaceable>filename</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Use an alternate system gimprc file</para>
          <para lang="de">Ein alternatives Systemprofil verwenden.</para>
          <para lang="it">Usa un file gimprc di sistema alternativo</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          -b, --batch=<replaceable>commands</replaceable>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Execute the set of commands non-interactively. The set of commands
            is typically in the form of a script that can be executed by one
            of the GIMP scripting extensions. When commands is
            <userinput>-</userinput>, the commands are read from standard
            input.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Provede příkazy (uvedené na místě
            <replaceable>commands</replaceable>) v dávkovém režimu. Pokud je
            jako příkaz uveden řetězec <userinput>-</userinput>,
            budou se příkazy číst ze standardního vstupu.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Befehle im Stapelmodus ausführen. Die Befehle werden normalerweise
            in Form eines Skriptes angegeben. Sollte <userinput>-</userinput>
            angegeben sein, werden die Kommandos von der Standardeingabe
            gelesen.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Ejecuta el conjunto de comandos de forma no interactiva. Este
            conjunto típicamente se da en forma de un guión que puede
            ejecutarse por una de las extensiones de guionado del GIMP. Cuando
            "commands" es un <userinput>-</userinput>,
            los comandos se leen de la entrada estándar.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Exécute les commandes de manière non interactive. Les commandes
            sont généralement sous la forme d'un script qui peut être exécuté
            par l'une des extensions de script du GIMP. Quand la commande est
            <userinput>-</userinput>, les commandes sont lues sur l'entrée
            standard.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Esegui l'insieme dei comandi in maniera non interattiva. L'insieme
            dei comandi è tipicamente in forma di script che può essere
            eseguito da una delle estensioni di script di GIMP. Se il comando
            è <userinput>-</userinput> i comandi vengono letti dallo standard
            input.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            비대화형 명령들의 모음 실행. 명령 모음은 일반적으로 김프
            스크립팅 확장에서 실행할 수 있는 스크립트 형태로 되어 있습니다.
            명령이 <userinput>-</userinput> 일 경우, 이는 표준 입력으로
            해석됩니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Laat <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            zelfstandig de ingegeven reeks van commando's uitvoeren. De
            commando's worden opgesteld in de vorm van een recept (`script')
            dat door de desbestreffende script-uitbreiding van
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uitgevoerd kan worden. Als er
            <userinput>-</userinput> als commando staat worden de commando's
            van de standard-input gelezen.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Utfør kommandosettet <quote>non-interactively</quote>.
            Kommandosettet er typisk eit skript som blir utført av ei av
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sine skriptutvidingar.
            Dersom kommandoen er <userinput>-</userinput>, vil kommandoane
            bli lesne frå standarinngangen.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Выполнить неинтерактивно набор команд. Набор команд обычно
            задаётся в форме скрипта, который пожет быть выполнен одним из
            скриптовых расширений GIMP. Если значение этого аргумента
            <userinput>-</userinput>, команды читаются из стандартного ввода.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            执行一系列命令(非交互的)。这些命令以 GIMP 脚本能执行的脚本形式存
            在，但命令是<userinput>-</userinput>时，就从标准输入读入命令。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--batch-interpreter=<replaceable>proc</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">The procedure to process batch commands with</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Prozedur zum Abarbeiten von Befehlsabfolgen.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">La procedura per elaborare i comandi batch</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--console-messages</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Do not popup dialog boxes on errors or warnings. Print the
            messages on the console instead.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Chyby a varování nebudou oznamovány v dialogových oknech, ale
            vypsány na konzoli.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Warnungen im Terminal statt in einem Dialog ausgeben.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            No aparecen diálogos informando de errores o advertencias. En
            cambio, se imprimen mensajes en la consola.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            N'ouvre pas de boîte de dialogues pour les messages
            d'avertissements mais les affiche dans la fenêtre console à la
            place.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Non mostrare le finestre di dialogo per errori e avvertimenti.
            Stampa tutti i messaggi sulla console.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">에러창이나 경고창 띄우지 않고 콘솔창에 표시하기</para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Onderdruk dialoogvensters met waarschuwingen of foutmeldingen en
            leidt deze berichten naar de console om.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Ikkje bruk sprettoppvindauge ved varsling av feil. Skriv
            meldingane til konsollen i staden.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Не вызывать всплывающие диалоги при ошибках или предупреждениях.
            Вместо этого печатать сообщения на консоль.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">出现错误或警告时不弹出对话框，而是在终端上打印消息。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--pdb-compat-mode=<replaceable>mode</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">PDB compatibility mode (off|on|warn).</para>
          <para lang="de">PDB-Kompatibilitätsmodus (off|on|warn).</para>
          <para lang="it">Modalità compatibile PDB (off|on|warn).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--stack-trace-mode=<replaceable>mode</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Debug in case of a crash (never|query|always)</para>
          <para lang="de">Fehlersuche beim Absturz (never|query|always).</para>
          <para lang="it">Esegui il debug nel caso di un blocco
          (never|query|always). Utile per regolare l'avvio delle procedure
          di debug in caso di blocco (mai|chiedi|sempre).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--debug-handlers</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Enable non-fatal debugging signal
          handlers. Useful for GIMP debugging.</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Aktiviert Fehlersuchroutinen für nicht-schwerwiegende Signale.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">Abilita debugging dei segnali non fatali. Utile
          per il debugging di GIMP.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--g-fatal-warnings</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Make all warnings fatal. Useful for debug.</para>
          <para lang="de">Alle Warnungen als kritisch einstufen.</para>
          <para lang="it">Fai in modo che tutti gli avvertimenti (warning)
          siano fatali. Utile per il debug.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;it">
        <term>--dump-gimprc</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Output a gimprc file with default
          settings. Useful if you messed up the gimprc file.</para>
          <para lang="de">
            Eine gimprc-Datei mit den Standardeinstellungen ausgeben.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">Genera un file gimprc con valori
          predefiniti. Utile se si ha il dubbio di aver rovinato il file
          gimprc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>--display=<replaceable>display</replaceable></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Use the designated X display (does not apply to all platforms).
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Použije určený X displej (neplatí pro GIMP ve Windows).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Den angegebene X-Bildschirm verwenden (nicht auf allen Systeme
            verfügbar).
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Usa la pantalla de X especificada (esta opción no se aplica al
            GIMP en Microsoft Windows)
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Utilise l'affichage spécifié du serveur X (ne fonctionne
            évidemment pas sous Windows)
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Usato per indicare il display X (non usato nella versione di GIMP
            per Microsoft Windows).
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">X-윈도우 스타일로 사용하기(Microsoft Windows에서는
          사용불가)</para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Start <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            op het ingegeven scherm op (Dit kan niet op Microsoft Windows).
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Bruk X visning (gjeld ikkje på Microsoft Windows).
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Использовать определённый X дисплей (неприменимо к GIMP на всех
            платформах)
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">使用指定的 X 显示(在Microsoft Windows此项无效)。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
