<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--Section History
  2019-12-18 j.h: add on-canvas layer selection
-->

<sect1 id="gimp-layer-groups">
  <title>Layer Groups</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer groups</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Pass through</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>On-canvas layer selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    <quote>Layer Groups</quote> enable you to group layers together in a
    hierarchical structure. This will make it easier to manage your project
    if you have many layers.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata format="PNG"
        fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Create a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can create a layer group by clicking the
          <guibutton>New Layer Group</guibutton> button at the bottom of the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>,
          by using the menu command
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>New Layer Group</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
          or through the Layers dialog context menu.
        </para>
        <para>
          This new empty layer group appears just above the current layer. It is
          recommended to give it a descriptive name. To change the layer group
          name, double-click the name, press <keycap>F2</keycap>, or
          right-click the layer and select
          <command>Edit Layer Attributes</command> from the context menu.
          If you don't rename your layer groups, you can get confused when
          several groups have been created with names such as Layer Group #1,
          Layer Group #2, etc.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can create multiple layer groups and you can
          <emphasis role="bold">embed</emphasis> them, that is include a
          layer group in another one.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Adding Layers to a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can add <emphasis>existing layers</emphasis> to a layer group
          by click-and-dragging them.
          <note>
            <para>
              The hand representing the mouse pointer must turn smaller
              before releasing the mouse button.
            </para>
            <para>
              A thin horizontal line marks where the layer will be inserted.
            </para>
          </note>
        </para>
        <para>
          To add a <emphasis>new layer</emphasis> to the current layer
          group,
          click the <guibutton>New Layer…</guibutton> button at the
          bottom of the Layers dialog, use the
          <guimenuitem>New Layer…</guimenuitem> command in the main menu,
          or press <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para>
          When a layer group is not empty, a small icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/stock-icons/pan-end-symbolic.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          appears. By clicking it, you can fold or unfold the group.
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-fold-unfold.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>
          Layers that belong to a layer group are slightly indented to the
          right, allowing you to easily see which layers are part of the
          group.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Visibility</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a layer group is made invisible using the eye icon but still open
          (so that the layers inside the group are shown in the list), there is
          a struck out eye shown besides the layers that are inside the
          group to indicate that these layers are not displayed in the final
          projection of the image, but theoretically visible in the layer group.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-visibility.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Raise and Lower Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can raise and lower layer groups in the Layers dialog as you do
          with normal layers: click-and-dragging, and by using
          <keycap>up arrow</keycap> and <keycap>down arrow</keycap>
          keys at the bottom of the Layers dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Duplicate a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          To duplicate a layer group, click the
          <guibutton>Create a duplicate of the layer</guibutton> button or
          right-click and select the <command>Duplicate Layers</command>
          command in the pop up context menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Move Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can <emphasis role="bold">move a layer group to another image
          </emphasis> by click-and-dragging.
          You can also copy-paste it using <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
          and <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>: then, you get
          a floating selection that you must anchor
          (<guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-anchor.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          anchor button
          at the
          bottom of the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>).
        </para>
        <para>
          You can also <emphasis role="bold">move a layer group to the
          canvas</emphasis>: this duplicates the group <emphasis>in</emphasis>
          the group. Select the layer group, select
          the <link linkend="gimp-tool-move">Move tool</link>, then, in the
          image, move the layer. That's one way to
          multiply multi-layer objects in an image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Delete Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          To delete one or more layer groups, click the
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/edit-delete.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>
                <phrase>Delete Layers</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          icon button on the bottom of the Layers dialog, or drag and drop the
          selected layer groups on top of that button,
          or use the <link linkend="gimp-layer-delete">Delete Layers</link>
          command from the main menu or from the Layers dialog context menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Embed Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When a layer group is activated, you can add another group inside
          it with the <quote>Add New Layer Group</quote> command. There
          seems to be no limit, except memory, to the number of embedded
          layer groups.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layer Modes and Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A layer mode applied to a layer group acts on layers that are in this
          group only. A layer mode above a layer group acts on all layers
          underneath, outside and inside the layer groups.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-original.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Original image
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <figure>
          <title>Layer Mode in Layer Group</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-merge-in-dialog.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                We added a white layer <emphasis>in</emphasis> the layer group
                with HSL Color mode.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-merge-in-example.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Only the square and triangle turned gray.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Layer Mode outside Layer Group</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-merge-out-dialog.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                We added a white layer <emphasis>outside</emphasis> and above
                the layer group with HSL Color mode.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-merge-out-example.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                All layers underneath changed to gray, including the
                background layer.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Layer groups have a special layer mode: the
          <guilabel>Pass through</guilabel> mode. This mode exists only if a
          layer group is active.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Pass through</guilabel> mode, is less a blending mode in and
          of itself than an instruction for the group as a whole: it indicates
          that layers inside the group are to be rendered in combination with
          other layers below the group, instead of being rendered separately
          from them.
        </para>
        <para>
          While with <guilabel>Normal</guilabel> mode, layers within a group
          are treated as if they were a single layer, which is then blended with
          other layers below in the stack; a modifier on a layer inside the
          group blends layers below in the group only.
        </para>
        <para>
          For more details about <guilabel>Pass through</guilabel>, see
          <xref linkend="glossary-pass-through"/> in the Glossary.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Opacity</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When a layer group is activated, opacity changes are applied to all
          the layers of the group.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layer Mask</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Masks are also available on layer groups.
          They work similarly to ordinary
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask">layer masks</link>, with the
          following considerations.
        </para>
        <para>
          The layer group’s mask size is the same as the combined size of all
          its children at all times. When the group’s size changes, the
          mask is cropped to the new size — areas of the mask that fall outside
          of the new bounds are discarded, and newly added areas are filled with
          black (and hence are transparent by default).
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-mask-dialog.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              We added a black (transparent) layer mask to the layer group.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-mask-example.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              The layers inside the group became transparent (invisible).
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
          Of course, you still can add a layer mask to a layer in the group to
          mask a part of the layer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Finding a layer</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When working with a lot of layers, finding a particular layer in the
          list can be difficult. To find the layer to which an image element
          belongs, use the <emphasis>on-canvas layer selection</emphasis> function
          via <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Middle click</keycap>
          </keycombo> on the image element.
          The available layers will be looped through to
          show the new active layer and the layer name will be temporarily
          displayed in the status bar.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layer preview</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There have been problems with slow preview rendering of layer
          groups in case of many layers in a large image. If you are
          experiencing this, you can disable rendering layer group previews in
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Interface</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

</sect1>
