<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--Section History
  2012-03-06 j.h: created
-->

<sect1 id="gimp-layer-groups">
  <title>Layer Groups</title>

  <para>
    This possibility appeared with <acronym>GIMP-2.8</acronym>.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can group layers that have similarities in a tree-like way. So, the
    layer list becomes easier to manage.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata format="PNG"
        fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Create a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can create a layer group by clicking on the
          <guibutton>Create a new layer group</guibutton><guiicon></guiicon>
          button at the bottom of the layer dialog,
        </para>
        <para>
          through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>New Layer Group</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
          or through the layer dialog context menu.
        </para>
        <para>
          This empty layer group appears just above the current layer. It is
          important to give it an evocative name (double-click or
          <keycap>F2</keycap> on the name, or use <command>Edit Layer
          Attributes</command> in the context menu you get by right clicking the
          Layer dialog, to edit it), else you will get confused when several
          ones are created.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can create several layer groups and you can
          <emphasis role= "bold">embbed</emphasis> them, that is include a
          layer group in another one.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Adding Layers to a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can add <emphasis>existing layers</emphasis> to a layer group
          by click-and-dragging them.
          <note>
            <para>
              The hand representing the mouse pointer must turn smaller
              before releasing the mouse button.
            </para>
            <para>
              A thin horizontal line marks where the layer will be laid
              down.
            </para>
          </note>
        </para>
        <para>
          To add a <emphasis>new layer</emphasis> to the current layer
          group,
          click on the <guibutton>Create a new layer</guibutton> at the
          bottom of the layer dialog, or use the
          <guimenuitem>New Layer</guimenuitem> command in the image menu.
        </para>
        <para>
          When a layer group is not empty, a small <quote>></quote> icon
          appears. By clicking on it, you can fold/unfold the layer list.
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/fold-unfold.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>
          You can put layers to be added together to a layer group by making
          them, them only, visible, and using the <quote>New From Visible
          </quote> command. All visible layers, outside and inside layer
          groups, will be added to the active layer group.
        </para>
        <para>
          Layers that belong to a layer group are slightly indented to the
          right, allowing you know easily which layers are part of the
          group.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Raise and Lower Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can raise and lower layer groups in the layer dialog as you do
          with normal layers: click-and-dragging, using arrow up and down
          keys at the bottom of the layer dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Duplicate a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can duplicate a layer group: click on the
          <guibutton>Create a duplicate of the layer</guibutton> button or
          right-click and select the <command>Duplicate Layer</command>
          command in the pop up context menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Move Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can <emphasis role="bold">move a layer group to another image
          </emphasis> by click-and-dragging.
          You can also copy-paste it using Ctrl-C and Ctrl-V: then, you get
          a floating selection that you must anchor (anchor button at the
          bottom of the layer dialog).
        </para>
        <para>
          You can also <emphasis role="bold">move a layer group to the
          canvas</emphasis>: this duplicates the group <emphasis>in</emphasis>
          the group. Chain all layers in the duplicated layer group, activate
          the Move tool, then, in the image, move the layer. That's a way to
          multiply multi-layer objects in an image.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Delete a Layer Group</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          To delete a layer group, click on the red cross button at the
          bottom of the layer dialog or right-click and select <command>
          Delete layer</command>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Embed Layer Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When a layer group is activated, you can add another group inside
          it with the <quote>Add New Layer Group</quote> command. There
          seems to be no limit, excepted memory, to the number of embedded
          layer groups.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layer Modes and Groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A layer mode applied to a layer group acts on layers that are in this
          group only. A layer mode above a layer group acts on all layers
underneath,
          outside and inside the layer groups.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-original.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Original image
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <figure>
          <title>Layer Mode in or out Layer Group</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-merge-in.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                We added a white layer <emphasis>in</emphasis> the layer group
                with saturation mode: only square and triangle are grayed out.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-merge-out.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                We added a white layer <emphasis>out</emphasis> of the layer
                group with saturation mode: all layers underneath are grayed
                out, background layer also.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>        
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Opacity</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When a layer group is activated, opacity changes are applied to all
          the layers of the group.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Layer Mask</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
           You cannot add a layer mask to a layer group (the corresponding
           option is grayed out). But, as with normal layers, you can add a layer
           mask to a layer in the group to mask a part of the layer.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layer-group-mask.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              We added a white (Full opacity) layer mask to the triangle layer.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

</sect1>


