<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="gimp-layer-types">
  <title>Layer Types</title>
  <!-- We don't want each sect2 on a separate page here -->
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Layer Types</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Besides the regular raster layers, there a several special purpose
      layer types available in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-layer-type-text-layer">
    <title>Text Layer</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text Layer</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Layers</primary>
      <secondary>Text</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
       Text layers are used to add text to your image. A text layer can use
       one or more fonts and colors for the text, as well as other text
       properties. To add a new text layer you use the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-text">Text Tool</link>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-layer-type-vector-layer">
    <title>Vector Layer</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Vector Layer</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Layers</primary>
      <secondary>Vector</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Vector layers, are layers based on paths, with their own
      fill and stroke settings, which can be edited at any time.
      To add a new vector layer, you first create a path with the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path Tool</link> and then use the
      <guibutton>Create new vector Layer</guibutton> button in the
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-path-options">Path Tool Options</link>
      to create a vector layer from that path.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-layer-type-link-layer">
    <title>Link Layer</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Link Layer</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Layers</primary>
      <secondary>Link</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Link layers connect a layer in your image to an external image available
      elsewhere on your computer or a connected device. This can be advantageous
      if you use the same image in multiple projects, e.g. a logo.
    </para>
    <para>
      When an external image is updated, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> automatically
      detects the change and updates the version you are using as a link layer
      too. Any image that GIMP can load can be used as a link layer.
    </para>
    <para>
      One important consideration when using link layers is, that the external
      image needs to stay available in the same location, or GIMP won't be
      able to update your image that uses it as a link layer.
    </para>
    <para>
      By default, the location of the external image is stored relative to the
      location of the image where you include it as a link layer. Which means
      that you can move your image somewhere else, as long as you also move the
      external image to the same relative location.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Link layers are similar to <quote>Smart Objects</quote> available in
        some other image editors.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
