<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-04-05 Mr.Dust : reviewed and added 'ko'
  2007-01-09 manuq: added es translation
  2006-09-06 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-02 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-11 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-04-30 HdJ: Added dutch translation.
  2006-03-05 Lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant
  2005-11-28 Lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures.
  2005-05-09 nn: added french translation
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-palettes">
  <title>Palettes</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Palette</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Color</primary>
    <secondary>Palettes (color map)</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Indexed palette</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    A <emphasis>palette</emphasis> is a set of discrete colors. In
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, palettes are used mainly for two purposes:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        They allow you to paint with a selected set of colors, in the same way
        an oil painter works with colors from a limited number of tubes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        They form the colormaps of indexed images. An indexed image can use a
        maximum of 256 different colors, but these can be any colors. The
        colormap of an indexed image is called an "indexed palette" in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    Actually neither of these functions fall very much into the mainstream of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> usage: it is possible to do rather sophisticated
    things in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    without ever dealing with palettes. Still, they are something that an
    advanced user should understand, and even a less advanced user may need to
    think about them in some situations, as for example when working with GIF
    files.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>The Palettes dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/palettes-list-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    When you install <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it comes supplied with several
    dozen predefined
    palettes, and you can also create new ones. Some of the predefined
    palettes are commonly useful, such as the <quote>Web</quote> palette,
    which contains the set of colors considered <quote>web safe</quote>;
    many of the palettes seem to have been chosen more or less whimsically.
    You can access all of the available palettes using the
    <link linkend="gimp-palette-dialog">Palettes dialog</link>.
    This is also the starting point if you want to create a new palette.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>The Palette Editor</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/palette-editor-dialog.png"
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    Double-clicking on a palette in the Palettes dialog brings up the
    <link linkend="gimp-palette-editor-dialog">Palette Editor</link>,
    showing the colors from the palette you clicked on. You can use this to
    paint with the palette: clicking on a color sets <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
    foreground to that
    color, as shown in the Color Area of the Toolbox. Holding down the
    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while clicking, on the other hand, sets
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
    background color to the color you click on.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can also, as the name implies, use the Palette Editor to change the
    colors in a palette, so long as it is a palette that you have created
    yourself. You cannot edit the palettes that are supplied with
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>;
    however you can duplicate them and then edit the copies.
  </para>
  <para>
    When you create palettes using the Palette Editor, they are automatically
    saved as soon as you exit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, in the
    <filename>palettes</filename>
    folder of your personal <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory.
    Any palette files in your
    directory, or in the system <filename>palettes</filename>
    directory created when <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is installed, are
    automatically loaded and
    shown in the Palettes dialog the next time you start
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You can also
    add other folders to the palette search path using the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-palettes">Palette Folders</link>
    page of the Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> palettes are stored using a special file format,
    in files with the
    extension <filename>.gpl</filename>.
    It is a very simple format, and they are ASCII files, so if you happen
    to obtain palettes from another source, and would like to use them in
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it probably won't be very hard to convert them:
    just take a look at
    any <filename>.gpl</filename> and you will see what to do.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Colormap</title>
    <para>
      Confusingly, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes use of two types of palettes.
      The more
      noticeable are the type shown in the Palettes dialog: palettes that
      exist independently of any image. The second type,
      <emphasis>indexed palettes</emphasis>,
      form the colormaps of indexed images. Each indexed image has its own
      private indexed palette, defining the set of colors available in the
      image: the maximum number of colors allowed in an indexed palette is
      256. These palettes are called <quote>indexed</quote> because each
      color is associated with an index number. (Actually, the colors in
      ordinary palettes are numbered as well, but the numbers have no
      functional significance.)
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The Colormap dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/colormap-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The colormap of an indexed image is shown in the
      <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Indexed Palette
      dialog</link>,
      which should not be confused with the Palettes dialog. The Palettes
      dialog shows a list of all of the palettes available; the Colormap
      dialog shows the colormap of the currently active image, if it is an
      indexed image &ndash; otherwise it shows nothing.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can, however, create an ordinary palette from the colors in an
      indexed image&mdash;actually from the colors in any image. To do this,
      choose <guimenuitem>Import Palette</guimenuitem>
      from the right-click popup menu in the Palettes dialog: this pops up a
      dialog that gives you several options, including the option to import
      the palette from an image. (You can also import any of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s gradients
      as a palette.) This possibility becomes important if you want to create
      a set of indexed images that all use the same set of colors.
    </para>
    <para>
      When you convert an image into indexed mode, a major part of the process
      is the creation of an indexed palette for the image. How this happens is
      described in detail in <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/>.
      Briefly, you have several methods to choose from, one of which is to
      use a specified palette from the Palettes dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      Thus, to sum up the foregoing, ordinary palettes can be turned into
      indexed palettes when you convert an image into indexed mode; indexed
      palettes can be turned into ordinary palettes by importing them into the
      Palettes dialog.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
