<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-concepts-palettes' lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang='cs'>Palety</title>
  <title lang='en'>Palettes</title>
  <title lang='fr'>Palettes</title>  <!--050509-->
  <title lang="zh_CN">色板</title>

  <para lang='cs'>
    <emphasis>Paleta</emphasis> je sada barev. V gimpu slouží palety ke dvoum
    účelům:
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>palette</emphasis> is a set of discrete
    colors.  In GIMP, palettes are used mainly for two purposes:
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Une <emphasis>palette</emphasis> est une collection de couleurs 
    différentes. Dans Gimp, les palette sont utilisées dans deux buts:
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <emphasis>色板</emphasis>是一组不连续的颜色。GIMP 中色板主要有两种用途：
  </para>

  <itemizedlist lang='cs'>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Palety umožňují malovat s předem danou sadou barev, podbně jako malíř
        pracuje s barvami z omezené sady tub. <!--FIXME-->
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Tvoří barevné mapy pro indexované obrázky. Indexovaný obrázek může
        používat maximálně 256 barev, mohou to však být barvy libovolné.
        Mapa barev indexovaného obrázku se také nazývá indexovaná paleta.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang='en'>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        They allow you to paint with a selected set of colors, in the
        same way an oil painter works with colors from a limited
        number of tubes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        They form the colormaps of indexed images.  An indexed image
        can use a maximum of 256 different colors, but these can be
        any colors.  The colormap of an indexed image is called an
        "indexed palette" in GIMP.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Elles vous permettent de peindre avec un lot réduit de 
        couleurs, de même qu'un peintre utilise un nombre réduit de 
        tubes de couleurs.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Elles constituent la carte des couleurs des images indexées. 
        Une image indexée peut avoir un maximum de 256 couleurs, mais 
        il peut s'agir de n'importe lesquelles. La carte des couleurs 
        d'une image indexée s'appelle «palette indexée» dans Gimp.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        您可以通过色板使用一组颜色进行绘图，想到于现实中使用有限的颜料进行油画。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        它定义了索引图像的颜色表。索引图像可以使用任何256种不同的颜色。索引图像的颜色表在 GIMP 中叫作“颜色表”。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Ve skutečnosti ale ani jedna z těchto funkcí není příliš často používaná;
    v Gimpu je možné pracovat léta a provádět s ním velmi složité věci bez
    použití palet. Stále se však jedná o něco, čemu by měl pokročilý uživatel
    rozumět, a i méně pokročilým uživatelům se palety mohou někdy hodit,
    například při práci s GIf soubory nebo optimalizaci určitého typu webové
    grafiky.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Actually neither of these functions fall very much into the
    mainstream of GIMP usage:  it is possible to do rather
    sophisticated things in GIMP without every dealing with palettes.
    Still, they are something that an advanced user should understand,
    and even a less advanced user may need to think about them in
    some situations, as for example when working with GIF files.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    A vrai dire, aucune de ces fonctions n'est indispensable dans gimp: 
    il est possible de faire des choses très compliquées dans Gimp 
    sans avoir recours aux palettes. Mais ce sont quand même des 
    choses qu'un utilisateur averti doit comprendre et un utilisateur 
    moins avancé doit y penser quand il manipule des images au format 
    GIF.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    实际上这些功能都不是 GIMP 中主要的用法：在 GIMP 中进行很复杂的处理而不必操作色板是可能的。不过高级用户甚至是中级用户在某些情况下(比如处理 GIF 文件)有必要运用它们。
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-palettes.png'
        format='PNG' />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
         Dialog Palety
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
         The Palettes dialog
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le dialogue des palettes
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          色板对话框
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Spolu s Gimpem se dodává mnoho předdefinovaných barevných palet, další
    může doinstalovávat nebo vytvářet sám uživatel. Některé z předdefinovaných
    palet jsou obecně užitečné, například paleta „Web“, která obsahuje
    bezpečné barvy pro použití na webu (barvy, které se s vysokou
    pravděpodobností beze změny zobrazí i na starších počítačích). Jiné byly
    vybrány víceméně náhodně, protože pěkně vypadají. Všechny dostupné palety
    jsou přístupné pomocí <link linkend='gimp-palette-dialog'>dialogu
    Palety</link>. V něm lze také zahájit vytváření palety nové.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    When you install GIMP, it comes supplied with several dozen
    predefined palettes, and you can also create new ones.  Some of
    the predefined palettes are commonly useful, such as the "Web"
    palette, which contains the set of colors considered "web safe";
    many of the palettes seem to have been chosen more or less
    whimsically.  You can access all of the available palettes using
    the <link linkend='gimp-palette-dialog'>Palettes dialog</link>.
    This is also the starting point if you want to create a new
    palette. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Gimp est livré avec plusieurs douzaines de palettes prédéfinies, 
    et vous pouvez en créer de nouvelles. Certaines de ces palettes 
    sont très utiles, en particulier la palette «Web» considérée 
    comme «à l'épreuve du Web», en ce sens que ses couleurs doivent 
    rester inchangées sur tous les navigateurs. Mais la plupart 
    semblent avoir été choisies au hasard. Vous pouvez accéder aux 
    palettes disponibles par le <link 
    linkend='gimp-palette-dialog'>Dialogue des Palettes</link>. C'est 
    aussi le point de départ pour créer de nouvelles palettes. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    安装 GIMP 时就提供了大量预先定义的色板，并且您也可以自己新建。很多预先定义的色板非常有用，如“Web”色板，它囊括了一组对网页安全的色板;许多被选中的色板或多或少来之突发奇想。您可以在<link linkend='gimp-palette-dialog'>色板对话框</link>中找到所有可用色板以及新建色板的选项。
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="cs;en;zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-palette-editor.png'
        format='PNG' />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Editor palety
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          The Palette Editor
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          色板编辑器
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject lang="fr">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-palette-editor.png'
        format='PNG' />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="fr">
          L'Éditeur de palettes
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Dvojité kliknutí na paletu v dialogu Palety otevře <link
    linkend='gimp-palette-editor-dialog'>Editor palety</link>,
    který zobrazí všechny barvy z otevřené palety. Kliknutí na některou
    z barev v paletě nastaví tuto barvu jako barvu popředí v Gimpu,
    kliknutí s podrženou klávesou <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> nastaví tuto barvu
    jako barvu pozadí.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Double-clicking on a palette in the Palettes dialog brings up the
    <link linkend='gimp-palette-editor-dialog'>Palette Editor</link>, showing
    the colors from the palette you clicked 
    on.  You can use this to paint with the palette:  clicking on a
    color sets GIMP's foreground to that color, as shown in the Color
    Area of the Toolbox.  Holding down the Ctrl key while clicking, on
    the other hand, sets GIMP's background color to the color you
    click on.   
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Un double-clic sur une des palettes du Dialogue des palettes ouvre 
    la fenêtre de l'<link 
    linkend='gimp-palette-editor-dialog'>Éditeur de Palettes</link> 
    qui affiche les couleurs de la palette sur laquelle vous avez 
    cliqué. Vous pouvez alors peindre avec les couleurs de cette 
    palette: en cliquant sur une couleur de la palette, cette couleur apparaît 
    comme couleur de Premier-plan dans la zone des couleurs de la 
    Boîte à outils. Et un Ctrl-clic placera la couleur comme couleur 
    d'Arrière-plan.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    双击色板对话框中的一个色板会唤出<link linkend='gimp-palette-editor-dialog'>色板编辑器</link>，显示该色板中的颜色。您可以使用它来用色板涂画：点击一个颜色将把它作为 GIMP 的前景色，并在工具箱的颜色区域显示，而按住 Ctrl 并点击则把该颜色作为 GIMP 的背景色。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    jak již název napovídá, můžete Editor palety použít i ke změně barev v
    paletě. Lze to však učinit pouze u uživatelem dodaných či vytvořených
    palet, nikoliv u plaet dodávaných spolu s Gimpem. Takové palety však lze
    duplikovat a upravit barvy v jejich kopii.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You can also, as the name implies, use the Palette Editor to
    change the colors in a palette, so long as it is a palette that
    you have created yourself.  You cannot edit the palettes that are
    supplied with GIMP; however you can duplicate them and then edit
    the copies.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Vous pouvez aussi, comme son nom l'indique, utiliser l'Éditeur de 
    palettes pour changer les couleurs de la palette, à condition que 
    vous ayiez créé cette palette vous-même. En effet, vous ne pouvez 
    pas modifier les palettes fournies par Gimp. Néanmoins, vous 
    pouvez les dupliquer pour les éditer.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    正如其名字所说，您可以用色板编辑器改变自己创建色板中的颜色，但不能编辑 GIMP 自带的色板;不过您可以先复制它们然后对拷贝进行编辑。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Palety vytvořené či pozměněné pomocí Editoru palet se automaticky ukládají
    při ukončení Gimpu do adresáře <filename>palettes</filename> v osobním
    uživatelském adresáři Gimpu. Všechny palety v tomto adresáři, stejně jako
    všechny palety v systémovém adresáři <filename>palettes</filename> (ten
    obsahuje palety dodávané spolu s Gimpem), se nahrají při příštím spuštění
    Gimpu. Do seznamu adresářů, ze kterých se cesty nahrávají, můžete přidat i
    další pložky. Slouží k tomu karta předvoleb <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Adresáře/Palety</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    When you create palettes using the Palette Editor, they are
    automatically saved as soon as you exit GIMP, in the
    <filename>palettes</filename> folder of your personal GIMP
    directory.  Any palette files in this directory, or in the system
    <filename>palettes</filename> directory created when GIMP is
    installed, are automatically loaded and shown in the Palettes
    dialog the next time you start GIMP.  You can also add other
    folders to the palette search path using the <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Palette Folders</link> page of
    the Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Quand vous créez des palettes avec l'Éditeur de palettes, elles 
    sont automatiquement enregistrées dans le dossier <filename>
    palettes</filename> de votre répertoire personnel. Toutes les 
    palettes situées dans ce répertoire ou dans le répertoire système 
    des palettes de Gimp, sont chargées au démarrage de Gimp et 
    présentées dans le Dialogue des palettes. Vous pouvez ajouter 
    d'autres dossiers aux chemins de recherche des palettes de Gimp 
    grâce à la page <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>Dossiers/Palettes</link> des 
    Préférences.  
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    在使用色板编辑器创建了新的色板后，退出 GIMP 后，这些色板就自动保存到您个人 GIMP 目录的<filename>palettes</filename>文件夹中。在该目录以及随 GIMP 安装建立的系统<filename>palettes</filename>目录中的所有色板文件都会在下次 GIMP 启动时自动加载并显示。也可以在首选项对话框的<link linkend='gimp-prefs-folders-data'>色板文件夹</link>页中添加其它文件夹到色板搜索路径中。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Palety Gimp ukládá ve speciálním souborovém formátu; soubory s paletami
    mají příponu <filename>.gpl</filename>. Jedná se o jednoduché ASCII
    soubory, takže případná konverze do tohoto typu souboru z jiných zdrojů
    není nikterak obtížná. V případě potřeby stačí nahlédnout do některého z
    existujících <filename>.gpl</filename> souborů textovým editorem.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP palettes are stored using a special file format, in files
    with the extension <filename>.gpl</filename>.  It is a very simple
    format, and they are ASCII files, so if you happen to obtain
    palettes from another source, and would like to use them in GIMP,
    it probably won't be very hard to convert them:  just take a look
    at any <filename>.gpl</filename> and you will see what to do.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les palettes de Gimp sont enregistrées dans un format spécial, 
    avec l'extension <filename>.gpl</filename>. C'est un format très 
    simple, et ce sont des fichiers ASCII. Si donc vous acquérez des 
    palettes d'une autre source et que vous vouliez les utiliser 
    dans Gimp, il ne devrait pas être trop difficile de les convertir: 
    jetez simplement un œil à un fichier .gpl quelconque et vous 
    verrez ce qu'il faut faire.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 使用<filename>.gpl</filename>这种专门的文件格式保存色板，它们是非常简单的 ASCII 文件格式，因此如果您想在 GIMP 中使用其它地方的色板，也许并不难转换它们：只需看下任何<filename>.gpl</filename>文件就明白该如何做了。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='cs'>Mapa barev</title>
    <title lang='en'>Colormap</title> <!-- Changed 20041123 -->
    <title lang='fr'>Palette des couleurs</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">颜色表</title>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Poněkud matoucí je, že Gimp používá dva typy palet. Prvním typem jsou
      palety z dialogu Palety, které existují nezávisle na obrázku. Druhý typ,
      tzv. <emphasis>indexované palety</emphasis>, tvoří mapy barev
      indexovaných obrázků.Každý indexovaný obrázek má svou vlastní
      indexovanou paletu, která určuje, jaké barvy jsou v obrázku dostupné.
      Maximální počet barev v indexované paletě je 256. Indexované se paletám
      říká proto, že každá barva je spojena s číslem, tzv. indexem.
      (Barvy v běžných paletách jsou také číslované, ale tam číslo nemá žádný
      význam.)
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      Confusingly, GIMP makes use of two types of palettes.  The more
      noticeable are the type shown in the Palettes dialog:  palettes
      that exist independently of any image.  The second type,
      <emphasis>indexed palettes</emphasis>, form the colormaps of
      indexed images.  Each indexed image has its own private indexed
      palette, defining the set of colors available in the image:  the
      maximum number of colors allowed in an indexed palette is 256.
      These palettes are called "indexed" because each color is
      associated with an index number.  (Actually, the colors in
      ordinary palettes are numbered as well, but the numbers have no
      functional significance.)
   </para>
   <para lang="fr">
      Pour compliquer les choses, Gimp utilise deux types de palettes. 
      Les plus importantes sont celles présentées dans le Dialogue des 
      palettes: ce sont des palettes indépendantes du type de l'image. 
      Le deuxième type, celui des <emphasis>palette des couleurs</emphasis>,
      constitue les cartes de couleurs des images indexées. Le nombre  
      maximum de couleurs dans une palette indexée est de 256. Ces 
      palettes s'appellent «indexées» parce que chaque couleur est 
      associée à un numéro index. (En fait, les couleurs des palettes 
      ordinaires sont également numérotées, mais les numéros n'ont pas 
      de signification fonctionnelle).
  </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      使人困惑的，GIMP使用两种类型的色板：最明显的是显示在色板对话框中：这些色板独立与任何图像。第二种类型是<emphasis>颜色表</emphasis>，构成索引图像的颜色表。每个索引图像都有自己的私用颜色表，定义一组图像可用的颜色：索引图像中最多使用 256 种颜色。这些色板被称为“索引”，因为每种颜色都与一个指数相关联。(实际上，普通色板中的颜色也与数字相关联，不过这些数字没有功能上的意义。)
    </para>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="cs;en;zh_CN">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata  fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-indexed-palette.png'
          format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang='cs'>
          Dialog Mapa barev
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
          The Colormap dialog
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            颜色表对话框
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject lang="fr">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata  fileref='../images/dialogs/fr/dialogs-colormap.png'
          format='PNG' />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="fr">
            La fenêtre de dialogue Palette des couleurs
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Mapa barev indexovaného obrázku je zobrazena v <!--<link
      linkend='gimp-indexed-palette-dialog'>-->dialogu Indexovaní
      paleta<!--</link>-->, který se nesmí zaměňovat s dialogem Palety.
      Dialog Palety zobrazuje všechny dostupné palety, dialog indexovaná
      paleta zobrazuje mapu barev aktivního obrázku (pokud je to indexovaný
      obrázek - jinak neukazuje nic).
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      The colormap of an indexed image is shown in the <link
      linkend='gimp-indexed-palette-dialog'>Indexed Palette
      dialog</link>, which should not be confused with the Palettes
      dialog.  The Palettes dialog shows a list of all of the palettes
      available; the Colormap dialog shows the colormap of the
      currently active image, if it is an indexed image---otherwise it
      shows nothing.
    </para>
   <para lang="fr">
      La carte des couleurs d'une image indexée est affichée dans le 
      <link linkend='gimp-indexed-palette-dialog'>Dialogue Palette
      des couleurs</link>, qui ne doit pas être confondu avec le Dialogue 
      des palettes. S'il ne s'agit pas d'une image indexée (.GIF), ce 
      dialogue reste vide.
  </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      索引图像的颜色表在<link linkend='gimp-indexed-palette-dialog'>颜色表对话框</link>中显示，不过不要和色板对话框搞混淆了。色板对话框显示所有可用色板的列表;而颜色表对话框显示当前活动索引图像的颜色表，如果不是索引图像则什么都不显示。
    </para>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Lze ovšem vytvořit běžnou paletu z barev indexované palety, respektive z
      barev libovolného obrázku. Lze tak učinit pomocí příkazu Importovat
      paletu z kontextové nabídky dialogu Palety. Otevře se tak dialog s řadou
      možností, z nichž jedna je import palety z obrázku. Je to důležité v
      případě, že chcete vytvořit řadu indexovaných obrázků používajících
      stejnou sadu barev.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      You can, however, create an ordinary palette from the colors in
      an indexed image---actually from the colors in any image.  To do
      this, choose "Import Palette" from the right-click popup menu in
      the Palettes dialog:  this pops up a dialog that gives you
      several options, including the option to import the palette from
      an image.  (You can also import any of GIMP's gradients as a
      palette.)  This possibility becomes important if you want to
      create a set of indexed images that all use the same set of
      colors. 
    </para>
   <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez néanmoins créer une palette à partir d'une image 
      indexée, comme à partir de n'importe qu'elle image en fait. Pour 
      cela, choisissez «Importer une palette» dans le menu local 
      obtenu par un clic droit sur le Dialogue des palettes, ce qui 
      ouvre une fenêtre vous offrant plusieurs options, dont celle 
      d'importer une palette à partir d'une image. Vous pouvez aussi 
      importer une palette à partir d'un dégradé.
  </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN"> 
      尽管如此，您可以从索引图像(实际上是任何图像)的颜色中创建一个普通色板。即在右键点击色板对话框弹出的菜单中选取“导出色板”：然后它会弹出一个对话框，其中有很多选项，包括从图像中导入色板。(也可以导入任何 GIMP 渐变到色板。)该选项对创建一组使用一系列相同颜色的索引图像至关重要。
    </para>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Když předvádíte obrázek do indexovaného režimu, důležitá část procesu je
      vytvoření indexované palety pro obrázek. Existuje několik možností, jak
      to udělat, jedna z nich je použití určité palety z dialogu Palety.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      When you convert an image into indexed mode, a major part of the
      process is the creation of an indexed palette for the image.
      How this happens is described in detail in ??.  Briefly, you
      have several methods to choose from, one of which is to use a
      specified palette from the Palettes dialog.
    </para>
   <para lang="fr">
      Quand vous convertissez une image en mode indexé, une grande 
      part du processus consiste à créer la palette indexée de 
      l'image. Voyez <link linkend='gimp-image-mode'>Mode</link>  
  </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      将图像转换为索引模式时，最主要的步骤就是给图像生成一个颜色表。您可以选择多种方法，其中一种就是在色板对话框中的选定一种。
    </para>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Tedy běžné palety lze převést na indexované při převodu obrázku do
      indexovaného režimu, zatímco indexované palety lze převést na běžné
      importem v dialogu Palety.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      Thus, to sum up the foregoing, ordinary palettes can be turned
      into indexed palettes when you convert an image into indexed
      mode; indexed palettes can be turned into ordinary palettes by
      importing them into the Palettes dialog.
    </para>
   <para lang="fr">
      En somme, les palettes ordinaire peuvent être transformées en 
      palettes indexées, et les palettes indexées transformées en 
      palettes ordinaires en les important dans le Dialogue des 
      palettes.
  </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      简单的总结上面所说的就是：当您将图像转换为索引模式时，普通色板能变为颜色表;通过导入到色板对话框，颜色表能变为普通色板。
    </para>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>

  
