<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-concepts-paths' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Paths</title>
  <title lang='de'>Pfade</title>
  <title lang="fr">Chemins</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">路径</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <primary lang='de'>Bild</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Paths</secondary>
    <secondary lang='de'>Pfade</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Chemins</secondary>  <!--050509-->
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">路径</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/path-examples.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>

       <caption>
         <para lang='en'>
           Four examples of GIMP paths: one closed and polygonal; one
           open and polygonal; one closed and curved; one with a mixture
           of straight and curved segments.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Vier beispielhafte Darstellungen von Pfaden in
          <acronym>Gimp</acronym>: geschlossen und polygonal, offen und
          polygonal, geschlossen und kurvig, Mix aus gerade und kurvige
          Segmente.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Quatre exemples de chemins Gimp: un fermé et polygonal; un ouvert 
          et polygonal; un fermé et courbe; un avec un mélange de segments 
          droits et courbes.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
           GIMP 路径的四个例子：一个封闭多边的；一个开放多边的；一个封闭曲线的；一个直线段和曲线段混合的。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    A <emphasis>path</emphasis> is a one-dimensional curve.  Paths are
    used for two main purposes:
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Ein Pfad ist eine eindimensionale Kurve. Pfade werden vor allem für
    zwei Hauptgründe benutzt:
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Un <emphasis>chemin</emphasis> est une courbe uni-dimensionnelle. Les 
    chemins sont utilisés dans deux buts:
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <emphasis>路径</emphasis>是一维的曲线，它主要有两个用途：
  </para>
  <itemizedlist lang='en'>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A closed path can be converted into a selection.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        An open or closed path can be <emphasis>stroked</emphasis>,
        that is, painted on the image, in a variety of ways.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang='de'>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Ein geschlossener Pfad<footnote>
          <para>
            Zur Vollständigkeit: Auch können Auswahlen aus offenen Pfaden
            in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> erstellt werden. Der Pfad wird
            automatisch geschlossen um die Auswahl zu erstellen.
          </para>
        </footnote> kann in eine Auswahl konvertiert werden.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Ein offener oder geschlossener Pfad kann benutzt werden, um ihn
        nach zu zeichnen. Ein unterstützendes Element zum malen von
        kurvigen Linien.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Un chemin fermé peut être transformé en sélection.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Un chemin fermé ou ouvert peut être <emphasis>tracé</emphasis>,
        càd dessiné de multiples façons.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        闭合的路径能转变为选区。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        开启或闭合的路径能被<emphasis>勾画</emphasis>，即用多种方式涂画到图像上。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'>
    Paths can be created and manipulated using the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-path'>Path tool</link>.  Paths, like layers and
    channels, are components of an image.  When an image is saved in
    GIMP's native XCF file format, any paths it has are saved along
    with it.  The list of paths in an image can be viewed and operated
    on using the <link linkend='gimp-path-dialog'>Paths
    dialog</link>.  If you want to move a path from one image to
    another, you can do so by copying and pasting using the popup menu
    in the Paths dialog, or by dragging an icon from the Paths dialog
    into the destination image's window.
  </para>
  <para lang='de'>
    Pfade können mit dem <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-path'>Pfadwerkzeug</link> erstellt und
    manipuliert werden. Sobald Sie ihr Bild als <link
    linkend='gimp-xcf-save'>XCF Format</link> speichern, werden auch
    ihre angelegten Pfade gespeichert. Eine Liste der erstellten Pfade
    in einem Bild, können Sie mit dem <link
    linkend='gimp-path-dialog'>Pfaddialog</link> herausfinden. Wenn sie
    Pfade in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> von ein Bild in das andere Bild
    übertragen wollen, benutzen Sie <guilabel>Kopieren</guilabel> und
    <guilabel>Einfügen</guilabel> im Kontextmenü des Pfaddialoges,
    welches Sie per rechten Mausklick<footnote>
      <para>
        Benutzer des Apple Macintosh benutzen
        <keycap>Strg</keycap>+linke Maustaste.
      </para>
    </footnote> aufrufe können.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les chemins peuvent être créés et manipulés grâce à l'outil <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-path'>Chemins</link>. Les chemins, comme les 
    calques et les canaux, font partie de l'image. Quand vous 
    enregistrez une image au format natif de Gimp XCF, les chemins 
    sont sauvegardés en même temps.
    La liste des chemins peut être visualisée et manipulée grâce au 
    <link linkend='gimp-path-dialog'>Dialogue des chemins</link>. Si 
    vous voulez déplacer un chemin d'une image dans l'autre, vous 
    pouvez faire un copier-coller grâce au menu local ouvert par un 
    clic droit dans le Dialogue des chemins, ou un cliquer-glisser de 
    l'icône du chemin dans le Dialogue des chemins jusque dans l'image 
    de destination.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    可以通过<link linkend='gimp-tool-path'>路径工具</link>来创建和处理路径。路径，像图层和通道一样都是图像的组成部分，当图像保存为 GIMP 内建的 XCF 文件格式时，路径也被保存进去。图像中的路径列表可以通过<link linkend='gimp-path-dialog'>路径对话框</link>查看和操作。假如您想将一个路径从一个图像移动另一个，可以在路径对话框中的弹出菜单使用拷贝和粘贴，或从路径对话框拖动一个图标到目标图像窗口中。
  </para>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/using/path-with-anchors.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>

       <caption>
         <para lang='en'>
           Appearance of a path while it is being manipulated using the
           Path tool.  Black squares are anchor points, the open circle
           is the selected anchor, and the two open squares are its
           handles.  Note that this path has two components.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Ansicht eines Pfades während er mit dem Pfadwerkzeug
          manipuliert wird. Die schwarzen Rechtecke sind Kontrollpunkte,
          der offene Kreis ist ein selektierter Kontrollpunkt. Beide
          offene Quadrate am selektierten Kontrollpunkt sind Handles
          <!--XXX-->. Beachten sie, dass dieser Pfad zwei Segmente hat.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Aspect d'un chemin manipulé avec l'outil Chemin. Les carrés noirs 
          sont les points d'ancrage,le cercle vide est l'ancre sélectionnée,
          et les deux carrés vides sont ses poignées. Notez que ce chemin a 
          deux composants. 
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          一个正在用路径工具处理的路径，黑色正方形是锚点，开启的圆形是选中的锚点，而两个空心的正方形是它的臂点。主要该路径有两部分。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP paths belong to a mathematical type called "Bezier paths".
    What this means in practical terms is that they are defined by
    <emphasis>anchors</emphasis> and <emphasis>handles</emphasis>.
    "Anchors" are points the path goes through.  "Handles" define the
    direction of a path when it enters or leaves an anchor point:
    each anchor point has two handles attached to it.  
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les chemins de Gimp appartiennent à un type de courbe mathématique 
    appelé «Courbes de Bézier». Les points d'ancrage sont les points 
    par où passe le chemin et les poignées définissent la direction du 
    chemin à l'entrée et à la sortie d'un point d'ancrage. Chaque 
    point d'ancrage a deux poignées qui lui sont attachées.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 路径属于一种叫“Bezier 路径”的数学类型，在实践中就是用<emphasis>锚点</emphasis>和<emphasis>臂点</emphasis>来定义它。“锚点”就是路径通过的点，“臂点”定义路径进入或离开锚点时的方向：每个锚点上带了两个臂点。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Paths can be very complex.  If you create them by hand using the
    Path tool, unless you are obsessive they probably won't contain
    more than a few dozen anchor points (often many fewer); but if you
    create them by transforming a selection into a path, or by
    transforming text into a path, the result can easily contain
    hundreds of anchor points, or even thousands.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les chemins peuvent être très complexes. Si vous les créez à la 
    main avec l'outil Chemin, il n'auront le plus souvent qu'une 
    douzaine de points d'ancrage. Mais si vous les créez par 
    transformation d'une sélection en chemin, ou par transformation 
    d'un texte en chemin, ils pourront contenir des centaines, voire 
    des milliers, de points d'ancrage.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    路径可能非常复杂。当您徒手用路径工具创建路径时，它们可能不会包含超过几十个锚点；不过当您将一个选区或文字转变为路径时，很容易就有几百甚至上千个锚点。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    A path may contain multiple <emphasis>components</emphasis>.  A
    "component" is a part of a path whose anchor points are all
    connected to each other by path segments.  The ability to have
    multiple components in paths allows you to convert them into
    selections having multiple disconnected parts.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Un chemin peut comporter plusieurs <emphasis>composants</emphasis>. 
    Un composant est une partie d'un chemin dont les points d'ancrages 
    sont unis les uns aux autres par des segments. La possibilité 
    d'avoir plusieurs composants vous permet de les convertir en 
    sélections indépendantes.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    一个路径可能包含多个<emphasis>部分</emphasis>。一个“部分”是指所有锚点通过路径段都连在一起的路径，路径的这种有多个部分的能力使它们可以被转变为有多个不相连部分的选区。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Each component of a path can be either <emphasis>open</emphasis>
    or <emphasis>closed</emphasis>: "closed" means that the last
    anchor point is connected to the first anchor point.  If you
    transform a path into a selection, any open components are
    automatically converted into closed components by connecting the
    last anchor point to the first anchor point with a straight line.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Chaque composant d'un chemin peut être <emphasis>ouvert</emphasis> 
    ou <emphasis>fermé</emphasis>: «fermé» signifie que le dernier 
    point d'ancrage est relié au premier. Si vous transformez un 
    chemin en sélection, les composants ouverts seront automatiquement 
    fermés en reliant le dernier point d'ancrage au premier par une 
    ligne droite.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    路径的每个部分要么是<emphasis>开放</emphasis>，要么是<emphasis>封闭</emphasis>：“封闭”指最后的锚点和起始锚点是相连的。当您将路径转变为选区时，任何开放部分都自动将最后的锚点用直线连接到起始锚点，从而变为一个封闭部分。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Path segments can be either straight or curved.  A path all of
    whose segments are straight is called "polygonal".  When you
    create a path segment, it starts out straight, because the handles
    for the anchor points are intially placed directly on top of the
    anchor points, yielding handles of zero length, which produce
    straight-line segments.  You can make a segment curved by dragging
    a handle away from one of the anchor points.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les segments d'un chemin peuvent être droits ou courbes. Un chemin 
    dont tous les segments sont droits est appelé «polygonal». Quand 
    vous créez un segment de chemin, il commence par être droit, parce 
    que les poignées placées par dessus ont alors une longueur nulle. 
    Vous pouvez courber un segment en déplaçant une poignée à partir 
    d'un des points d'ancrage. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    路径段可以是直线或曲线。所有段都是直线的路径叫“多边的”。当新建一个路径段时，它默认是直线，因为锚点的臂点初始是直接重合在锚点上的，将锚点上的一个臂点拖开则会长生一个曲线段。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    One nice thing about paths is that they are very light in terms of
    resource consumption, especially in comparison with images.
    Representing a path in RAM only requires storing the
    coordinates of its anchors and handles:  1K of memory is enough to
    hold quite a complex path, but not enough to hold even a 20x20
    pixel RGB layer.  Therefore, it is quite possible to have
    literally hundreds of paths in an image without putting any
    signficant stress of your system.  (How much stress managing them
    would put on <emphasis>you</emphasis> is, of course, another
    question.)  Even a path with thousands of segments consumes
    minimal resources in comparison to a typical layer or channel.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Une bonne chose avec les chemins est qu'ils sont économes en 
    ressources, à la différence des images. Représenter un chemin en 
    mémoire ne nécessite que le stockage des coordonnées des ancres et 
    des poignées. 1Ko de mémoire suffit pour un chemin complexe alors 
    que ça ne suffit pas même à un calque RVB de 20x20 pixels. Il est 
    donc possible d'avoir des centaines de chemins dans une image sans 
    surcharge de votre système (la difficulté que vous aurez à les gérer 
    est un autre problème).
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN"> 
    路径一个优点就是其消耗资源非常少，特别是和图像相比。在 RAM 中表示一个路径只需要保存它的锚点和臂点座标：1K 内存保存一个复杂的路径已经足够，确保存不了一个 20x20 像素的 RGB 图层。因此，有几百个路径图像完全有可能不给您的系统带来任何明显的压力，即使一个有几百个路径段的路径在与一般的图层或通道相比时，也是消耗最少了。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Paths and Selections</title>
    <title lang='de'>Pfade und Auswahlen</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Chemins et sélections</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">路径和选区</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      GIMP lets you transform the selection for an image into a path;
      it also lets you transform paths into selections.  For
      information about the selection and how it works, see the <link
      linkend='gimp-concepts-selection'>Selection</link> section.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Gimp vous permet de transformer une sélection en chemin, et un 
      chemin en sélection. Voyez <link 
      linkend='gimp-concepts-selection'>Sélection</link> 
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Sie können mit <acronym>Gimp</acronym> eine Auswahl mittels Pfad
      erstellen. Wenn Sie einen Pfad aus einer Auswahl erstellen, wird
      der Pfad eine ähnliche Form wie die Auswahl annehmen. Beachten sie
      hierbei jedoch, dass die Erstellung des Pfades verlustbehaftet
      ist.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      GIMP
      让您将图像上的选区转换为路径；而可以将路径转换为选区。请看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-selection'>选区</link>获取选区及如何使用的信息。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      When you transform a selection into a path, the path closely
      follows the "marching ants".  Now, the selection is a
      two-dimensional entity, but a path is a one-dimensional entity,
      so there is no way to transform the selection into a path
      without losing information.  In fact, any information about
      partially selected areas (i.e., feathering) will be lost when
      the selection is turned into a path.  If the path is transformed
      back into a selection, the result is an all-or-none selection,
      similar to what would be obtained by executing "Sharpen" from
      the Select menu.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Quand vous transformez une sélection en chemin, le chemin suit 
      de près les «pointillés mobiles» qui délimitent la sélection. 
      Maintenant, la sélection est une entité bi-dimensionnelle alors 
      que le chemin est uni-dimensionnel, si bien que la 
      transformation entraîne une perte d'information. C'est ainsi 
      qu'une bordure adoucie ne sera pas conservée si vous 
      retransformez le chemin en sélection.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Ausserdem werden die Informatione eines weichen(ausgeblendeten)
      Randes bei einer Auswahl ebenfalls verworfen, sobald der Pfad
      erstellt wird. Wird wieder eine Auswahl aus dem Pfad erstellt,
      erhalten wieder eine Auswahle, aber ohne weichen(ausgeblendeten)
      Rand.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当将选区转换为路径时，路径被“行进中的蚂蚁”紧密跟随。现在，选区是二维的，而路径是一维，因此将选区转换为路径时肯定要丢失信息，实际上所有有关部分选中区域(比如羽化)的信息都丢失了。而将路径转换回到选区时，其结果是一个“全有或全无”选区
，和进行“锐化”效果是相同的。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Paths and Text</title>
    <title lang='de'>Pfade und Text</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Chemins et Texte</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">路径和文字</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/using/path-from-text.png'
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang='en'>
            Text converted to a path and then transformed using the
            Perspective tool.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Ein Pfad aus einem Text konvertiert und
            perspektivisch transformiert.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Texte converti en chemin puis transformé par l'outil 
            Perspective
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            文字被转换为一个路径，然后用透视工具进行变换。
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/using/path-text-stroked.png'
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang='en'>
           The path shown above, stroked with a fuzzy brush and then
           gradient-mapped using the Gradient Map filter with the
           "Yellow Contrast" gradient.
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Der Pfad wurde mittels einem weichem Pinsel nachgezeichnet.
            Darauf wurde ein Gradient abgebildet und mit dem "Gelben
            Konstrast" Filter verändert.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
             Le chemin précédent, tracé avec une brosse floue puis mappée en 
             utilisant le filtre Carte de dégradé avec le dégradé «Yellow 
             contrast».
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
             上面显示的路径是用一个模糊画笔勾画，然后对它使用渐变映射滤镜，渐变为“Yellow Contrast”。
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      A text item created using the Text tool can be transformed into
      a path using the "Create path from text" button in the Tool
      Options for the Text tool.  This can be useful for several
      purposes, including:
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Ein Text kann mittels <link
      linkend='gimp-tool-text'>Textwerkzeug</link> in ein Pfad
      konveriert werden. Benutzen Sie dafür die <guilabel>Pfad aus Text
      erzeugen</guilabel> Schaltfläche nach Erstellen des Textes. Das
      eröffnet unter anderem folgende Möglichkeiten:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un texte créé avec l'outil Texte peut être transformé en chemin 
      en utilisant le bouton «Créer un chemin depuis le texte" dans 
      le Dialogue des Options de l'outil.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      由文字工具创建的文字可以通过文字工具工具选项中的“从文字创建路径”按钮转换为一个路径。这非常有用，包括：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang='en'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Stroking the path, which gives you many possibilities for
          fancy text.
        </para>
      </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
          More importantly, transforming the text.  Converting text
          into a path, then transforming the path, and finally either
          stroking the path or converting it to a selection and
          filling it, often leads to much higher-quality results than
          rendering the text as a layer and transforming the pixel
          data. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist lang='de'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Durch Nachziehen des Pfades mit unendlich vielen Möglichkeiten
          von wunderbaren Texteffekten.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Transformieren von Text. Zur Zeit bieten die
          Transformationswerkzeuge die einzige Möglichkeit Text zu
          transformieren.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tracer le chemin, ce qui vous donne beaucoup de possibilités 
          de texte élaboré.
        </para>
      </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
          Plus important, la transformation du texte. Convertir un 
          texte en chemin, transformer le chemin, et finalement le 
          tracer ou le transformer en sélection et alors le remplir, 
          aboutit souvent à des résultats de qualité bien supérieure à 
          celle obtenue en plaçant le texte dans un calque et en le 
          traitant au niveau des pixels.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          勾画路径，可以产生很多漂亮的文字。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          更重要的是，变换文字。先将文字转换为一个路径，然后变换路径，最后勾画路径或将它变为一个选区并填充，这样常常生成比将文字渲染为一个图层并变换像素数据更高质量的效果。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </simplesect>
   
  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Paths and SVG files</title>
    <title lang='de'>Pfade und SVG Dateien</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Chemins et fichiers SVG</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">路径和 SVG 文件</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      SVG, standing for "Scalable Vector Graphics", is an increasingly
      popular file format for <emphasis>vector graphics</emphasis>, in
      which graphical elements are represented in a
      resolution-independent format, in contrast to <emphasis>raster
      graphics</emphasis>, in which graphical elements are represented
      as arrays of pixels.  GIMP is mainly a raster graphics program,
      but paths are vector entities.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics: graphismes vectoriels de taille 
      variable) est un format de fichier dont la popularité va 
      croissante parmi les <emphasis>graphismes vectoriels</emphasis>. 
      Les éléments graphiques y sont représentés dans un format 
      indépendant de la résolution, à la différence des <emphasis>
      graphismes tramés (raster)</emphasis> où les éléments graphiques 
      sont représentés en tableaux de pixels. Gimp est avant tout un 
      programme traitant des images pix-map, mais les chemins sont des 
      entités vectorielles.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      SVG 代表“可缩放矢量图形(Scalable Vector Graphics)”，它一种逐渐流行的<emphasis>矢量图形</emphasis>文件格式，其中图形元素以一种独立于分辨率的格式表现，它与图形元素被表现为像素阵列的<emphasis>光栅图形</emphasis>完全不同。GIMP 主要是一个光栅图形程序，不过路径是矢量的。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Fortunately, paths are represented in SVG files in almost
      exactly the same way they are represented in GIMP.  (Actually
      fortune has nothing to do with it:  GIMP's path handling was
      rewritten for GIMP 2.0 with SVG paths in mind.)  This
      compatibility makes it possible to store GIMP paths as SVG files
      without losing any information.   You can access this capability
      in the Paths dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Das SVG Format (Scalable Vector Graphics) ist ein Vektorformat
      welches Pfade benutzt um Formen zu beschreiben. Gimp selber,
      obwohl ein Pixelbearbeitungsprogramm, kann ihre Pfade in das SVG
      Format abspeichern, da Pfade simple Vektorobjekte darstellen.
      Diese Funktionalität finden Sie im <link
      linkend='gimp-path-dialog'>Pfaddialog</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Heureusement, les graphismes SVG sont représentés de la même 
      façon que les chemins de Gimp (en fait, la gestion des chemins 
      de Gimp a été réécrite avec le format SVG en vue). Cette 
      compatibilité rend possible l'enregistrement des chemins Gimp en 
      fichiers SVG sans perte d'information. Vous pouvez accéder à 
      cette possibilité dans le Dialogue des chemins.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      幸运的是，路径在 SVG 文件中表现方式几乎与在 GIMP 中完全相同，(实际上幸运没什么用：GIMP 2.0 重写其路径处理时就盘算要用 SVG 路径了。)这使得可以保存 GIMP 路径为 SVG 文件而不会丢失任何信息。您可以在路径对话框中使用这种能力。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      It also means that GIMP can create paths from SVG files saved in
      other programs, such as <application>Inkscape</application> or
      <application>Sodipodi</application>, two popular open-source
      vector graphics applications.  This is nice because those
      programs have much more powerful path-manipulation tools than
      GIMP does.  You can import a path from an SVG file using the
      Paths dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cela signifie aussi que Gimp peut créer des chemins à partir de 
      fichiers SVG enregistrés avec d'autres programmes, comme 
      <application>Inkscape</application> ou <application>Sodipodi
      </application>. C'est intéressant car ces programmes manipulent 
      bien mieux les chemins que ne le fait Gimp. Vous pouvez importer 
      un chemin d'un fichier SVG en utilisant le Dialogue des chemins.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这也表示 GIMP 能通过其它程序如 <application>Inkscape</application> 或 <application>Sodipodi</application> 保存的 SVG 文件来创建路径，这很好，因为这些程序比 GIMP 拥有更强大的路径处理工具。您可以使用路径对话框中从一个 SVG 文件中导入路径。
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The SVG format handles many other graphical elements than just
      paths:  among other things, it handles figures such as squares,
      rectangles, circles, ellipses, regular polygons, etc.  GIMP 2.0
      cannot do anything with these entities, but GIMP 2.2 can load
      them as paths.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le format SVG gère bien d'autres éléments graphiques que les 
      chemins, entre autres des carrés, des rectangles,des cercles, 
      des ellipses, des polygones réguliers...etc. Gimp 2.0 ne peut 
      rien faire avec ces entités, mais gimp 2.2 peut les charger en 
      tant que chemins.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了路径，SVG 格式还处理其它很多的图形元素：其中包括除了图形如正方形，矩形，圆形，椭圆和基本多边形等。GIMP 2.0 无法使用这些，不过 GIMP 2.2 可以将它们读取为路径。
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
      Creating paths is not the only thing GIMP can do with SVG
      files.  It can also open SVG files as GIMP images, in the usual
      way. 
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        Gimp kann nicht nur SVG Dateien als Pfade importieren, sondern
        diese Dateien auch ganz normal als <link
        linkend='gimp-file-open'>Pixelgrafik importieren</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
      La création de chemins n'est pas la seule chose que Gimp sache 
      faire avec les fichiers SVG. Il peut aussi les ouvrir en tant 
      qu'images Gimp, de la façon habituelle.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
      GIMP 不是只能用 SVG 文件来创建路径，还可以将它像普通的 GIMP 图形一样打开。
      </para>
    </note>
 
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
