<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-patterns">
  <title>Patterns</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Patterns</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    A <emphasis>pattern</emphasis> is an image, usually small, used
    for filling regions by <emphasis>tiling</emphasis>, that is, by
    placing copies of the pattern side by side like ceramic tiles.  A
    pattern is said to be <emphasis>tileable</emphasis> if copies of
    it can be adjoined left-edge-to-right-edge and
    top-edge-to-bottom-edge without creating obvious seams.  Not all
    useful patterns are tileable, but tileable patterns are nicest for
    many purposes.  (A <emphasis>texture</emphasis>, by the way, is
    the same thing as a pattern.)
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Pattern usage</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/patterns-usage.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Three ways of using the <quote>Leopard</quote> pattern:
          bucket-filling a selection, painting with the Clone tool, and
          stroking an elliptical selection with the pattern.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>In GIMP there are three main uses for patterns:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        With the <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket
        Fill</link> tool, you can choose to fill a region with a
        pattern instead of a solid color.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>The checked box for use a pattern</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/pattern-checked.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              The box for pattern fill is checked and a click on the pattern
              shows you all patterns in grid mode.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        With the <link linkend="gimp-tool-clone">Clone</link> tool,
        you can paint using a pattern, with a wide variety of
        paintbrush shapes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        When you <emphasis>stroke</emphasis> a path or selection, you
        can do it with a pattern instead of a solid color.  You can
        also use the Clone tool as your choice if you stroke the
        selection using a painting tool.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <tip>
    <para>
      Note: Patterns do not need to be opaque. If you fill or paint using a
      pattern with translucent or transparent areas, then the previous
      contents of the area will show through from behind it. This is one of
      many ways of doing <quote>overlays</quote> in GIMP.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
    When you install GIMP, it comes presupplied with a few dozen
    patterns, which seem to have been chosen more or less randomly.
    You can also add new patterns, either ones you create yourself, or
    ones you download from the vast number available online.
  </para>
  <para>
    GIMP's <emphasis>current pattern</emphasis>,
    used in most pattern-related operations, is shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox. Clicking on the pattern symbol
    brings up the <link linkend="gimp-pattern-dialog">Patterns dialog</link>,
    which allows you to select a different pattern. You can also access the
    Patterns dialog by menu, or dock it so that it is present continuously.
  </para>
  <para>
    To add a new pattern to the collection, so that it shows up in the
    Patterns dialog, you need to save it in a format GIMP can use, in a folder
    included in GIMP's pattern search path. There are several file formats you
    can use for patterns:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>PAT</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <filename class="extension">.pat</filename> format is used for
          patterns which were created specifically for GIMP. You can convert
          any image into a <filename class="extension">.pat</filename> file by
          opening it in GIMP and then saving it using a file name ending in
          <filename class="extension">.pat</filename>.
        </para>
        <caution>
          <!-- see bug #573828 -->
          <para>
            Do not confuse <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-generated
            <filename class="extension">.pat</filename> files with files
            created by other programs (e.g.
            <application>Photoshop</application>) &ndash; after all,
            <filename class="extension">.pat</filename> is just a part of an
            (arbitrary) file name.
          </para>
          <para>
            (However, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> <emphasis>does</emphasis>
            support <application>Photoshop</application>
            <filename class="extension">.pat</filename> files until a certain
            version.)
          </para>
        </caution>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>PNG, JPEG, BMP, GIF, TIFF</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can use
          <filename class="extension">.png</filename>,
          <filename class="extension">.jpg</filename>,
          <filename class="extension">.bmp</filename>,
          <filename class="extension">.gif</filename>, or
          <filename class="extension">.tiff</filename> files as patterns.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    To make a pattern available, you place it in one of the folders in GIMP's
    pattern search path. By default, the pattern search path includes two
    folders, the system <filename>patterns</filename> folder, which you should
    not use or alter, and the <filename>patterns</filename>
    folder inside your personal GIMP directory. You can add new folders to the
    pattern search path using the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Pattern Folders</link>
    page of the Preferences dialog. Any PAT file (or any of the
    other acceptable formats) included in a folder in the pattern search path
    will show up in the Patterns dialog the next time you start GIMP.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      You can add a new pattern quickly as you do for brushes. See 
        <xref linkend="gimp-creating-brush-quickly"/>.
    </para>
  </note>
  <para>
    There are countless ways of creating interesting pattern images in GIMP, 
    using the wide variety of available tools and filters -- particularly the
    rendering filters. You can find tutorials for this in many locations,
    including the GIMP home page <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp"/>.
    Some of the filters have options that allows you to make their results
    tileable. Also, see <xref linkend="script-fu-tile-blur"/>, this
    filter allows you to blend the edges of an image in order to make it more
    smoothly tileable.
  </para>
</sect1>
