<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-05-03 lexa: added plugin installation info for OS X
  2007-01-28 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-09-17 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-31 lexa: applied patch from hans de jonge
  2008-02-08 jpl: relecture et légères corrections
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-plugins">
  <title>Plugins</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Plugins</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <sect2>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      One of the nicest things about <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is how easily its
      functionality can be extended, by using plugins.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plugins are external programs that run under the
      control of the main <acronym>GIMP</acronym> application and interact
      with it very closely. Plugins can manipulate images in almost any way
      that users can. Their advantage is that it is much easier to add a
      capability to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> by writing a small plugin than by
      modifying the huge mass of complex code that makes up the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core. Many valuable plugins have C source code
      that only comes to 100-200 lines or so.
    </para>
    <para>
      Several dozen plugins are included in the main <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      distribution, and installed automatically along with
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Most of them can be accessed through the
      <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu (in fact, everything in that menu is a
      plugin), but a number are located in other menus. In many cases you can
      use one without ever realizing that it is a plugin: for example, the
      "Normalize" function for automatic color correction is actually a
      plugin, although there is nothing about the way it works that would tell
      you this.
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to the plugins included with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> , many
      more are available on the net. A large number can be found at the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>,
      a web site whose purpose is to provide a central repository for
      plugins. Creators of plugins can upload them there; users in search of
      plugins for a specific purpose can search the site in a variety of ways.
    </para>
    <para>
      Anybody in the world can write a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plugin and make
      it available over the web, either via the Registry or a personal web
      site, and many very valuable plugins can be obtained in this way ­ some
      are described elsewhere in the User's Manual. With this freedom from
      constraint comes a certain degree of risk, though: the fact that anybody
      can do it means that there is no effective quality control. The plugins
      distributed with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> have all been tested and tuned
      by the developers, but many that you can download were just hacked
      together in a few hours and then tossed to the winds. Some plugin
      creators just don't care about robustness, and even for those who do,
      their ability to test on a variety of systems in a variety of situations
      is often quite limited. Basically, when you download a plugin, you are
      getting something for free, and sometimes you get exactly what you pay
      for. This is not said in an attempt to discourage you, just to make sure
      you understand reality.
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>
        Plugins, being full-fledged executable programs, can do any of the
        things that any other program can do, including install back-doors on
        your system or otherwise compromise its security. Don't install a
        plugin unless it comes from a trusted source.
      </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
      These caveats apply as much to the Plugin Registry as to any other
      source of plugins. The Registry is available to any plugin creator who
      wants to use it:  there is no systematic oversight. Obviously if the
      maintainers became aware that something evil was there, they would
      remove it. (That hasn't happened yet.)  There is, however, for
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and its plugins the same warranty as for any
      other free software: namely, none.
    </para>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Plugins have been a feature of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> for many
        versions. However, plugins written for one version of
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can hardly ever be used successfully with
        other versions. They need to be ported: sometimes this is easy,
        sometimes not. Many plugins are already available in several
        versions. Bottom line: before trying to install a plugin, make sure
        that it is written for your version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Using Plugins</title>
    <para>
      For the most part you can use a plugin like any other
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tool, without needing to be aware that it is a
      plugin. But there are a few things about plugins that are useful to
      understand.
    </para>
    <para>
      One is that plugins are generally not as robust as the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core. When <acronym>GIMP</acronym> crashes, it
      is considered a very serious thing: it can cost the user a lot of
      trouble and headache. When a plugin crashes, the consequences are
      usually not so serious.  In most cases you can just continuing working
      without worrying about it.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Because plugins are separate programs, they communicate with the
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core in a special way: The
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developers call it <quote>talking over a
          wire</quote>. When a plugin crashes, the communication breaks down,
        and you will see an error message about a <quote>wire read
          error</quote>.
      </para>
    </note>
    <tip>
      <para>
        When a plugin crashes, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gives you a very
        ominous-looking message telling you that the plugin may have left
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in a corrupted state, and you should consider
        saving your images and exiting. Strictly speaking, this is quite
        correct, because plugins have the power to alter almost anything in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but for practical purposes, experience has
        shown that corruption is actually quite rare, and many users just
        continue working and don't worry about it. Our advice is that you
        simply think about how much trouble it would cause you if something
        went wrong, and weigh it against the odds.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
      Because of the way plugins communicate with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      they do not have any mechanism for being informed about changes you make
      to an image after the plugin has been started. If you start a plugin,
      and then alter the image using some other tool, the plugin will often
      crash, and when it doesn't will usually give a bogus result. You should
      avoid running more than one plugin at a time on an image, and avoid
      doing anything to the image until the plugin has finished working on it.
      If you ignore this advice, not only will you probably screw up the
      image, you will probably screw up the undo system as well, so that you
      won't even be able to recover from your foolishness.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-plugins-install">
    <title>Installing New Plugins</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Plugins</primary>
      <secondary>Install</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The plugins that are distributed with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> don't
      require any special installation. Plugins that you download yourself do.
      There are several scenarios, depending on what OS you are using and how
      the plugin is structured. In Linux it is usually pretty easy to install
      a new plugin; in Windows, it is either easy or very hard. In any case,
      the two are best considered separately.
    </para>
    <sect3>
      <title>Linux / Unix-sytem like systems</title>
      <para>
        Most plugins fall into two categories: small ones whose source
        code is distributed as a single .c file, and larger ones whose
        source code is distributed as a directory containing multiple
        files including a <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
        For a simple one-file plugin, call it <filename>borker.c</filename>,
        installing it is just a matter of running the command
        <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>.   This command
        compiles the plugin and installs it in your personal plugin directory,
        <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> unless you have changed it.
        This will cause it to be loaded automatically the next time you start
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You don't need to be root to do these things;
        in fact, you shouldn't be. If the plugin fails to compile, well, be
        creative.
      </para>
      <para><!-- changed 11-10-2004 -->
        Once you have installed the plugin, how do you activate it? The menu
        path is determined by the plugin itself, so to answer this you need to
        either look at the documentation for the plugin (if there is any), or
        launch the Plugin Description dialog (from Xtns/Plugins Details)
        search the plug-in by its name and look of the
        <guilabel>Tree view</guilabel>
        tab. If you still don't find, finally explore the menus or look at the
        source code in the Register section -- whichever is easiest.
      </para>
      <para>
        For more complex plugins, organized as a directory with multiple
        files, there ought to be a file inside called either
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> or <filename>README</filename>, with
        instructions. If not, the best advice is to toss the plugin in the
        trash and spend your time on something else:  any code written with so
        little concern for the user is likely to be frustrating in myriad
        ways.
      </para>
      <para>
        Some plugins (specifically those based on the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        Plugin Template) are designed to be installed in the main system
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory, rather than your home directory.
        For these, you will need to be root to perform the final stage of
        installation (when issuing the <command>make install</command>
        command).
      </para>
      <para>
        If you install in your personal plugin directory a plugin that has the
        same name as one in the system plugin directory, only one can be
        loaded, and it will be the one in your home directory. You will
        receive messages telling you this each time you start
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. This is probably a situation best avoided.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Windows</title>
      <para>
        Windows is a much more problematic environment for building software
        than Linux. Every decent Linux distribution comes fully supplied with
        tools for compiling software, and they are all very similar in the way
        they work, but Windows does not come with such tools. It is possible
        to set up a good software-building environment in Windows, but it
        requires either a substantial amount of money or a substantial amount
        of effort and knowledge.
      </para>
      <para>
        What this means in relation to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plugins is the
        following: either you have an environment in which you can build
        software, or you don't. If you don't, then your best hope is to find a
        precompiled version of the plugin somewhere (or persuade somebody to
        compile it for you), in which case you simply need to put it into your
        personal plugin directory. If you do have an environment in which you
        can build software (which for present purposes means an environment in
        which you can build <acronym>GIMP</acronym>), then you no doubt
        already know quite a bit about these things, and just need to follow
        the Linux instructions.
      </para>
      <!--
      <para>
        If you would like to set up a build environment, and are ready for the
        heroism involved, you can find a reasonably recent description of how
        to go about it in the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Wiki, at
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Since it is a Wiki, anybody is free to edit it, so please keep it up
        to date by adding advice based on your own experiences.
      </para>
      -->
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Apple Mac OS X</title>
      <para>
        How you install plugins on OS X mostly depends on how you installed
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> itself. If you were one of the brave and
        installed <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        through one of the package managers like fink
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-darwinports"/> or darwinports,
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-fink"/> the
        plugin installation works exactly the way it is described for the
        Linux platform already. The only difference is, that a couple of
        plugins might be even available in the repository of you package
        manager, so give it a try.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you on the other hand are one of the Users that preferred to grab a
        prebuild <acronym>GIMP</acronym> package like GIMP.app, you most
        probably want to stick
        to that prebuild stuff. So you can try to get a prebuild version of
        the plugin of you dreams from the author of the plugin, but I'd not
        want to bet on this. Building your own binaries unfortunately involves
        installing <acronym>GIMP</acronym> through one of the package managers
        mentioned above.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="plugins-write">
    <title>Writing Plugins</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Plugins</primary>
      <secondary>Write</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      If you want to learn how to write a plugin, you can find plenty of help
      at the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Developers web site
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a complex
      program, but the development team has made strenuous efforts to flatten
      the learning curve for plugin writing:  there are good instructions and
      examples, and the main library that plugins use to interface with
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (called <quote>libgimp</quote>) has a
      well-documented <acronym>API</acronym>.  Good programmers, learning by
      modifying existing plugins, are often able to accomplish interesting
      things after just a couple of days of work.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
