<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-05-03 lexa: added plugin installation info for OS X
  2007-01-28 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-09-17 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-31 lexa: applied patch from hans de jonge
  2008-02-08 jpl: relecture et légères corrections
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-plugins" lang="cs;de;es;en;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="de;es;fr;ko;nl;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2007-05-03</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">lexA</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-28</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="fr">2007-07-05</date>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="ko">2007-07-14</date>
        <authorinitials lang="ko">Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="nl">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="nl">2006-07-31</date>
        <authorinitials lang="nl">??</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="no">2006-09-17</date>
        <authorinitials lang="no">KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Zásuvné moduly</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Erweiterungen (Plugins)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Complementos (plugins)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Plugins</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Greffons</phrase>
    <phrase lang="sv">Använda GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Plugin</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">플러그인</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Uitbreidingen (Plugins)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Programtillegg</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Плагины</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">插件</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Plugins</primary><secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Zásuvné moduly</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Erweiterung</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Complementos</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Greffons</primary><secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Plugin</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>플러그인</primary><secondary>소개</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>Uitbreidingen</primary><secondary>Plugins</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Programtillegg</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Плагины</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>插件</primary></indexterm>

  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Introduction</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Úvod</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Einführung</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Introducción</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Introduction</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Introduzione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">소개</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Introduktie</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innleiing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Введение</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">简介</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      One of the nicest things about <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is how easily its
      functionality can be extended, by using plugins.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plugins are external programs that run under the
      control of the main <acronym>GIMP</acronym> application and interact
      with it very closely. Plugins can manipulate images in almost any way
      that users can. Their advantage is that it is much easier to add a
      capability to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> by writing a small plugin than by
      modifying the huge mass of complex code that makes up the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core. Many valuable plugins have C source code
      that only comes to 100-200 lines or so.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Jednou z nejlepších vlastností Gimpu je jeho snadná rozšiřitelnost o
      nové funkce pomocí zásuvných modulů (pluginů). Zásuvné moduly jsou
      externí programy spouštěné pod kontrolou Gimpu a úzce s ním
      spolupracující. Zásuvné moduly mohou s obrázky manipulovat v podstatě
      libovolným způsobem. Je mnohem snazší napsat malý zásuvný modul, než
      novou funkci složitě implementovat do jádra Gimpu. Mnoho cenných modulů
      má jen několik málo set řádků C kódu.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Eine der besten Eigenschaften vom <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      ist, wie einfach man die Funktionalität erweitern kann, nämlich mit
      <quote>Plugins</quote> (Erweiterungen).
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Erweiterungen sind externe Programme, die unter
      der Kontrolle des <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Hauptprogrammes laufen und
      sehr eng mit diesem zusammenarbeiten.
      Plugins können Bilder praktisch genauso verändern, wie Benutzer es
      können. Ihr Vorteil liegt darin, dass es sehr viel einfacher ist,
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> um eine Fähigkeit zu erweitern, indem man ein
      kleines Plugin schreibt, als den extrem umfangreichen und komplexen
      Code des <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Kernes zu verändern. Viele wichtige
      Erweiterungen bestehen lediglich aus 100 oder 200 Zeilen C-Code.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Una de las principales bondades del GIMP es la facilidad con que se
      puede extender su funcionalidad, por medio de complementos (también
      llamados plugins). Los complementos del GIMP son programas externos que
      corren bajo el control de la aplicación, e interactúan con ella. Los
      complementos pueden modificar las imágenes casi de la misma manera con
      que pueden hacerlo los usuarios. Si se necesita una nueva capacidad en
      el GIMP, puede ser mucho más fácil agregarla escribiendo un pequeño
      complemento, que modificando la gran masa de código complejo que hace a
      la propia aplicación. Muchos de los complementos más valorables están
      hechos sólo de unas cien o doscientas líneas de código fuente en C.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'un des points les plus agréables du <acronym>GIMP</acronym> est qu'on
      peut aisément lui ajouter des fonctionnalités en utilisant des greffons.
      Les greffons de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sont des programmes extérieurs
      qui tournent sous le contrôle de l'application principale du
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en interaction très proche avec lui. Les
      greffons peuvent manipuler une image presque de la même manière qu'un
      utilisateur. Leur avantage est qu'il est beaucoup plus simple d'ajouter
      une possibilité à <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en écrivant un petit greffon
      plutôt qu'en modifiant l'énorme quantité de lignes de codes qui
      constituent le noyau de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. De nombreux greffons
      sont écrits en langage C et ne font que 100-200 lignes.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Uno degli aspetti più interessanti di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è quanto
      sia semplice estenderne le funzionalità usando i plugin. I plugin di
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sono programmi esterni che vengono eseguiti
      sotto il controllo dell'applicazione principale con la quale
      interagiscono in maniera molto stretta. I plugin possono elaborare le
      immagini quasi quanto può farlo l'utente in maniera interattiva. Il
      vantaggio di questi ultimi è che è molto più semplice aggiungere
      funzionalità a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> scrivendo un piccolo plugin
      piuttosto che modificando direttamente quell'enorme massa di codice che
      è il nucleo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Molti plugin molto validi
      constano di appena 100-200 circa linee di codice C.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym>의 멋진 점 중 하나는 플러그인을 통해 쉽게
      기능확장을 할 수 있다라는 것입니다. <acronym>김프</acronym>
      플러그인은 <acronym>김프</acronym> 자체에 의해 제어되며
      <acronym>김프</acronym>와 밀접하게 상호 동작하는 외부 프로그램입니다.
      플러그인을 이용하면 사용할 수 있는 거의 모든 방법으로 이미지를 편집할
      수 있습니다. 플러그인의 장점은 거대하고 복잡하기 짝이없는
      <acronym>김프</acronym> 코어 코드를 고치지 않고, 작은 플러그인을
      작성하는 것만으로 기능확장을 할 수 있다라는 점입니다. 많은 주요
      플러그인들은 100-200 라인 정도의 C 언어로 작성되었습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Het gemak waarmee nieuwe functies aan <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      toe te voegen zijn is een van de beste aspecten van ervan. Dit word
      mogelijk gemaakt door het <quote>Plugin</quote> -mechanime.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-<quote>plugins</quote>
      zijn externe programma's; oftewijl <quote>uitbreidingen</quote>,
      die door het hoofdprogramma aangestuurd worden en ermee samenwerken.
      Deze uitbreidingen kunnen op dezelfde manier als de gebruiker zelf,
      afbeeldingen bewerken, maar dan min of meer geautomatiseerd. Een sterk
      punt van het gebruik van dit soort uitbreidingen is dat ze makkelijker
      aan het programma toe te voegen; een klein, los <quote>plugin</quote>
      -programma is makkelijker te schrijven dan de functionaliteit ervan in
      de hoofdcode van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      op te nemen waarna er in een hele hoop programmacode gecontroleerd moet
      worden op noodzakelijke aanpassingen. Veel waardevolle uitbreidingen
      maken gebruik van dit mechanisme en hebben door de weldoordachtheid
      ervan vaak maar een stuk of 100 tot 200 regels C-code nodig.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Ein av fordelane med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er at det er lett å
      utvida funksjonane ved hjelp av såkalla programtillegg (engelsk:
      <quote>Plugins</quote>). Programtillegga samarbeider svært nær med
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, men det er <acronym>GIMP</acronym> som har
      kontrollen med dei. Ofte gjer ikkje programtillegga anna enn det
      du også kan gjere direkte, men på ein for deg enklare måte. Den store
      fordelen med desse programma, er at det er lett å lage tilleggsfunksjonar
      utan å måtte gjere endringar i det nokså kompliserte programmet
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er. Mange verdfulle programtillegg har ei
      kjeldekode på bare 100 - 200 linjer. Dei fleste er skrivne i språket
      <quote>C</quote> eller ein variant av dette.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Одна из наилучших вещей в <acronym>GIMP</acronym> это возможность легко
      расширить его функциональность с помощью использования плагинов. Плагины
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> являются внешними программами, которые
      запускаются под контролем основной программы и очень тесно с ней
      взаимодействуют. Плагины могут обрабатывать изображения почти любыми
      методами, также, как могут пользователи. Их преимущество заключается в
      том, что намного легче добавить к <acronym>GIMP</acronym> возможность с
      помощью написания небольшого плагина, чем измение большой массы сложного
      кода, который составляет ядро <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Множество ценных
      плагинов, написанных на C, содержат всего около 100-200 строк исходного
      кода.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 中一件最棒的事就是扩展其功能非常容易，通过插件。
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 插件是一些被主 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      程序控制并与它紧密交互的外部程序。插件能以用户所能做到的几乎是任何方式来处理图像。它们的优势在于通过编写小插件增加功能比修改构成
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      核心冗长而复杂的代码更为容易。许多非常有用的插件也就仅仅只有 100-200 行的 C 代码。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Several dozen plugins are included in the main <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      distribution, and installed automatically along with
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Most of them can be accessed through the
      <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu (in fact, everything in that menu is a
      plugin), but a number are located in other menus. In many cases you can
      use one without ever realizing that it is a plugin: for example, the
      "Normalize" function for automatic color correction is actually a
      plugin, although there is nothing about the way it works that would tell
      you this.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Spolu s Gimpem se standardně dodává několik desítek zásuvných modulů.
      Většina z nich je dostupná přes nabídku <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
      (veškerý obsah této nabídky je tvořen zásuvnými moduly), ale mnohé další
      jsou dostupné i v jiných nabídkách. V mnoha případech ani uživatel
      netuší, že používá zásuvný modul. Například funkce „Normalizovat“
      pro automatickou korekci barev je ve skutečnosti zásuvným modul, ačkoli
      z uživatelského hlediska tomu nic nenapovídá.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Einige Dutzend Erweiterungen werden zusammen mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      ausgeliefert und automatisch installiert. Auf die meisten Plugins können
      Sie über das <guimenu>Filtermenü</guimenu> zugreifen (tatsächlich sind
      nahezu alle Kommandos in diesem Menü Plugins), aber einige
      sind auch in anderen Menüs zu finden. In vielen Fällen können Sie eines
      benutzen, ohne überhaupt zu merken, dass es ein Plugin ist.
      Beispielsweise ist die <quote>Normalisierungsfunktion</quote>
      für die automatische Farbkorrektur tatsächlich eine Erweiterung, auch
      wenn das auf den ersten Blick nicht zu erkennen ist.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      La distribución principal del GIMP incluye varias decenas de
      complementos, que se instalan automáticamente junto con la aplicación.
      La mayoría pueden ser accedidos por el menú
      <guimenu>Filtros</guimenu>. De hecho, cada entrada a ese menú se
      corresponde con un complemento.  Otro tanto está ubicado en otros menús.
      En muchos casos puede hacer uso de alguno sin siquiera enterarse.  Por
      ejemplo, la función <quote>Normalizar</quote> para la corrección
      automática del color es en realidad un complemento, aunque no haya nada
      en su funcionamiento que lo haga parecer tal.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Plusieurs douzaines de greffons sont inclus dans la distribution
      principale de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> et installés en même temps que
      lui. La plupart sont accessibles via le menu <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
      (en fait, ce menu n'est constitué que de greffons), mais bon nombre se
      répartissent dans les autres menus. La plupart du temps vous les
      utiliserez sans même le savoir : par exemple, la fonction "Normaliser"
      qui corrige les couleurs automatiquement est un greffon, bien que rien
      dans la façon dont elle travaille ne le laisse supposer.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Diverse dozzine di plugin sono inclusi nella distribuzione principale di
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> e quindi vengono installati automaticamente con
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Molti sono accessibili attraverso il menu
      <guimenu>Filtri</guimenu> (in effetti, qualsiasi cosa in quel menu è un
      plugin), mentre gli altri sono distribuiti nei restanti menu. Spesso
      vengono usati senza neanche la consapevolezza di usare un plugin: per
      esempio la funzione "Normalizza" per la correzzione automatica del
      colore è un plugin malgrado non ci sia niente nel suo funzionamento che
      ne indichi la natura.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym> 배포판에는 많은 플러그인들이 포함되어 있어,
      <acronym>김프</acronym> 설치와 함께 설치됩니다. 이것들의 대부분은
      <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> 메뉴를 통해 사용할 수 있지만(사실 이곳에
      있는 것들은 모두 플러그인들이다), 몇몇은 다른 메뉴에 위치합니다.
      플러그인 중에는 자동 색상 교정을 위한 "Normalize" 처럼 사용자가
      그것이 플러그인이라는 것을 모른채 사용하는 플러그인들도 많습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Bij de standaard installatie van <acronym>GIMP</acronym> worden enkele
      tientallen uitbreidingen meegeleverd en met de rest van het programa
      meegeïnstalleerd. De meesten zijn via het
      <guimenu>Filte<accel>r</accel>s</guimenu>-menu toegankelijk, (Feitelijk
      zijn alle items in dat menu uitbreidingen) maar er zijn er ook een paar
      die op een andere plaats te gebruiken zijn. In veel gevallen maakt u
      gebruik van een uitbreiding zonder dat u dat in de gaten heeft; de
      <quote>Normalisatie</quote> <!-- FIXME: NL is dat het correcte item?? -->
      functie om kleuren vanzelf te corrigeren is daar een voorbeeld van.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Fleire titals programtillegg er inkluderte i grunnutgåva av
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, og blir automatisk installerte saman med
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Dei fleste av desse er tilgjengelege gjennom
      menyen <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>. (Alt i denne menyen er faktisk
      programtillegg). Ein del av programtillegga er likevel plasserte i
      andre menyar. Som oftast merkar du ikkje at funksjonen du nyttar deg av
      er eit tillegg. T.d. er funksjonen <quote>Normaliser</quote> for
      automatisk fargekorreksjon eigentleg eit programtillegg, men det er
      ingenting i måten det arbeider på som røper dette.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Несколько дюжин плагинов включены в основную поставку
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> и устанавливаются автоматически вместе с ним.
      Большинство из них может быть доступно через меню
      <guimenu>Фильтры</guimenu> (фактически всё, что доступно в этом меню,
      является плагинами), но некоторое количество расположено в других меню.
      В большинстве случаев вы можете его использовать какого-либо без
      представления о том, что это плагин: к примеру, функция автоматической
      цветокоррекции "Нормализовать" в действительности является плагином.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      很多插件已经包含在 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 版本，并随着
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 自动安装了。通过 <guimenu>滤镜</guimenu>
      菜单(实际上那个菜单中都是插件)能够使用大部分插件，另一部分则在其它菜单中。许多情况下，您会用到插件，并且您还没有意识到它是：比如，“标准化”能够自动更正色彩的功能实际上就是一个插件，虽然它运行的方式并没有告诉您。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      In addition to the plugins included with GIMP , many more are available
      on the net. A large number can be found at the GIMP Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />,
      a web site whose purpose is to provide a central repository for
      plugins. Creators of plugins can upload them there; users in search of
      plugins for a specific purpose can search the site in a variety of ways.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Kromě zásuvných modulů dodávaných přímo s Gimpem existuje mnoho dalších
      modulů na Internetu. Mnoho jich lze nalézt na stránkách
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />
      (anglicky), které slouží jako centrální skladiště zásuvných modulů pro
      GIMP. Uživatelé tam mohou zásuvné moduly různými způsoby vyhledávat,
      autoři zásuvných modulů naopak své výtvory na server nahrávat.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Zusätzlich zu den mit GIMP ausgelieferten Erweiterungen gibt es noch
      viele weitere im Internet. Insbesondere können Sie viele Plugins im
      GIMP-Plugin-Register
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />
      finden, einer Webseite, deren Ziel eine zentrale Datenbank für
      Erweiterungen ist. Autoren können ihre Erweiterungen dort bereitstellen
      und Benutzer, auf der Suche nach einem speziellen Plugin, können dort
      auf vielfältige Weise suchen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Además de los complementos que vienen incluídos con el GIMP, hay muchos
      otros disponibles en la red. Una gran cantidad se hallan en el GIMP
      Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />,
      un sitio web cuyo propósito es proporcionar un repositorio central de
      complementos. Los creadores de complementos los pueden subir allí, y los
      usuarios interesados los pueden descargar, realizando búsquedas de
      diversas formas.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Beaucoup d'autres greffons que ceux fournis avec le GIMP sont
      disponibles sur la Toile. Un bon nombre se trouvent dans le Registre des
      greffons de GIMP
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />,
      un site web dont le but est de centraliser la distribution des
      greffons. Les créateurs de greffons peuvent les y déposer ; les
      utilisateurs à la recherche d'un greffon spécifique peuvent le
      rechercher sur ce site de plusieurs manières.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      In aggiunta ai plugin inclusi in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      molti altri sono disponibili nella Rete. Molti sono pubblicati sul
      Registro dei Plugin di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />,
      un sito il cui unico scopo è di fornire un archivio centrale per i
      plugin. Gli autori di plugin li depositano lì in maniera tale che gli
      utenti alla ricerca di un plugin per uno scopo particolare possano
      cercarlo con diversi metodi su questo sito.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      김프 배포판에 포함된 플러그인 외에 다른 많은 플러그인들을 넷상에서
      구할 수 있습니다. 특히 플러그인들을 모아 배포하는
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />
      에서 많은 플러그인들을 얻을 수 있습니다. 플러그인 제작자들은 그
      사이트에 업로드를 하고, 사용자들은 해당 사이트에서 원하는 플러그인을
      찾게 됩니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Naast de uitbreidingen die standaard met <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      meegeleverd worden, kunt u er meer op het Web vinden. Er staan een hoop
      verzameld op de stek: <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />;
      een webstek die als centraal verzamelpunt voor uitbreidingen of
      <quote>plugins</quote>
      ingericht is. De makers van uitbreidingen kunnen ze daar naartoe
      uploaden en gebruikers die een bepaalde extra functionaliteit nodig
      hebben kunnen daar op verschillende manieren naar de gewenste
      uitbreiding zoeken.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I tillegg til dei innebygde programtillegga, er det store mengder
      tilgjengelege på Internett. Prøv å ta ein tur innom
      GIMP Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />, ein
      nettstad som ønskjer å vere eit sentrallager programtillegg.
      Nettstaden er open for å laste opp nylaga programtillegg, og har eit
      greitt søkesystem for deg som ønskjer å finne bestemte programtillegg.
      (Har du tenkt å søke internasjonalt etter programtillegg, bruk
      <quote>plugin</quote> som søkeord avgrensa med <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er ikkje åleine om å bruke plugins).
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В дополнение к включенным в <acronym>GIMP</acronym> плагинам, намного
      больше доступно в сети. Большое количество можно найти на вебсайте
      Реестр плагинов для <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />, назначение
      которого обеспечить
      центральный репозиторий для плагинов. Создатели плагинов могут загружать
      их сюда; пользователи в поиске плагинов определённого назначения могут
      производить поиск по сайту различными методами.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 附带的插件外，网上还有更多。您能在
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 插件注册处
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />
      找到大量插件，该网站的目的就是为插件提供一个中央储藏的地方。插件制作者可以上传到这里;寻找完成某些目的插件的用户能用多种方式在这个网站搜索。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Anybody in the world can write a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plugin and make
      it available over the web, either via the Registry or a personal web
      site, and many very valuable plugins can be obtained in this way ­ some
      are described elsewhere in the User's Manual. With this freedom from
      constraint comes a certain degree of risk, though: the fact that anybody
      can do it means that there is no effective quality control. The plugins
      distributed with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> have all been tested and tuned
      by the developers, but many that you can download were just hacked
      together in a few hours and then tossed to the winds. Some plugin
      creators just don't care about robustness, and even for those who do,
      their ability to test on a variety of systems in a variety of situations
      is often quite limited. Basically, when you download a plugin, you are
      getting something for free, and sometimes you get exactly what you pay
      for. This is not said in an attempt to discourage you, just to make sure
      you understand reality.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Kdokoliv na světě může napsat zásuvný modul pro <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      a zpřístupnit ho po síti, ať už přes stránku Registrů nebo na své osobní
      stránce. Tímto způsobem lze získat mnoho nesmírně zajímavých a cenných
      zásuvných modulů. S takovou svobodou ovšem přichází i jistá rizika,
      skutečnost, že modul může vytvořit kdokoliv, znamená, že neexistuje
      možnost hlídat jejich kvalitu. Zásuvné moduly distribuované přímo s
      Gimpem jsou pečlivě testovány a laděny vývojáři Gimpu, ale mnoho z těch,
      které naleznete na síti, bylo zbastleno během několika hodin a pak
      ponecháno na pospas osudu. Někteří tvůrci zásuvných modulů si se
      stabilitou nedělají těžkou hlavu a i ti, kteří jsou pečliví, nemají
      často možnost provádět rozsáhlé testy na řadě různých systémů a v
      různých situacích. Když si z webu stáhnete zásuvný modul, dostáváte něco
      zdarma, a mnohdy dostanete přesně to, za co jste zaplatili. Tím vás
      nechceme odradit, jen si chceme být jistí, že chápete tvrdou realitu
      světa Internetu.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Jeder auf der ganzen Welt kann ein <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Plugin
      programmieren und es über das Internet zur Verfügung stellen,
      entweder über die Datenbank oder auf einer persönlichen Webseite, und
      viele wichtige Erweiterungen kann man sich so beschaffen. Einige davon
      werden an anderen Stellen im Benutzerhandbuch beschrieben. Mit dieser
      uneingeschränkten Freiheit geht allerdings auch ein gewisses Risiko
      einher: da jeder ein Plugin schreiben kann, gibt es keine effektive
      Qualitätskontrolle. Die zusammen mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      ausgelieferten Erweiterungen wurden alle von den Entwicklern getestet
      und angepasst, aber viele von denen, die Sie herunterladen können,
      wurden nur schnell zusammengeschustert und dann
      <quote>nach mir die Sintflut</quote>.
      Einige Pluginprogrammierer interessiert Robustheit überhaupt nicht,
      und selbst bei den übrigen sind die Möglichkeiten, auf verschieden
      Systemen in verschiedenen Situationen zu testen, oftmals nur beschränkt.
      Wenn Sie eine Erweiterung herunterladen, erhalten Sie letztlich etwas
      umsonst, und manchmal bekommen Sie genau den entsprechenden Gegenwert
      dafür. Das eben Gesagte soll Sie jetzt keineswegs entmutigen, sondern
      sicherstellen, dass Sie der Realität ins Auge sehen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Cualquier persona del mundo puede escribir un complemento para el GIMP y
      hacerlo disponible en la web, tanto en el registro anteriormente dicho,
      como en un sitio personal, y muchos complementos valiosos se obtienen de
      esta forma.  Algunos se describen en este manual.  Junto con esta
      libertad viene acaparado cierto riesgo, ya que el hecho de que
      cualquiera pueda hacerlo significa que no hay ningún control de calidad.
      Los complementos que se distribuyen con el GIMP han sido probados y
      refinados por los desarrolladores, pero muchos de los que se encuentran
      en la web han sido hackeados en unos minutos, y luego dejados a la
      deriva.  Algunos creadores de complementos simplemente no se preocupan
      por su robustez, e incluso los que sí lo hacen no tienen la capacidad de
      probarlos en diversos sistemas y en diversas situaciones.  Básicamente,
      cuando Ud. descarga un complemento, lo está obteniendo libremente, pero
      aveces puede tener que pagar por ello.  Esto no es para decepcionarlo,
      sino para que conozca la realidad.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      N'importe qui dans le monde peut écrire un greffon pour
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> et le mettre à disposition sur le web, dans le
      Registre des Greffons de GIMP
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />
      ou sur un site personnel, et de nombreux greffons intéressants
      peuvent être obtenus ainsi - certains sont décrits plus loin dans le
      manuel utilisateur. Avec une telle liberté il y a une part de risque :
      le fait que n'importe qui puisse le faire signifie qu'il n'y a pas de
      contrôle qualité. Les greffons distribués avec <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      ont tous été testés et ajustés par les développeurs, mais parmi ceux que
      vous pourrez télécharger, certains ont été écrits en quelques heures et
      distribués sans autre forme de procès. Certain créateurs de greffons ne
      s'inquiètent pas de la robustesse, et même pour ceux qui le font, leur
      possibilité de les tester sur de nombreux systèmes, dans de nombreuses
      conditions, est souvent limitée. En résumé, quand vous téléchargez un
      greffon, cela ne vous coûte rien et parfois la qualité s'en ressent.
      Nous ne disons pas cela pour vous décourager mais juste pour que vous
      compreniez ce qu'il en est.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Tutti al mondo hanno la possibilità di scrivere un plugin di
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> e pubblicarlo sul web sia per mezzo del Registro
      o tramite un sito personale e spesso molti validi plugin sono proprio
      disponibili in questo modo - alcuni di essi sono pure descritti nel
      manuale utente di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Tutta questa libertà
      naturalmente ha anche degli aspetti negativi: il fatto che chiunque
      possa fare ciò implica che esiste una certa dose di rischio dovuta al
      fatto che non c'è un efficace controllo di qualità. Invece i plugin
      distribuiti con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sono tutti testati e curati
      dagli sviluppatori diversamente dai molti che si possono scaricare che
      spesso sono assemblati in maniera approssimativa in poche ore e
      distribuiti al mondo intero. Ad alcuni autori di plugin semplicemente
      non interessa la robustezza e anche se ad alcuni interessa, la
      rispettiva capacità fare seriamente delle prove su un certo numero di
      piattaforme è spesso limitata. Praticamente quando si scarica un plugin,
      lo si ottiene gratuitamente e spesso questo è proprio il valore che
      merita. Non diciamo tutto ciò con l'intento di scoraggiare ma
      semplicemente per onor del vero.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      전세계의 누구라도 <acronym>김프</acronym> 플러그인을 만들어 Plugin
      Registry 나 개인 웹사이트를 통해 배포할 수 있습니다. 사용자 설명서에
      설명된 플러그인과 같은 중요 플러그인들도 그러한 방법으로 알려진
      것입니다. 그런데 이러한 무제약적인 개발은 적정 수준의 품질 유지가
      힘들다라는 단점이 있습니다. <acronym>김프</acronym>와 함께 배포되는
      플러그인들은 모두 개발자들에 의해 테스트되고 수정된 것들이지만,
      웹사이트에 올려진 많은 플러그인들은 대부분 테스트없이 배포된
      것들입니다. 몇몇 플러그인 제작자들은 버그에 대해 별로 신경쓰지 않기도
      하고, 그렇지 않더라하더라도 다양한 상황과 시스템에서 테스트하는
      것에는 분명 한계가 있습니다. 따라서 기본적으로 플러그인을 다운로드
      받을 경우, 비록 무료로 다운받지만 때로는 댓가를 지불해야 할 경우도
      있습니다. 이것은 겁주는 것이 아니라 명확한 이해를 돕기 위한 것입니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Iedereen kan en mag <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uitbreidingen schrijven en
      ze via het Web beschikbaar stellen; via de voorgenoemde verzamelplaats
      of op een persoonlijke pagina. Veel handige uitbreidingen zijn op deze
      manier beschikbaar en sommige ervan worden elders in deze handleiding
      behandeld. Dit betekend een sterke vrijwaring van beperkingen, maar deze
      vrijheid komt met de prijs dat er geen sluitende kwaliteitscontrôle is.
      De uitbreidingen die met de standaard meegeleverd worden zijn allemaal
      getest en bijgesteld door de ontwikkelaars van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      maar veel van degenen u kunt downloaden zijn in een paar uur in elkaar
      geflanst en vervolgens vrijgelaten. Sommige makers malen helemaal niet
      om de betrouwbaarheid en anderen die dat wel doen hebben slechts
      beperkte mogelijkheden om de werking op verschillende systemen te
      testen. Door een uitbreiding van het web op te halen en uit te proberen
      krijgt u iets voor niets en soms krijgt u dan ook precies waarvoor u
      betaald heeft. We zeggen dit niet om u te ontmoedigen, maar om u erop te
      wijzen hoe de zaken nu eenmaal in elkaar steken.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Alle med litt kjennskap til programmering, kan skrive programtillegg og
      eventuelt gjere dei tilgjengelege for andre anten gjennom
      GIMP Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />, private
      heimesider eller andre nettstader. Noen av desse programma er omtalte
      andre stader i denne handboka. Sjølvsagt er det også ein risiko med
      dette frie livet. Sidan kven som helst kan lage og spreie programma, er
      det heller ingen former for kvalitetskontroll av programma. Mange av dei
      ser ut som dei er snikra saman i seine kveldstimar til eit avgrensa
      føremål og deretter spreidde for alle vindar. Ikkje alle utviklarane har
      kunnskap eller utstyr nok til å kunne prøva ut programma med alle dei
      systema og systemvariasjonane programma kan kome ut for. Du står
      sjølvsagt fritt i å prøva ut programma, men har altså ingen garanti for
      resultatet. Dette er ikkje sagt for å skræme deg, men for å vise kva som
      er den verkelege verda. Dei programtillegga som blir leverte saman med
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er sjølvsagt sikra og kontrollerte så langt det
      er praktisk mogleg. Du kan difor bruke desse nokså trygt.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Кто угодно в мире может написать плагин и сделать его доступным через
      сеть, через реестр плагинов или через персональный вебсайт, и множество
      очень ценных плагинов может быть получено таким способом - некоторые
      описаны где-нибудь в руководстве пользователя. Вместе с этой свободой
      появляется определённая степень риска: тот факт, что любой может сделать
      плагин означает, что не существует эффективного контроля качества. Все
      поставляемые вместе с <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      плагины были протестированы и настроены разработчиками, но многие
      скачанные вами были написаны за пару часов и брошены на ветер. Некоторые
      создатели плагинов просто не заботятся о стабильности, и даже те, кто в
      этом заинтересован, их возможности тестирования на множестве систем в
      разных ситуациях часто весьма ограничены. В основном, когда вы
      загружаете плагин, вы получаете кое-что бесплатно, и иногда вы получаете
      именно то, за что вы платили. Сказано это не для того, чтобы
      разочаровать вас, просто чтобы была уверенность, что вы понимаете
      действительность.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      任何人都能写 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      插件，然后通过注册处或个人网站在网络上发布，一些非常有价值的插件可以就通过这样获得---在用户手册中有一些描述。这种相对的自由有时会产生一定的风险。事实上，任何人都可以这样做意味这缺少有效的质量控制。<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 发行版本所附带的插件都是经过开发人员测试和调整过，但是许多您能下载的是几小时前才被整理出来，还不稳定。一些插件制作人员并不在乎代码的健壮性。即使都那些注意了的人，他们在各种系统中不同情况下的测试能力还非常有限。一般来说，当您下载一个插件时，您得到了些实惠，但有时您也要付出代价。这并不是说要打击您，只是让您认识到这是事实。
    </para>

    <warning>
      <para lang="en">
        Plugins, being full-fledged executable programs, can do any of the
        things that any other program can do, including install back-doors on
        your system or otherwise compromise its security. Don't install a
        plugin unless it comes from a trusted source.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Zásuvné moduly jsou plnohodnotné spustitelné programy a mohou dělat
        cokoliv, co ostatní programy. To zahrnuje i možnost instalace zadních
        vrátek do systému, poškození dat či jiné ohrožení bezpečnosti. Nikdy
        neinstalujte zásuvný modul ze zdroje, kterému plně nedůvěřujete.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Erweiterungen sind vollwertige ausführbare Programme und können alles
        das tun, was jedes andere Programm tun kann, einschließlich
        Hintertüren auf Ihrem System installieren oder anderweitig die
        Sicherheit kompromittieren. Installieren Sie kein Plugin, das nicht
        aus einer vertrauenswürdigen Quelle stammt!
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Los complementos, al ser completos programas ejecutables, pueden hacer
        todas las cosas que los otros programas pueden hacer, incluyendo la
        instalación de puertas traseras en su sistema, entre otras formas de
        comprometer su seguridad. Por lo tanto no instale complementos, a
        menos que provengan de una fuente confiable.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les greffons sont des programmes exécutables, ils peuvent faire tout
        ce que d'autres programmes font, y compris installer des
        <quote>Back door</quote>
        (porte dérobée) sur votre système ou compromettre sa sécurité.
        N'installez un greffon que s'il vient d'une source sûre.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        I plugin, essendo dei programmi eseguibili completi, possono fare ogni
        genere di cose che altri programmi possono fare, incluso installare
        delle back-door o compromettere in ogni modo la sua sicurezza. Non
        installare un plugin se non si è sicuri della sua provenienza da una
        fonte di fiducia.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        플러그인은 다른 프로그램에서도 사용할 수 있는 완전하게 실행가능한
        프로그램입니다. 따라서 이를 이용해 시스템에 백도어를 설치하거나
        시스템 보안을 위협할 수도 있습니다. 그러므로 신뢰할만한 사이트가
        아닌 사이트로부터 플러그인을 다운로드받아 설치하지 마십시오.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Omdat uitbreidingen volwaardige programma's zijn, kunnen ze alle
        dingen doen die andere programma's ook kunnen, inclusief het
        installeren van achterdeuren in uw systeem of op andere manieren de
        veiligheid en stabiliteit ervan in gevaar brengen. Daarom dient u zich
        ervoor de hoeden een uitbreiding vanaf een niet-vertrouwde bron te
        installeren.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Sidan programtillegga er fullverdige program, kan dei gjere alt det
        andre slike program kan gjere. Dette omfattar også funksjonar som kan
        påverka tryggleiken til maskinen din. Ikkje installer eit
        programtillegg utan at du er nokså sikker på at det kjem frå ei
        truverdig kjelde.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Плагины являются полноценными исполняемыми программами, они могут
        тоже, что и другие программы, включая установку "back-door" (тайного
        входа) в вашу систему или иным образом подвергать риску.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        插件，作为完整的可执行程序，能做其它任何程序所能做的，包括在您的系统上安装后门或其它为害安全的事。不要轻易安装插件除非它的来源是可信任的。
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para lang="en">
      These caveats apply as much to the Plugin Registry as to any other
      source of plugins. The Registry is available to any plugin creator who
      wants to use it:  there is no systematic oversight. Obviously if the
      maintainers became aware that something evil was there, they would
      remove it. (That hasn't happened yet.)  There is, however, for
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and its plugins the same warranty as for any
      other free software: namely, none.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Toto varování se vztahuje jak ke stránkám Plugin Registry, tak k
      jakémukoliv jinému zdroji zásuvných modulů. Stránky Plugin Registry jsou
      přístupné každému autorovi, který je chce použít; nikdo nad nimi bedlivě
      nedohlíží. Samozřejmě, pokud správci zjistí, že je na stránkách něco
      špatného, odstraní to. Nicméně je nutno si uvědomit, že pro
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> i jeho zásuvné moduly je stejná záruka, jako pro
      každý jiný volně distribuovatelný software: tedy žádná.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Diese Vorsichtsmaßnahmen gelten sowohl für das Pluginregister als auch
      für jede andere Quelle. Das Register steht jedem Autor von Erweiterungen
      zur Verfügung: es gibt keine systematische Aufsicht. Natürlich würden
      die Verwalter jedes Schadprogramm, dessen sie Gewahr werden, sofort
      entfernen (bisher ist das noch nicht vorgekommen). Allerdings gibt es
      für <acronym>GIMP</acronym> und seine Erweiterungen dieselben
      Gewährleistungen wie für jede andere freie Software, nämlich gar keine.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Estas cuestiones se aplican tanto a los complementos del Plugin Registry
      como a cualquier otra fuente. El Plugin Registry se encuentra disponible
      para cualquier creador que quiera usarlo, sin excepsión. Obviamente, si
      los administradores son advertidos de que se ha registrado un
      complemento malicioso, lo pueden eliminar (esto aún no ha sucedido). Los
      complementos se proporcionan con la misma garantía que el resto del
      software libre, es decir, con ninguna.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Cet avertissement vaut aussi bien pour le Registre des greffons que pour
      les autres sources. Le Registre est à disposition de n'importe quel
      créateur qui veut l'utiliser : il n'y a pas de supervision systématique.
      Bien sûr si les webmestres apprennent la présence de quelque chose de
      diabolique, ils l'enlèveront (cela n'est pas encore arrivé). Il y a
      toutefois, pour <acronym>GIMP</acronym> et ses greffons, la même
      garantie que pour tout autre logiciel libre : à savoir aucune.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Queste considerazioni sono applicabili sia al Registro dei plugin che ad
      ogni altra sorte di sorgente di plugin. Il Registro è disponibile ad
      ogni autore di plugin che lo voglia usare: non c'è un controllo
      sistematico. Ovviamente se il manutentore viene a conoscenza di qualche
      cosa di dannoso, lo rimuoverebbe (ma sembra che fino ad ora ciò sia
      successo). Naturalmente <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ed i suoi plugin hanno
      le garanzie di ogni altro software libero: cioè, nessuna.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이러한 경고는 Plugin Registry 뿐만 아니라 다른 사이트에서 얻을 수
      있는 플러그인들에 대한 것입니다. Plugin Registry 은 모든 플러그인
      제작자들이 이용할 수 있고, 특별히 체계적인 관리를 하지는 않기
      때문입니다. 물론 악의적인 것들은 관리자들이 선별해 차단합니다. 하지만
      사실상 <acronym>김프</acronym>와 김프의 플러그인들은 다른 자유
      프로그램과 마찬가지로 사용상의 문제에 대한 아무런 보증도 하지
      않습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Deze waarschuwingen zijn net zo van toepassing  op het <quote>Plugin
        Registry</quote> als andere bronnen van uitbreidingen. Het
      <quote>Registry</quote> kan door iedere maker van uitbreidingen die het
      wil gebruikt worden, er is geen geregeld toezicht. Als de beheerders van
      de stek doorkrijgen dat er iets door kwaadwillenden op staat, halen ze
      het weg (Dit is nog niet voorgekomen overigens). Voor
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en z'n uitbreidingen bestaat dezelfde garantie
      als voor alle vrije programmatuur: geen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Denne åtvaringa gjeld like mykje for <quote>GIMP Plugin Registry</quote>
      som for andre kjelder du måtte nytta deg av. <quote>GIMP Plugin
        Registry</quote> er tilgjengeleg for alle som utviklar programtillegg,
      også dei useriøse. Dersom dei som driv nettstaden kjem over snuskete
      program, vil desse sjølvsagt bli fjerna. (Til nå har ingen lagt inn
      slike program). Den same garantiregelen gjeld for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      sine programtillegg som for alle andre frie program: Ingen garanti.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Эти предупреждения относятся как к реестру плагинов так  и к другим
      источникам плагинов. Реестр плагинов доступен  для всех создателей
      плагинов кто хочет его использовать:  не существует систематического
      наблюдения. Очевидно  если майнтейнеры будут осведомлены о существовании
      здесь  чего-то плохого, они это удалят.(Чего пока не случалось.)
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> и его плагины имеют такую же гарантию, как и
      любое  другое свободное программное обеспечение: а именно, никакой.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在插件注册处也有和其它插件代码一样的危险。注册处允许任何想使用的插件制作者使用：这里并没有系统地监控。显而易见，如果当维护人员意识到那里有危险，他会将它们删除。(到目前还没发生过。)尽管如此，对 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>和其插件 就像其它自由软件一样：没有担保。
    </para>

    <caution>
      <para lang="en">
        Plugins have been a feature of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> for many
        versions. However, plugins written for one version of
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can hardly ever be used successfully with
        other versions. They need to be ported: sometimes this is easy,
        sometimes not. Many plugins are already available in several
        versions. Bottom line: before trying to install a plugin, make sure
        that it is written for your version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Zásuvné moduly jsou součástí Gimpu již po dlouhou dobu. Nicméně
        zásuvné moduly napsané pro jednu verzi Gimpu nelze úspěšně používat s
        jinou verzí. Předtím je nutno moduly upravit, což může být snadné nebo
        ne. Mnoho zásuvných modulů je dostupých v různých verzích pro různé
        verze Gimpu. Před instalací zásuvného modulu si ověřte, že je určen
        pro vámi používanou verzi.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Erweiterungen gehören seit vielen Versionen zu
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> dazu. Allerdings können Plugins, die für
        eine <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Version geschrieben wurden, nur selten
        ohne Probleme von anderen Versionen verwendet werden. Sie müssen
        portiert werden. Manchmal ist das einfach, manchmal nicht. Zum Glück
        gibt es viele Erweiterungen bereits in verschiedenen Versionen. Fazit:
        Bevor Sie versuchen, ein Plugin zu installieren, vergewissern Sie
        sich, dass es tatsächlich für Ihre <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Version
        geschrieben wurde.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        La capacidad de extender por complementos se ha introducido en el GIMP
        desde hace muchas versiones. Sin embargo, los complementos escritos
        para una versión determinada difícilmente funcionen en otras
        versiones. Necesitan ser portados, lo que aveces es fácil, y otras
        veces no. Muchos complementos se han transcrito de una versión a otra.
        Para tener en cuenta: antes de instalar un complemento, asegúrese que
        esté escrito para su versión del GIMP.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les greffons existent dans <acronym>GIMP</acronym> depuis de
        nombreuses versions. Toutefois, un greffon écrit pour une version de
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ne peut presque jamais être utilisé avec une
        des autres versions. Il faut les <quote>porter</quote> : parfois c'est
        facile, parfois non. De nombreux greffons sont disponibles pour de
        nombreuses versions. Aussi, avant d'installer un greffon assurez-vous
        qu'il est écrit pour votre version de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        I plugin sono stati una caratteristica di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> da
        molte versioni e difficilmente possono essere usati con successo per
        una versione diversa da quella per cui sono stati scritti. È
        necessario portarli alla versione desiderata e quest'operazione alle
        volte può molto difficoltosa. Molti plugin sono già disponibili in
        diverse versioni. Morale: prima di provare ad installare un plugin
        assicurarsi che sia stato scritto per la versione di
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> desiderata.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        대부분의 플러그인들은 여러 버전의 <acronym>김프</acronym>에서
        사용할 수 있습니다. 하지만 특정 버전에서만 사용가능한 것도 있는데,
        이러한 것들은 변환 작업을 통해 사용할 수 있습니다. 하지만 이 변환
        작업이 어려울 수도 있으므로, 플러그인을 설치하기 전에 현재 사용중인
        <acronym>김프</acronym>의 버전과 호환이 되는지 확인해야 합니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        De mogelijkheid om uitbreidingen in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> te
        gebruiken bestaat al enige tijd. Helaas is het echter zo dat een
        uitbreiding die voor een bepaalde versie van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        is geschreven is meestal niet bruikbaar in een andere programmaversie.
        Ze moeten hiervoor aangepast worden: soms is dit heel eenvoudig, mar
        soms ook niet. Veel uitbreidingen zijn zo al aan verschillende
        programmaversies aangepast. Conclusie: vòòrdat u een uitbreiding
        installeerd, dien u eerst te verifieëren of deze wel aan uw versie van
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gemaakt of aangepast is.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Programtillegga har følgd <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gjennom mange
        versjonar. Eit programtillegg skriven for ein versjon høver sjeldan
        for andre versjonar. Pass difor på at det programtillegget du
        ønskjer å installera er skriven for den versjonen av
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> du bruker.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Плагины <acronym>GIMP</acronym> написаны для разных версий. Однако
        плагины, написанные для одной версии едва ли могут  быть успешно
        использованы с другими версиями. Они должны быть портированы: иногда
        это легко,  иногда нет. Многие плагины доступны для нескольких
        версий. Перед тем, как пробовать  установить плагин, удостоверьтесь
        что он был  написан для вашей версии <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        插件做为 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 的特性已经存在多个版本中。尽管如此，为一个版本所写的插件很能在另一个版本中成功使用。它们需要被移植：有时是很容易，有时不是。许多插件已经在多个版本中都存在。最后记住：在您开始安装插件前，确认这是为您的 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>版本所写的。
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect2>


  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Using Plugins</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Používání zásuvných modulů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Mit Plugins arbeiten</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Uso de los complementos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Utiliser les greffons</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Uso dei plugin</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">플러그인 사용하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Uitbreidingen gebruiken</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å bruke programtillegg</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Использование плагинов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用插件</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      For the most part you can use a plugin like any other
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tool, without needing to be aware that it is a
      plugin. But there are a few things about plugins that are useful to
      understand.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Zásuvné moduly se používají stejně, jako jakékoliv jiné funkce Gimpu,
      není nutno vědět, že používáte zásuvný modul. Existuje ale pár věcí,
      kterým je užitečné rozumět.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Meistens können Sie eine Erweiterung wie jedes andere
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Werkzeug verwenden, ohne sich dessen bewusst
      zu sein, dass es ein Plugin ist. Allerdings ist es hilfreich, ein paar
      Dinge über Plugins zu verstehen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      En general Ud. hace uso de un complemento sin siquiera notarlo, como lo
      hace con las otras herramientas del GIMP.  Pero hay algunos detalles
      concernientes a los complementos que quisiera conocer.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La plupart du temps vous utiliserez un greffon tout comme les autres
      outils de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, sans même savoir qu'il s'agit d'un
      greffon. Mais il y a quelques petites choses qu'il est utile de savoir
      sur les greffons.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Per la maggior parte è possibile usare un plugin come se fosse un
      qualsiasi altro strumento di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> senza la
      consapevolezza del fatto che sia effettivamente un plugin. Ci sono però
      dettagli riguardo i plugin che è utile sapere.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      대부분의 경우 플러그인이라는 것을 의식하지 않고도
      <acronym>김프</acronym>의 다른 도구들처럼 플러그인을 사용할 수
      있습니다. 하지만 플러그인의 속성에 대해 알아두면 조금더 편리하게
      사용할 수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Een uitbreiding gedraagt zich voor een groot deel zoals ieder ander
      gereedschap van de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, het is echter handig om
      enkele specifieke eigenschappen ervan te kennen en begrijpen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Oftast vil du kunne bruke eit programtillegg i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      utan å bry deg om eller merka at det eigentleg er eit tillegg. Det er
      likevel noe småting med programtillegga som det kan vere nyttig å
      kjenne litt til.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В большинстве случаев вы можете использовать плагин также,  как и любой
      другой инструмент <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'a, без необходимости
      осознания того, что это плагин. Однако при использовани  плагинов есть
      несколько вещей, которые полезно понимать.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      大多数情况下，像使用其它 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 工具一样使用插件，并不需要意识到这是个插件。但是这里有些东西了解下对您是有帮助的。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      One is that plugins are generally not as robust as the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core. When <acronym>GIMP</acronym> crashes, it
      is considered a very serious thing: it can cost the user a lot of
      trouble and headache. When a plugin crashes, the consequences are
      usually not so serious.  In most cases you can just continuing working
      without worrying about it.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Zásuvné moduly nejsou obvykle tak stabilní jako jádro Gimpu. Pokud se
      zhroutí <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, je to považováno za velmi závažný
      problém, který může přinést uživateli hodně trápení. Pokud spadne
      zásuvný modul, nejsou obvykle důsledky tak vážné. Většinou lze plynule
      pokračovat v práci.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Als erstes gilt, dass Erweiterungen im allgemeinen nicht so robust
      sind wie der <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Kern. Wenn <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      abstürzt, ist das eine ernste Sache: es kann dem Benutzer eine Menge
      Ärger und Kopfschmerzen bereiten. Wenn ein Plugin abstürzt, sind die
      Folgen üblicherweise nicht so gravierend. In den meisten Fällen
      kann man einfach weiterarbeiten, ohne sich irgendwelche Gedanken zu
      machen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Primero, los complementos no son tan robustos como el cuerpo de la
      aplicación GIMP. Cuando el GIMP se rompe, se considera que ha sucedido
      algo muy serio, ya que le puede costar al usuario un buen dolor de
      cabeza. Cuando un componente se rompe, las consecuencias usualmente no
      son tan serias. En la mayoría de los casos Ud. puede continuar
      trabajando sin preocuparse de lo que ha sucedido.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Généralement, les greffons sont moins robustes que le noyau de
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Quand <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plante, c'est une
      affaire très sérieuse qui peut provoquer des problèmes et des maux de
      têtes. Quand un greffon plante, les conséquences sont généralement moins
      dramatiques. La plupart du temps vous pouvez continuer votre travail
      sans vous en soucier.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Uno di questi è che i plugin sono generalmente affidabili come il nucleo
      di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Se <acronym>GIMP</acronym> dovesse andare in
      crash, sarebbe considerato un fatto molto grave: una situazione simile
      potrebbe costare ad un utente molte preoccupazioni e difficoltà. Se un
      plugin dovesse andare in crash le conseguenze non sono normalmente così
      preoccupanti dato che spesso è possibile continuare il proprio lavoro
      come nulla fosse accaduto.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      플러그인들의 코드는 보통 김프 코어처럼 견고하게 짜여지지 않았습니다.
      대신 김프는 거의 충돌을 일으키진 않지만 한번 충돌을 일으키면 굉장히
      골치아픈 문제가 되는 반면, 플러그인의 충돌은 큰 문제가 되지 않아
      계속해서 작업을 진행할 수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Een aspect is dat uitbreidingen over het algemeen niet zo enorm stabiel
      als het centrale deel van het <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-programma zijn.
      Indien <acronym>GIMP</acronym> afstort, wordt dat ale een serieus
      probleem behandeld omdat het de gebruiker heel wat problemen en
      kopzorgen kan geven. Bij het afstorten van een uitbreiding zijn de
      problemen vaak niet zo ernstig; meestal kunt u zonder problemen
      doorwerken, maar dat kunt u zelf te beoordelen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Som oftast er programtillegga ikkje like robuste som programkjerna
      i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Når <acronym>GIMP</acronym> krasjar, må du
      ofte starte heile prosessen på nytt. Kanskje blir også mykje arbeid
      øydelagt. Når eit programtillegg krasjar, kan du ofte likevel arbeida
      vidare med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> utan å bry deg meir om heile
      krasjet.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Одна из них это то, что плагины обычно не так устойчивы как ядро
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Когда в <acronym>GIMP</acronym> происходит
      сбой, это считается очень серьезным обстоятельством: пользователю это
      может принести множество неприятностей и головную боль. Когда в плагине
      происходит сбой, то обычно последствия не столь серьезны. В болшинстве
      случаев вы можете просто продолжать работать, не беспокоясь по этому
      поводу
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      一个就是插件一般来健壮性不如 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 核心。当 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 崩溃时，这是一件非常灾难性的事：它可能给用户带来许多麻烦和痛苦。而当插件死掉时，后果就常常并不是那么不堪设想。大多数情况下您能继续您的工作而没有必要担心。
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        Because plugins are separate programs, they communicate with the
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core in a special way: The
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developers call it <quote>talking over a
          wire</quote>. When a plugin crashes, the communication breaks down,
        and you will see an error message about a <quote>wire read
          error</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Zásuvné moduly jsou samostatnými programy a proto musí s jádrem Gimpu
        komunikovat zvláštním způsobem. Hackeři pracující na Gimpu mluví o
        <quote>hovoru po drátě</quote> Když zásuvný modul spadne, komunikace
        se přeruší a objeví se chybová hláška <quote>wire read error</quote>
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Weil Plugins eigene Programme sind, kommunizieren sie mit dem
        GIMP-Kern in einer besonderen Art und Weise. Die Entwickler nennen es
        <quote>über eine Leitung sprechen</quote>. Wenn ein Plugin abstürzt,
        bricht die Verbindung ab, und Sie sehen eine Fehlermeldung mit dem
        Text <quote>wire read error</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Los complementos son programas aislados, y se comunican con el cuerpo
        del GIMP de una manera especial: los desarrolladores del GIMP lo
        llaman <quote>hablar por medio de un cable</quote>
        (en inglés <quote>talking over a wire</quote>
        ). Cuando un complemento se rompe, la comunicación se corta, y Ud.
        obtiene un mensaje de error <quote>wire read error</quote>
        ( <quote>error de lectura del cable</quote> ).
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Du fait que les greffons sont des programmes séparés, ils communiquent
        avec le noyau de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> d'une manière spéciale : les
        développeurs de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> appellent cela <quote>talking
          over a wire </quote> (parler sur un fil). Quand un greffon se plante,
        la communication s'arrête et vous voyez un message d'erreur à propos
        d'une <quote>erreur de lecture d'un fil</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Dato che i plugin sono programmi separati, essi comunicano con il
        nucleo di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in maniera particolare: gli
        sviluppatori di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> lo chiamano <quote>parlare sui
          fili</quote> Quando un plugin va in crash, la comunicazione viene
        interrotta ed il fatto viene segnalato da un messaggio di errore circa
        un <quote>errore di lettura filo ('wire read error')</quote>
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        그것은 플러그인은 독립된 프로그램들로 <acronym>김프</acronym>
        개발자들이 <quote>talking over a wire</quote> 라고 부르는 특수한
        방법으로 <acronym>김프</acronym> 코어와 연동되기 때문입니다.
        플러그인이 충돌하면 이러한 연동이 끊어지며 <quote>읽기 오류</quote>
        라는 에러 메세지가 나오게 됩니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Omdat uitbreidingen afzonderlijke programma's zijn, wisselen ze op een
        speciale manier gegevens met het
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-hoofdprogramma gegevens uit die door de
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ontwikkelaars <quote>Praten door een pijp
        </quote> gedoopt is. Als een uitbreiding afstort, wordt de
        communicatie over deze draad onderbroken en zul u een foutmelding
        over een <quote>Gebroken Pijp</quote> zien.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Fordi programtillegga er sjølvstendige program, kommuniserer dei med
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> via det utviklarane kallar <quote>talking over
          a wire</quote>. Når eit programtillegg krasjar, bryt dette sambandet
        saman, og det vil dukka opp ei feilmelding om <quote>wire read
          error</quote> eller noe i den duren.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Поскольку плагины представляют собой отдельные программы,  они
        сообщаются с <acronym>GIMP</acronym> при помощи особого метода:
        разработчики GIMPа называют его <quote>говорить по проводу</quote>.
        <!--FIXME: ru ?--> Когда в плагине происходит сбой, связь обрывается,
        и вы увидите сообщение об ошибке <quote>wire read error</quote>.
        <!--FIXME: ru ?-->
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        因为插件是些独立的程序，它们和 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        核心通过特殊的方式通信： <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 开发者称其为
        <quote>taking over a wire</quote> 。当插件崩溃时，通信就被中断，您会看到出现
        <quote>wire read error</quote> 的错误消息。
      </para>
    </note>

    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        When a plugin crashes, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gives you a very
        ominous-looking message telling you that the plugin may have left
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in a corrupted state, and you should consider
        saving your images and exiting. Strictly speaking, this is quite
        correct, because plugins have the power to alter almost anything in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but for practical purposes, experience has
        shown that corruption is actually quite rare, and many users just
        continue working and don't worry about it. Our advice is that you
        simply think about how much trouble it would cause you if something
        went wrong, and weigh it against the odds.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Po pádu zásuvného modulu na vás <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vyhrkne velmi
        znepokojující chybovou zprávu s varováním, že pád modulu mohl zanechat
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> v narušeném stavu a že by bylo lepší uložit
        obrázky a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> restartovat. Přísně řečeno, je to
        správný postup, neboť zásuvné moduly mají skutečně možnost běh Gimpu
        narušit. Praxe ale říká, že takové narušení je poměrně vzácné, a
        většina uživatelů prostě bez přerušení pokračuje v práci. Musíte se
        rozhodnout sami, zvážit, jaké problémy by případná nestabilita Gimpu
        pro vás znamenala.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn eine Erweiterung abstürzt, erhalten Sie von GIMP die sehr
        beunruhigende Meldung, dass das Plugin GIMP möglicherweise in einem
        fehlerhaften Zustand hinterlassen hat und Sie besser Ihre Daten
        sichern und das Programm beenden sollten. Genau genommen ist das
        völlig korrekt, da Erweiterungen nahezu alles in GIMP verändern
        können, aber praktisch zeigt die Erfahrung, dass eine
        Datenverfälschung tatsächlich sehr selten ist, daher arbeiten viele
        Benutzer einfach weiter und kümmern sich nicht darum. Unsere
        Empfehlung lautet: überlegen Sie einfach, wie groß der angerichtete
        Schaden ist, falls etwas schief geht, und wägen Sie danach ab.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Cuando un complemento se rompe, se le proporciona un mensaje diciendo
        que se pudo haber dejado al GIMP en un estado corrupto, y que debería
        considerar guardar las imágenes y salir.  Estrictamente hablando, esto
        es correcto, porque los complementos tienen la capacidad de modificar
        casi todo en el GIMP.  Pero en la práctica, la experiencia ha
        demostrado que dicha corrupción ocurre muy raramente, y muchos
        usuarios continuan trabajando sin preocuparse.  Nuestro consejo es que
        Ud. considere qué tan problemático sería si algo anduviera mal, y lo
        enfrente con lo incómodo que es salir y volver a iniciar.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quand un greffon se plante, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vous affiche un
        message menaçant qui vous informe que le greffon peut l'avoir laissé
        dans un état corrompu, vous devrez alors sauvegarder vos images et
        quitter <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. En théorie, cela est vrai, parce que
        les greffons peuvent altérer à peu près tout dans
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, mais en pratique, l'expérience montre que la
        corruption est plutôt rare, et beaucoup d'utilisateurs continuent de
        travailler sans se soucier de cela.  Notre conseil est de réfléchir
        aux conséquences d'un éventuel problème et de peser le pour et le
        contre.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Quando un plugin va in crash, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> segnala la cosa
        con un messaggio di avvertimento del fatto che il plugin potrebbe aver
        lasciato il programma in uno stato imprevisto e consiglia di salvare
        le immagini su cui si stava lavorando ed uscire da
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> immediatamente. Strettamente parlando tutto
        ciò è corretto dato che i plugin hanno la capacità di alterare quasi
        tutto il funzionamento di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ma, nella pratica, è
        piuttosto raro avere dei problemi e spesso è possibile continuare a
        lavorare senza preoccupazione. Il nostro consiglio è di valutare
        attentamente la possibilità di un eventuale problema considerando il
        caso peggiore (perdita di dati) e confrontare con i vantaggi del poter
        continuare a lavorare.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        플러그인이 충돌하면, <acronym>김프</acronym>는 해당 플러그인이
        <acronym>김프</acronym>를 위험한 상태로 빠뜨릴 수 있다라는
        무시무시한 경고 메세지를 보여줍니다. 그럴 경우에는 일단 이미지를
        저장하고 김프를 종료하는 것이 좋습니다. 플러그인은 실제로
        <acronym>김프</acronym>의 거의 모든 것을 바꿀 수 있지만, 일반적인
        사용에 있어서 큰 문제가 되는 경우는 극히 드뭅니다. 따라서 대부분은
        이에 대해 걱정하지 않고 작업을 계속해도 무방합니다. 이런 문제가
        발생했을 경우에는 그 심각성이 어느 정도인지를 판단한 뒤 그에 맞게
        조치하는 것이 좋습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Als een uitbreiding afstort, geeft <acronym>GIMP</acronym> de zeer
        dreigende melding dat de uitbreiding <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in een
        instabiele toestand kan hebben achtergelaten en dat het aan te raden
        is om al uw afbeeldingen op te slaan en het programma af te sluiten.
        Strikt genomen is dit correct omdat uitbreidingen aan bijna alle
        gegevens in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kunnen rommelen. In de praktijk
        gebeurt het slechts zeer zelden dat er iets in het hoofdprogramma
        beschadigd raakt en veel gebruikers werken negeren dit advies dan ook
        vaak om zorgeloos door te werken. Ons advies is dan ook dat u eerst
        nadenk hoeveel problemen het op zou leveren als er iets verkeerd gaat
        en de nadelen tegen de voordelen af te wegen.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Når eit programtillegg krasjar, dukkar det opp ei melding frå
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> om at programtillegget kan ha øydelagt
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Du får beskjed om å lagre alt du held på med
        og avslutta <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Dette kan i teorien vere heilt
        rett. Programtillegga er i stand til å endre nesten kva det skal
        vere i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Praktisk røynsle har derimot vist at
        det er sjeldan at programtillegga gjer nemnande skade. Som oftast
        kan du halde fram som om ingenting var hendt. Kanskje etter å ha
        vurdert kva du taper dersom programmet likevel skulle vere øydelagt
        og arbeidet ditt forsvinna.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Когда в плагине происходит сбой, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> выдаёт вам
        выглядящее зловещим сообщение о том, что плагин возможно покинул
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> в испорченном состоянии, вы должны решить
        насчёт сохранения изображения и выйти из программы. Строго говоря, это
        вполне правильно, поскольку плагины имеют силу изменения в
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> почти всего, но на практике опыт показал, что
        разрушения весьма редки, и множество пользователей просто продолжают
        работать не беспокоясь о этом. Наш совет заключается в том, что вы
        просто подумайте, какие проблемы это причинит вам, если что-то пойдёт
        не так, и взвесьте это против приемуществ.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当插件崩溃时，<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 显示一条看上去可怕的消息高诉您插件在崩溃的边缘，考虑是保存图像还是退出。严格来说，这非常正确，因为插件几乎有能力改变 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>中任何东西，但是实际上，经验表明这种崩溃却是很少发生，很多用户继续工作而并不担心。我们的建议是，考虑如果出错会给您带来多少麻烦，然后自己衡量后再决定。
      </para>
    </tip>

    <para lang="en">
      Because of the way plugins communicate with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      they do not have any mechanism for being informed about changes you make
      to an image after the plugin has been started. If you start a plugin,
      and then alter the image using some other tool, the plugin will often
      crash, and when it doesn't will usually give a bogus result. You should
      avoid running more than one plugin at a time on an image, and avoid
      doing anything to the image until the plugin has finished working on it.
      If you ignore this advice, not only will you probably screw up the
      image, you will probably screw up the undo system as well, so that you
      won't even be able to recover from your foolishness.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Vzhledem ke způsobu komunikace mezi zásuvnými moduly a Gimpem, není
      možno informovat je o změnách v obrázku provedených po startu modulu.
      Pokud spustíte zásuvný modul a během jeho činnosti provedete zásah do
      obrázku jiným nástrojem, zásuvný modul může spadnout nebo vrátit
      nesmyslný výsledek. Měli byste se vyhýbat spouštění více zásuvných
      modulů současně a s obrázkem před ukončením modulu nijak nemanipulovat.
      Pokud tomuto varování nebudete věnovat pozornost, pravděpodobně si
      zkazíte obrázek a navíc možná poškodíte historii změn, takže ani svou
      chybu nebudete moci napravit.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wegen der besonderen Art und Weise, wie Plugins mit GIMP kommunizieren,
      haben sie keinen Mechanismus, um über Änderungen informiert zu werden,
      die Sie nach dem Starten des Plugins an einem Bild vorgenommen haben.
      Wenn Sie eine Erweiterung starten und dann das Bild mit einem anderen
      Werkzeug verändern, wird das Plugin des öfteren abstürzen oder falsche
      Resultate liefern. Sie sollten es vermeiden, ein Bild mit mehr als einem
      Plugin gleichzeitig zu bearbeiten oder irgendetwas mit dem Bild zu
      machen, bis das Plugin seine Arbeit beendet hat. Wenn Sie diesen Rat
      ignorieren, werden Sie vermutlich nicht nur Ihr Bild vermurksen, sondern
      wahrscheinlich auch gleich das System zum Zurücknehmen von Aktionen, so
      dass Sie nicht einmal mehr in der Lage sein werden, Ihren Blödsinn
      wieder rückgängig zu machen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Debido a la manera en que los complementos se comunican con el GIMP,
      ellos no tienen manera de conocer los cambios que Ud. ha hecho en una
      imagen antes de que sean iniciados. Si Ud. inicia un complemento, y
      luego modifica la imagen empleando otra herramienta, el complemento
      probablemente se romperá, y cuando no lo haga dará un resultado
      incorrecto. Debería evitar correr más de un complemento al mismo tiempo
      sobre una imagen, y evite también hacer modificaciones a la imagen hasta
      que el complemento termine de trabajar. Si Ud. ignora este consejo, no
      sólo se dañará la imagen, sino que además se dañará el sistema de
      deshacer, con lo que ni siquiera podrá recuperarse del accidente.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Du fait de leur manière de communiquer avec <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, les
      greffons n'ont pas de moyen de savoir si vous avez effectué des
      changements sur l'image après leur lancement. Si vous lancez un greffon
      et modifiez l'image en utilisant un outil en même temps, le greffon se
      plantera sûrement et s'il ne le fait pas il vous amènera à un résultat
      erroné. Vous ne devez pas lancer plus d'un greffon à la fois sur une
      image, ni faire quoi que ce soit sur l'image avant que le greffon n'en
      ait fini avec elle. Si vous ne suivez pas ce conseil, non seulement vous
      abîmerez probablement l'image, mais vous abîmerez aussi probablement le
      système d'annulation, aussi ne pourrez-vous pas revenir à l'état d'avant
      vos erreurs.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Dato la maniera con cui i plugin comunicano con <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
      essi non possiedono nessun meccanismo per essere informati sui
      cambiamenti che si fa su un'immagine dopo che il plugin è stato avviato.
      Se si avvia un plugin e dopo si modifica l'immagine usando un qualche
      altro strumento, spesso il plugin va in crash e quando non succede
      spesso viene prodotto un risultato incorretto. Evitare di eseguire più
      di un plugin alla volta su di un'immagine e di fare qualsiasi cosa
      all'immagine prima che il plugin abbia finito di lavorarci sopra. Se si
      ignora quest'avvertimento, non solo probabilmente si rovinerà
      l'immagine, ma non si sarà più in grado di recuperare nemmeno il sistema
      degli annullamenti, in maniera tale da non essere più in grado di
      recuperare nulla del proprio lavoro.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      플러그인이 <acronym>김프</acronym>와 소통하는 방식에는 플러그인이
      시작된 이후에, 이미지가 바뀐 부분에 대해 플러그인에 통보하는 과정이
      없습니다. 따라서 플러그인을 실행한 후 다른 도구로 이미지를 편집하면,
      플러그인은 종종 충돌하게 됩니다. 그런까닭에 하나의 이미지에 대해
      한번에 하나의 플러그인만 사용하고, 동작중인 플러그인이 종료될때까지
      다른 작업을 하지 않는 것이 좋습니다. 그렇지 않으면 이미지를 망치는
      것뿐만 아니라 실행취소 시스템까지 망가뜨려, 그림을 복구하지 못하게
      될수도 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Door de manier waarop uitbreidingen met het hoofdprogramma communiceren
      worden ze na hun opstarten niet meer op de hoogte van nieuwe
      veranderingen in de afbeelding gebracht. Als u dus na het opstarten van
      een uitbreiding met een ander gereedschap wijzigingen in de afbeelding
      aanbrengt zal de uitbreiding meestal afstorten of, als dit niet gebeurd,
      een onzinnig resultaat geven. U moet dus voorkomen dat er meer dan een
      uitbreiding tegelijkertijd opgestart zijn en ook geen bewerkingen op de
      afbeelding uitvoeren tot de uitbreiding ermee klaar is. Als u dit advies
      in de wind slaat, beschadigd u waarschijnlijk niet alleen de afbeelding
      zelf, maar ook het mechanisme om wijzigingen ondedaan te maken, dus u
      zult uw vlaag van verstandsverbijstering waarschijnlijk ook niet kunnen
      herstellen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      På grunn av den måten programtillegga kommuniserer med
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> på, har dei ingen måte å få greie på endringar
      du har gjort i biletet etter at programtillegget har starta. Gjer du
      forandringar på eit bilete medan eit programtillegg er i arbeid, vil
      dette ofte føre til at programtillegget  krasjar og etterlet seg eit
      noe forvirrande bilete. Du bør difor unngå å køyre meir enn eitt
      tileggsprogram om gongen (noe som stort sett ikkje er mogleg i nyare
      versjonar av <acronym>GIMP</acronym>), og unngå å gjere noe som helst
      med biletet før programtillegget er ferdig. Dersom du ikkje følgjer
      dette rådet, er det stor sjanse for at du endar opp med eit øydelagt
      bilete i tillegg til at også angreloggen er øydelagt. Du kan altså
      heller ikkje tilbakeføra biletet til slik det var før krasjet. Kanskje
      lurt å lagra biletet før du bruker programtillegget.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Из-за особенностей метода связи плагинов с <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,  они
      не имеют никакого механизма информирования  о изменениях, которые вы
      производите на  изображении после запуска плагина.  Если вы запустите
      плагин, а затем с помощью какого-либо  другого инструмента измените
      изображение, плагин чаще  всего будет падать, и даже когда это не
      происходит, результат  окажется искаженным. Вы должны избегать запуска
      более чем одного плагина, и избегать операций над изображением  до тех
      пор, пока на нём не завершит работу плагин. Если вы игнорируете этот
      совет, вы можете испортить не  только изображение, но также и механизм
      истории отмен,  следовательно, у вас не будет возможности исправить
      вашу глупость.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      因为插件和 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 通信的这种方式，它们没有任何在插件启动后通报对图像所做的改变的机制。当您开始使用一个插件而同时用其它工具来改变图像时，插件常常就会崩溃，即使没有，也常常给您一个错误的结果。您应该避免同时对图像运行一个以上的插件，并且不要对图像做任何操作直到插件处理完毕。要是您忽略这些建议，不光您处理的图像要遭殃，重做系统也可能受到破坏，到那时您就无法从您的所干的蠢事中恢复了。
    </para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="gimp-plugins-install">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Installing New Plugins</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Instalace nových zásuvných modulů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Neue Plugins installieren </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Instalación de nuevos complementos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Installation de nouveaux greffons</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Installazione di nuovi Plugin</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">새 플러그인 설치하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Installatie van nieuwe uitbreidingen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å installera nye programtillegg</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Установка новых плагинов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">安装新插件</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Plugins</primary><secondary>Install</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Plugin</primary><secondary>installieren</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Greffons</primary><secondary>Installer</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>플러그인</primary><secondary>설치</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      The plugins that are distributed with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> don't
      require any special installation. Plugins that you download yourself do.
      There are several scenarios, depending on what OS you are using and how
      the plugin is structured. In Linux it is usually pretty easy to install
      a new plugin; in Windows, it is either easy or very hard. In any case,
      the two are best considered separately.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Zásuvné moduly dodávané přímo s Gimpem nevyžadují žádnou zvláštní
      instalaci. Moduly, které si stáhnete sami, ale musíte nainstalovat.
      Způsobů je několik, v závislosti na vašem operačním systému a
      vlastnostech zásuvného modulu. V Linuxu je instalace nového zásuvného
      modulu obvykle velice jednoduchá, ve Windows to může být jednoduché ale
      i pekelně složité (ne, Windows už dávno nejsou snáze ovladatelným
      systémem). V každém případě je lépe obě možnosti probrat zvlášť.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die mit GIMP ausgelieferten Erweiterungen müssen nicht extra installiert
      werden; Plugins, die Sie selbst herunterladen, schon. Dafür gibt es
      verschiedene Szenarien, je nachdem, welches Betriebssystem Sie benutzen
      und wie das Plugin strukturiert ist. Beispielsweise gilt es unter Linux
      als ganz simpel, eine neue Erweiterung zu installieren, unter Windows
      ist es entweder leicht oder sehr schwer. Auf jeden Fall sollten daher
      die verschiedenen Szenarien getrennt betrachtet werden.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Los complementos distribuidos con el GIMP no requieren una instalación
      especial.  Son los que se descargan de la web los que requieren
      instalarse.  Hay varios escenarios, dependiendo de su sistema operativo,
      y de cómo se encuentra estructurado el complemento mismo.  En Linux
      usualmente es muy fácil instalar un nuevo complemento.  En Windows,
      puede ser tanto fácil como difícil.  Es por eso que resulta mejor
      considerar ambos sistemas por separado.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les greffons fournis avec <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ne nécessitent pas
      d'installation particulière, contrairement à ceux que vous téléchargez.
      Il y a plusieurs scénarios, dépendant de votre système d'exploitation et
      de la structure du greffon. Sous Linux il est généralement aisé
      d'installer un nouveau greffon ; sous Windows c'est soit très simple
      soit très compliqué. De toute façon il vaut mieux examiner ces deux cas
      séparément.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      I plugin distribuiti con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> non abbisognano di
      nessuna installazione speciale diversamente da quelli scaricati da se
      dalla Rete. Ci sono diversi scenari a seconda del sistema operativo che
      si sta utilizzando e a seconda di come è strutturato il plugin. In Linux
      è abbastanza semplice installare un nuovo plugin; in Windows o è molto
      semplice oppure molto difficile. Ad ogni modo è meglio considerare
      separatamente i due sistemi.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      <acronym>김프</acronym>와 함께 배포되는 플러인들은 별도의 설치과정이
      필요없지만 직접 다운로드받은 플러그인을 따로 설치해주어야 합니다.
      설치과정은 사용하는 OS와 플러그인의 구조에 따라 달라집니다.
      리눅스에서 새 플러그인을 설치하는 것은 대체적으로 쉽습니다. 하지만
      윈도우에서는 매우 쉽거나 매우 어렵기 때문에 따로 설명을 할 것입니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      De uitbreidingen die met <acronym>GIMP</acronym> meegeleverd worden,
      hebben meestal geen speciale installatie nodig. De uitbreidingen die u
      zelf van het web ophaalt echter wel. Met de verschillende
      besturingssystemen en manieren waarop de uitbreiding in elkaar steekt,
      zijn er verschillende manieren waarop u dat doen kunt. In
      <acronym>Linux</acronym> is het betrekkelijk eenvoudig; in
      <acronym>Windows</acronym> is het óf makkelijk óf heel moeilijk.  In
      ieder geval is het het beste om ze beiden apart uit te leggen.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dei programtillegga som følgjer med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> treng du
      ikkje installera spesielt. Det må du derimot gjere med dei du lastar ned
      eller skriv sjølv. Måten du installerar eit programtillegg på, er
      sterkt avhengig av kva for operativsystem (OS) du køyrer og korleis
      programtillegget er bygd opp. I Linux er det som oftast ein enkel
      jobb, i Windows stort sett anten svært lett eller (nesten) umogleg.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Поставляемые вместе с <acronym>GIMP</acronym> плагины не требуют никакой
      особой установки. Скачанным вами плагинам установка  необходима. Вот
      несколько сценариев, в  зависимости от используемой вами ОС и структуры
      плагина. В Linux обычно достаточно просто  установить новый плагин; В
      Windows, это или легко  или очень сложно. В любом случае, два случая
      лучше  рассмотреть отдельно.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 发行版本所附带的插件不需要任何特别的安装。而那些您自己下载的则需要。这有一些方法，它们依赖与您使用何种操作系统以及插件的结构。在 Linux 下，安装新插件常常是相当简单的;在 Windows 下，要么简单要么非常难。不管怎么说，最好把它们单独分开讨论。
    </para>


    <sect3>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">Linux</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">리눅스(Linux)</phrase>
      </title>

      <para lang="en">
        Most plugins fall into two categories: small ones whose source
        code is distributed as a single .c file, and larger ones whose
        source code is distributed as a directory containing multiple
        files including a <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Většina zásuvných modulů spadá do jedné ze dvou kategorií. První
        jsou malé moduly distribuované jako jeden zdrojový C soubor
        (<filename>.c</filename>). Druhou skupinu tvoří moduly, jejichž
        zdrojový kód je šířen jako adresář s více soubory včetně
        Makefile.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die meisten Plugins gehören in eine von zwei Kategorien: kleine,
        deren Quellcode in einer einzigen C-Datei ausgeliefert wird, und
        größere, deren Quellcode in einem Verzeichnis mit mehreren Dateien
        inklusive einem <filename>Makefile</filename> ausgeliefert wird.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        La mayoría de los complementos caen en dos categorías: lo pequeños
        cuyo código fuente se distribuye en un único archivo .c, y los grandes
        cuyo código fuerte se distribuye como un directorio que contiene
        varios archivos, incluyendo un archivo <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        La plupart des greffons peuvent être classés en deux catégories :
        les petits dont le code source tient dans un seul fichier .c, et
        les plus gros dont le code source est distribué dans un
        répertoire contenant de nombreux fichiers dont un
        <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Molti plugin ricadono in due categorie: i piccoli il cui sorgente
        viene distribuito come un singolo file sorgente .c e quelli più grandi
        il cui codice sorgente viene distribuito nella forma di una cartella
        contenente più file ed un file <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        대부분의 플러그인은 두 가지로 분류할 수 있습니다. 하나는 .c 파일의
        소스 코드 형태로 배포되는 소수의 플러그인들이고, 다른 하나는
        <filename>Makefile</filename> 을 포함한 많은 파일과 디렉토리를 가진
        형태로 배포되는 대부분의 플러그인입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        De meeste uitbreidingen zijn in twee soorten op te delen: Kleine,
        waarvan de programmacode in een enkel <filename>.c</filename>
        aangeleverd wordt en grotere waarin de programmacode in meerdere
        bestanden in een eigen map geleverd worden inclusief een eigen
        <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dei fleste programtillegga kan delast i to grupper, dei små med
        kjeldekoden levert i ei enkelt .c-fil, og dei større der kjeldekoden
        kjem i ei mappe med fleire ulike filer, deriblant også ei
        <quote>Makefile</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Большинство плагинов делятся на две категории: небольшие, чей исходный
        код распространяется в одном файле с расширением ".c", и большие, чей
        исходный код распространяется в директории, содержащей многочисленные
        файлы, включая <filename>Makefile</filename>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        大部分插件可划分为两类：源代码由单个的 .c 文件构成的比较小的一类和源代码由多个文件和一个
        Makefile 包含在一个目录中的比较大的一类。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        For a simple one-file plugin, call it <filename>borker.c</filename>,
        installing it is just a matter of running the command
        <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>.   This command
        compiles the plugin and installs it in your personal plugin directory,
        <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> unless you have changed it.
        This will cause it to be loaded automatically the next time you start
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You don't need to be root to do these things;
        in fact, you shouldn't be. If the plugin fails to compile, well, be
        creative.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        V případě jednoduchého zásuvného modulu tvořeného jedním souborem,
        řekněme <filename>borker.c</filename>, stačí spustit příkaz
        <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>. Tento příkaz
        zásuvný modul přeloží a nainstaluje do vašeho osobního adresáře pro
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (<filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename>,
        pokud jste ho nezměnili). To způsobí automatické nahrání zásuvného
        modulu při dalším spuštění Gimpu. Pro tento typ instalace není nutné
        být superuživatelem root, ve skutečnosti byste jím být ani neměli.
        Pokud překlad zásuvného modulu selže, buďte tvořiví.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Für den simplen Fall einer einfachen Datei(-Erweiterung), nennen wir
        sie mal <filename>borker.c</filename>, besteht das Installieren einfach
        nur darin, den Befehl <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>
        einzugeben. Dieses Kommando übersetzt das Plugin und installiert
        es in Ihrem persönlichen Pluginverzeichnis
        <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> (falls Sie das nicht geändert
        haben). Dann wird es automatisch geladen, wenn Sie
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> das nächste Mal starten.
        Sie müssen nicht root sein, um das Ganze auszuführen, tatsächlich
        sollten Sie es nicht einmal.  Falls die Erweiterung nicht übersetzt
        werden kann, na ja, dann seien Sie halt etwas kreativ.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Tomemos como ejemplo un pequeño complemento de un archivo, llamémosle
        <filename>borker.c</filename>.  Instalarlo sólo toma correr el comando
        <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>.  Este comando
        compila el complemento y lo instala en su directorio personal de
        complementos, por ejemplo <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename>.
        Esto lo deja disponible para la próxima vez que inice la aplicación.
        No necesita tener privilegios de root para realizar esta tarea.  De
        hecho, no debería hacerlo.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour un simple greffon "fichier unique", appelons-le
        <filename>border.c</filename>, l'installation consiste a lancer la
        commande <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command> (pour
        disposer de cette commande, il faut avoir chargé le paquet
        <quote>libgimp2.0-dev</quote> de votre distribution Linux). Cette
        commande compile le greffon et l'installe dans votre répertoire
        personnel "plug-ins", qui est
        <filename>~/gimp-version/plugins</filename> à moins que vous ne l'ayez
        changé. Il sera chargé automatiquement lors du prochain lancement de
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Vous n'avez pas besoin d'avoir les
        droits d'administrateur (root) pour faire cela ; en fait vous ne devriez
        pas l'être. Si la compilation du greffon ne fonctionne pas, eh bien
        soyez créatif !
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per un semplice plugin a singolo file, chiamiamolo
        <filename>borker.c</filename>, per installaro è solo questione di
        eseguire il comando <command>gimptool-2.0 --install
          borker.c</command>. Questo comando compila il plugin e lo installa
        nella cartella personale dei plugin in
        <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> a meno che non sia stata
        cambiata. Quest'operazione farà in modo che esso venga automaticamente
        caricato al prossimo avvio di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Non serve
        essere amministratori, cioè root, per fare queste cose. Se il plugin
        non si compila, beh, siate creativi!
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        예를 들어 <filename>borker.c</filename> 라는 하나의 파일로 된
        플러그인이 있다면 <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>
        라고 명령을 입력합니다. 그러면 플러그인이 컴파일된 후 사용자
        플러그인 디렉토리인 <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> 로
        설치가 됩니다. 이 플러그인은 다음번 <acronym>김프</acronym> 시작시
        자동으로 읽어들여지게 되며, 이 과정은 루트 권한으로 실행하지 않아도
        됩니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        In het eerste geval met een enkel bestand, met de fictieve naam
        <filename>borker.c</filename>, installeert u de uitbreiding
        eenvoudigweg door het uitvoeren van het commando:
        <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>.  Met dit commando
        wordt de uitbreiding in een door <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uitvoerbaar
        programma gecompileerd en in uw persoonlijke uitbreidingsmap
        geïnstalleerd: <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> (tenzij u dit
        natuurlijk zelf anders ingesteld heeft). De volgende keer dat u
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opstart wordt de uitbreiding dan automatisch
        geladen. De toegangsrechten van de systeembeheerder heeft u niet nodig
        om dit allemaal te doen; zeker gezien de voorgaande waarschuwingen zou
        dit zelfs onverstandig zijn. Als er iets fout gaat bij het compileren
        van de uitbreiding? Tja; dan zult u zelf een creatieve oplossing moeten
        vinden.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Eit programtillegg som blir levert på ei enkelt fil, la oss kalla
        det <filename>borker.c</filename>, kan installerast ved å køyra
        kommandoen <command>gimptool-2.0 –install borker.c</command>. Denne
        kommandoen kompilerer programtillegget og installerer det i den
        private mappa di <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> dersom du
        ikkje har forandra adressa. Programtillegget vil vere aktivisert
        frå neste gong du startar GIMP. Du treng ikkje vere i
        <quote>root</quote> for å gjere dette. Faktisk så skal du ikkje
        heller. Dersom du ikkje får kompilert programmet skikkeleg, må du
        finne fram dei kreative evnene dine.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Для одного простого плагина, назовём его
        <filename>borker.c</filename>, установка представляет  собой просто
        запуск команды  <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command>.
        Эта команда компилирует плагин и устанавливает его  в вашу
        персональную директорию плагинов,
        <filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename>, если вы её не изменили. Это
        заставит его автоматически загружаться   при следующем запуске
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Для того, чтобы  проделать эти дейстия, вам
        не нужно для получать права  администратора. Если плагин не
        скомпилируется, ну,  подойдите к этому творчески.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        对单个文件的插件，比如叫 <filename>borker.c</filename>，通过命令 <command>gimptool-2.0 --install borker.c</command> 来安装它。该命令编译插件然后安装到您的个人插件目录中，<filename>~/gimp-2.4/plugins</filename> 除非您已经改变。这将使下次启动 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 时自动载入。您不需要 root 权限来干这些事;实际上，您也不应当这样。当然如果插件编译失败，那就是另外一回事了。
      </para>

      <para lang="en"><!-- changed 11-10-2004 -->
        Once you have installed the plugin, how do you activate it? The menu
        path is determined by the plugin itself, so to answer this you need to
        either look at the documentation for the plugin (if there is any), or
        launch the Plugin Description dialog (from Xtns/Plugins Details)
        search the plug-in by its name and look of the
        <guilabel>Tree view</guilabel>
        tab. If you still don't find, finally explore the menus or look at the
        source code in the Register section -- whichever is easiest.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Jak použijete úspěšně nainstalovaný zásuvný modul? Místo v nabídkách,
        kde se objeví, závisí na modulu samotném. Proto si buď musíte
        nastudovat dokumentaci k modulu (pokud existuje), nebo otevřít
        Prohlížeč zásuvných modulů (z nabídky <guimenu>Rozš.</guimenu>
        panelu nástrojů) a vyhledat v něm zásuvný modul podle jména.
        Můžete si také prostě jen pečlivě prohlédnout všechny nabídky
        Gimpu nebo, což je nejspolehlivější, přečíst zdrojový kód zásuvného
        modulu.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie erstmal das Plugin installiert haben, wie aktivieren Sie es
        dann? Der Menüpfad wird durch das Plugin selbst festgelegt, d.h. um
        diese Frage zu beantworten, müssen Sie entweder einen Blick in die
        Dokumentation der Erweiterung werfen (falls vorhanden) oder den
        Plugin-Beschreibungsdialog (aus
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Extras</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Plugin-Browser</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        ) aufrufen, das Plugin über seinen Namen suchen und auf den Reiter
        <quote>Baumansichts</quote> schauen. Beachten Sie hierzu auch
        <xref linkend="gimp-xtns-plug-in-browser" />
        Wenn Sie es dann immer noch nicht finden, durchsuchen Sie die Menüs
        oder werfen Sie einen Blick auf den Quellcode (Registerabschnitt) - je
        nachdem, was einfacher ist.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Ahora bien, si ya ha instalado el complemento, ¿cómo lo activa? El
        complemento determina una entrada de menú para accederlo, así que para
        conocer su ubicación puede revisar la documentación del mismo. También
        puede lanzar el diálogo "Visor de complementos" desde Exts/Explorador
        de complementos. Busque el complemento por su nombre y luevo observe
        la solapa <guilabel>Vista de árbol</guilabel>.
        Si aún no lo encuentra, explore los menús o dele un vistazo al
        código fuente y busque la sección Register.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Une fois que vous avez installé un greffon, comment le lancer ? Le
        chemin dans le menu est déterminé par le greffon lui même, aussi pour
        répondre à cette question vous devrez au choix regarder la
        documentation du greffon (s'il y en a une) ou lancer le dialogue de
        description des greffons (via le menu Exts/Navigateur de greffons GIMP),
        rechercher le greffon par son nom et regarder dans l'onglet
        <guilabel>Affichage en arborescence</guilabel>.
        Si vous n'avez toujours pas trouvé, finalement explorez les menus
        jusqu'à ce que vous l'y trouviez, ou bien regardez le code source ce
        qui est encore le plus simple.
      </para>
      <para lang="it"><!-- changed 11-10-2004 -->
        Una volta installato il plugin, come attivarlo? Il percorso del menu è
        determinato dal plugin, perciò per rispondere a questa domanda è
        necessatio consultare la documentazione allegata al plugin (se c'è) o
        lanciare la finestra di descrizione del plugin (dal menu
        Xtns/Navigatore dei plugin) cercare il plugin per il suo nome e
        osservare la linguetta della <guilabel>Vista ad albero</guilabel>.
        Se ancora non lo si trova, esplorare i menu o guardare nel codice
        sorgente nella sezione Registro.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        설치한 플러그인을 활성화시키려면 어떻게 해야할까요? 플러그인의 메뉴
        경로는 플러그인에 따라 결정됩니다. 따라서 플러그인 설명서를 보거나
        플러그인 설명 대화상자(Xtns/Plugins Details)에서 해당 플러그인을
        찾고 <guilabel>Tree view</guilabel> 탭을 보아 확인합니다. 그래도 못
        찾겠다면 메뉴들을 다 뒤져보던가 등록 섹션에서 소스 코드를 찾아봅니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Op welke plaats, in welk menu u de uitbreiding kunt terugvinden na de
        installatie, wordt door de uitbreiding zelf bepaald. Dus dit zult u in
        eventueel meegeleverde documentatie moeten opzoeken, of in de
        <quote>Plugin browser</quote>  (via het
        <guimenu><accel>X</accel>tra</guimenu>-menu) Als u het nog steeds niet
        kunt vinden, moet u wellicht domweg alle menu's aflopen of in de
        programmacode in de <quote>Register</quote> sectie kijken.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Korleis aktivisera programtillegget etter at du har installert
        det? Kva meny det legg seg i, blir bestemt av programtillegget.
        Du må difor sjå i dokumentasjonen for programtillegget, dersom
        denne finst, eller finne fram til ei beskriving i dei ulike menyvala
        i hovudmenyen under
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Utvid</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Lesar for programtillegg</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
        Du kan også sjå i <guimenuitem>Prosedyrelesar</guimenuitem> i same
        menyen. Endeleg kan du leite gjennom alle menyane for å sjå om
        programmet har dukka opp einkvan staden.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Как только вы установили плагин, возникает вопрос:  как его
        активировать? Расположение в меню  определяется самим плагином,
        поэтому ответ на этот  вопрос вам нужно искать или в документации к
        плагину (если таковая имеется), или запустив диалог описания  плагина
        (в Расш./Список дополнений) поискать плагин  по его имени и посмотреть
        на закладке <guilabel>Просмотр дерева</guilabel>. Если вы  всё же еще
        не найдёте, окончательно исследуйте меню  или посмотрите в исходном
        коде в разделе "Register" - наиболее простой способ.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        可是一旦您安装完毕，如何运行它们呢？其在菜单的路径由插件本身决定。所以要回答这个问题，您可以通过看插件的文档(如果有的话)，或打开插件描述对话框(扩展/插件浏览器)搜索其插件名并使用<guilabel>树状列表</guilabel>。如果仍然没有找到，就只能浏览各个菜单或看该插件源代码的注册部分---这或许是最简单的。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        For more complex plugins, organized as a directory with multiple
        files, there ought to be a file inside called either
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> or <filename>README</filename>, with
        instructions. If not, the best advice is to toss the plugin in the
        trash and spend your time on something else:  any code written with so
        little concern for the user is likely to be frustrating in myriad
        ways.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        V případě složitějších zásuvných modulů šířených v podobě adresáře
        s více soubory, by měl být součástí i soubor pojmenovaný
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> nebo <filename>README</filename>.
        Ten obsahuje instrukce (ovšem většinou v angličtině). Pokud žádné
        instrukce k modulu přibaleny nejsou, bude ho nejlépe zahodit a věnovat
        se něčemu jinému, protože kód bez dokumentace bude stejně
        pravděpodobně obsahovat příliš nepříjemných chyb a přinášet řadu
        problémů.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Für komplexere Erweiterungen, die als ein Verzeichnis mit mehreren
        Dateien organisiert sind, sollte im Verzeichnis eine Datei namens
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> oder <filename>README</filename> mit
        Instruktionen vorhanden sein. Falls nicht, lautet der beste Rat,
        das Plugin auf den Müll zu werfen und die Zeit für etwas anderes
        zu nutzen. Jeder Code, der geschrieben wurde, ohne sich um den
        Benutzer zu scheren, wird vermutlich nur jede Menge Frustration
        verursachen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Para complementos más complejos, organizados en un directorio con
        múltiples archivos, puede ver que incluyen un archivo llamado
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> o un archivo <filename>README</filename>,
        con instrucciones.  Si no es así, es mejor que no lo utilice, porque
        ha sido escrito con pocas intensiones de que sea utilizado por otros.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour les greffons plus complexes, organisés comme un répertoire avec
        plusieurs fichiers, il devrait y avoir un fichier appelé soit
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> soit <filename>README</filename>,
        contenant les instructions. S'il n'y a rien, le mieux est de jeter le
        greffon à la poubelle et de passer du temps sur autre chose : du code
        écrit avec aussi peu de considération pour l'utilisateur risque d'être
        expérimental.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per plugin più complessi, organizzati come una cartella con più fila,
        dovrebbe esserci un file all'interno di essa chiamato
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> o <filename>README</filename>, con le
        istruzioni. Se non c'è, il consiglio migliore che possiamo darvi è di
        gettarlo nel cestino e investire il proprio tempo in qualcosa di più
        produttivo: tutto il codice con così poca considerazione per l'utente
        è probabile che sia frustrante in molti altri aspetti.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        여러 개의 파일과 디렉토리로 구성된 복잡한 플러그인은 포함된
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> 파일이나 <filename>README</filename>
        파일을 읽어보고 따라해야 합니다.  해당 파일이 없으면 그냥 휴지통으로
        던져버리고 다른 일을 하는 것이 낫습니다. 사용자를 고려하지 않은 채
        작성된 플러그인은 골치만 아플 것이 뻔하기 때문입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Bij de uitgebreide uitbreidingen met verschillende codebestanden in
        een eigen map zou er een bestand genaamd <filename>INSTALL</filename>
        of <filename>README</filename> moeten bestaan met daarin aanwijzingen
        over het hoe en wat van de uitbreiding. Als dit niet het geval is kunt
        u maar beter deze code verwijderen en uw tijd ergens anders voor
        gebruiken: iedere code waarbij er zo weinig rekening met de gebruiker
        gehouden is, levert geheid op talloze manieren enorm veel fustratie op.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        For meir komplekse programtillegg skal det ein eller annan stad i
        mappa finnast ei <quote>install</quote> eller <quote>readme</quote>
        fil med nødvendige instruksjonar. Dersom du ikkje finn desse
        forklaringane, er det betre å gi blaffen i heile programmet. Ein
        kode som er skriven heilt utan omtanke for andre brukarar, vil ofte
        gi deg myriadar av frustrasjonar uansett.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Для более сложных плагинов, организованных как каталог с множеством
        файлов, вероятно должен находится  файл с именем
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> или <filename>README</filename>,
        содержащий инструкции. Если такого файла нет, наилучшим советом
        является выбрасывание этого плагина  на помойку, и растратой вашего
        времени на  что-нибудь другое: любой код, написанный с такой малой
        заботой о пользователе вероятно разочаровывает бесчисленное количество
        раз.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        对于包装成一个目录的复杂些的插件，一般其中都有 <filename>INSTALL</filename> 或 <filename>README</filename> 这两个文件，其中有安装指令。如果没有，最好将这些插件放入回收站而把时间花在另外的上面：这种毫不关心用户的代码将使人感到非常沮丧。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        Some plugins (specifically those based on the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        Plugin Template) are designed to be installed in the main system
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory, rather than your home directory.
        For these, you will need to be root to perform the final stage of
        installation (when issuing the <command>make install</command>
        command).
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Některé zásuvné moduly (zejména ty založené na oficiální předloze –
        <emphasis><acronym>GIMP</acronym> Plugin Template</emphasis>) jsou
        navrženy pro instalaci do hlavního adresáře Gimpu, nikoliv do
        uživatelského adresáře. V jejich případě potřebujete pro konečnou fázi
        (<command>make install</command>) instalace rootovská práva.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Einige Plugins (insbesondere diejenigen, die auf der
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Pluginschablone basieren) sind so entworfen,
        dass sie im <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Hauptverzeichnis statt in
        Ihren persönlichem Verzeichnis installiert werden. Bei diesen müssen
        Sie den letzten Installationsschritt (also den Befehl <command>make
          install</command>) als root ausführen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Algunos complementos (especialmente aquellos basados en la plantilla
        de complementos del GIMP, GIMP Plugin Template) están diseñados para
        ser instalados en el sistema, en vez de en su directorio personal.
        Para estos, necesita tener privilegios de root para realizar la última
        etapa de instalación (al ejecutar el comando <command>make
        install</command>).
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Certains greffons (et plus spécialement ceux basé sur le modèle des
        greffons de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>) sont prévus pour être installés
        dans le répertoire principal de <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, plutôt que
        dans votre répertoire personnel. Pour ceux-là, il vous faudra avoir les
        droits d'administrateur (root) pour lancer la dernière étape de
        l'installation (<command>make install</command>).
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Alcuni plugin (in special modo quelli basati sul modello dei plugin di
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>) sono progettati per essere installati nella
        cartella di sistema principale di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> piuttosto
        che nella propria cartella home. Per questi è necessario assumere
        l'identità dell'amministratore (root) per eseguire lo stadio finale
        dell'installazione (<command>make install</command>).
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <acronym>김프</acronym> 플러그인 템플릿을 기초로 한 일부
        플러그인들은 사용자 디렉토리가 아닌 <acronym>김프</acronym> 시스템
        디렉토리에 설치되도록 설계되어 있습니다. 이럴 경우에는 루트
        권한으로 <quote>make install</quote> 을 실행해야 합니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Sommige uitbreidingen (in het bijzonder degenen die met behulp van het
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Pluging sjabloon zijn gemaakt) zijn ontworpen
        om in de centrale systeemmap van <acronym>GIMP</acronym> geïnstalleerd
        te worden in plaats van in uw gebruikersmap. Om dit voor elkaar te
        krijgen moet u tegen het einde van de installatie (bij het geven van
        het <command>make install</command> commando) systeembeheerdersrechten
        hebben.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Noen programtillegg, spesielt slike som er baserte på GIMP Plugin
        Template, er laga for å bli installerte i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        si hovudsystemmappe i staden for i ei privat mappe. For å
        installera desse må du vere administrator (root) for å få lov til å
        installera programmet (<quote>make install</quote>).
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Некоторые плагины (особенно те, которые основаны на  шаблоне плагина
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>) предназначены для установки  в основную
        системную директорию <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, вместо вашей  домашней
        директории. Для таких вам будут нужны  права администратора, чтобы
        выполнить последнюю стадию установки (<command>make install</command>).
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        一些插件(特别是那些基于 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 插件模板的)被设计为安装到 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 主系统目录中，而不是您个用户目录下。这时，您需要变为 root 来完成安装的最后一步(<command>make install</command>)。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        If you install in your personal plugin directory a plugin that has the
        same name as one in the system plugin directory, only one can be
        loaded, and it will be the one in your home directory. You will
        receive messages telling you this each time you start
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. This is probably a situation best avoided.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pokud do svého osobního adresáře pro zásuvné moduly nainstalujete
        modul, který se jmenuje stejně, jako některý z modulů v systémovém
        adresáři, nahraje se pouze jeden z nich, a to ten, který je ve vašem
        osobním adresáři. Při každém spouštění Gimpu na to budete
        upozorňování. Je lépe se takové situaci vyhýbat.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie eine Erweiterung in Ihrem persönlichen Pluginverzeichnis
        installieren, die den selben Namen wie eine Erweiterung aus dem
        Systemverzeichnis hat, kann nur eine davon geladen werden. Priorität
        genießt in diesem Fall diejenige, die in Ihrem persönlichen
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Verzeichnis. Sie werden jedoch jedesmal, wenn
        Sie <acronym>GIMP</acronym> starten, eine entsprechende Meldung
        bekommen.  Das Beste ist, eine solche Situation ganz zu vermeiden und
        immer schön Ordnung in den Plugins zu halten.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Si instala un complemento en su directorio personal que tiene el mismo
        nombre que uno de los complementos instalados en el sistema, sólo uno
        puede ser cargado, y se tratará del que se encuentra en su directorio.
        Recibirá un mensaje comunicándole que ha sucedido esto.  Lo mejor es
        evitar esta situación.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Si vous installez dans votre répertoire de greffons personnels un
        greffon ayant le même nom que l'un du répertoires des greffons du
        système, seul celui de votre répertoire sera chargé.  Vous aurez des
        messages vous en informant chaque fois que vous lancerez
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. C'est probablement une situation à éviter.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Se si installa un plugin nella propria cartella personale che ha lo
        stesso nome di una cartella plugin di sistema, solo una viene presa in
        considerazione e caricata; quella nella cartella personale. Si
        riceverà un messaggio di avvertimento a questo proposito ad ogni avvio
        di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Di solito è meglio evitare questa
        eventualità.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        동일한 이름을 가진 플러그인이 시스템 플러그인 디렉토리와 사용자
        플러그인 디렉토리에 동시에 설치되어 있을 경우
        <acronym>김프</acronym>는 사용자 디렉토리에 있는 플러그인만을
        읽어들이며, <acronym>김프</acronym>를 시작할 때마다 그 사실을
        통보해 줍니다. 이는 플러그인 간의 충돌을 피하기에 좋은 방법입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Als u in uw persoonlijke <quote>plugin</quote>-map een uitbreiding met
        dezelfde naam als een in de systeem <quote>plugin</quote>-map
        installeerd, kan slechts één van deze twee geladen worden.  Dit zal
        dan degene in uw persoonlijke map zijn. Dit wordt echter wel iedere
        keer extra gemeld bij het opstarten van <acronym>GIMP</acronym> en
        deze situatie kan eigenlijk het beste vermeden worden.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Har du eit programtillegg i den private mappa di med same namnet som
        eit anna programtillegg i hovudmappa, vil bare programmet i hovudmappa
        bli lasta inn. Kvar gong du startar <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
        vil du få melding om at det finst fleire program med same namnet.
        Dette bør du sjølvsagt unngå.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Если вы установите в вашу персональную директорию плагин с таким же
        именем, как и в системной директории,  будет загружен только один, и
        это будет расположенный  в вашей домашней директории. Вы будете
        получать  сообщения об этом при каждом запуске
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Такой ситуации лучше избегать.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        如果安装在个人插件目录中插件和在系统插件目录中的有相同的名字，就只有一个被载入，那就是在您用户目录中的。当您每次启动<acronym>GIMP</acronym>时，您都会收到消息告知您这些。因此可能最好要避免这种情况发生。
      </para>
    </sect3>


    <sect3>
      <title lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">Windows</title>

      <para lang="en">
        Windows is a much more problematic environment for building software
        than Linux. Every decent Linux distribution comes fully supplied with
        tools for compiling software, and they are all very similar in the way
        they work, but Windows does not come with such tools. It is possible
        to set up a good software-building environment in Windows, but it
        requires either a substantial amount of money or a substantial amount
        of effort and knowledge.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Windows jsou pro tvorbu programů ve srovnání s Linuxem velmi nešikovný
        systém. Každá slušná linuxová distribuce je perfektně vybavena všemi
        nástroji potřebnými pro překládání programů, ale Windows tak vybaveny
        nejsou. I ve Windows je možné vytvořit vhodné prostředí pro tvorbu
        software, ale vyžaduje to buď mnoho peněz nebo mnoho vědomostí a pevné
        nervy.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Windows ist für die Programmentwicklung eine sehr viel
        problematischere Umgebung als Linux. Jede ordentliche
        Linuxdistribution enthält sämtliche Werkzeuge, um Software zu
        übersetzen, und sie sind sich in ihrer Arbeitsweise alle sehr ähnlich,
        aber solche Werkzeuge sind bei Windows nicht dabei. Es ist zwar
        möglich, eine gute Programmentwicklungs-Umgebung unter Windows
        aufzusetzen, aber dazu benötigt man entweder genügend Geld oder sehr
        viel Anstrengungen und Wissen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        El entorno Windows es mucho más problemático que Linux para compilar
        software.  Todas las distribuciones decentes de Linux traen todas las
        herramientas necesarias para la compilación, y todas trabajan de
        manera muy similar.  Pero Windows no viene con estas herramientas.  Es
        posible establecer un buen entorno de compilación de software en
        Windows, pero requiere una cantidad sustancial de dinero, o una
        cantidad sustancial de esfuerzo y conocimiento.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Windows est un environnement plus problématique que Linux pour la
        construction de logiciels. Toute distribution décente de Linux inclut
        tous les outils nécessaires à la compilation de logiciels, et ils
        ont tous un mode de fonctionnement similaire, mais Windows n'offre pas
        de tels outils. Il est possible de configurer un bon environnement de
        développement sous Windows, mais cela nécessite une bonne quantité
        d'argent ou de connaissances et d'efforts.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Windows è un ambiente molto più problematico di Linux per compilare
        il software. Ogni distribuzione Linux che si rispetti è corredata
        da tutti gli strumenti necessari per compilare ed essi sono tutti
        dal funzionamento molte simile; invece Windows è sprovvisto di tali
        strumenti. È comunque possibile impostare tale ambiente anche in
        Windows ma richiede un notevole quantitativo di soldi o di tempo ed
        esperienza.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        윈도우즈에서는 리눅스보다 복잡한 프로그램 개발 환경을 필요로
        합니다. 최신의 모든 리눅스 배포판은 프로그램 컴파일을 위한 각종
        도구들을 지원하며, 대부분이 비슷하게 동작합니다. 하지만 윈도우즈는
        그렇지 않은 까닭에 적절한 프로그램 개발 환경을 구축하려면 상당한
        비용이나 지식과 노력이 필요합니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        In <acronym>Windows</acronym> is het nu eenmaal moeilijker om zelf
        software te bouwen dan in <acronym>Linux</acronym>. In iedere
        gangbare <acronym>Linux</acronym>-distributie worden
        ontwikkelgereedschappen meegeleverd en deze werken veelal op een sterk
        vergelijkbare (standaard) manier. Het is wel mogelijk een goede
        ontwikkelomgeving in <acronym>Windows</acronym> op te zetten, dit kost
        echter wel een behoorlijke som geld of een hele hoop kennis en
        moeite.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Windows er mykje meir problematisk enn Linux med omsyn til å lage og
        legge inn ny programvare. Alle utgåver av Linux blir leverte med
        verktøy for å kompilere programvare. I Windows finst det ikkje slike
        hjelpemiddel. Det er råd å installera gode program for å lage program
        også i Windows, men det krev anten tilgang til uhorvelege pengemengder
        eller tilsvarande mengder med tålmod og kunnskap.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Windows представляет собой намного более проблематичное окружение для
        сборки программного обеспечения чем Linux. Каждый порядочный
        дистрибутив Linux полностью укомплектован инструментами для компиляции
        программ, и все они работают очень схожими способами, но Windows в
        своей поставке не содержит таковых инструментов. Можно создать хорошее
        окружение для сборки программного обеспечения и в Windows, но это
        требует значительного количества денег или значительного количества
        попыток и знаний.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        Windows 是一个在编软件方面比 Linux 更难捉摸的环境。现在每个 Linux 发行版本提供完整的编译软件工具，而且它们运作的方式也差不多。但是 Windows 并步附带这些工具。虽然有可能在 Windows 中建立一个很好编软件的环境，但是需要要么有足够的金钱，要么有大量的知识并耗费相当的精力。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        What this means in relation to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> plugins is the
        following: either you have an environment in which you can build
        software, or you don't. If you don't, then your best hope is to find a
        precompiled version of the plugin somewhere (or persuade somebody to
        compile it for you), in which case you simply need to put it into your
        personal plugin directory. If you do have an environment in which you
        can build software (which for present purposes means an environment in
        which you can build <acronym>GIMP</acronym>), then you no doubt
        already know quite a bit about these things, and just need to follow
        the Linux instructions.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        V případě zásuvných modulů do Gimpu to znamená následující: buď vhodné
        prostředí pro tvorbu software máte, nebo nikoliv. Pokud ne, nejlépe je
        sehnat již přeloženou verzi modulu či přemluvit někoho zkušeného, aby
        vám ji vytvořil. Takový hotový modul prostě jen vhodťte do adresáře
        pro zásuvné moduly. Pokud máte ve Windows vhodné prostředí pro tvorbu
        software, pravděpodobně s ním umíte zacházet. Postupujte pak podle
        linuxových instrukcí.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        In Bezug auf <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Plugins bedeutet das folgendes:
        entweder haben Sie eine Umgebung, in der Sie Software entwickeln
        können, oder Sie haben Sie nicht. Wenn nicht, dann besteht Ihre beste
        Hoffnung darin, irgendwo eine bereits übersetzte Version der
        Erweiterung zu finden (oder jemanden dazu zu überreden, sie für Sie
        zu übersetzen). In diesem Fall müssen Sie sie nur in Ihren
        persönlichen Pluginordner kopieren. Wenn Sie eine Umgebung haben,
        um Software zu entwickeln (also eine Umgebung, in der Sie
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> übersetzen können), dann haben Sie
        zweifellos schon etwas Vorwissen und können einfach den
        Instruktionen für Linux folgen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Lo que esto significa en relación a los complementos del GIMP es lo
        siguiente: Ud. posee un entorno en el cual puede construir software, o
        no lo posee.  Si no lo posee, tenga la esperanza de encontrar una
        versión precompilada en algún sitio (o persuada a alguien para que lo
        compile por Ud.), en cuyo caso simplemente necesita colocarlo en su
        directorio personal para complementos.  Si Ud. sí tiene dicho entorno
        (lo que además significa que puede compilar el GIMP), entonces
        seguramente tiene el conocimiento suficiente y puede seguir las
        instrucciones para Linux.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour en revenir au greffon de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> soit vous avez
        de quoi compiler, soit vous ne pouvez pas. Si vous ne pouvez pas, il
        vous faudra trouver une version compilée du greffon (ou bien demander
        à quelqu'un de le compiler pour vous) que vous n'aurez qu'à mettre
        dans votre répertoire de greffon personnel. Si vous pouvez compiler
        (en l'occurrence si votre environnement vous permet de compiler
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>), alors vous devez sans doute être au fait de
        ces choses et vous n'avez plus qu'à suivre les instructions données
        pour Linux.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Il significato di ciò in relazione a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è che o
        si ha un ambiente nel quale è possibile compilare del software oppure
        no. Se è impossibile, la nostra speranza è di trovare da qualche parte
        una versione precompilata (o convincere qualcuno a compilarla per
        noi); in tal caso basta sistemare il plugin nella nostra cartella
        personale dei plugin. Se si ha un ambiente predisposto alla
        compilazione di software (che significa nel nostro caso un ambiente
        nel quale è possibile compilare <acronym>GIMP</acronym>) è possibile
        che già si sia abbastanza esperti sulla compilazione da poter seguire
        le istruzioni apposite.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        만약 프로그램을 개발할 수 있는 환경을 갖추지 못했다면, 이미
        컴파일된 플러그인을 구하거나 컴파일해줄 누군가를 찾는 것이 낫습니다.
        그러면 그저 사용자 디렉토리로 옮겨주는 것만으로 플러그인을 사용할
        수 있습니다. 혹 <acronym>김프</acronym>를 컴파일할 수 있을 정도의
        프로그램 개발 환경을 갖추고 있다면, 주저할 것 없이 리눅스 명령을
        따라하면 됩니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Voor de  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uitbreidingen betekend dat dat er
        alleen twee extreem verschillende situaties bestaan: U heeft al dan
        niet de beschikking over een omgeving waarin u programmatuur kunt
        bouwen. Indien niet, bent u aangewezen op voorgecompileerde
        uitbreidingen (of moet u iemand zien te vinden die ze voor u comileren
        wil) als u deze vinden kunt hoeft u deze alleen maar in uw
        persoonlijke <quote>plugin</quote> map te zetten. Als u reeds over een
        omgeving beschikt waarin u de programmacode kunt compileren beschikt u
        hoogstwaarschijnlijk reeds over uitgebreide ervaring in deze zaken en
        kunt u waarschijnlijk goed met de <acronym>Linux</acronym>
        aanwijzingen uit de voeten.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dette betyr i praksis, i høve til programtillegga for
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, at anten så har du utstyr som du kan setje
        opp programvaren med, eller så har du det ikkje. I det siste
        tilfellet den einaste utvegen å finne ei ferdigkompilert utgåve av
        programmet, eller få noen til å gjere det for deg. Er du så heldig,
        er det bare å legge det inn i den private mappa di for programtillegg.
        Dersom du skulle ha program for å lage Windows-program for
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, veit du truleg såpass mykje om desse tinga at
        du lett kan følgje instruksjonane for Linux.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Это означает применительно к плагинам <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        следующее:  или вы имеете окружение в котором можете собирать
        программы, или нет.  Если такой возможности нет, тогда  лучше
        надейтесь найти где-нибудь откомпилированную  версию плагина (или
        уговорить кого-нибудь  скомпилировать его для вас.), в этом случае вам
        необходимо просто положить его в вашу персональную  директорию
        плагинов. Если у вас есть окружение в котором  вы можете собирать
        программы (что в данной случае  означает окружение, в котором вы
        можете собрать <acronym>GIMP</acronym>),  тогда вы без сомнения уже
        знаете немного об этих вещах,  и вам нужно просто следовать
        инструкциям Linux.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        在关于 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 插件中，意味着：要么您有编软件的环境，要么没有。如果没有，最好希望能找到在某处找到一个已经编译好的版本(或说服某人帮您编译)，然后您只需要简单地把其放到您的个人插件目录下。如果您确实有编软件地环境(这里是指您能编译 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>),也就是说您毫无疑问已经知道不少这方面的东西了，所以只需要跟着 Linux 的指令做。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        If you would like to set up a build environment, and are ready for the
        heroism involved, you can find a reasonably recent description of how
        to go about it in the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Wiki, at
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Since it is a Wiki, anybody is free to edit it, so please keep it up
        to date by adding advice based on your own experiences.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pokud si chcete prostředí pro překlad Gimpu a jeho zásuvných modulů ve
        Windows vytvořit, a máte skutečně odvahu k tak hrdinskému činu,
        najdete víceméně aktuální popis v gimpí wiki na stránce
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Je to wiki, kterou může
        kdokoliv upravovat, proto prosím připište své zkušenosti, pokud
        myslíte, že mohou být ostatním užitečné.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie genügend Wagemut besitzen und eine Entwicklungsumgebung
        aufsetzen wollen, können Sie eine hinreichend aktuelle Beschreibung
        dazu im <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Wiki unter
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows <xref
        linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows" /> finden.
        Da es ein Wiki ist, ist jedem freigestellt, den Text zu bearbeiten.
        Also halten Sie ihn ruhig aktuell, indem Sie auf Ihren Erfahrungen
        basierende Hinweise ergänzen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Si desea establecer un entorno de compilación, y se cree capaz del
        heroísmo que esto involucra, puede hallar una descripción bastante
        decente de cómo hacerlo en el wiki del GIMP, en
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Como se encuentra en un
        wiki, cualquiera lo puede editar, así que siéntase libre de mantenerlo
        actualizado agregando consejos basados en su propia experiencia.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Si vous voulez vous lancez dans l'aventure de la compilation de GIMP
        sous Windows, vous trouverez la description la plus récente du
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows" />
        (en Anglais). Comme il s'agit d'un Wiki, tout le monde peut librement
        le compléter, aussi, s'il vous plaît, tenez-le à jour en y ajoutant
        vos conseils tirés de votre expérience (ou de vos expériences!).
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Se si desidera impostare un ambiente per la compilazione e si è
        disposti all'eroismo che ne consegue, è possibile trovare una
        descrizione ragionevolmente recente su come fare quest'operazione
        nel Wiki di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, su
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Dato che è un wiki,
        tutti sono liberi di modificarlo, perciò sentitevi liberi di
        aggiornarlo inserendo le vostre esperienze.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        만일 충만한 도전 정신으로 직접 개발 환경을 구축하고자 한다면, 김프
        위키의 다음 페이지를 참고하세요. HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>
        위키는 모든 사용자가 편집할 수 있으므로, 직접 하면서 얻은 팁이나
        조언을 추가해 주시기 바랍니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Als u resoluut genoeg bent en genoeg moed heeft om uw eigen
        <acronym>Windows</acronym>-ontwikkelomgeving op te zetten, kunt u een
        redelijk recente beschrijving hierover in de
        <acronym>GIMP-Wiki</acronym> vinden op:
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Omdat dit een
        <acronym>Wiki</acronym> is, kan iedereen hier wijzigingen op
        aanbrengen. Dus als u nieuwe ervaringen in dit proces opdoet, bent u
        van harte uitgenodigd deze te delen door adviezen op deze webstek in
        te voeren.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dersom du ønskjer å setje opp alt frå grunnen av, og er klar for
        berømminga dette fører med seg, kan du finne brukbare oppskrifter i
        GIMP Wiki på HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>.
        Sidan dette er ein Wiki,
        er det ope for alle å gjere endringar. Difor bør du i tilfelle vere
        med på å halde opplysningane oppdaterte ved at du fører inn eigne
        røynsler.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Если вы желаете настроить окружение для сборки, и готовы к героическим
        поступкам, можете найти достаточно недавнее описание этих действий на
        странице GIMP Wiki HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows" />.
        Поскольку это Wiki, кто угодно может его править, поэтому
        пожалуйста, поддержите эту страницу добавлением совета, основанном на
        вашем собственном опыте.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        如果您想建立一个编软件环境，并准备无所畏惧地投入其中，您可以在
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Wiki 中找到一个适当的当前关于如何开始的介绍
        HowToCompileGimp/MicrosoftWindows
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-wiki-compile-windows"/>
        。由于这是个 Wiki,任何人都可以编辑它，所以请添加基于您自己经验的建议，以便让它保持最新。
      </para>
    </sect3>


    <!-- TODO: cs es it ko zh_CN translation missing here -->
    <sect3>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">Apple Mac OS X</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">애플 맥 OS X(Apple Mac OS X)</phrase>
      </title>

      <para lang="en">
        How you install plugins on OS X mostly depends on how you installed
        GIMP itself. If you were one of the brave and installed GIMP
        through one of the package managers like fink
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-darwinports"/> or darwinports,
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-fink"/> the
        plugin installation works exactly the way it is described for the
        Linux platform already. The only difference is, that a couple of
        plugins might be even available in the repository of you package
        manager, so give it a try.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        If you on the other hand are one of the Users that preferred to grab a
        prebuild GIMP package like GIMP.app, you most probably want to stick
        to that prebuild stuff. So you can try to get a prebuild version of
        the plugin of you dreams from the author of the plugin, but I'd not
        want to bet on this. Building your own binaries unfortunately involves
        installing GIMP through one of the package managers mentioned above.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">Tato část vyžaduje doplnění.</para>

      <para lang="de">
        Die Art und Weise, in der Sie Plugins für GIMP auf Ihrem Mac
        installieren können, hängt im Wesentlichen davon ab, wie Sie GIMP
        selbst installiert haben. Wenn Sie zu den Mutigen gehört haben, die
        ihr GIMP mittels eines Paketmanagers wie
        <application>Fink</application>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-fink"/> oder
        <application>Darwinports</application>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-darwinports"/> installiert haben,
        erfolgt die Übersetzung und Installation von Plugins genau nach der im
        Abschnitt für Linux beschriebenen Vorgehensweise. Einige wenige
        Plugins sind sogar direkt über die verschiedenen Paketmanager
        verfügbar, ein Blick auf die aktuell verfügbaren Pakete kann sich also
        durchaus lohnen.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Sollten Sie hingegen zu der Gruppe von Mac-Benutzern gehören, welche
        GIMP als vorgefertigte Anwendung, wie beispielsweise GIMP.app,
        installiert hat, so werden Sie vermutlich auch die Plugins nicht
        selbst übersetzen und installieren wollen. Sie können im Gegenzug
        versuchen, eine vorgefertigte Version des Plugins für OS X im Web oder
        beim Autor zu bekommen, allerdings stehen Ihre Chancen hierbei nicht
        sonderlich gut. Die Plugins selbst zu übersetzen beinhaltet
        unglücklicherweise auch die Installation von GIMP über einen der oben
        genannten Paketmanager. Aber es kann ja nie schaden, sich ein bisschen
        mit der Software zu beschäftigen, die man auf seinem Rechner hat.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">Todavía no hay contribuciones para esta parte.</para>

      <para lang="fr">
        La façon d'installer des greffons sur un système X dépend de la
        façon dont vous avez installé GIMP lui-même. Si vous êtes un des
        courageux qui a installé GIMP au moyen d'un des gestionnaires de
        paquetages comme fink
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-fink"/> ou darwinports,
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-darwinports"/>, l'installation se
        fait comme il a été dit pour Linux. La seule différence est que
        certains greffons peuvent même être présents dans le dépot central de
        votre gestionnaire de paquetage : essayez-les.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Si vous êtes de ceux qui préfèrent utiliser un paquetage précompilé
        tel que GIMP.app, vous voudrez certainement vous en tenir à ce
        paquetage. Vous pouvez essayer d'obtenir de l'auteur le greffon
        précompilé de vos rêves mais je ne parierai pas sur le résultat.
        Produire vos propres binaires nécessite malheureusement de recourir
        aux gestionnaires de paquetage ci-dessus mentionnés.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Prego contribuite con del materiale a questa voce!
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        OS X 에 플러그인을 설치하는 방법은 김프를 설치한 방법에 따라
        달라집니다. 만약 fink <xref linkend="bibliography-online-darwinports"/>
        나 darwinports <xref linkend="bibliography-online-fink"/>같은
        패키지 매니저를 통해 김프를 설치했다면, 플러그인을 리눅스와 같은
        방법으로 설치할 수 있습니다. 리눅스와의 차이점이라면, 패키지
        매니저의 저장소에서만 플러그인을 사용할 수 있다라는 점입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        아니면 GIMP.app 와 같이 GIMP 패키지를 제공하는 사이트를 통해 김프를
        설치했다면, 미리 만들어진 플러그인 다운로드 받아 사용할 수 있습니다.
        하지만 미리 만들어진 플러그인을 항상 구할 수 있는 것은 아니며, 직접
        플러그인을 컴파일하기 위해 앞서 언급된 패키지 매니저를 통해 김프를
        설치해야 하는 일이 발생할 수도 있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">Hier kunnen we wel wat meer informatie gebruiken.</para>
      <para lang="no">Manglar kunnskap. Kan noen skrive denne?</para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Как вы устанавливаете плагины на OS X зависит в большей степени от
        того, как вы установили сам <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Если вы установили
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> через
        управляющего пакетами <quote>darwinports</quote>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-darwinports"/> или
        <quote>fink</quote> <xref linkend="bibliography-online-fink"/>, то
        установление плагинов происходит так же, как было описано для Linux.
        Единственное отличие может быть в том, что список самого управляющего
        может содержать эти плагины. Так что вы можете установить плагины из
        него.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Если же вы предпочитаете уже упакованный пакет <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
        то лучше придерживаться этого пути и с плагинами. Постарайтесь получить
        преупакованный пакет <acronym>GIMP</acronym> и интересующим вас плагином
        от его автора.
        Это не всегда получается, но в противном случае создание своего пакета
        требует работы с вышеуказанными управляющими.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">我们可以使用这儿的一些材料。</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="plugins-write">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Writing Plugins</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Psaní vlastních zásuvných modulů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Plugins schreiben</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Creación de complementos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Écrire des greffons</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Scrittura dei plugin</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">플러그인 작성하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Uitbreidingen maken</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å skrive programtillegg</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Написание плагинов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">写插件</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Plugins</primary><secondary>Write</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de">
      <primary>Plugin</primary><secondary>programmieren</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Greffons</primary><secondary>Écrire</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>플러그인</primary><secondary>작성하기</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      If you want to learn how to write a plugin, you can find plenty of help
      at the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Developers web site
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a complex
      program, but the development team has made strenuous efforts to flatten
      the learning curve for plugin writing:  there are good instructions and
      examples, and the main library that plugins use to interface with
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (called <quote>libgimp</quote>) has a
      well-documented <acronym>API</acronym>.  Good programmers, learning by
      modifying existing plugins, are often able to accomplish interesting
      things after just a couple of days of work.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Pokud se chcete naučit psát své vlastní zásuvné moduly, najdete
      užitečnou pomoc na vývojářském webu Gimpu
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> je velmi složitý
      program, vývojáři však učinili všechno proto, aby bylo psaní zásuvných
      modulů co nejjednodušší.  Na webu najdete dobře napsané instrukce a
      příklady a hlavní knihovna, kterou zásuvné moduly používají pro
      komunikaci s Gimpem (libgimp) má dobře dokumentované programovací
      aplikační rozhraní (<acronym>API</acronym>). Dobří programátoři jsou
      schopni vytvořit zajímavé moduly již po několika dnech učení a práce.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie lernen möchten, wie man eine Erweiterung schreibt, können Sie
      reichlich Hilfestellungen auf der GIMP-Entwicklerwebseite
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/> finden.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ist ein komplexes Programm, aber das
      Entwicklerteam hat erhebliche Anstrengungen unternommen, die Lernkurve
      fürs Schreiben von Plugins flach zu halten. Es gibt ausgezeichnete
      Unterweisungen und Beispiele, und die Programmbibliothek, die Plugins
      zur Kommunikation mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> verwenden
      (<quote>libgimp</quote>), besitzt eine gut dokumentierte Schnittstelle
      (<acronym>API</acronym>). Gute Programmierer, die dadurch lernen, dass
      sie vorhandene Erweiterung modifizieren, sind oft schon nach wenigen
      Tagen in der Lage, erstaunliche Dinge zu erreichen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Si desea aprender a escribir complementos, puede hallar mucha ayuda en
      el sitio web de los desarrolladores del GIMP
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      El GIMP es un programa complejo, pero los
      desarrolladores han hecho un gran esfuerzo para que la curva de
      aprendizaje sea suave, especialmente para la codificación de
      complementos.  Hay muy buenas instrucciones y ejemplos, y la biblioteca
      principal que emplean los complementos como interfaz con el GIMP
      (llamada <quote>libgimp</quote>) cuenta con una API muy bien
      documentada.  Los buenos programadores, que aprenden modificando los
      complementos existentes, llegan a lograr cosas interesantes en unos
      pocos días de trabajo.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Si vous voulez apprendre comment écrire un greffon, vous trouverez de
      l'aide sur le site des développeurs du <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>
      (en anglais). <acronym>GIMP</acronym> est un programme complexe, mais
      l'équipe de développement a fait d'ardents efforts pour faciliter
      l'apprentissage de l'écriture des greffons : de bonnes instructions, des
      exemples et la principale bibliothèque que les  greffons utilisent comme
      interface avec <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (appelée <quote>libgimp </quote>)
      a une <acronym>API</acronym> très bien documentée. Les bons
      programmeurs, qui apprennent en modifiant les greffons existants,
      peuvent accomplir des choses intéressantes après quelques jours de
      travail.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se si desidera imparare a scrivere un plugin, è possibile trovare aiuto
      sul sito degli sviluppatori di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è un programma
      complesso ma il gruppo di sviluppo ha fatto un grande sforzo per
      abbassare la curva di apprendimento per la scrittura di plugin: ci sono
      buone istruzioni ed esempi e la libreria principale che i plugin usano
      per collegarsi con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (chiamata <quote>libgimp
      </quote>) possiede un'<acronym>API</acronym> ben documentata. I bravi
      programmatori, imparando modificando plugin esistenti, sono spesso in
      grado di ottenere dei buoni risultati in appena in un paio di giorni di
      lavoro.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      플러그인을 작성하는 법을 배우고 싶다면, <acronym>김프</acronym>
      개발자 사이트인 <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>
      에서 많은 도움을 얻을 수 있을 것입니다. <acronym>김프</acronym>는
      복잡한 프로그램이지만 개발팀의 노력으로 쉽게 플러그인을 작성할 수
      있게 되었습니다. 많은 과정안내와 예제가 있고, 플러그인들에 사용되는
      주요 라이브러리(<quote>libgimp</quote>)는 문서화가 잘된
      <acronym>API</acronym> 를 가지고 있으므로, 기존의 플러그인을 수정해
      사용해본 프로그래머라면 곧 익숙해질 것입니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Als u wilt leren hoe u een uitbreiding (<quote>plugin</quote>) kunt
      schrijven, kunt u veel (engelstalige) hulp op de
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-ontwikkelaars webstek vinden
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is een ingewikkeld
      programma, maar het team van ontwikkelaars heeft zware inspanningen
      verricht om de leercurve af te vlakken: Er zijn goede instructies en
      voorbeelden en de funcie-bibliotheek die de uitbreidingen gebruiken om
      met het hoofdprogramma te communiceren en samen te werken
      (<quote>libgimp</quote> genaamd) heeft een goed gedocumenteerde
      <acronym>API</acronym>. Goede programmeurs, die ervaringen opdoen door
      in bestaande uitbreidingen wijzigingen aan te brengen, kunnen vaak al
      binnen enkele dagen interressante dingen verwezenlijken.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Har du ønskje om å lære å skrive programtillegg, kan du finne mykje
      hjelp på utviklingssidene til <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er eit nokså
      komplisert program, men utviklarane har lagt mykje arbeid i å flate
      ut læringskurva for å lage programtillegg. Du finn fyldige
      instruksjonar og gode eksempel på dei nemnde sidene. Hovudbiblioteket
      (<quote>libgimp</quote>) som programtillegga nyttar for å
      kommunisera med <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, er i tillegg veldokumentert.
      Ein mykje brukt måte for å lære seg programmeringa, er å modifisere
      eksisterande program. Dyktige programmerarar er dermed ofte i stand
      til å lage svært så interessante ting bare etter eit par netters arbeid.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Если вы желаете научиться написанию плагинов, вы можете найти
      исчерпывающую помощь на вебсайте разработчиков <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> это сложная
      программа, но команда разработчиков приложила усилия для сглаживания
      трудностей обучения написанию плагинов: доступны хорошие инструкции и
      примеры, и основная библиотека, используемая для взаимодействия с
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (именуемая <quote>libgimp </quote>) имеет хорошо
      документированный <acronym>API</acronym>. Хорошие программисты, обучаясь
      с помощью изменения существующих плагинов,  часто способны осуществить
      интресные вещи всего лишь  после пары дней работы.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      如果您想知道如何写插件，您能在 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 开发者网站上找到些有用的帮助
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev-plugin"/>.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      是一个复杂的程序，但是开发者团队作出了艰辛的工作使写插件的学习曲线变得平坦：许多好的步骤指令和范例
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 的主库作为其插件接口(叫
      <quote>libgimp</quote> )有一个拥有好的完整文档的 <acronym>API</acronym>
      。好的程序员，通过学习已有的插件，常常只需几天的工作就能完成一些很有趣的东西。
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
