<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--Section History
  2006-02-17: added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-01-07: Small revisions in the dutch text by HdJ
  2005-12-25: added german translation and made the file docbook compliant by lexa
  2005-12-09: tip changed according to GimpDocsWip-Errors in manual by j.h
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-window-qmask-button" lang="en;de;fr;nl;it;sv;zh_CN">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">QuickMask</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Schnelle Maske (QuickMask)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Masque rapide</phrase>
    <phrase lang="sv">Snabbmask</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Het Snelmasker</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Maschera veloce</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">快速蒙板</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en;de">
    <primary>QuickMask</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Schnelle Maske</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Auswahl</primary>
    <secondary>erstellen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Masque Rapide</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="sv">
    <primary>Snabbmask</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>Snelmasker</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Maschera veloce</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>快速蒙板</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;fr;sv;zh_CN">Image with QuickMask enabled</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Bild mit eingeschalteter <quote>Schneller Maske</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Immagine con la <quote>Maschera veloce</quote>
      abilitata</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">
        Afbeelding met het ingeschakelde <quote>Snelmasker</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;de;fr;nl;it;sv;zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">selection tools</link>
    sometimes show their limits when they have to be used for creating a
    complex selection. In these cases, using the QuickMask can make
    things much easier.  Simply put, the QuickMask allows you to paint a
    selection instead of just tracing its outline.                             
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die Schnelle Maske ist ein sehr hilfreiches Mittel, wenn Sie bei der
    Erstellung von Auswahlen mit den normalen
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">Auswahlwerkzeugen</link>
    nicht weiterkommen. Mit Hilfe der Schnellen Maske können Sie Auswahlen mit
    den Malwerkzeugen bearbeiten. Hierzu wird eine halbdurchsichtige,
    standardmäßig rot gefärbte, Maske über das Bild gelegt. An allen Stellen,
    an denen Sie die Maske entfernen, wird eine Auswahl erstellt.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Les <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">outils de sélection</link>
    montrent parfois leurs limites lorsqu'il s'agit de créer des
    sélections aux contours complexes, voir progressifs. Dans ce cas
    l'utilisation du Masque rapide s'avère particulièrement efficace.
  </para>
  <para lang="sv">
    Ibland visar <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">Markeringsverktygen</link>
    sina gränser för kompliserade målningar progressivt.
    Om detta är fallet, då är snabbmask en god idé att använda vilket
    kan ge goda resultat.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Gli <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">strumenti di selezione</link>
    alle volte mostrano i loro limiti quando vengono usati per creare una
    selezione complessa. In questi casi, usare la maschera veloce può
    semplificare molto la vita. In parole povere, la maschera veloce
    permette di disegnare una selezione invece di semplicemente delinearla.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    De <!--link linkend="gimp-tools-selection"XXX_NL-->selectie
    gereedschappen<!--/link--> laten soms de de grenzen van de selectie zien
    als er een ingewikkeld deel van de afbeelding geselecteerd is. In deze
    gevallen kan het gebruik van het snelmasker de zaken enigzins eenvoudiger
    maken. Eenvoudig gezegd, laat het SnelMasker u een selectie tekenen
    inplaats van alleen de buitenrand aan te geven.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">选择工具</link>在进行复杂图形选取时能力非常有限。在这种情况下，使用快速蒙板会使这一切变得简单。只需放上快速蒙板就让您可以在画出选区而不需要描出其轮廓线。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Überblick</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="sv">Översikt</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Overzicht</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">概述</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      Normally when you create a selection in GIMP, you see it represented by
      the "marching ants" that trace along its outline. But really there may
      be a lot more to a selection than the marching ants show you: in GIMP a
      selection is actually a full-fledged grayscale channel, covering the
      image, with pixel values ranging from 0 (unselected) to 255 (fully
      selected). The marching ants are drawn along a contour of half-selected
      pixels. Thus, what the marching ants show you as either-or–inside or
      outside the boundary–is really just a slice through a continuum.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie in GIMP eine Auswahl erstellen, wird diese normalerweise durch
      die <quote>marschierenden Ameisen</quote> markiert, die an der
      Auswahlkante <quote>entlang laufen</quote>. In Wirklichkeit ist eine
      Auswahl in GIMP wesentlich mehr, als das was diese Linie entlang der
      Auswahlkante zeigt. In GIMP ist eine Auswahl ein vollständiger Kanal,
      der 256 verschiedene Werte abbilden kann. Pixel dieses Kanals, welche
      den Wert 0 (Schwarz) haben, sind vollständig unausgewählt, Pixel mit dem
      Wert 255 (Weiss) hingegen vollständig ausgewählt. Dazwischen liegen
      eine ganze Reihe von Werten die als Graustufen im Kanal abgebildet
      werden und mit denen Sie eine weiche Auswahlkante erzeugen können. Die
      in der normalen Ansicht sichtbaren marschierenden Ameisen markieren
      dabei lediglich die Linie der Pixel, welche genau zur Hälfte ausgewählt
      sind. In Wirklichkeit sind Pixel nicht wirklich drin, oder draussen,
      sondern es kann eine unscharfe Übergangszone geben.  
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Normaal als u iets selecteerd in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zal er in de
      afbeelding een lijn met daarop schuivende lichte en donkere stukken
      verschijnen, de zogenaamde `marcherende mieren' om de selectie heen. 
      Het selecteren van delen van de afbeelding heeft echter stukken meer om
      het lijf dan deze bewegende lijn u laat zien. In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      is een selectie een volledig grijswaarden kanaal die over de hele
      afbeelding heenligt en de mate van geselecteerdheid van een beeldpunt
      aangeeft met een waarde tussen de 0(ongeselecteerd) en 255(volledig
      geselecteerd). De marcherende mierenlijn is getekent op de omtrek waar
      de beeldpunten voor de helft geselecteerd zijn. Dus de marcherende
      mieren laten een iets té eenvoudige situatie zien; een beeldpunt zit
      niet óf binnen óf buiten een selectie, maar de lijn van marcherende
      mieren is in werkelijkheid een bepaalde waarde aan in een verloop van
      geselecteerdheid.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Normalmente, quando si crea una selezione in GIMP, essa è visibile
      grazie al tratteggio tipo "formiche che camminano" delineato intorno
      alla zona. In realtà la selezione è molto più di un tratteggio
      lampeggiante: in GIMP una selezione è in realtà un canale in scala di
      grigi che ricopre l'immagine, con i valori dei punti che vanno da 0
      (non selezionato) a 255 (selezionato completamente); il tratteggio
      viene posto sopra il confine dei punti selezionati esattamente a
      metà. Perciò il tratteggio, separando una zona interna da una
      esterna, è realmente solo un limite posta sopra una zona continua.
    </para>


    <para lang="zh_CN">
      正常情况下，在 GIMP 创建一个选区时，它的外边缘标记好像是一群“行进中的蚂蚁”。但事实上它就创建了一个选区：GIMP 中的选区准确地说是在图像上完全独立的通道，其像素值从 0 (未选中)到 255 (全选中)。“行进中的蚂蚁”似的边缘占了半个像素。因此，“行进中的蚂蚁”显示给您的---在边界外或内---其实就是把连续区域分割开了。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      The QuickMask is GIMP's way of showing you the full structure of the
      selection. Activating it also gives you the ability to interact with the
      selection in new, and substantially more powerful, ways. To activate the
      QuickMask, click on the small red-outlined button at the lower left of
      the image window. The button is a toggle, so clicking it again will
      return you to normal marching-ant mode. You can also activate the
      QuickMask by selecting in the image window menu
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Toggle QuickMask</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>, or by using the
      <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>
      shortcut.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Mit der Schnellen Maske haben Sie nicht nur die Möglichkeit diesen
      unscharfen Übergangsbereich zu sehen, sondern Sie können diesen damit
      auch sehr einfach bearbeiten. Um die Schnelle Maske zu aktivieren
      gibt es eine Schaltfläche in der linken unteren Ecke des Bildfensters.
      Mit dieser können Sie die Schnelle Maske sehr einfach ein- und
      ausschalten. Alternativ können Sie auch den Menüeintrag
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>
          <accel>S</accel>chnelle Maske aktivieren/deaktivieren
        </guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>, oder das Tastenkürzel
      <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>
      verwenden.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour activer le Masque rapide cliquez sur le button en bas à
      gauche tel qu'indiqué en rouge dans la capture d'écran
      ci-dessus ou sélectionnez dans le menu d'image
      <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>élection/(Dés)Activer le mas
      <accel>q</accel>ue rapide</guimenuitem>.  Il peut aussi être
      activé à l'aide du raccourci clavier <keycap>Maj+Q</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Het Snelmasker is de wijze waarop <acronym>GIMP</acronym> u de volledige
      structuur van de selectie laat zien. Indien u het activeert kunt u op
      een aantal nieuwe geavanceerde manieren de selectie bewerken. Om het
      Snelmasker te activeren dient u de knop linksonder in te drukken waarbij
      de zwart-witte lijn van het vierkantje een ononderbroken rode lijn
      wordt. De knop is een schakelaar, dus door er weer een keer op te klikken
      wordt het vierkantje weer zwart-wit omlijnd en worden selecties weer met
      marcherende mierenlijnen weergegeven.
      Via de afbeeldingsmenubalk kunt u het snelmasker ook uit of aanschakelen
      via:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>S</accel>electeren</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>nelmasker schakelen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>, of met behulp van de
      <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>
      sneltoetscombinatie.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="sv">
      För att aktivera snabbmask, klicka på ikonen som visas i
      rött som skrämdumpen ovanför visar eller gå via
      bildfönstrets meny <guimenuitem><accel>V</accel>älj/Visa
      sna<accel>b</accel>bmask</guimenuitem>.  Det går även att
      aktivera snabbmask med snabbtangenterna
      <keycap>Skift+Q</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      La maschera veloce è il modo in GIMP per mostrare la completa
      struttura della selezione. Attivandola mette in condizione l'utente
      di interagire con la selezione in nuove e notevolmente più efficaci
      modalità. Per attivare la maschera veloce, fare clic sul piccolo
      pulsante bordato di rosso nell'angolo in basso a sinistra della
      finestra immagine. Il pulsante ha funzione di commutazione perciò se
      lo si preme nuovamente, si ritorna alla selezione normale. È
      possibile attivare la maschera veloce anche selezionando, dal menu immagine,
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Seleziona</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Copmmuta maschera veloce</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>, o usando la scorciatoia da tastiera
      <keycombo><keycap>Maiusc</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>
      .
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      快速蒙板是 GIMP 表示选区结构的方式。开启它也让您能够与选区通过新的和实质上更加强大的方式来交互。您可以通过点击图像窗口中左下角有红色外框的按钮来开启快速蒙板。该按钮是个开关，再点一下就让图像回到“行进中蚂蚁”的模式。也可以通过图像窗口菜单中的<guimenuitem>选择/切换快速蒙板</guimenuitem>或用快捷键 <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap> 开打开快速蒙板。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Activating the QuickMask shows you the selection as though it were a
      translucent screen overlying the image, whose transparency at each pixel
      indicates the degree to which that pixel is selected. By default the
      mask is shown in red, but you can change this if another mask color
      would be more convenient. The less a pixel is selected, the more it is
      obscured by the mask. Fully selected pixels are shown completely clear.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      In den Standardeinstellungen wird die Schnelle Maske als
      halbtransparente, rote Maske über das Bild gelegt. Sollten Sie die Farbe
      oder Transparenz der Maske ändern wollen, so können Sie dies über das
      Kommando <guimenuitem>Farbe und Deckkraft festlegen</guimenuitem>
      im Kontextmenü der Schaltfläche zur Aktivierung der Schnellen Maske tun.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Cette commande génère un canal temporaire 8-bit (0-255) sur lequel le
      travail de sélection progressivement établi est peu à peu enregistré. Si
      une sélection est déjà présente, le masque est initialisé avec le
      contenu de la sélection. Une fois le Masque Rapide activé, l'image est
      recouverte d'un voile rouge semi-transparent. Celui-ci représente les
      pixels non-sélectionnés de l'image. N'importe quel
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">outil de dessin</link>
      peut être utilisé pour modifier ce masque et créer la sélection
      résultante. Ces outils devraient être utilisés uniquement en niveaux de
      gris, conformément à la nature des canaux, le blanc permettant de
      définir la future zone à sélectionner. Cette sélection ne sera affichée
      que lorsque le Masque rapide sera desactivé. Mais à partir de ce moment,
      le canal temporaire est définitivement perdu et seul un retour immédiat
      au mode masque permet de la récupérer.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Als het Snelmasker aanstaat wordt de selectie weergegeven alsof er een
      doorzichtig scherm over de afbeelding heen gelegd is. de doorzichtigheid
      van dit scherm op ieder beeldpunt geeft aan hoe sterk dat punt
      geselecteerd is. Standaard heeft dit scherm, of masker, een rode kleur,
      maar dit kunt u ook veranderen als u vind dat dat beter werkt. Hoe
      minder een beeldpunt geselecteerd is des te meer bedekt het is door het
      masker: volledig geselecteerde beeldpunten worden in vol ornaat, helder
      weergegeven.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      L'attivazione della maschera veloce mostra la selezione come se ci
      fosse uno schermo traslucido posto sopra l'immagine, la trasparenza
      di ogni pixel del quale indica il grado di selezione di quel
      determinato pixel dell'immagine. Normalmente la maschera è
      colorata di rosso ma è possibile cambiare quest'impostazione con
      qualsiasi altro colore, se lo si ritiene conveniente. Meno il pixel è
      selezionato e più viene oscurato dalla maschera; i pixel
      completamente selezionati sono quindi completamente trasparenti.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      开启快速蒙板就可以看到好像是半透明薄膜在图像上的选区，各个像素上的透明度表明像素被选择的程度。蒙板的默认颜色是红色，您可以改变它为任何您认为更方便的颜色。您选择的像素越少，像素被蒙板遮掩的就越多。全部选择的像素则是完全清晰。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      When you are in QuickMask mode, many image manipulations act on the
      selection channel rather than the image itself. This includes, in
      particular, paint tools. Painting with white causes the painted pixels
      to be selected; painting with black causes them to be unselected. You
      can use any of the paint tools, as well as the bucket fill and gradient
      fill tools, in this way. Advanced users of the GIMP learn that "painting
      the selection" is the easiest and most effective way to delicately
      manipulate it.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie die Schnelle Maske aktiviert haben, können Sie alle
      Malwerkzeuge und viele weitere Kommandos genau so verwenden, als würden
      Sie das Bild selbst bearbeiten wollen. Um Bereiche zur Auswahl
      hinzuzufügen müssen Sie einfach nur die Maske an der gewünschten Stelle
      teilweise oder vollständig entfernen. Dies geschieht entweder durch
      Einsatz des Radierers, oder durch malen mit der Farbe weiss. Um die
      Maske an einer Stelle wieder herzustellen, übermalen Sie den
      entsprechenden Bereich einfach mit Schwarz. Für erfahrende GIMP Anwender
      ist das <quote>Malen</quote> einer Auswahl der einfachste und
      effektivste Weg zur Erstellung komplizierterer Auswahlen.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Als het Snelmasker aanstaat, worden veel bewerkingsmogelijkheden niet
      meer op de afbeelding maar op het selectiemasker uitgevoerd. Dit geldt
      in het bijzonder voor de tekengereedschappen. Indien u iets met wit
      tekent worden de `gewitte' beeldpunten geselecteerd, met zwart worden ze
      dan weer niet geselecteerd. U kunt ieder verfgereedschap hiervoor
      gebruiken en verder ook nog de emmer-vullingen de
      verloopvullingsgereedschappen. Geoefende gebruikers hebben vaak ervaren
      dat het tekenen van de selectie een hele eenvoudige en effectieve manier
      is om een afbeelding op een elegante manier te bewerken.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Quando si è in modalità maschera veloce, molte operazioni sulle
      immagini agiscono sul canale di selezione piuttosto che sull'immagine
      stessa, in particolar modo per gli strumenti di disegno. Disegnando
      con il bianco ha l'effetto di selezionare i punti disegnati; invece
      disegnando con il nero li si deseleziona. È possibile usare in questo
      modo uno qualsiasi degli strumenti di disegno, compresi il
      riempimento colore e il riempimento con gradiente. Gli utenti esperti
      di GIMP sanno che "disegnare la selezione" è il modo più efficiente e
      preciso per gestirla.    
    </para>

    <para lang="sv">
      Vad som händer nu är att det skapas en temporär 8-bit (0-255) kanal
      där den progressiva markeringen lagras. Om det redan finns en
      markering så kommer masken att använda markeringens innehåll. När
      snabbmask är aktiverad kommer bilden att fyllas med en röd
      semi-transparent grund. De röda delarna är de icke markerade
      pixlarna. För att skapa en markering i snabbmasken går det att
      använda vilket <link linkend="gimp-tool-paint">målarverktyg</link>
      som helst. Färg användning ska vara gråskalig för att markeringarna
      ska bli korrekta, använd vit färg för att ta bort snabbmask och
      skapa markering runt om det vita. Markeringen visas så fort
      snabbmask är avstängd, kanalen för snabbmask kommer inte längre att
      finnas kvar efter det att markeringen syns.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在快速蒙板模式下，许多图像处理在选区通道上操作而不是图像本身。特别的，这些操作包括涂画工具。用白色涂画使得被画的像素被选中；黑色涂画则使其未选中。您可以使用包括油漆桶填充和颜色渐变填充在内的所有涂画工具，因此，GIMP 高级用户觉得“涂画选区”是细致处理它们的最简单和有效的方法。
    </para>

    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        To save the selection done by the Quickmask to a new channel; Make 
        sure that there is a selection and that Quickmask is not active in 
        the image window. Select in the image menu 
        <guimenuitem>Select/Save to Channel</guimenuitem>. This will create 
        a new channel in the channel dialog called SelectionMask 1.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Sie können eine Auswahl, egal ob Sie diese mit oder ohne die Schnelle
        Maske erstellt haben, in einen neuen Kanal speichern. Hierzu darf die
        Schnelle Maske nicht aktiviert sein und es muss natürlich eine
        Auswahl existieren. Dann führen Sie einfach das Kommando
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>In <accel>K</accel>anal speichern</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> aus. Die Auswahl wird dann in einen neuen Kanal mit dem
        Namen <quote>Auswahlmaske-Kopie</quote> gespeichert.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Pour sauvegarder dans un canal la sélection créée avec le
        masque rapide, assurez-vous qu'une sélection existe et que le 
        masque rapide n'est pas actif dans la fenêtre d'image. Choisissez
        <guimenuitem>Sélection/Enregister dans un canal</guimenuitem>  dans 
        le menu d'image. Cela créera un nouveau canal appelé Selection 
        Mask 1 dans la fenêtre de dialogue des canaux.
      </para>

      <para lang="nl">
        U kunt de selectie, zoals u die met het Snelmasker gemaakt, in een
        kanaal opslaan op de afbeeldingsmenubalk via:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>S</accel>electeren</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Opslaan in <accel>k</accel>anaal</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
	Per salvare la selezione fatta con la maschera veloce in un nuovo
        canale, siate sicuri che ci sia una selezione e che la maschera
        veloce non sia attiva nella finestra immagine. Scegliere nel menu
        immagine 
        <guimenuitem>Seleziona/Salva nel canale</guimenuitem>. Questo
        creerà un nuovo canale nella finestra di dialogo dei canali con il
        nome "Maschera di selezione copia" (eventualmente se si ripete
        l'operazione seguirà un numero 1 ... 2 per ogni copia successiva).
      </para>

      <para lang="sv">
        Du kan spara markeringen gjord efter snabbmask till en ny kanal genom
        att välja <guimenuitem>Välj/Spara till kanal</guimenuitem>
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        要保存通道中用快速蒙板产生的选区，选取图像菜单中<guimenuitem>选择/保存到通道</guimenuitem>
      </para>
    </tip>
    
    <tip lang="en;de;it;zh_CN">
      <para lang="en">
        When QuickMask is active, Cut and Paste act on the selection rather
        than the image. You can sometimes make use of this as the most
        convenient way of transferring a selection from one image to another.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie die Schnelle Maske aktiviert haben, wirken die Kommandos
        Ausschneiden und Einfügen auf der Maske und nicht auf dem Bild selbst.
        Dies ist sehr hilfreich, um Auswahlen als Maske von einem Bild in ein
        anderes zu übertragen.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Als het Snelmasker aanstaat worden de knip en plak-bewerkingen ook op
        het Snelmasker uitgevoerd. U kunt hier soms erg handig gebruik van
        maken omdat dit een erg makkelijke manier is om een selectie van de
        ene naar een andere afbeelding over te brengen.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
	Quando la maschera veloce è attiva, i comandi di taglia e incolla
        agiscono sulla selezione invece che sull'immagine. Alle volte
        questo è il modo più semplice per trasferire una selezione da
        un'immagine ad un'altra.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        在快速蒙板开启时，剪切和粘贴在选区上进行而不是图像。当有时要将选区从一个图像传到另一个图像时，您能使用这个最方便的办法。
      </para>
    </tip>
    
    <para lang="en">
      You can learn more on <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quickmask</link> and
      <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Selection masks</link> in the
      section dedicated to the channel dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Weitere Informationen finden Sie in <xref linkend="gimp-qmask" /> und
      <xref linkend="dialogs-selection-masks" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pourrez en apprendre bien plus sur le <link
      linkend="gimp-qmask">masque rapide</link> et les <link
      linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">masques de
      selection</link> dans la section dédiée au dialogue des
      canaux.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      È possibile approfondire l'argomento
      sulla <link linkend="gimp-qmask">maschera veloce</link> e sulla
      <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">maschera di selezione</link>
      nella sezione dedicata alla finestra di dialogo dei canali.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      U kunt meer informatie over het <!--link linkend="gimp-qmask"
      XXX_NL-->Snelmasker<!--/link--> en <!--link
      linkend="dialogs-selection-masks" XXX_NL-->Selectie maskers<!--/link-->
      vinden in het hoofdstuk dat de kanaal dialoogvensters behandeld.
    </para>

    <para lang="sv">
      Du kan lära dig mer om <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Snabbmask</link>
      och <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Markeringsmasker</link>
      i sektionen skriven för kanal fönstret.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="zh_CN">
        可以在这下面学到更多：<link linkend="gimp-qmask">快速蒙版</link>和在通道对话框章节下的<link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">选区蒙板</link>。
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3 lang="ed;de;fr;nl;it;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Properties</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Propriétés</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Eigenschappen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Proprietà</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">属性</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      There are two QuickMask properties you can change by right-clicking on
      the QuickMask button.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Es gibt zwei Eigenschaften, welche Sie über Kommandos im Kontextmenü der
      Schaltfläche zum Aktivieren der Schnellen Maske einstellen können.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il y a deux propriétés du masque rapide qui sont accessibles et
      modifiables via un clic droit sur le bouton du masque rapide.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Door op de rechtermuisknop op de Snelmasker schakelaar te klikken kunt u
      twee eigenschappen van het snelmasker wijzigen.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono due proprietà della maschera veloce che possono essere
      cambiate facendo clic con il tasto destro sul pulsante della maschera
      veloce.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      用鼠标右键点快速蒙板按钮可以看到两个快速蒙板的属性。
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Normally the QuickMask shows unselected areas "fogged over" and
          selected areas "in clear", but you can reverse this by choosing
          "Mask Selected Areas" instead of the default "Mask Unselected
          Areas".
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Normalerweise werden die Bereiche aus denen die Auswahl erzeugt wird
          in der Schnellen Maske als unmaskierte Bereiche angezeigt und die
          Bereiche in denen keine Auswahl entsteht durch einen roten Schleier
          gekennzeichnet. Sie können diese Darstellung umkehren, indem Sie
          im Kontextmenü das Kommando
          <guimenuitem>Maske aus Auswahl</guimenuitem>, statt des in den
          Standardeinstellungen aktiven <guimenuitem>Maske aus invertierter
          Auswahl</guimenuitem> ausführen.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          En utilisation normale le masque assombrit les régions
          non sélectionnées mais il est possible d'inverser ce
          comportement avec le menu <guilabel>Masquer les
          régions sélectionnées</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para lang="nl">
          Normaal toont het Snelmasker de ongeselecteerde delen als bedekt
          door een mist en de geselecteerde delen helder. Dit kunt u omdraaien
          door de optie <guimenuitem>Geselecteerde <accel>g</accel>ebieden
          maskeren</guimenuitem> te kiezen inplaats van het
          standaard ingestelde <guimenuitem><accel>N</accel>iet geselecteerde
          gebieden maskeren</guimenuitem>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
	  Normalmente la maschera veloce mostra le aree non selezionate
          "offuscate" e quelle selezionate "in chiaro" ma si può invertire
          questo comportamente scegliendo "Maschera le aree selezionate"
          invece del valore predefinito "Maschera le aree non selezionate".
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
           正常情况下，快速蒙板显示未选中区域被蒙板遮蔽，而选中区域则是清晰的，但是可以通过选“遮蔽选中区域”而不是默认的“遮蔽未选中区域”来其颠倒。
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          By choosing "Configure Color and Opacity", you can bring up a dialog
          that allows you to set these to values other than the defaults,
          which are red at 50% opacity.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Durch ausführen des Kommandos
          <guimenuitem>Farbe und Deckkraft festlegen</guimenuitem>, gelangen
          Sie in einen Dialog, in dem Sie die Farbe der Maske und die Stärke
          der Transparenz der Maske einstellen können. Dies kann hilfreich
          sein, wenn der Bildbereich in dem Sie arbeiten die gleiche Farbe hat
          wie die Maske.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          <guilabel>Configurer la couleur et l'opacité</guilabel>
          ouvre un dialogue qui permet de modifier l'assombrissement
          qui permet de visualiser le masque.
        </para>
        <para lang="nl">
          Door <guilabel>Kleur en ondoorzichtigheid
          <accel>configureren</accel></guilabel> te selecteren, activeert u
          een dialoogvenster waarmee u deze eigenschappen anders dan de
          standaardinstellingen kunt instellen, de standaardinstelling is rood
          en 50% doorzichtigheid.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
	  Scegliendo "Configura colore e opacità" si porta in evidenza la
          finestra di dialogo che permette di impostare questo e altri
          parametri a valori diversi dai predefiniti. Nel caso specifico il
          valore predefinito del parametro corrisponde a rosso al 50% di
          opacità.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          当选“配置颜色和不透明度”时，就会显示一个可用来改变默认值(红色和 50% 不透明度)的对话框。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
