<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--  section history:
  2008-02-28 update fr by jpl
  2007-01-29 added Spanish translation by manuq
  2006-08-14 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-03 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-06-15 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-01-06 updated fr
  2006-01-05 fixed ambigous description of installing new script-fu
  scripts (#324309)
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-script-fu" lang="cs;de;es;en;fr;it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="de;es;fr;ko;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        <authorinitials>N.N.</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-03-17</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-01-29</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-03-12</date>
        <authorinitials>jpl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-07-17</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-03-09</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Using Script-Fu Scripts</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Používání Script-Fu skriptů</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Skript-Fu verwenden</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Uso de guiones Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Utiliser les Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Uso degli script Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">Script-Fu 스크립트 사용하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Å bruke Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Использование скриптов Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="sv">Använda GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用 Script-Fu 脚本</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="cs;es;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
    <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en;fr">
    <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction></secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Skript-Fu</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
    <secondary>소개></secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Script-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Script-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Skript-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">¿Qué es Script-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Script-Fu ?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">스크립트-푸(Script-Fu)?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Script-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Script-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Script-Fu?</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Script-Fu？</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      Script-Fu is what the Windows world would call "macros" But Script-Fu is
      more powerful than that. Script-Fu is based on an interpreting language
      called Scheme, and works by using querying functions to the GIMP
      database. You can do all kinds of things with Script-Fu, but an ordinary
      GIMP user will probably use it for automating things that:
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Script-Fu je to, čemu by se ve světě Windows říkalo „makra“. Script-Fu
      je ale mnohem víc. Script-Fu je založeno na interpretovaném jazyku
      Scheme, což je dialekt Lispu, a při své činnosti se dotazuje na funkce z
      databáze Gimpu. Script-Fu lze používat k ohromnému množství účelů, ale
      začátečníci obvykle používají Script-Fu k automatizaci úkonů, které:
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Skript-Fu ist das, was die Windows-Welt "Makros" nennen würde. Aber
      Skript-Fu ist viel mehr als das. Skript-Fu basiert auf einer
      Interpretersprache namens <quote>Scheme</quote> und fragt mittels
      Funktionen die <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Datenbank ab. Sie können alles
      mögliche mit Skript-Fu machen, aber ein typischer Benutzer wird es
      vermutlich zur Automatisierung einsetzen, insbesondere für Aktionen, die
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Script-Fu es lo que en el mundo de Windows se llamaría "macros", pero en
      realidad es mucho más poderoso que éstas.  Se basa en un lenguaje
      interpretado llamado Scheme, y trabaja consultando funciones a la base
      de datos del GIMP.  Puede hacer una gran variedad de cosas con
      Script-Fu, pero en general se utiliza para automatizar tareas que:
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Script-Fu est ce que le monde Windows appellerait des "macros" mais
      Script-Fu est bien plus puissant que cela. Script-Fu est basé sur un
      langage interprété appelé le Scheme, et fonctionne en utilisant des
      fonctions de requêtes sur la base de données de GIMP. Vous pouvez faire
      toutes sortes de choses avec Script-Fu, mais l'utilisateur de base de
      GIMP l'utilisera pour automatiser des actions :
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Gli Script-Fu sono quello che nel mondo Windows si chiamano "macro" solo
      più potenti. Gli Script-Fu sono basati su un linguaggio interpretato
      chiamato Scheme, e lavorano interrogando le funzioni nel database di
      GIMP. È possibile fare qualsiasi operazione con gli Script-Fu, anche se
      gli utenti normali di GIMP li usano prevalentemente per automatizzare
      operazioni che:
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      스크립트-푸(Script-Fu) 는 윈도우즈의 "매크로" 와 비슷하지만 조금더
      강력합니다. Script-Fu 는 Scheme 이라는 인터프리팅 언어에 기반을 두고
      있으며 김프 데이터베이스에 쿼리문을 요청하는 방식으로 동작합니다.
      원한다면 Script-Fu 의 모든 기능을 사용할 수 있지만, 일반적인 김프
      사용자들은 주로 다음과 같은 경우에 사용합니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Script-Fu er noe av det same som Windows sine <quote>makroar</quote>,
      men mykje kraftigare. Script-Fu er basert på programmeringsspråket
      <quote>Scheme</quote> og arbeider ved å nytte spørjefunksjonar mot
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sin database. Du kan eigentleg gjere ganske
      mykje med Script-Fu, men den vanlege bruken er vel å automatisere
      ulike oppgåver som for eksempel slike som
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Script-Fu это то, что в мире Windows называется "макросами". Но в
      сравнении с ними Script-Fu явлется более мощным инструментом. Script-Fu
      основан на интерпретируемом языке, называемом Scheme, и работает с
      помощью использования запрашиваемых функций из базы данных GIMP. С
      помощью Script-Fu вы можете производить все виды действий, но обычный
      пользователь GIMP вероятно использует его для автоматизации таких вещей
      как:
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      Script-Fu 在 Windows 世界中叫做“宏”，不过 Script-Fu 比宏更强大。
      Script-Fu 是基于一个叫 Scheme 的解释语言，通过查询 GIMP 数据库的功能来
      工作。您可以使用 Script-Fu 干各种各样的事，不过一般的 GIMP 用户可能用
      它做些自动化的操作如：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem>
        <para>You want to do frequently.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Are really complicated to do, and hard to remember.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="cs">
      <listitem>
        <para>Chce často provádět.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Jsou velmi složité a těžce zapamatovatelné.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
        <para>regelmäßig ausgeführt werden sollen oder</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>kompliziert in der Ausführung und schwer zu merken sind.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="es">
      <listitem>
        <para>Ud. realiza con frecuencia.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Son realmente complicadas de hacer, y difíciles de recordar.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="fr">
      <listitem>
        <para>qu'il fait fréquemment,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>qui sont très compliquées et difficiles à retenir.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="it">
      <listitem>
        <para>si esegue frequentemente;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>molto complesse da eseguire e difficili da ricordare.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ko">
      <listitem>
        <para>자주 쓰게 되는 기능</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>꽤 복잡하며 기억하기 어려운 작업</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="no">
      <listitem>
        <para>du gjer ofte</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>er kompliserte å gjere og vanskelege å hugsa</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ru">
      <listitem>
        <para>Часто производимые операции.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Действительно сложные и трудные для запоминания операции.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem>
        <para>您经常要做的。</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>做起来很麻烦的和很难记住的。</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="en">
      Remember that you can do a whole lot with Script-Fu. The scripts that
      come with GIMP can be quite useful, but they can also serve as models
      for learning Script-Fu, or at least as a framework and source of
      modification when you make your own script. Read the Script-Fu Tutorial
      in the next section if you want to learn more about how to make scripts.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Pamatujte si však, že se Script-Fu můžete dělat mnohem víc. Skripty
      dodávané s Gimpem mohou být velmi užitečné, ale to nejcennější co vám
      mohou dát, je studijní materiál, který vás může přivést ke zvládnutí a
      později i mistrovství ve Script-Fu. Nebo alespoň mohou být základem k
      úpravám při tvorbě nového skriptu. Pokud ve vás slovo Fu vzbuzuje
      asociace s mistry bojových umění, hlubokými meditacemi a téměř
      nadlidskými schopnostmi, nejste daleko od pravdy. Odtud má své jméno.
      Chcete-li se vydat cestou Script-Fu, pokračujte tutoriálem v následující
      sekci.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wie gesagt, Sie können sehr viel mit Skript-Fu machen. Die Skripte, die
      mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ausgeliefert werden, sind sehr nützlich,
      und sie können überdies als Beispiele dienen, um Skript-Fu zu lernen,
      oder als Vorlage für Modifikationen, wenn Sie Ihr eigenes Skript
      schreiben. Lesen Sie das Skript-Fu-Tutorial im nächsten Abschnitt,
      wenn Sie mehr darüber erfahren möchten, wie man Skripte erstellt.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Tenga en cuenta que puede hacer una gran cantidad de cosas con
      Script-Fu.  Los guiones que vienen provistos junto con el GIMP pueden
      resultarle muy útiles, y además pueden servirle como modelos para
      aprender Script-Fu, o al menos como una plantilla para cuando desee
      escribir su propio guión.  Lea el tutorial sobre Script-Fu en la próxima
      sección si desea aprender más acerca de cómo se hacen los guiones.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Souvenez-vous que vous pouvez faire beaucoup avec Script-Fu. Les scripts
      qui sont fournis avec le GIMP peuvent être très utiles, mais ils peuvent
      aussi servir de modèle pour comprendre Script-Fu, ou au moins de
      charpente et de source lorsque vous faites vos propres scripts. Lisez le
      Tutoriel Script-Fu dans la section suivante si vous voulez apprendre
      comment écrire des scripts.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Si può fare molto con gli Script-Fu. Gli script forniti con GIMP possono
      essere molto utili, e possono servire ottimamente anche come esempi per
      imparare a creare gli Script-Fu, o per lo meno come struttura e sorgente
      di ispirazione per la creazione delle proprie procedure. Leggere
      attentamente il tutorial nella sezione seguente se si desidera
      cominciare a imparare a creare degli script.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 를 이용하면 굉장히 많은 일들을 할 수 있습니다. 그리고
      Script-Fu 를 배우기 위한 모델이나 직접 작성한 스크립트의 수정을 위한
      프레임워크도 제공됩니다. Script-Fu 에 대해 더 많은 것을 배우고 싶다면
      다음 장에 있는 Script-Fu 강좌를 읽어보시기 바랍니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Skripta som følgjer med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er nyttige på fleire
      måtar. Ikkje bare kan dei nyttast direkte slik dei er tenkt, men du
      kan også bruke dei som mønster for å lære Script-Fu, eller i det minste
      som grunnlag og kjelde for eigenproduserte skript. Les vidare om dette
      i neste kapittel.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Помните, что вы можете сделать множество вещей с помощью Script-Fu.
      Установливаемые вместе с GIMP скрипты весма полезны, но они также могут
      служить в качестве примеров для изучения Script-Fu, или как основа и
      исходник, модифицируя который вы создаёте свой скрипт. Прочитайте
      руководство по созданию Script-Fu в следующем разделе, если вы желаете
      узнать больше о том, как создавать скрипты.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      记住您可以用 Script-Fu 做大量的事。GIMP 自带的脚本十分有用，不过您也可
      以用它们了学习了解 Script-Fu，或是用它们作为您自己编写脚本的框架和参考。
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      We will describe some of the most useful scripts in this chapter, but we
      won't cover them all. There are simply too many scripts. Some of the
      scripts are also very simple and you will probably not need any
      documentation to be able to use them.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      V této kapitole popíšeme některé z nejužitečnějších skriptů, nikoliv
      však všechny. Je jich totiž prostě příliš mnoho. Některé jsou navíc
      velmi jednoduché a k jejich používání není třeba žádné dokumentace.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wir werden in diesem Kapitel einige der nützlichsten Skripte
      beschreiben, aber wir können nicht alle behandeln - es gibt einfach zu
      viele Skripte. Einige Skripte sind aber so einfach, dass Sie vermutlich
      gar keine Dokumentation benötigen, um mit ihnen arbeiten zu können.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      En este capítulo se describen algunos de los guiones más útiles, pero no
      todos.  Simplemente porque hay demasiados guiones.  Algunos de ellos son
      tan simples que ni siquiera necesitará valerse de documentación para
      poder utilizarlos.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Nous décrirons certains des scripts les plus utiles dans ce chapitre,
      mais nous ne les couvrirons pas tous. Il sont tout simplement trop
      nombreux. De plus, certains scripts sont très simples et vous n'aurez pas
      besoin de documentation pour les utiliser.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      In questo capitolo verranno descritti alcuni dei più utili script anche
      se (per ragioni di spazio) non tutti; ce ne sono troppi! Alcuni degli
      script sono così semplici che non necessitano di nessuna documentazione
      per padroneggiarne l'uso.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이 장에서 유용한 스크립트들에 대해 설명을 할 것이지만, 모든
      스크립트들을 소개하지는 않을 것입니다. 사실 대부분의 스크립트들은 굉장히
      단순해서 설명서가 없어도 사용하는데 아무런 지장이 없습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I dette kapitlet skal vi sjå på noen av dei mest nyttige skripta, men
      det er alt for mange skript til at vi kan nå over alle. Enkelte av
      skripta er i tillegg så enkle at du ikkje treng noe oppskrift på bruken
      av dei.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В этой главе мы опишем некоторые из наиболее полезных скриптов, но мы не
      будем рассматривать все. Просто доступно слишком много скриптов.
      Некоторые из скриптов также очень просты, и вам вероятно не понадобится
      никакой документации для обучения их использованию.
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Script-Fu (a dialect of Scheme) isn't the only scripting language
      available for GIMP. But Script-Fu is the only scripting language that is
      installed by default. Other available scripting extensions are Perl and
      Tcl. You can download and install both extensions at the GIMP Plugin
      Registry <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Script-Fu (respektive Scheme) není jediný skriptovací jazyk vhodný pro
      GIMP. Script-Fu je však jediný skriptovací jazyk dostupný ve výchozí
      instalaci.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Skript-Fu (ein Scheme-Dialekt) ist nicht die einzige Skriptsprache
      für <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, aber die einzige, die bereits von
      vornherein installiert ist. Andere mögliche Skripterweiterungen sind
      Perl und Tcl. Sie können beide Erweiterungen vom GIMP-Pluginregister
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>
      herunterladen und installieren.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El lenguaje Script-Fu (que es un dialecto de Scheme) es el único
      lenguaje de guionado (scripting) que se instala en el sistema.  Pero hay
      otras extensiones, por ejemplo para Perl y Tcl.  Puede descargar e
      instalar ambas extensiones desde el GIMP Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Script-Fu (un dialecte du Scheme) n'est pas le seul langage de script
      disponible avec le GIMP. Mais Script-Fu est le seul qui soit installé
      par défaut. Les autres langages disponibles en extension sont Perl et
      Tcl. Vous pouvez télécharger et installer ces deux extensions dans le
      registre des greffons du GIMP
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Script-Fu (un dialetto del linguaggio Scheme) non è il solo
      linguaggio di scripting disponibile per GIMP anche se Script-Fu è
      l'unico predefinito nell'installazione. Altre estensioni di scripting
      sono disponibili per il linguaggio Perl e Tcl. Le estensioni sono
      disponibili da scaricare e da installare sul sito Registro dei Plugin di
      GIMP <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu(Scheme 의 일종인) 는 김프에서만 사용가능한 언어는 아니지만
      김프에서 기본으로 설치되는 유일한 스크립팅 언어입니다. 그 외로 Perl
      이나 Tcl 등의 다른 스크립팅 확장을 사용할 수도 있습니다. 이러한
      것들은 GIMP Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>
      에서 다운로드 받아 설치할 수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Script-Fu, som altså er ein dialekt av Scheme, er ikkje det einaste
      programmeringsspråket som er tilgjengeleg i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      Men det er det einaste som blir lagt inn i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ved
      installeringa. Andre brukbare språk er Perl og Tcl. Begge desse kan du
      laste ned frå GIMP Plugin Registry
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Script-Fu (диалект языка Scheme) не единственный доступный  для
      GIMP скриптовый язык. Но Script-Fu это единственный  язык, который
      устанавливается по умолчанию. Другими доступными скриптовыми
      расширениями являются Perl и Tcl. Вы можете загрузить  и
      установить оба расширения со страницы  Реестр плагинов GIMP
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-plugin-registry"/>.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      我们在这里要介绍一些最有用的脚本，不过不是全部。因为实在是有太多的脚本，
      有些也非常简单而不需要任何文档就能使用它们。
    </para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 lang="en;de;es;fr;ko;it;no;ru;zh_CN" id="install-script-fu">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Installing Script-Fus</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Skript-Fus installieren</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Instalación de guiones Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Installer des Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Installazione degli Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">Script-Fu 설치하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Å installere Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Установка скриптов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">安装脚本</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>Install</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>Installer</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>설치</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      One of the great things about Script-Fu is that you can share your
      script with all your GIMP friends. There are many scripts that come with
      GIMP by default, but there are also vast quantities of scripts that are
      available for download all around the Internet.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Einer der Vorteile von Skript-Fu ist, dass Sie Ihr Skript mit all
      Ihren <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Freunden teilen können. Viele Skripte
      werden bereits mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ausgeliefert, aber im
      Internet gibt es noch Unmengen von Skripten zum Herunterladen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Lo bueno de Script-Fu es que puede compartir sus guiones con todos sus
      amigos.  Hay muchos guiones que vienen con el GIMP, pero hay una vasta
      cantidad de guiones que se encuentran disponibles para descargar en
      Internet.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un des points forts de GIMP est que vous pouvez échanger vos
      scripts avec ceux de vos amis. Nombreux sont les scripts présents
      par défaut dans GIMP, mais encore plus nombreux ceux que vous
      pourrez trouver sur la Toile.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Uno dei fattori notevoli degli Script-Fu è che è possibile
      condividerli con gli amici. Ci sono molti script che vengono forniti
      predefiniti con GIMP, ma ci sono anche un gran numero di script
      disponibili per il prelievo su Internet.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 의 주요 장점중 하나는 스크립트를 다른 김프 사용자들과
      공유해 쓸수 있다라는 점입니다. 김프 배포판에는 많은 스크립트들이
      포함되어 있지만 그보다 훨씬 많은 스크립트들을 인터넷에서 다운로드
      받을 수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Ein av fordelane med Script-Fu er at du kan dela skripta dine med andre.
      I tillegg til dei skripta som blir leverte saman med
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, finst det uteljande mange tilgjengelege for
      nedlasting rundt om på Internett.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Одной из самых замечательный вещей в Script-Fu является возможность
      делиться скриптами с вашими GIMP'овыми друзьями. Доступно множество
      скриптов которые установлены по умолчанию вместе с GIMP, но также
      существует огромное количество скриптов, которые доступны для закачки из
      Интернет.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      Script-Fu 的一个优点就是您可以将它们共享给所有的 GIMP 朋友。虽然 GIMP
      默认就安装了许多脚本，但是互联网上还有非常多可下载的脚本。
    </para>

    <procedure lang="en">
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          If you have downloaded a script, copy or move it to your
          scripts directory. It can be found in the Preferences:
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Folders</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Do a refresh by using
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Refresh Scripts</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          from the toolbox.
          The script will now appear in one of your menus.
          If you don't find it, look for it under the root file menu
          filters. If it doesn't appear at all, something was wrong with
          the script (e.g. it contains syntax errors).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="de">
      <step>
        <para lang="de">
          Wenn Sie ein Skript herunter geladen haben, kopieren oder
          verschieben Sie es in Ihr Skript-Verzeichnis, das Sie unter
          Einstellungen finden:
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Ordner</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Skripte</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="de">
          Laden Sie die Konfiguration neu mit
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Extras</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Skript-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Auffrischen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Das Skript wird nun in einem Ihrer Menüs erscheinen.
          Falls Sie es nicht finden, suchen Sie unter den Filtern des
          Bildfensters. Wenn es auch da nicht zu sehen ist, ist mit dem
          Skript irgend etwas nicht in Ordnung (z.B. könnte es Syntaxfehler
          enthalten).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="es">
      <step>
        <para lang="es">
          Si ha descargado un guión, cópielo o muévalo a su directorio
          personal de guiones.  Este directorio puede hallarse en las
          preferencias:
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Carpetas</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="es">
          Actualice la aplicación seleccionando
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Exts</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Refrescar scripts</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          desde el menú de la caja de herramientas.  El guión debería aparecer
          ahora en uno de sus menús.  Si no lo encuentra, puede que algo haya
          ido mal (puede tener errores sintácticos, por ejemplo).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="fr">
      <step>
        <para lang="fr">
          Si vous avez téléchargé un script, copiez-le ou déplacez-le dans
          votre répertoire de scripts.
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Ce répertoire de scripts peut être trouvé dans les Préférences :
              <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Dossiers</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
              </link>
            </para>
          </footnote>.
        </para>
      </step>


      <step>
        <para lang="fr">
          Faites un rafraîchissement en utilisant
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Exts</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Actualiser les scripts</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          dans le menu de la Boîte à outils. Le script doit apparaître dans
          la liste déroulante du menu Script-Fu. Si vous ne le trouvez pas,
          voyez dans le menu Scrip-fu de l'image. Et s'il ne s'y trouve pas
          non plus, c'est qu'il y a une erreur de syntaxe dans le script.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="it">
      <step>
        <para lang="it">
          Se si è scaricato uno script, per usarlo è necessario copiarlo o
          spostarlo nella cartella personale degli script di GIMP. Questa è
          definita nella finestra delle preferenze:
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Cartelle</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Script</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="it">
          Ricaricate l'elenco usando
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Rinfresca gli script</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          dal pannello degli strumenti.
          Ora gli script scaricati dovrebbero apparire in uno dei menu.
          Se non lo trovate, cercatelo sotto il menu principale dei
          filtri. Se non appare da nessuna parte significa che deve
          esserci un qualche tipo di errore nello script (per es. un
          errore di sintassi).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="ko">
      <step>
        <para lang="ko">
          스크립트를 다운로드 받아 사용자 스크립트 디렉토리로 옮긴 뒤에
          기본 설정의
          <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">  -->
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>폴더</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>스크립트</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          <!-- </link> -->
          를 보면 해당 스크립트를 확인할 수 있습니다.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="ko">
          그리고 도구상자의
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>확장</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Refresh Scripts</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          를 통해 새로고침을 합니다. 그러면 이제 메뉴에서 스크립트를 볼 수
          있게 됩니다. 만약 스크립트가 보이지 않는다면 이미지창의 필터
          메뉴를 찾아 보십시오. 그래도 없다면 스크립트 자체에 문법오류와
          같은 문제가 있는 것입니다.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="no">
      <step>
        <para lang="no">
          Når du har lasta ned eit skript, kopierar eller flytter du det til
          mappa di for skript. Kva for mappe dette er, finn du i menyen
          Innstillingar i hovudmenyen: <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Mapper</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Skript</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          </link>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="no">
          Oppdater skripta frå hovudmenyens
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Utvid</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Oppdater skript</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Skriptet skal nå dukka opp i ein av menyane. Den mest sannsynlege
          er Filtermenyen. Dersom du ikkje finn det i noen av menyane, er det
          noe gale med skriptet. (Den vanlegaste feilen er syntaksfeil, altså
          skrivefeil).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="ru">
      <step>
        <para>
          Если вы скачали скрипт, скопируйте или переместите ваш новый скрипт
          в директорию скриптов. Её можно найти в настройках директорий
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Директории</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Скрипты</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Обновите скрипты через меню панели инструментов
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Дополнения</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Обновить скрипты</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
          Скрипт появится в одном из ваших меню. Если вы его не нашли, поищите в
          основном меню фильтров. Если он всё еще не появился, с этим скриптом
          что-то не так (на пример, синтактические ошибки).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <tip lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        下载一个脚本后，将它拷贝或移动
        到 <filename>.gimp-2.2/scripts</filename> 目录然后刷新，这样该脚本就
        会在某个菜单中显示。如果没有发现，说明该脚本可能有问题。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 lang="de;en;fr;it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Do's and Don'ts</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Typische Fehler</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Ce qu'il faut faire et ne pas faire</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Cose che si possono e che non si possono fare</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">해야 할 것과 하지 말아야 할 것</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Råd og vink</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Работа и ошибки</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">注意事项</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      A common error when you are dealing with Script-Fus is that you simply
      bring them up and press the OK button. When nothing happens, you
      probably think that the script is broken or buggy, but there is most
      likely nothing wrong with it.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Ein häufiger Fehler beim Umgang mit Skript-Fu ist, ein Skript aufzurufen
      und den OK-Schalter zu drücken. Wenn nichts passiert, glauben Sie
      vermutlich, dass das Skript einen Fehler hat, aber höchstwahrscheinlich
      ist mit ihm alles in Ordnung.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Un malentendido muy común que se presenta al utilizar guiones Script-Fu
      es que el usuario simplemente los inicia y presiona el botón Aceptar.
      Luego no pasa nada, y el usuario cree que el guión está mal.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Une erreur classique lorsque vous utilisez un Script-Fu est de
      simplement le lancer et appuyer sur le bouton OK. Lorsque rien ne se
      passe vous penserez que le script s'est planté ou est occupé, mais il
      est plus probable qu'il n'y ait rien d'anormal là-dedans.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Un errore molto frequente quando si sta lavorando con gli Script-Fu
      accade quando li si porta in primo piano e si preme il punsante di OK
      e sembra non succedere niente. Si pensa subito che c'è qualcosa che
      non va con lo script, probabilmente un difetto o altro ma spesso
      invece non c'è nulla di errato.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 를 사용하면서 가장 흔하게 저지르는 실수는 Script-Fu 를
      호출하고 바로 "확인" 버튼을 누르는 것입니다. 이후 아무 변화도 생기지
      않으면 해당 스크립트가 깨졌거나 오류가 있다고 생각하겠지만, 사실
      대부분은 정상 작동한 것입니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Ein vanleg feil når du arbeider med Script-Fu er å tru at det er
      noe gale med skriptet fordi du ikkje ser noen forandringar i biletet
      etter å ha trykt på <quote>OK</quote>-knappen. Den mest sannsynlege
      forklaringa er at det ikkje er noe gale med skriptet.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Распространённым убеждением, часто вызывающим ошибку, является убеждение
      о том, что для работы со скриптами нужно просто вызывать их и нажать
      кнопку ОК. Когда ничего не происходит, вы вероятно думаете,что работа
      скрипта прервана или он содержит ошибку.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN"> 使用 Script-Fu 最常见的错误就是打开它们然后直接按下
      “确定”按钮。当什么也没发生时，您可以认为该脚本坏了或有 BUG，其实最可能
      是它什么问题都没有。
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Pero si no se lee atentamente la información que brinda el diálogo, y
      simplemente se presiona el botón, puede que falte alguna entrada que el
      guión necesita, o se le puede estar proporcionando una entrada
      incorrecta, y por lo tanto el guión falla.  Un ejemplo de esto ocurre
      cuando la tipografía especificada en el guión no ha sido instalada en el
      sistema.  Así que asegúrese de leer la información que brinda el diálogo
      antes de maldecir al guión.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Denken Sie nochmals nach. Haben Sie die Informationen im Dialog wirklich
      gelesen oder einfach nur den Schalter gedrückt? Wenn Sie eine vom Skript
      benötigte Eingabe vergessen oder ihm die falsche Eingabe gegeben haben,
      wird das Skript nicht funktionieren. Einer der häufigsten Fehler ist das
      Fehlen der im Skriptdialog angegebenen Schriftart (Font) auf Ihrem
      System. Bevor Sie also das Skript verantwortlich machen, überprüfen Sie
      bitte die Informationen im Dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Réfléchissez. Avez-vous lu les informations dans le dialogue, ou
      avez-vous juste cliqué ? Si vous avez omis une entrée dont le script a
      besoin, ou si vous avez fourni une fausse information, le script
      plantera. L'une des erreurs les plus communes est que la police de
      caractère spécifiée dans le dialogue du script n'a pas été installée sur
      votre système. Aussi, s'il vous plaît, vérifiez les informations du
      dialogue avant de maudire le script.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ripensandoci. Le informazioni sulla finestra di dialogo sono state lette
      attentamente o si è premuto semplicemente il pulsante OK senza pensare?
      Se si dimentica i dati in ingresso che sono necessari per lo script o se
      si immettono dati errati, lo script non funzionerà. Uno degli errori più
      comuni è che il tipo di carattere specificato nella finestra di dialogo
      dello script non è stato installato o non è presente nel sistema.
      Controllare sempre attentamente le informazioni nella finestra di
      dialogo prima di incolpare lo script!
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      기억을 더듬어 보십시오. 대화상자에 나온 정보들을 제대로 읽어보았는가,
      아니면 그저 확인 버튼만 눌렀는가? 스크립트에 필요한 입력값을 넣지
      않았거나 잘못된 값을 입력했다면 스크립트는 제대로 실행되지 않을
      것입니다. 사실 대부분의 에러는 스크립트 대화상자에 열거된 폰트가
      시스템에 설치되어 있지 않은 경우에 발생한다. 따라서 괜히 스크립트를
      탓하기 전에 대화상자의 정보를 확인해두는 것이 좋습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Tenk deg om. Har du lese informasjonen om skriptet skikkeleg? Gløymer du
      å gi skriptet dei opplysningane det bed om, eller du gir det feil data,
      vil mange av skriptet feila. Ein vanleg feil er at den skrifttypen
      skriptet krev, ikkje finst tilgjengeleg i datamaskinen. Så igjen, les
      opplysningane i dialogvindauget før du legg skulda på skriptet.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Подумайте снова. Действительно ли вы прочитали содержавшуюся в диалоге
      информацию, или вы просто нажали кнопку? Если вы забыли ввести
      необходимые скрипту параметры, или ввели ошибочные данные, он завершится
      с ошибкой.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      再想想您是不是仔细读了对话框中的信息，或只是简单地按了按钮？如果忘记输
      入脚本需要的东西或输入错误，它将运行失败。一个最常见的错误就是脚本对话
      框所需要的字体在您的系统中没被安装。因此请在责怪脚本之前仔细检查对话框
      中的信息。
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 lang="de;en;fr;it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Different Kinds Of Script-Fus</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Verschiedene Skript-Fu-Arten</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Différentes sortes de Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tipi differenti di Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">다른 종류의 Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Ulike typar av Script-Fu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Виды Скрипт-Фу</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Script-Fu 的不同类型</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      There are two kinds of Script-Fus:
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Es gibt zwei Arten von Skript-Fu-Programmen:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il y a deux sortes de Script-Fu:
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Det er to utgåver av Script-Fu-programma:
    </para>

    <variablelist lang="en;de;fr;no">
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Standalone Script-Fus</term>
        <term lang="de">
          Selbständige (<foreignphrase>standalone</foreignphrase>) Skripte
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">Les script-fu autonomes</term>
        <term lang="no">Sjølvstendige Script-Fu</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You will find the standalone variants under
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
               <guisubmenu>Type of Script</guisubmenu>
            </menuchoice> in the main toolbox menu (see the figure below).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die selbständigen Skripte finden Sie unter
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Extras</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Skript-Fu</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem><replaceable>Skriptart</replaceable></guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> im Hauptmenü.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous trouverez les scripts <quote>autonomes</quote> dans le menu
            principal de la boîte à outils sous
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Exts</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type de Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> (voir figure ci-dessous).
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Desse finn du i hovudmenyen under
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Utvidingar</guimenu>
               <guisubmenu>Type skript</guisubmenu>
            </menuchoice> (sjå figuren nedanfor).
          </para>
          <figure lang="en;fr;no">
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">Script-Fus by category</phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">Skript-Fu-Skripte nach Kategorie</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Liste des Script-Fu par catégorie</phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">Script-Fu etter kategori</phrase>
            </title>
            <!--TODO de: images/using/de/script-fu-exts.png-->
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/using/script-fu-exts.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/script-fu-exts.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="no">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/script-fu-exts.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Image-dependent Script-Fus</term>
        <term lang="de">Bildabhängige Skripte</term>
        <term lang="fr">Les script-fu images</term>
        <term lang="no">Biletavhengige Script-Fu</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Menus have been reorganized. A new Colors-menu appears. It groups
            together all scripts that work on colors, for example tools that
            adjust hue, saturation, lightness..., filters...etc. Filters-menu
            and Script-Fu-menu are merged in one Filters-menu and it is
            organized according to new categories. Image-dependent Plug-ins and
            Script-Fus are now disseminated in the image-menus. For example,
            Color to Alpha filter is in Colors-menu. At the beginning, it's
            disconcerting, but you finish to get used to this because it's more
            logical.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.4 wurden die Menüs neu angeordnet.
            So gibt es jetzt beispielsweise ein neues
            <guimenu>Farben</guimenu>-Menü, welches Befehle, Werkzeuge, Filter
            und Skripte, die die Farbe betreffen, zusammenfasst. Das
            Filter-Menü wurde mit dem Skript-Fu-Menü vereint und nach
            Kategorien geordnet. Bildabhängige Plugins und Skripte sind nun
            über das Bildmenü verteilt. Beispielsweise ist das Filter
            <quote>Farbe zu Transparenz</quote> im Menü <quote>Farben</quote>
            zu finden. Wer die alte Menüstruktur gewohnt war, wird anfangs
            vielleicht etwas suchen müssen, aber man gewöhnt sich sehr schnell
            an die neue Ordnung, da sie viel logischer ist.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les menus ont été réorganisés. Un menu Couleurs supplémentaire a
            fait son apparition. Il regroupe tout ce qui concerne les travaux
            sur les couleurs, par exemple les outils d'ajustement de teinte ou
            de niveaux, des filtres, etc. Le menu Filtres et le menu Scripts-Fu
            ont été fusionnés dans un menu Filtres unique et l'ensemble organisé
            selon de nouvelles catégories. Les scripts (et greffons) qui
            dépendent de l'image se trouvent maintenant disséminés un peu
            partout dans les menus, en fonction de leur catégorie d'utilisation.
            Par exemple le filtre Couleur vers alpha est dans le menu couleur.
            Cela déconcerte un peu au départ, mais on s'y habitue très vite et
            c'est tout de même plus logique.
            <!--Source http://abcdugimp.free.fr &
            Source http://wiki.gimp-attitude.org/-->
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Frå versjon 2.4 blei menyane i GIMP forandra. Alle skripta som har
            med fargar å gjere blei samla i menyen
            <guimenu>Fargar</guimenu>. Her vil du finne t.d. verktøy for å
            justere kulør, metning osv. Den gamle filter-menyen og
            Script-Fu-menyen er slått saman til ein ny filtermeny som er sett
            opp i høve til dei nye filterkategoriane. Biletavhengige
            programtillegg og Script-Fu er nå fordelte i biletmenyane. For
            eksempel er filteret <quote>farge til alfa</quote> nå lagt i
            farge-menyen. I det heile skulle menyane nå vere meire logiske.
            Du finn verktøya stort sett der du ventar å finne dei.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            The figure below show where you can find them in the image-menu.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La figure ci-dessous vous montre où vous les trouverez dans le menu
            image.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du legg inn andre programtillegg enn dei som følgjer med
            GIMP, vil desse ofte legge seg i ein ny
            <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>-meny. Figuren nedanfor viser kvar
            du kan finne scripta i biletmenyen.
          </para>
          <!--TODO de: images/using/de/script-fu-image.png-->
          <figure lang="en;fr;no">
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">Where find Image-dependent scripts</phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">Où trouver les scripts image</phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">Plasseringa av biletavhengige skript</phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="en">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/using/script-fu-image.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="fr">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/script-fu-image.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="no">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/script-fu-image.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

      <!--TODO it;ko;ru;zh_CN integrate your text in the different parts
        of the variablelist above. For the imagedata see
        .../src/images/using/script-fu-exts.xcf.gz-->

    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono due tipi di Script-Fu -- script a sé stanti e script
      dipendenti dall'immagine. La variante indipendente si trova sotto
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>(tipo di script)</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> presente nel menu principale del pannello degli strumenti,
      mentre il tipo dipendente dall'immagine è sistemato sotto
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>(tipo di script)</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> nel menu immagine.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      스크립트-푸(Script-Fu)는 독립형 스크립트와 이미지 의존형 스크립트가
      있습니다. 독립형 스크립트는 기본 도구상자 메뉴의
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>확장</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>스크립트 종류</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      에서 찾을 수 있고, 이미지 의존형 스크립트는 이미지 메뉴의
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>스크립트 종류</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      에 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Существует два вида скриптов - самостоятельные и зависящие от
      изображения. Самостоятельные вы найдёте в меню панели инструментов
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Расш.</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Скрипт-Фу</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>тип скрипта</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      зависимые от изображения скрипты расположены в меню
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Скрипт-Фу</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>тип скрипта</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      有两种类型的 Script-Fu -- 独立脚本和依赖图像的脚本。独立脚本在工具箱菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>扩展</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>，而依赖图像的脚本在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <!--TODO es: translate-->
  <sect2 lang="de;en;fr;it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN" id="standalone-script-fu">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Standalone Scripts</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Selbständige Skripte</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Les scripts autonomes</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Script autonomi</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">독립형 스크립트</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Sjølvstendige skript</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Самостоятельные скрипты</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">独立脚本</phrase>
    </title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>Standalone</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Patterns</primary>
      <secondary>Making pattern for Web page with Script-fu</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>Autonome</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Motifs</primary>
      <secondary>Créer des motifs de page Web avec des script-fu</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>독립형</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko">
      <primary>무늬</primary>
      <secondary>Script-Fu 를 이용해 웹페이지용 무늬 만들기</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
      <secondary>Sjølvstendige skript</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no">
      <primary>Mønster</primary>
      <secondary>tema for nettsider</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      We will not try to describe every script in depth. Most Script-Fus are
      very easy to understand and use. At the time of this writing, the
      following types are installed by default:
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wir werden nicht versuchen, jedes Skript im Detail zu beschreiben. Die
      meisten sind sehr einfach zu verstehen und zu benutzen. Aktuell sind
      folgende Arten standardmäßig installiert:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Nous n'essayerons pas de décrire à fond chaque script. La plupart des
      Script-Fu sont très faciles à comprendre et à utiliser. Au moment de
      l'écriture de ce manuel, les catégories suivantes sont installées par
      défaut :
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Non tenteremo di descrivere in dettaglio ogni tipo di script. Molti sono
      banali da capire e usare. Quando questo capitolo è stato scritto, i tipi
      seguenti di script erano predefinitivamente installati:
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      여기서 모든 스크립트들을 자세하게 다룰 수는 없으며 대부분의
      스크립트들은 굉장히 쉽게 사용할 수 있습니다. 기본으로 설치되는
      스크립트의 종류는 다음과 같습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Desse skripta lagar eigne bilete som du eventuelt kan arbeida vidare
      med. Det er unødvendig å forklara skripta i detalj, dei fleste er
      sjølvforklarande. For tida er desse skripttypane lagt inn i
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> frå starten av:
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Мы не ставим перед собой цель детального описания каждого скрипта.
      Большинство скрипт-фу очень и легки для понимания и использования. На
      момент написания этих строк, по умолчанию устанавливаются следующие
      типы:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      我们不会深入介绍每个脚本，大多数 Script-Fu 都很容易使用。截至撰写该文
      档时，GIMP 默认安装了下列独立脚本：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Patterns</para>
        <para lang="de">Muster</para>
        <para lang="fr">Motifs</para>
        <para lang="it">Motivi</para>
        <para lang="ko">Patterns</para>
        <para lang="no">Mønster</para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Текстуры<!--в интерфейсе всё еще "шаблоны-->"
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">图案</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Web page themes</para>
        <para lang="de">Webseiten(-Themen)</para>
        <para lang="fr">Thèmes de page web</para>
        <para lang="it">Temi per pagine web</para>
        <para lang="ko">Web page themes</para>
        <para lang="no">Tema for nettsider</para>
        <para lang="ru">Темы Web-страниц</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">网页主题</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Logos</para>
        <para lang="de">Logos</para>
        <para lang="fr">Logos</para>
        <para lang="it">Logotipi</para>
        <para lang="ko">Logos</para>
        <para lang="no">Logoar</para>
        <para lang="ru">Эмблемы</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">徽标</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Buttons</para>
        <para lang="de">Schaltflächen</para>
        <para lang="fr">Boutons</para>
        <para lang="it">Pulsanti</para>
        <para lang="ko">Buttons</para>
        <para lang="no">Knappar</para>
        <para lang="ru">Кнопки</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">按钮</para>
      </listitem>

<!--      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Utils</para>
        <para lang="de">Hilfsmittel</para>
        <para lang="fr">Utilitaires</para>
        <para lang="it">Utilità</para>
        <para lang="ko">Utils</para>
        <para lang="no">Hjelpemiddel (ikkje i versjon 2.4)</para>
        <para lang="ru">Утилиты</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">工具</para>
      </listitem>-->

<!--      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Make Brush</para>
        <para lang="de">Pinsel erstellen</para>
        <para lang="fr">Créer une brosse</para>
        <para lang="it">Crea pennello</para>
        <para lang="ko">Make Brush</para>
        <para lang="no">Lage pensel (ikkje i versjon 2.4)</para>
        <para lang="ru">Создать кисть</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">制作画笔</para>
      </listitem>-->

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">Misc.</para>
        <para lang="de">Verschiedenes</para>
        <para lang="fr">Divers</para>
        <para lang="it">Varie</para>
        <para lang="ko">Misc.</para>
        <para lang="no">Diverse</para>
        <para lang="ru">Разное</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">杂项</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Patterns</term>
        <term lang="de">Muster</term>
        <term lang="fr">Motifs</term>
        <term lang="it">Motivi</term>
        <term lang="ko">Patterns</term>
        <term lang="no">Mønster</term>
        <term lang="ru">Текстуры</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">图案</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You will find all kinds of pattern-generating scripts here.
            Generally, they are quite useful because you can add many
            arguments to your own patterns.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            We'll take a look at the Land script. In this script you have to
            set the image/pattern size, and specify what levels of random to
            use for your land creation. The colors used to generate the land
            map are taken from the currently selected gradient in the gradient
            editor. You must also supply values for the level of detail, land
            and sea height/depth and the scale. Scale refers to the scale of
            your map, just as in an ordinary road map, 1:10 will be typed as
            10.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Hier finden sie alle möglichen Muster-erstellende Skripte, die
            normalerweise ziemlich nützlich sind, weil Sie Ihren eigenen
            Mustern viele Argumente hinzufügen können.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Als Beispiel betrachten wir einmal das
            <quote>Land</quote>-Skript. In diesem Skript müssen Sie die
            Bild- und Mustergröße angeben sowie das für die Landerstellung
            verwendete Zufallsniveau. Die Farben, die zur Erstellung der
            Landkarte verwendet werden, werden dem aktuell ausgewählten
            Farbverlauf aus dem Farbverlaufseditor entnommen. Sie müssen
            außerdem Werte für Detailreichtum, Landhöhe, Wassertiefe und
            Skalierungen angeben. Skalierungen beziehen sich auf die
            Skalierung Ihrer Karte, genau wie in einer normalen Landkarte.
            Eine Skalierung von 1:10 wird beispielsweise als 10 angeben.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Vous trouverez là toutes sortes de scripts générateurs de motifs.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Prenons par exemple le script Terre (Land). Dans ce script, vous
            devez régler la taille de l'image/motif, et spécifier quels niveaux
            de hasard vous désirez pour votre création. Les couleurs utilisées
            pour générer la carte du paysage sont prises dans le dégradé
            sélectionné grace à la fenêtre <guimenu>Sélection du Dégradé
            Scrip-Fu</guimenu> qui apparaît en cliquant sur le bouton
            <guimenu>Dégradé</guimenu>. Vous devez aussi préciser le niveau de
            détails, la hauteur/profondeur de la terre et de la mer ainsi que
            l'échelle. L'échelle se réfère à l'échelle de votre carte, comme
            dans une carte de géographie, le 1/10ème étant indiqué 10.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Qui si trovano tutti i tipi di script utili per la generazione di
            motivi. Sono molto utili in quanto è possibile personalizzarli
            inserendo molti argomenti.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Diamo un'occhiata allo script Paesaggio. In questo script è
            necessario impostare la dimensione dell'immagine/motivo e
            specificare il livello di casualità da usare la la creazione
            dell'immagine della landa. I colori usati per generare la mappa
            della terra vengono presi dal gradiente attualmente selezionato
            nell'editor del gradiente. È necessario anche fornire i valori del
            livello di dettaglio, altezza della terra e profondità del mare e
            la scala. La scala si riferisce alla scala della mappa, come in
            una normale carta stradale; 1:10 sarà scritto come 10.
          </para>

          <para  lang="ko">
            이곳에는 무늬 생성 스크립트들이 모여 있습니다. 여러가지 인자들을
            사용해서 다양한 무늬를 만들 수 있습니다.
          </para>
          <para  lang="ko">
            Land 스크립트를 보면, 이미지/무늬 크기, 그리고 Land 생성에
            필요한 임의 레벨값을 설정해야 합니다. Land map 생성에 사용되는
            색상은 그라디언트 편집기에서 선택된 그라디언트의 색상입니다.
            그리고 세밀도 레벨, land 의 높이, sea 의 깊이, 스케일 등도
            정해줘야 합니다. 스케일은 맵의 배율로, 일반적인 지도와 같이
            1:10 인 경우 10을 넣어 줍니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Her er det samla ein del skript som produserer ulike former for
            mønster. Du kan forandre ein del data og såleis påverke det
            endelege resultatet.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du opnar t.d. skriptet <quote>Land</quote>, vil du sjå
            at det er mogleg å forandre ein del data i dialogvindauget som
            dukkar opp. Først har du storleiken på biletet og såleis også
            på mønsteret. Det er også råd å bestemme kor tilfeldig dette landet
            skal bli. Fargane som blir brukte kan varierast i og med at dei blir
            henta frå den aktive fargeovergangen. Du kan også bestemme kor
            detaljert kartet skal bli og kva målestokk det skal ha. Notasjonen
            for målestokk er som på vanlege kart. Ønskjer du 1 : 10 skriv du
            10. Som med dei fleste av desse filtra, må du nok prøve deg fram
            med ulike forslag før du får eit resultat som er brukande i ein
            bestemt samanheng.
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Здесь вы найдете все скрипты, генерирующие текстуры. Вообще, они
            довольно полезны, поскольку вы можете добавить множество
            аргументов к своим текстурам.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Рассмотрм скрипт "Земля". В этом скрипте вы должны установить
            размер изображения/текстуры, и задать уровень случайности,
            используемый для создания земли. Используемые для генерации карты
            цвета взяты из текущего выбранного градиента в редакторе
            градиентов. Вы также должны установить значения для уровня
            детализации, высоту/глубину земли и моря, также как в обычной
            дорожной карте, 1:10 представляется как 10.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">这里有生成图案的所有脚本，它们是很有用的可以对
            您的图案添加很多参数。</para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            以凹凸地图脚本为例，您需要设置图像/图案尺寸和随机种子数,以及从渐
            变编辑器中选取生成凹凸地图颜色的渐变，另外必须设定细节等级，地面
            和海洋的高度/深度和缩放，缩放就是地图的比例，和普通的道路地图中
            的一样，1:10 就输入 10。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Web Page Themes</term>
        <term lang="de">Webseiten</term>
        <term lang="fr">Thèmes de pages Web</term>
        <term lang="it">Temi per pagine web</term>
        <term lang="ko">Web Page Themes</term>
        <term lang="no">Tema for nettsider</term>
        <term lang="ru">Темы Web-страниц</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">网页主题</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Here is clearly a practical use for scripts. By creating a script
            for making custom text, logos, buttons arrows, etc., for your web
            site, you will give them all the same style and shape. You will
            also be saving a lot of time, because you don't have to create
            every logo, text or button by hand.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            You will find the GIMP.org theme under the Web page theme submenu.
            If you want to create your own theme, this script will serve as an
            excellent template that you can modify to create a theme for your
            web site.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Most of the scripts are quite self-explanatory, but here are some
            hints:
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Hier ist ganz klar ein praktischer Nutzen für Skripte. Indem Sie
            ein Skript schreiben, um individuell entworfenen Text, Logos,
            Pfeile für Schaltflächen etc. für Ihre Webseite zu erstellen,
            erhalten diese alle denselben Stil und dieselbe Form.
            Außerdem ersparen Sie sich eine Menge Zeit, da Sie nicht alle
            Komponenten per Hand erstellen müssen.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Sie finden das GIMP.org-Thema unter dem Webseiten-Untermenü.
            Wenn Sie Ihr eigenes Thema erstellen wollen, ist dieses Skript
            eine ausgezeichnete Vorlage, die Sie modifizieren und
            so ein Thema für Ihre Webseite erstellen können.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die meisten Skripte sind selbsterklärend, trotzdem hier noch
            ein paar kurze Hinweise:
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Il y a là un usage très pratique des scripts. En réalisant
            vous-même des scripts pour créer pour votre page web, des textes
            sur mesure, des logos, des boutons-flèches...etc, vous donnerez à
            tous un même style. Et vous économiserez beaucoup de temps puisque
            vous n'aurez pas à les créer à la main.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous trouverez le thème Classic.Gimp.org dans le sous-menu pages
            Web.  Ce script vous servira de modèle que vous pourrez modifier
            pour créer votre propre thème,.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La plupart des scripts n'ont pas besoin d'explication. Voici
            néanmoins quelques conseils :
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Ecco un uso pratico per gli script. Fare uno script per creare
            testo personalizzato, logotipi, pulsanti frecce, ecc. per il
            proprio sito web è un modo pratico per mantenere coerente lo stile
            del sito e contemporaneamente risparmiare molto tempo in queste
            operazioni ripetitive.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Nel sottomenu dei temi per le pagine web si troverà anche il tema
            gimp.org. Se si desidera creare un proprio tema, questo script è
            un eccellente modello personalizzabile per creare il tema del
            proprio sito.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Molti degli script sono auto-documentati ma ecco un po' di
            suggerimenti:
          </para>

          <para  lang="ko">
            스크립트를 이용해 웹사이트를 위한 텍스트, 로고, 화살표 버튼
            등을 동일한 스타일로 만들 수 있습니다. 이를 이용하면 모든 로고,
            텍스트, 버튼 등을 직접 그리지 않아도 되기 때문에 많은 시간을
            절약할 수 있습니다.
          </para>
          <para  lang="ko">
            Web page theme의 하위 메뉴를 보면 GIMP.org 테마를 볼 수
            있습니다. 이곳에 있는 스크립트가 제공하는 템플릿을 이용하면
            근사한 웹사이트용 테마를 만들 수 있습니다.
          </para>
          <para  lang="ko">
            대부분의 스크립트들은 자체적인 설명을 가지고 있지만 몇 가지
            힌트를 적어봅니다.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Her er nytteverdien nokså synleg. Du finn her skript for å lage
            tekst, logoar, knappar og mykje meir for nettsidene dine. Alle med
            same stilen og samsvarande utsjånad. Dermed er det råd å spare ein
            del tid sidan du ikkje treng finpussa detaljane for hand.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            I denne avdelinga finn du mellom anna dei tema som er brukte i
            <quote>GIMP.org</quote>. Dersom du ønskjer å lage eigne tema
            for nettsidene dine, kan du bruke desse skripta som mønster.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dialogvindauga til desse skripta er stort sett sjølvforklarande.
            Har du ønskje om å forandre sjølve skripta, kan desse tipsa vere
            til litt hjelp:
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Вот это очевидное практическое применение скриптов. Создавая
            скрипт для создания текста, эмблем, кнопок-указателей, и т.д. вы
            даёте всем им одинаковый стиль и форму. Вы также сохраняете массу
            времени, поскольку вам не нужно создавать каждую эмблему, текст
            или кнопку вручную.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Вы найдёте тему GIMP.org в подменю тем web-страниц. Если вы
            желаете создать свою собственную тему, этот скрипт может послужить
            вам отличным шаблоном, модифицируя который вы можете создать тему
            для своего сайта.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Большинство скриптов достаточно самодокументированы, но вот
            несколько подсказок:
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这里是一些关于脚本的实际应用。通过一个创建自定义文字， 徽标，按
            钮箭头等的脚本，可以给您的网页统一的风格和样式。它也可以给您节约
            很多时间，因为不用自己手动创建每一个徽标，文字和图标。
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            在网页主题子菜单下的 GIMP.org 给您创建自己的主题提供一个完美的模
            板， 通过修改它就可以创建自己的网站主题。
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">大部分脚本都很容易理解其用法，不过这里有些有用的提示：</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Leave all strange characters like ' and " intact.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Lassen Sie alle ungewöhnlichen Zeichen wie ' und " so wie
                sie sind.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Laissez intacts les caractères étranges comme ' et ".
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Lasciare tutti quegli strani caratteri come ' e " come sono.
              </para>
              <para  lang="ko">' 와 " 같은 특수 문자는 모두 제거한다.</para>
              <para lang="no">Ikkje rør spesialteikna, slike som ' og "</para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Оставьте все странные символы, такие как ' и " нетронутыми.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">保留完整的像 ' 和 " 一样的奇怪字符。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Make sure that the pattern specified in the script exists.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Vergewissern Sie sich, dass es das im Skript angegebene Muster
                wirklich gibt.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Assurez-vous que le motif spécifié dans le script existe.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Controllare che il motivo specificato nello script esista.
              </para>
              <para  lang="ko">
                스크립트에 명시된 무늬가 존재하는지 확인한다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Forsikra deg om at mønsteret du spesifiserer i skriptet
                verkeleg finst.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Удостоверьтесь, что указанная в скрипте текстура существует.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">确认脚本中使用的图案是存在的。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Padding refers to the amount of space around your text.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <quote>Padding</quote> (Innenabstand)
                bezieht sich auf den Rand um Ihren Text.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Remplissage (padding) se réfère à l'importance de l'espace
                vide autour de votre texte.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Lo riempimento si riferisce alla quantità di spazio attorno al
                testo.
              </para>
              <para  lang="ko">
                패딩은 텍스트 주변의 공간에 따라 결정된다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <quote>Luft</quote> (padding) bestemmer
                kor mykje plass det skal vere rundt teksten.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Заполнение определяет колчиество пространства вокруг вашего
                текста.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">衬垫指文字周围空格的数量。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                A high value for bevel width gives the illusion of a higher
                button.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Ein höherer Wert für <quote>bevel</quote> (Schrägung)
                ergibt die Illusion eines höheren Schalters.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Une forte valeur de biseau (bevel) donne l'illusion d'un
                bouton plus haut.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Un valore alto di spessore smussatura dà l'illusione di un
                pulsante in rilievo.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                높은 bevel 너비값은 그 상위 버튼의 환영(幻影)을 만든다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Ein høg verdi for <quote>fasettbreidde</quote>
                (bevel width) gir ein illusjon av høgare knapp.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Большое значение ширины скоса создаст иллюзию более высокой
                кнопки.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">一个高的“斜面宽度”值体现一个更高的按钮。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                If you type TRUE for "Press", the button will look pushed
                down.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Wenn Sie <quote>TRUE</quote> (wahr) für <quote>Press</quote>
                (Drücken) angeben, wird der Schalter aussehen, als ob er
                gedrückt wäre.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Si vous donnez la valeur TRUE (Vrai) à <quote>Press</quote>, le
                bouton semblera enfoncé.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Se si imposta la casella di "premuto", il pulsante avrà
                l'effetto premuto.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                "Press" 항목에 TRUE 를 입력하면 눌려진 버튼이 생성된다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Skriv du <quote>TRUE</quote> for <quote>Press</quote>,
                (trykt) vil knappen sjå ut som han er trykt ned.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Если вы отметите пункт "нажатая", кнопка будет выглядеть
                нажатой.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">勾选“按下”，按钮就好像被按下一样。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Choose transparency if you don't want a solid background. If
                you choose a solid background, make sure it is the same color
                as the web page background.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Wählen Sie Transparenz, falls Sie keinen undurchsichtigen
                Hintergrund wünschen. Im anderen Falle vergewissern Sie sich,
                dass die Hintergrundfarbe dieselbe ist wie die der Webseite.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Choisissez la transparence si vous ne voulez pas avoir un fond
                plein. Si vous choisissez un fond plein, veillez à ce qu'il
                soit de la même couleur que le fond de votre page Web.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Scegliere la trasparenza se non si vuole uno sfondo pieno. Se
                si sceglie lo sfondo pieno, assicuratevi che sia dello stesso
                colore dello sfondo della pagina web.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                단색 배경을 원치 않는다면 투명을 선택한다. 만약 단색 배경을
                사용한다면 그것이 웹페이지 배경과 같은지 확인해야 한다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Vel <quote>transparency</quote> dersom du ønskjer eit
                gjennomsiktig bilete. Vel du ein farga bakgrunn, forsikra deg
                om at han har same farge som bakgrunnen til nettsidene dine.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Выберите прозрачность если не хотите сплошной фон. Если вы
                выберите сплошной фон, удостоверьтесь, что это такой же цвет
                как и у фона веб страницы.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">如果不想要一个纯色背景就要选择透明。使用纯
                色背景时要确保它和网页背景颜色相同。</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Logos</term>
        <term lang="de">Logos</term>
        <term lang="fr">Logos</term>
        <term lang="it">Logotipi</term>
        <term lang="ko">Logos</term>
        <term lang="no">Logoar</term>
        <term lang="ru">Эмблемы</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">徽标</term>

        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Logo</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Logo</primary>
            <secondary>Script-Fu for logo</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm lang="fr">
            <primary>Logo</primary>
            <secondary>Script-Fu pour logo</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="fr">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Logo</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm lang="ko">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Logo</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ko">
            <primary>Logo</primary>
            <secondary>로고를 위한 Script-Fu</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm lang="no">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Logo</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="no">
            <primary>Logo</primary>
            <secondary>Lag logo med Script-Fu</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <para lang="en">
            Here you will find all kinds of logo-generating scripts. This is
            nice, but use it with care, as people might recognize your logo as
            being made by a known GIMP script. You should rather regard it as
            a base that you can modify to fit your needs. The dialog for
            making a logo is more or less the same for all such scripts:
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Hier finden Sie alle möglichen Logo-erstellende Skripte. Das ist
            ganz nett, aber seien Sie vorsichtig, da man Ihre Logos als von
            einem bekannten <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Skript erstellt erkennen
            könnte. Sie sollten sie eher als Ausgangspunkte betrachten, die
            Sie nach Ihren Bedürfnissen anpassen können. Der Dialog zum
            Erstellen eines Logos ist mehr oder weniger derselbe wie für
            alle solche Skripte:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous trouverez là des scripts pour générer des logos. C'est bien,
            mais on pourra voir que votre logo a été fait avec un script GIMP
            connu. Voyez-les plutôt comme une base que vous pouvez modifier
            pour créer quelque chose d'original. La boîte de dialogue est à
            peu près la même dans tous ces scripts :
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Qui si trovano tutti i tipi di script per la generazione di
            logotipi. Simpatico ma da usare cum grano salis, dato che è facile
            che la gente riconosca che il logo è stato fatto con un comune
            script GIMP. È meglio considerarli come una base modificabile per
            soddisfare le proprie esigenze dopo una adeguata
            personalizzazione. La finestra di dialogo per la generazione di un
            logotipo è più o meno la stessa per tutti gli script:
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            여기엔 로고 제작과 관련된 스크립트들이 모여 있습니다. 이것은 꽤
            유용하지만 조심해서 써야 합니다. 그것은 유명한 김프 스크립트로
            만든 것이 티날 수도 있기 때문입니다. 따라서 원하는 형태로 만들기
            위한 기본틀 정도로 생각하는 것이 좋습니다. 로고 제작을 위한 모든
            스크립트가 제공하는 대화상자는 거의 비슷한 형태를 취하고
            있습니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her finn du skript som lagar logoar og overskrifter. Mange er både
            fine og finurlege, men ver litt varsam med å bruke dei direkte frå
            grunninnstillingane. Blir litt einsformig om alle stiller opp med
            overskrifter med dei same effektane, tydeleg henta frå desse
            skripta. Bruk dei heller som eit utgangspunkt for eigen fantasi og
            vidare arbeid. Dei aller fleste skripta nyttar same oppsettet med
            omsyn til kva data du kan forandre på. Det aller meste er
            sjølvforklarande:
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Здесь вы найдёте все типы генерирующие логотипы скриптов. Это
            хорошо, но используйте их с предосторожностью, поскольку люди
            могут узнать вашу эмблему, как сделанную известным скриптом GIMP.
            Вы должны скорее расценивать это как основу, которую вы можете
            изменить в соответствии вашим потребностями. Диалог создания
            эмблем более или менее такой же как и для всех подобных скриптов:
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这里是生成徽标的所有脚本。它们很不错，不过要注意，人 们可能会发
            现您的徽标是由大家都知道的 GIMP 脚本创建的。最好把它们作为您修改
            和满足需要的模板。对于所有的这些脚本其对话框都很相似：
          </para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                In the Text String field, type your logo name, like
                Frozenriver.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Im Textfeld geben Sie den Namen des Logos an.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Dans le champ Chaîne de texte (Text String), tapez le nom de
                votre logo.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Nel campo di testo insterire il nome del logotipo, come
                Fiumeghiacciato.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                문자열 입력란에는 Frozenriver처럼 로고 이름을 입력한다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Skriv ønskt logotekst i tekstfeltet.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                В поле ввода текста введите имя вашей эмблемы, например,
                Frozenriver.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">在文字区域，输入徽标的名字，如 Frozenriver。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                In the Font Size text field, type the size of your logo in
                pixels.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Im Feld <quote>Font size</quote> (Schriftgröße) geben Sie
                die Größe Ihres Logos in Pixeln an.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Dans le champ taille de police (Font Size), tapez la taille de
                votre logo en pixels.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Nel campo della dimensione del carattere, inserire la
                dimensione del logo in pixel.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                폰트 크기 입력란에는 로고의 크기를 픽셀단위로 입력한다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Teiknstorleiken blir gitt i pikslar.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                В поле ввода размера шрифта введите размер вашей эмблемы в
                пикселах.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">在字体大小区域，输入您徽标的像素大小。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                In the Font text field, type the name of the font that you
                want to use for your logo.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Im Feld <quote>Font</quote> (Schriftart) wählen Sie
                die gewünschte Schrift für Ihr Logo aus.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Dans le champ Police (Font), tapez le nom de la police que vous
                voulez utiliser.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Nel campo del carattere, inserire il nome del font che si
                intende utilizzare per il logotipo.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                폰트 입력란에는 로고에 사용하려고 하는 폰트 이름을
                입력한다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Vel skrifttypen du vil bruke for logoteksten.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                В поле ввода текста введите имя шрифта, который вы хотите
                использовать для вашей эмблемы.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">在字体区域，输入您徽标要使用的字体。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                To choose the color of your logo, just click on the color
                button. This brings up a color dialog.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Um die Farbe Ihres Logos auszuwählen, klicken Sie auf den
                Farben-Schalter, daraufhin öffnet sich ein Farbdialogfenster.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Pour choisir la couleur de votre logo, cliquez simplement sur
                le bouton couleur, ce qui ouvrira une fenêtre de choix de
                couleurs.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Per scegliere il colore del logo, fare clic sul pulsante del
                colore. L'operazione porterà in primo piano la finestra di
                selezione del colore.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                로고의 색상은 색버튼을 클릭하면 나타나는 색상 대화상자에서
                선택한다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Når du klikkar på fargeknappen, dukkar det opp eit
                dialogvindauge der du kan velje skriftfarge.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Для выбор цвета вашей эмблемы просто щёлкните по кнопке выбора
                цвета. Это вызовет диалог выбора цвета.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">要给您的徽标选择颜色，点击颜色按钮，会出现
                一个颜色对话框。</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                If you look at the current command field, you can watch the
                script run.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Wenn Sie dann auf das Kommandofeld schauen, können Sie den
                Ablauf des Skriptes verfolgen.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Si vous regardez le champ de commande courant, vous pouvez
                voir comment le script agit.
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Se si guarda il campo del comando corrente è possibile
                osservare l'andamento dello script durante l'esecuzione.
              </para>
              <para lang="ko">
                현재 명령행을 통해 스크립트가 진행되는 과정을 볼 수 있다.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Etter at du har trykt <quote>OK</quote>, vil feltet nedst i
                dialogvindauget vise framdrifta for skriptet.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                Если вы посмотрите на поле выполнения текущей
                команды<!--FIXME: ru--> , вы увидите, что скрипт запущен.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">您可以在当前命令区域看到脚本在运行。</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Make Buttons</term>
        <term lang="de">Schaltflächen erstellen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Créer des boutons</term>
        <term lang="it">Pulsanti</term>
        <term lang="ko">Make Buttons</term>
        <term lang="no">Knappar</term>
        <term lang="ru">Создать кнопки</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">按钮</term>

        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Button</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Button</primary>
            <secondary>Script-Fu for button</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm lang="fr">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Bouton</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="fr">
            <primary>Bouton</primary>
            <secondary>Script-Fu pour bouton</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm lang="ko">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Button</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ko">
            <primary>Button</primary>
            <secondary>버튼을 위한 Script-Fu</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm lang="no">
            <primary>Script-Fu</primary>
            <secondary>Knappar</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="no">
            <primary>Knappar</primary>
            <secondary>Lage vha. Script-Fu</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <!--TODO it ko ru zh_CN: update-->
          <para lang="en">
            Under this headline you'll find two scripts that makes rectangular
            beveled buttons, with or without round corners (Round Button or
            Simple Beveled Button). They have a dozen parameters or so, and
            most of them are similar to those in the logo scripts. You can
            experiment with different settings to come up with a button you
            like.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Unter dieser Überschrift finden Sie zwei Skripte, die abgeschrägte
            Schaltflächen mit oder ohne abgerundete Ecken erstellen. Sie haben
            jeweils etwa ein Dutzend Parameter, von denen die meisten ähnlich
            wie bei den Logo-Skripten wirken. Sie können ruhig mit
            verschiedenen Einstellungen experimentieren, um zu einer
            Schaltfläche nach Ihren Wünschen zu kommen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Sous cette tête de chapitre, vous trouverez deux scripts qui créent
            des boutons rectangulaires en relief avec biseau, avec ou sans
            coins arrondis (Bouton arrondi ou Simple bouton biseauté). Ils
            possèdent de nombreux paramètres dont la plupart ressemblent à ceux
            des scripts de logo. Expérimentez par vous-même.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Sotto quest'intestazione si troveranno gli script che servono per
            generare automaticamente immagini di pulsanti in rilievo. Gli
            script hanno dozzine di parametri e molti sono simili o
            equivalenti a quelli presenti negli script dei logotipi.
            Sperimentate tranquillamente fino ad ottenere il pulsante
            desiderato.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            이 항목 아래에 있는 스크립트들은 버튼을 만들기 위한 것들입니다.
            많은 인수값들이 있지만, 그 대부분은 로고 스크립트와 비슷합니다.
            이 값들을 잘 조정하면 원하는 버튼을 만들 수 있습니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her finn du to skript for å lage rektangulære, fasetterte knappar.
            Det eine skriptet lager firkanta knappar medan det andre lager
            knappar som er avrunda i begge endane. Mange av innstillingane
            er dei same som for innstillingane i logoskripta. Du må nok 
            eksperimentera ein del med ulike innstillingar før du blir tilfreds.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Под этим заголовком вы найдёте скрипт, создающий выпуклые кнопки.
            Скрипт имеет приблизительно дюжину параметров, и большинство из
            них подобно тем, что описаны в скриптах создания эмблем. Вы можете
            экспериментировать с различными параметрами настройки, чтобы
            получить кнопку, которую вам нравится.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            这里可以找到产生斜面按钮的脚本。该脚本有非常多参数， 其中大部分
            都和徽标脚本中的相同。您可以体验不同参数产生的按钮。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Misc.</term>
        <term lang="de">Verschiedenes</term>
        <term lang="fr">Divers</term>
        <term lang="it">Varie.</term>
        <term lang="ko">Misc.</term>
        <term lang="no">Diverse</term>
        <term lang="ru">Разное</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">杂项</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Under Misc. you'll find scripts that can be quite useful, but
            aren't suitable for the other submenus. An example is the Sphere
            script. You will have to set the radius in pixels to determine the
            sphere size. The lighting angle is where at the sphere you point
            the spotlight. This value also has an impact on the sphere shadow.
            If you don't want a shadow, you just have remove the tick
            on the "shadow" checkbox. The last thing you have to select is
            background color, and the color of your sphere.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Unter <quote>Verschiedenes</quote> finden Sie nützliche Skripte,
            die nicht in die anderen Untermenüs passen. Als Beispiel
            betrachten wir das <quote>Kugel</quote>-Skript. Geben Sie den
            Radius in Pixeln an, um die Größe der Kugel festzulegen. Der
            Beleuchtungsgrad gibt an, von wo die Kugel angestrahlt wird,
            und hat entsprechend Auswirkungen auf den Schatten. Wenn Sie gar
            keinen Schatten wollen, entfernen Sie die Markierung aus dem
            <quote>Schatten</quote>-Kontrollfeld. Als letztes müssen Sie
            noch die Hintergrundfarbe und die Farbe der Kugel auswählen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Sous Divers (Misc.), vous trouverez des scripts qui peuvent être
            utiles mais ne peuvent figurer dans les autres sous-menus. Par
            exemple le script Sphère. Vous aurez à fixer le rayon de la sphère
            en pixels. L'angle d'éclairage détermine la position de
            la source de lumière éclairant la sphère, ce qui agit aussi sur
            l'ombre de la sphère. Si vous ne voulez pas d'ombre, entrez la
            valeur FALSE. Enfin, choisissez la couleur de la sphère et du
            fond.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Sotto la voce Varie si trovano script molto utili che non
            rientrano i nessuna delle categorie suindicate. Un esempio è lo
            script Sfera. È necessario inserire il raggio in pixel per
            impostare la dimensione della sfera. L'angolazione della luce è
            dove si punta il faro sulla sfera. Questo valore ha conseguenze
            anche sull'ombra della sfera. Se non si desidera un'ombra basta
            togliere la spunta alla casella "ombra". Gli ultimi parametri da
            impostare sono il colore di primo piano e quello dello sfondo
            della sfera.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            Misc. 항목 아래에는 Sphere 스크립트와 같은 유용한 스크립트들이
            있습니다. Sphere 스크립트에는 구체 크기를 위한 반지름(픽셀),
            빛이 비추는 각도인 조명(각도)값을 넣어주어야 합니다.
            조명(각도)값은 구체의 그림자에도 관여합니다. 그림자를 원치
            않으면 "그림자" 체크상자를 해제합니다. 마지막으로 배경색과 구의
            색상을 정해주면 멋진 구체가 만들어집니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Her finn du dei skripta som ikkje passar inn i dei andre
            kategoriane. Akkurat nå ligg det bare eitt skript her,
            <quote>Kule</quote>. Etter at du har sett data for radius, for-
            og bakgrunnsfarge og lysvinkel, vil dette skriptet generere eit
            bilete av ei kule. Du kan også markera for om kula skal vere med
            eller utan skygge.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            В разном вы найдёте скрипты, которые могут быть вполне полезны, но
            которые не подходят для других подменю. В качестве примера
            представлен скрипт "Сфера". Вы должны установить радиус в
            пискелах, определяющий размер сферы. Угол освещения задаёт центр
            освещения сферы. Это значение также влияет на тень сферы. Если вам
            не нужна тень, вы должны убрать соответствующую отметку. Последняя
            вещь, которую вы должны выбрать это цвет фона и цвет вашей сферы.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            在杂项下是一些很有用但不在其它子菜单中的脚本。比如球体脚本，您需要
            设置半径的像素大小。光照角度是点光源指向球体的位置，该对球体阴影也有影
            响。如果您不想要阴影，就不要勾选“阴影”。最后要选取背景颜色和球体颜色。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <!--TODO es: translate-->
  <sect2 lang="de;en;fr;it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Image-Dependent Scripts</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bildabhängige Skripte</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Scripts dépendant d'une image</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Script immagine dipendenti</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">이미지 의존형 스크립트</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Biletavhengige skript</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Зависящие от изображения скрипты</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">依赖图像的脚本</phrase>
    </title>

   <!-- Modified for corresponding Gimp 2.4-->
   <!--TODO it;ko;ru;zh_CN: update-->

    <para lang="en">
      Now, scripts and filters that perform operations on an existing image are
      accessible directly by the appropriate menu. For example, the script
      <guimenu>New Brush</guimenu> (script-fu-paste-as-brush)
      is integrated in the <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> image menu
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Paste as...</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>New Brush</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>),
      that is more logical.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Furthermore, a new <guimenu>Color</guimenu> menu has been created that
      regroups together all that concern works on colors, the hue or level color
      adjustment tools, etc...
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu and <guimenu>Scripts-Fu</guimenu> menu are
      regrouped in one <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu and organised according
      to new categories. Now if a plugin and a filter works similarly, they are
      nearby in the menu.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The <guimenu>Scripts-Fu</guimenu> menu only appears if you have loaded
      additional scripts: for example the gimp-resynthesizer pack corresponding
      to your Linux distribution (.deb, .rpm, .gz...).
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Auf Skripte und Filter, die Operationen auf einem existierenden Bild
      ausführen, können Sie über das entsprechende Menü im Bildfenster
      zugreifen. So ist beispielsweise das Skript <quote>Neuer Pinsel</quote>
      in das Menü <quote>Bearbeiten</quote> im Bildfenster integriert
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Einfügen als</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>Neuer Pinsel</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>),
      was sehr viel logischer ist als früher.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Ferner gibt es nun ein neues Bildmenü <guimenu>Farben</guimenu>, das
      alle farbmanipulierenden Kommandos, wie etwa die Werkzeuge zur Änderung
      des <link linkend="gimp-tool-hue-saturation">Farbtons</link> oder der
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Werte</link>, zusammenfasst.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die Menüs <quote>Filter</quote> und <quote>Skript-Fu</quote> sind nun im
      Menü <guimenu>Filter</guimenu> zusammenfasst und nach neuen Kategorien
      angeordnet worden. Wenn ein Filter und ein Plugin ähnliche Aufgaben
      haben, liegen sie jetzt im selben Menü.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das <guimenu>Skript-Fu</guimenu>-Menü erscheint nur noch dann, wenn Sie
      zusätzliche Skripte installiert haben, beispielsweise das
      <quote>gimp-resynthesizer</quote>-Paket Ihrer Linuxdistribution.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Maintenant, les scripts et les filtres qui opèrent des transformations sur
      une image existante sont accessibles directement dans le menu adéquat. Par
      exemple, le script
      <guimenu>Nouvelle brosse</guimenu> (New Brush --> script-fu-paste-as-brush)
      a été intégré directement au menu <guimenu>Édition</guimenu> de l'image
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Édition</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Coller comme...</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>Nouvelle brosse</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>),
      ce qui est plus logique.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      De plus, un nouveau menu <guimenu>Couleur</guimenu> est apparu. Il regroupe
      tout ce qui concerne les travaux sur les couleurs, les outils d'ajustement
      de teinte ou de niveaux par exemple, etc.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le menu <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu> et le menu <guimenu>Scripts-Fu</guimenu>
      ont été fusionnés dans un menu <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu> unique et
      l'ensemble organisé selon de nouvelles catégories. Maintenant si un
      greffon et un script réalisent des opérations voisines, ils seront
      également voisins dans le menu.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le menu <guimenu>Scripts-Fu</guimenu> n'apparaît que si vous avez chargé
      des scripts supplémentaires: par exemple le paquet gimp-resynthesizer
      correspondant à votre distribution (.deb, .rpm, .gz...).
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Questi sono script che eseguono delle operazioni su un'immagine
      esistente. In molti versi questi agiscono come fossero dei plug-in del
      menu filtri. Il seguente gruppo di script viene installato insieme a
      GIMP:
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이곳의 스크립트들은 기존 이미지에 작업을 실행하기 위한 것들입니다.
      따라서 필터 메뉴에 있는 플러그인과 많은 부분이 닮아 있습니다. 다음은
      기본적으로 설치되는 스크립트들입니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Frå og med versjon 2.4 av GIMP blei skript og filter som arbeider
      direkte på eit eksisterande bilete lagt inn i andre menyar. For
      eksempel er skriptet <guimenu>Ny pensel</guimenu> 
      (script-fu-paste-as-brush) lagt inn i biletmenyen som 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Rediger</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Lim inn som...</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>Ny pensel</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> der det logisk høyrer heime.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Det er også sett inn ein ny meny, <guimenu>Fargar</guimenu>, der alle
      operasjonane som har med fargar å gjere er samla. 
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Menyane <guimenu>Filter</guimenu> og <guimenu>Scripts-Fu</guimenu>
      er ombygde og er nå samla i den nye menyen <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
      slik at programtillegg og filter som gjer nokolunde det same er samla på
      ein stad.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Menyen <guimenu>Scripts-Fu</guimenu> dukkar bare opp dersom du 
      legg inn tilleggsskript som for eksempel pakka 
      <quote>gimp-resynthesizer</quote> som følgjer med ein del 
      Linuxdistribusjonar (.deb, .rpm, .gz...).
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Эти скрипты выполняют операции на существующем изображении. В
      большинстве методов они сходны с плагинами из меню фильтров. Следующие
      группы скриптов устанавливаются по умолчанию:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">这些脚本对现有图像进行操作。它们在很多方面就像是滤镜菜单中的插件。默认 安装了下列组的脚本：</para>

    <!-- warning: not present in gimp >= 2.4 -->
    <!--TODO it;ko;ru;zh_CN must eliminate all that is below-->

    <itemizedlist lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
      <listitem lang="it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Alchimia</para>
        <para lang="ko">Decor</para>
        <para lang="ru">Декор</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">装饰</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Alfa a logotipo</para>
        <para lang="ko">Modify</para>
        <para lang="ru">Алхимия</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">动画</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Animatori</para>
        <para lang="ko">Animators</para>
        <para lang="ru">Аниматоры</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">Stencil Ops</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Decorazioni</para>
        <para lang="ko">Stencil Ops</para>
        <para lang="ru">Трафарет</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">炼金术</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Ombre</para>
        <para lang="ko">Alchemy</para>
        <para lang="ru">Алхимия</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">阴影</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Render</para>
        <para lang="ko">Shadow</para>
        <para lang="ru">Тень</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">绘制</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Selezione</para>
        <para lang="ko">Render</para>
        <para lang="ru">Визуализация</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">工具</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Stencil Ops</para>
        <para lang="ko">Utils</para>
        <para lang="ru">Утилиты</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">选区</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="it">Utilità</para>
        <para lang="ko">Selection</para>
        <para lang="ru">Выделение</para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">选区</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <variablelist lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
      <varlistentry lang="it;ko;no;ru;zh_CN">
        <term lang="it">Stencil Ops</term>
        <term lang="ko">Stencil Ops</term>
        <term lang="ru">Трафарет</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">Stencil Ops</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="it">
            Qui si possono trovare due script: Scolpiscilo e Cromalo, che
            effettuano degli effetti veramente interessanti su immagini in
            scala di grigi.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            Carve-It 과 Chrome-It 스크립트는 회색톤 이미지에 근사한 예술
            효과를 만들어줍니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Здесь вы найдёте два скрипта: "Вырезать" и "Хромировать", которые
            могут отрисовывать кое-какие действительно хорошие эффекты на
            изображениях в градациях серого.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">这里有两个滤镜： Carve-It 和 Chrome-It，它们能
            在灰度图像上绘制非常艺术的效果。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <term lang="it">Crea ombra</term>
        <term lang="ko">Drop Shadow</term>
        <term lang="ru">Падающая тень</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">投影</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="it">
            Crea ombra creerà un'ombra dietro l'oggetto selezionato. Possiede
            tre importanti parametri: gli spostamenti in X e in Y che
            determinano dove verrà posta l'ombra relativamente all'oggetto
            selezionato. Lo spostamento è misurato sempre in pixel. Valori
            molto alti fanno sembrare l'ombra molto distante mentre valori
            piccoli la fanno sembrare vicina all'oggetto. Il valore di
            sfocatura è anche molto importante dato che un'ombra molto
            distante da un oggetto in genere dovrebbe avere un'ombra molto
            sfocata.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            드롭 쉐도우는 선택한 물체에 그림자를 만듭니다. 여기에는 세
            가지 중요한 인수가 있습니다. X, Y 오프셋은 선택된 물체의
            어느쪽에 그림자를 만들지 결정하게 되며, 오프셋 단위는
            픽셀입니다. 높은 값은 그림자가 멀리 떨어진 듯 보이게 되며, 낮은
            값은 물체에 가깝게 있는 것처럼 보이게 됩니다. 그리고 블루어 값도
            중요한데, 이는 블루어 값이 높을수록 그림자가 멀리 떨어진 느낌을
            주기 때문입니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            "Падающая тень" создаст тень позади выбранного вами объекта.
            Существует три важных параметра. Смещение по оси X и Y определяет
            расположение тени по отношению к выбранному объекту. Смещение
            измеряется в пикселах. Большое значение создаст видимость тени на
            большом расстоянии, небольшое значение создаст видимость тени
            ближе к объекту. Радиус размывания также важен, поскольку
            находящаяся на удалённом расстоянии от объекта тень имеет больший
            уровень размытия.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            投影将在您选取物体后面生成阴影。它有三个重要的参数。位移 X 和 Y
            决定阴影相对于选取物体的位置，位移的单位是像素。高值使阴影看上去
            非常远，低指则使它和物体更近。模糊半径值也比较重要，因为一个表现
            为离物体较远的阴影有一个高的模糊等级。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
        <term lang="it">Prospettiva</term>
        <term lang="ko">Perspective Shadow</term>
        <term lang="ru">Перспектива</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">透视阴影</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="it">
            Il comando ombre/prospettiva ha un parametro molto importante:
            l'angolo di prospettiva. Se questo angolo è impostato tra 0 e 180
            gradi, non ci sarà ombra, dato che lo script assume che l'oggetto
            non abbia spessore. Ciò significa anche che questo script
            funzionerà bene per certi angoli ma non troppo naturale per altri.
            Gli altri parametri sono abbastanta auto-espliciti. L'ombra sarà
            molto più sfocata se l'orizzonte è distante e la lunghezza
            dell'ombra è relativa alla dimensione dell'oggetto selezionato.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            원근 그림자에서 가장 중요한 인수는 원근 각도입니다. 각도가 0
            에서 180 의 값을 가질때에는, 물체에 두께가 없다고 가정되어
            그림자가 생기지 않습니다. 이 말은 제대로 된 각도에서는 비록
            자연스럽지는 않지만 좋은 그림자를 만들어 준다라는 것입니다.
            다른 인수값들은 굳이 설명히 필요하지 않을 것입니다. 블루어 값을
            증가시키면 수평선이 점차 멀어지게 되고, 그림자 길이는 선택된
            물체에 대한 상대적인 길이입니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            "Перспектива" имеет один очень важный параметр: угол перспективы.
            Если угол установлен на 0 или 180, тени не будет, поскольку скрипт
            предполагает, что объект не имеет никакой толщины. Также это
            означает, что результат работы скрипта выглядит прекрасно с
            определёнными значениями угла, и неестественно с другими.
            Остальные параметры весьма очевидны. Вы получите больше размытое
            пятно, если горизонт будет далеко, и длина тени это длина
            относительно выбранного объекта.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            透视阴影有一个非常重要的参数：透视角度。该脚本假设物体没有厚度，
            因此该值为 0 或180，则没有阴影。这也表明该脚本在某些角度看上去
            不错，但在其它角度就不自然。其它的参数都容易看懂。水平太远就会更
            加模糊，阴影长度就是相对于选取物体的长度。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
