<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!--  section history:
  2006-08-03 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-06-15 added Korean translation by Dust 
  2006-01-06 updated fr
  2006-01-05 fixed ambigous description of installing new script-fu
             scripts (#324309) 
 -->
<sect1 id='gimp-concepts-script-fu' lang="cs;en;fr;it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="fr;ko">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-01-06</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-15</date>
        <authorinitials>먼지군</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Používání Script-Fu skriptů</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Using Script-Fu Scripts</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Utiliser les Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Uso degli script Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">Script-Fu 스크립트 사용하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="sv">Använda GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Использование скриптов Script-Fu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">使用 Script-Fu 脚本</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en;cs;fr;it;ko;ru;zh_CN">Script-Fu</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Script-Fu?</title>
    <title lang="en">Script-Fu?</title>
    <title lang="fr">Script-Fu ?</title>
    <title lang="ko">Script-Fu?</title>
    <title lang="it">Script-Fu?</title>
    <title lang="ru">Script-Fu?</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">Script-Fu？</title>

    <para lang="cs">
      Script-Fu je to, čemu by se ve světě Windows říkalo „makra“. Script-Fu
      je ale mnohem víc. Script-Fu je založeno na interpretovaném jazyku
      Scheme, což je dialekt Lispu, a při své činnosti se dotazuje na funkce z
      databáze Gimpu. Script-Fu lze používat k ohromnému množství účelů, ale
      začátečníci obvykle používají Script-Fu k automatizaci úkonů, které:
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Script-Fu is what the Windows world would call "macros" But Script-Fu is
      more powerful than that. Script-Fu is based on an interpreting language
      called Scheme, and works by using querying functions to the Gimp
      database. You can do all kinds of things with Script-Fu, but an ordinary
      Gimp user will probably use it for automating things that:
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Script-Fu est ce que le monde Windows appellerait des "macros" mais
      Script-Fu est bien plus puissant que cela. Script-Fu est basé sur un
      langage interprêté appelé le Scheme, et fonctionne en utilisant des
      fonctions de requêtes sur la base de données de Gimp. Vous pouvez faire
      toutes sortes de choses avec Script-Fu, mais l'utilisateur de base de
      Gimp l'utilisera pour automatiser des choses :
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Gli Script-Fu sono quello che nel mondo Windows si chiamano "macro"
      solo più potenti. Gli Script-Fu sono basati su un linguaggio
      interpretato chiamato Scheme, e lavorano interrogando le funzioni nel
      database di Gimp. È possibile fare qualsiasi operazione con gli
      Script-Fu, anche se gli utenti normali di GIMP li usano
      prevalentemente per automatizzare operazioni che:
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 는 윈도우즈의 "매크로"와 비슷한 기능을 하지만 조금더 
      강력하다. Script-Fu 는 Scheme 이라는 인터프리팅 언어에 기반을 두고
      있으며 김프 데이터베이스에 쿼리문을 요청하는 방식으로 동작한다.
      원한다면 Script-Fu 의 모든 기능을 사용할 수 있지만, 일반적인 김프
      사용자들은 주로 다음과 같은 경우에 사용한다.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Script-Fu это то, что в мире Windows называется  "макросами". Но в
      сравнении с ними Script-Fu  явлется более мощным инструментом. 
      Script-Fu основан на интерпретируемом  языке, называемом Scheme, и
      работает с помощью  использования запрашиваемых функций из базы 
      данных GIMP. С помощью Script-Fu вы можете  производить все виды
      действий, но обычный  пользователь GIMP вероятно использует его 
      для автоматизации таких вещей как: 
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      Script-Fu 在 Windows 世界中叫做“宏”，不过 Script-Fu 比宏更强大。
      Script-Fu 是基于一个叫 Scheme 的解释语言，通过查询 GIMP 数据库的功能来
      工作。您可以使用 Script-Fu 干各种各样的事，不过一般的 GIMP 用户可能用
      它做些自动化的操作如：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang="cs">
      <listitem><para>
        Chce často provádět.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Jsou velmi složité a těžce zapamatovatelné.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem><para>
        You want to do frequently.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Are really complicated to do, and hard to remember.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="fr">
      <listitem><para>
        qu'il fait fréquemment,
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        qui sont très compliquées et dures à retenir.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="it">
      <listitem><para>
	  si esegue frequentemente;
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
	  molto complesse da eseguire e difficili da ricordare.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ko">
      <listitem><para> 
        자주 쓰게 되는 기능.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para> 
        꽤 복잡하며 기억하기 어려운 작업.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ru">
      <listitem><para>
        Часто производимые операции.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Действительно сложные и трудные для запоминания операции.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem><para>
        您经常要做的。
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        做起来很麻烦的和很难记住的。
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="cs">
      Pamatujte si však, že se Script-Fu můžete dělat mnohem víc. Skripty
      dodávané s Gimpem mohou být velmi užitečné, ale to nejcennější co vám
      mohou dát, je studijní materiál, který vás může přivést ke zvládnutí a
      později i mistrovství ve Script-Fu. Nebo alespoň mohou být základem k
      úpravám při tvorbě nového skriptu. Pokud ve vás slovo Fu vzbuzuje
      asociace s mistry bojových umění, hlubokými meditacemi a téměř
      nadlidskými schopnostmi, nejste daleko od pravdy. Odtud má své jméno.
      Chcete-li se vydat cestou Script-Fu, pokračujte tutoriálem v následující
      sekci.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Remember that you can do a whole lot with Script-Fu. The scripts that
      come with Gimp can be quite useful, but they can also serve as models
      for learning Script-Fu, or at least as a framework and source of
      modification when you make your own script. Read the Script-Fu Tutorial
      in the next section if you want to learn more about how to make scripts.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Souvenez-vous que vous pouvez faire beaucoup avec Script-Fu. Les scripts
      qui sont fournis avec le Gimp peuvent être très utiles, mais ils peuvent
      aussi servir de modèle pour comprendre Script-Fu, ou au moins de
      charpente et de source lorsque vous faites vos propres scripts. Lisez le
      Tutoriel Script-Fu dans la section suivante si vous soulez apprendre
      comment faire écrire des scripts.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Si può fare molto con gli Script-Fu. Gli script forniti con Gimp
      possono essere molto utili, e possono servire ottimamente anche come
      esempi per imparare a creare gli Script-Fu, o per lo meno come
      struttura e sorgente di ispirazione per la creazione delle proprie
      procedure. Leggere attentamente il tutorial nella sezione seguente se
      si desidera cominciare a imparare a creare degli script.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 를 이용하면 굉장히 많은 일들을 할 수 있다. 김프의 
      스크립트들은 굉장히 유용하며, Script-Fu 를 배우기 위한 모델을 
      제공하거나 직접 작성한 스크립트의 수정을 위한 틀을 제공한다. 
      Script-Fu 에 대해 더 많은 것을 배우고 싶다면 다음 장에 있는 
      Script-Fu 강좌를 읽어보기 바란다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Помните, что вы можете сделать множество вещей с  помощью
      Script-Fu. Установливаемые вместе с GIMP  скрипты весма полезны,
      но они также могут  служить в качестве примеров для изучения
      Script-Fu, или как основа и исходник, модифицируя который  вы
      создаёте свой скрипт. Прочитайте руководство по созданию 
      Script-Fu в следующем разделе, если вы желаете узнать больше  о
      том, как создавать скрипты. 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      记住您可以用 Script-Fu 做大量的事。GIMP 自带的脚本十分有用，不过您也可
      以用它们了学习了解 Script-Fu，或是用它们作为您自己编写脚本的框架和参考。
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      V této kapitole popíšeme některé z nejužitečnějších skriptů, nikoliv
      však všechny. Je jich totiž prostě příliš mnoho. Některé jsou navíc
      velmi jednoduché a k jejich používání není třeba žádné dokumentace.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      We will describe some of the most useful scripts in this chapter, but we
      won't cover them all. There are simply too many scripts. Some of the
      scripts are also very simple and you will probably not need any
      documentation to be able to use them.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Nous décrirons certains des scripts les plus utiles dans ce chapitre,
      mais nous ne les couvrirons pas tous. Il sont tout simplement trop
      nombreux. De plus, certain scripts sont très simples et vous n'aurez pas
      besoin de documentation pour les utiliser.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      In questo capitolo verranno descritti alcuni dei più utili script
      anche se (per ragioni di spazio) non tutti; ce ne sono troppi! Alcuni
      degli script sono così semplici che non necessitano di nessuna
      documentazione per padroneggiarne l'uso.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이 장에서 유용한 스크립트들에 대해 설명을 할 것이지만 모든 
      스크립트들을 소개하지는 않을 것이다. 그리고 많은 스크립트들은 굉장히
      단순해서 설명서가 없어도 사용하는데 아무런 지장이 없을 것이다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В этой главе мы опишем некоторые из наиболее полезных скриптов, 
      но мы не будем рассматривать все. Просто доступно слишком много 
      скриптов. Некоторые из скриптов также очень просты, и вам вероятно 
      не понадобится никакой документации для обучения их использованию.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="cs">
      Script-Fu (respektive Scheme) není jediný skriptovací jazyk vhodný pro
      Gimp. Script-Fu je však jediný skriptovací jazyk dostupný ve výchozí
      instalaci.
      
      isn't the only scripting
      language available for Gimp. But Script-Fu is the only scripting
      language that is installed by default. Other available scripting
      extensions are Perl and Tcl. You can download and install both
      extensions at the <ulink url='http://registry.gimp.org'>Gimp
      Plugin Registry</ulink>. 
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Script-Fu (a dialect of Scheme) isn't the only scripting
      language available for Gimp. But Script-Fu is the only scripting
      language that is installed by default. Other available scripting
      extensions are Perl and Tcl. You can download and install both
      extensions at the <ulink url='http://registry.gimp.org'>Gimp
      Plugin Registry</ulink>. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Script-Fu (un dialecte du Scheme) n'est pas le seul langage de 
      script disponible avec le Gimp. Mais Script-Fu est le seul qui 
      soit installé par défaut. Les autres languages disponibles en 
      extension sont Perl et Tcl. Vous pouvez télécharger et installer 
      ces deux extensions dans
      <ulink url='http://registry.gimp.org'>le registre de plugins du
      Gimp</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Script-Fu (un dialetto del linguaggio Scheme) non è il solo
      linguaggio di scripting disponibile per GIMP anche se Script-Fu è
      l'unico predefinito nell'installazione. Altre estensioni di scripting
      sono disponibili per il linguaggio Perl e Tcl. Le estensioni sono
      disponibili da scaricare e da installare sul sito
      del <ulink url='http://registry.gimp.org'>Registro dei Plugin di
      GIMP</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu(Scheme 의 일종인) 는 김프에서만 사용가능한 언어는 아니다.
      하지만 김프에서 기본으로 설치되는 유일한 스크립팅 언어이다. 물론 
      Perl 이나 Tcl 등의 다른 스크립팅 확장을 사용할 수도 있다. 이러한 
      것들은 
      <ulink url='http://registry.gimp.org'>Gimp Plugin Registry</ulink>
      에서 다운로드 받아 설치할 수 있다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Script-Fu (диалект языка Scheme) не единственный доступный  для
      GIMP скриптовый язык. Но Script-Fu это единственный  язык, который
      устанавливается по умолчанию. Другими доступными скриптовыми
      расширениями являются Perl и Tcl. Вы можете загрузить  и
      установить оба расширения со страницы  <ulink
      url='http://registry.gimp.org'>Реестр плагинов GIMP</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      我们在这里要介绍一些最有用的脚本，不过不是全部。因为实在是有太多的脚本，
      有些也非常简单而不需要任何文档就能使用它们。
    </para>
    
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="en;fr;ko;ru;zh_CN">
    <title lang="en">Installing Script-Fus</title>
    <title lang="fr">Installer des Script-Fu</title>
    <title lang="it">Installazione degli Script-Fu</title>
    <title lang="ko">Script-Fu 설치하기</title>
    <title lang="ru">Установка скриптов</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">安装脚本</title>
    <para lang="en">
      One of the great things about Script-Fu is that you can share your
      script with all your Gimp friends. There are many scripts that come with
      Gimp by default, but there are also vast quantities of scripts that are
      available for download all around the Internet.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Un des points forts de Gimp est que vous pouvez échanger vos 
      scripts avec ceux de vos amis. Nombreux sont les scripts présents 
      par défaut dans Gimp, mais encore plus nombreux ceux que vous 
      pourrez trouver sur la Toile.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Uno dei fattori notevoli degli Script-Fu è che è possibile
      condividerli con gli amici. Ci sono molti script che vengono forniti
      predefiniti con GIMP, ma ci sono anche un gran numero di script
      disponibili per il prelievo su Internet.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 의 주요 장점중 하나는 스크립트를 다른 김프 사용자들과 
      공유해 쓸수 있다라는 점이다. 또한 김프와 함께 배포되는 스크립트들은
      인터넷에 있는 모든 스크립트들 중에서 가장 유용한 것들만 모아놓은 
      것이다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Одной из самых замечательный вещей в Script-Fu является 
      возможность делиться скриптами с вашими 
      GIMP'овыми друзьями. Доступно множество скриптов которые 
      установлены по умолчанию вместе с GIMP, но также существует 
      огромное количество скриптов, которые доступны для закачки 
      из Интернет.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      Script-Fu 的一个优点就是您可以将它们共享给所有的 GIMP 朋友。虽然 GIMP
      默认就安装了许多脚本，但是互联网上还有非常多可下载的脚本。
    </para>
    
    <procedure lang="en">
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          If you have downloaded a script, copy or move it to your
          scripts directory. It can be found in the Preferences:
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Folders</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.         
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Do a refresh by using
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Exts</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Refresh Scripts</guimenuitem>   
            </menuchoice>
           from the toolbox.
          The script will now appear in one of your menus.
          If you don't find it, look for it under the root file menu
          filters. If it doesn't appear at all, something was wrong with
          the script (e.g. it contains syntax errors).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    
    <procedure lang="fr">
      <step>
        <para lang="fr">
          Si vous avez téléchargé un script, copiez-le ou déplacez-le dans 
          votre répertoire de scripts.
          <footnote>
            <para>
              Ce répertoire de scripts peut être trouvé dans les Préférences: 
              <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Dossiers</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
              </link>
            </para>
          </footnote>.         
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="fr">
          Faites un rafraîchissement en utilisant
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Exts</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Rafraîchir les scripts</guimenuitem>   
            </menuchoice>
          dans le menu de la Boîte à outils. Le script doit apparaître dans 
          la liste déroulante du menu Script-fu. Si vous ne le trouvez pas, 
          voyez dans le menu Scrip-fu de l'image. Et s'il ne s'y trouve pas 
          non plus, c'est qu'il y a une erreur de syntaxe dans le script.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="it">
      <step>
        <para lang="it">
	  Se si è scaricato uno script, per usarlo è necessario copiarlo o
          spostarlo nella cartella personale degli script di GIMP. Questa è
	  definita nella finestra delle preferenze:
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Cartelle</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>Script</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
          </link>.         
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="it">
	  Ricaricate l'elenco usando
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Rinfresca gli script</guimenuitem>   
            </menuchoice>
	    dal pannello degli strumenti.
            Ora gli script scaricati dovrebbero apparire in uno dei menu.
            Se non lo trovate, cercatelo sotto il menu principale dei
            filtri. Se non appare da nessuna parte significa che deve
            esserci un qualche tipo di errore nello script (per es. un
            errore di sintassi).
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure lang="ko">
      <step>
        <para lang="ko">
          스크립트를 다운로드 받거나 사용자 스크립트 디렉토리로 옮겼을 경우
          기본 설정의 
          <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders">  -->
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>폴더</guimenu>
              <guimenuitem>스크립트</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
           에서 찾을 수 있을 것이다.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para lang="ko">
          그리고
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>확장</guimenu>
              <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
              <guimenuitem>Refresh Scripts</guimenuitem>   
            </menuchoice>
          를 통해 도구상자를 새로고침한다.
          그러면 이제 메뉴에서 스크립트를 볼 수 있을 것이다. 만약 보이지 
          않는다면 이미지창의 필터 메뉴를 찾아본다. 그래도 없다면 스크립트 
          자체에 문법오류와 같은 문제가 있는 것이다.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <tip lang="ru">
       <para>
        Если вы скачали скрипт, скопируйте или переместите ваш 
        новый скрипт в директорию 
        <filename>.gimp-2.2/scripts</filename> и произведите 
        обновление. Скрипт появится в одном из ваших меню. Если вы 
        его не нашли, поищите в основном меню фильтров. 
        Если он всё еще не появился, с этим скриптом что-то не так.
      </para>
    </tip>
    
    <tip lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        下载一个脚本后，将它拷贝或移动
        到 <filename>.gimp-2.2/scripts</filename> 目录然后刷新，这样该脚本就
        会在某个菜单中显示。如果没有发现，说明该脚本可能有问题。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="en;fr;it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
    <title lang="en">Do's and Don'ts</title>
    <title lang="fr">Ce qu'il faut faire et ce qu'il ne faut pas</title>
    <title lang="it">Cose che si possono e che non si possono fare</title>
    <title lang="ko">해야 할 것과 하지 말아야 할 것</title>
    <title lang="ru">Работа и ошибки</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">注意事项</title>

    <para lang="en">
      A common error when you are dealing with Script-Fus is that you simply
      bring them up and press the OK button. When nothing happens, you
      probably think that the script is broken or buggy, but there is most
      likely nothing wrong with it.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Une erreur classique lorsque vous utilisez un Script-Fu est de
      simplement le lancer et appuyer sur le bouton OK. Lorsque rien ne se
      passe vous penserez que le script s'est planté ou est occupé, mais il
      est plus probable qu'il n'y a rien d'anormal là-dedans.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Un errore molto frequente quando si sta lavorando con gli Script-Fu
      accade quando li si porta in primo piano e si preme il punsante di OK
      e sembra non succedere niente. Si pensa subito che c'è qualcosa che
      non va con lo script, probabilmente un difetto o altro ma spesso
      invece non c'è nulla di errato.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      Script-Fu 를 사용하는데 가장 흔한 실수는 Script-Fu 를 실행시킨 후 
      성급히 "확인" 버튼을 누르는 것이다. 이후 아무 변화도 생기지 않으면
      흔히 해당 스크립트가 깨졌거나 오류가 있다고 생각하겠지만, 사실 
      대부분은 정상 작동한 것이다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Распространённым убеждением, часто вызывающим ошибку,             
      является убеждение о том, что для работы со скриптами нужно      
      просто вызывать их и нажать кнопку ОК. Когда ничего не      
      происходит, вы вероятно думаете,что работа скрипта прервана или      
      он содержит ошибку. 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN"> 使用 Script-Fu 最常见的错误就是打开它们然后直接按下
      “确定”按钮。当什么也没发生时，您可以认为该脚本坏了或有 BUG，其实最可能
      是它什么问题都没有。
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Think again. Did you really read the information in the dialog,
      or did you just press the button? If you forgot an input the
      script needs, or if you gave it the wrong input, the script will
      fail. One of the most common errors is that the font specified
      in the script dialog hasn't been installed on your system. So
      please check the information in the dialog before blaming the
      script. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Réfléchissez. Avez-vous lu les informations dans le dialogue, ou 
      avez-vous juste cliqué ? Si vous avez omis une entrée dont le 
      script a besoin, ou si vous avez fourni une fausse information, le 
      script plantera. L'une des erreurs les plus communes est que la 
      police de caractère spécifiée dans le dialogue du script n'a pas 
      été installée sur votre système. Aussi, s'il vous plaît, vérifiez 
      les informations du dialogue avant de maudire le script.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ripensandoci. Le informazioni sulla finestra di dialogo sono state
      lette attentamente o si è premuto semplicemente il pulsante OK senza
      pensare? Se si dimentica i dati in ingresso che sono necessari per lo
      script o se si immettono dati errati, lo script non funzionerà. Uno
      degli errori più comuni è che il tipo di carattere specificato nella
      finestra di dialogo dello script non è stato installato o non è
      presente nel sistema. Controllare sempre attentamente le informazioni
      nella finestra di dialogo prima di incolpare lo script!
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      생각해보자. 대화상자에 나온 정보들을 제대로 읽어보았는가, 아니면 그저
      버튼을 눌렀는가? 스크립트에 필요한 입력값을 넣지 않았거나 잘못된 값을
      입력했다면 스크립트는 제대로 실행되지 않을 것이다. 사실 대부분의 
      에러는 스크립트 대화상자에 열거된 폰트가 시스템에 설치되어 있지 않은
      경우에 발생한다. 따라서 괜히 스크립트를 탓하기 전에 대화상자의 정보를
      확인해두는 것이 좋다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Подумайте снова. Действительно ли вы прочитали содержавшуюся 
      в диалоге информацию, или вы просто нажали кнопку? 
      Если вы забыли ввести необходимые скрипту параметры, или 
      ввели ошибочные данные, он завершится с ошибкой.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      再想想您是不是仔细读了对话框中的信息，或只是简单地按了按钮？如果忘记输
      入脚本需要的东西或输入错误，它将运行失败。一个最常见的错误就是脚本对话
      框所需要的字体在您的系统中没被安装。因此请在责怪脚本之前仔细检查对话框
      中的信息。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="en;fr;it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
    <title lang="en">Different Kinds Of Script-Fus</title>
    <title lang="fr">Différentes sortes de Script-Fu</title>
    <title lang="it">Tipi differenti di Script-Fu</title>
    <title lang="ko">다른 종류의 Script-Fu</title>
    <title lang="ru">Виды Скрипт-Фу</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">Script-Fu 的不同类型</title>
    <para lang="en">
      There are two kinds of Script-Fus -- standalone scripts and
      image-dependent scripts. You will find the standalone variants
      under 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type of Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> in the main toolbox menu, 
      and the image-dependent scripts are placed under 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type of Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> in the image menu.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il y a deux sortes de Script-Fu -- les scripts qui dépendent d'une 
      image et les autres (que nous appelerons "autonomes").
      Vous trouverez ces derniers dans le menu principal de la boîte
      à outil sous
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Exts</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type de Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>, alors que les scripts qui dépendent d'une image sont 
      sous 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>Type de Script</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> du menu image.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ci sono due tipi di Script-Fu -- script a sé stanti e script
      dipendenti dall'immagine. La variante indipendente si trova sotto
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Xtns</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>(tipo di script)</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> presente nel menu principale del pannello degli strumenti, 
      mentre il tipo dipendente dall'immagine è sistemato sotto
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>(tipo di script)</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> nel menu immagine.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      스크립트는 독립형 스크립트와 이미지 의존형 스크립트가 있다. 독립형
      스크립트는 기본 도구상자 메뉴의 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>확장</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>스크립트 종류</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      에서 찾을 수 있고, 이미지 의존형 스크립트는 이미지 메뉴의
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>스크립트 종류</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      에 있다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Существует два вида скриптов - самостоятельные и зависящие от 
      изображения. Самостоятельные вы найдёте в меню панели инструментов
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Расш.</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Скрипт-Фу</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>тип скрипта</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> 
      зависимые от изображения скрипты расположены в меню 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Скрипт-Фу</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem><replaceable>тип скрипта</replaceable></guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      有两种类型的 Script-Fu -- 独立脚本和依赖图像的脚本。独立脚本在工具箱菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>扩展</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Script-Fu</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>，而依赖图像的脚本在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Script-Fu</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="en;fr;it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
    <title lang="en">Standalone Scripts</title>
    <title lang="fr">Les scripts autonomes</title>
    <title lang="it">Script autonomi</title>
    <title lang="ko">독립형 스크립트</title>
    <title lang="ru">Самостоятельные скрипты</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">独立脚本</title>
    <para lang="en">
      We will not try to describe every script in depth. Most
      Script-Fus are very easy to understand and use. At the time of
      this writing, the following types are installed by default:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Nous n'essayerons pas de décrire à fond chaque script. La plupart 
      des Script-Fu sont très faciles à comprendre et à utiliser. Au 
      moment de l'écriture de ce manuel, les catégories suivantes sont 
      installées par défaut :
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Non tenteremo di descrivere in dettaglio ogni tipo di script. Molti
      sono banali da capire e usare. Quando questo capitolo è stato
      scritto, i tipi seguenti di script erano predefinitivamente
      installati:
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      여기서 모든 스크립트들을 자세하게 다룰 수는 없다. 그리고 대부분의 
      스크립트들은 굉장히 쉽게 사용할 수 있다. 기본으로 설치되는 스크립트의
      종류는 다음과 같다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Мы не ставим перед собой цель детального описания  каждого
      скрипта. Большинство скрипт-фу очень   и легки для понимания и
      использования. На момент  написания этих строк,  по умолчанию
      устанавливаются следующие типы:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      我们不会深入介绍每个脚本，大多数 Script-Fu 都很容易使用。截至撰写该文
      档时，GIMP 默认安装了下列独立脚本：
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem><para>
        Patterns
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Web page themes
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Logos
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Buttons
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utils
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Make Brush
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Misc.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="fr">
      <listitem><para>
        Boutons
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Créer brosse
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Divers
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Logos
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Motifs
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Thèmes de page web
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utilitaires
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="it">
      <listitem><para>
        Motivi
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Temi per pagine web
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Logotipi
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Pulsanti
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utilità
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Crea pennello
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Varie
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ko">
      <listitem><para>
        Patterns
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Web page themes
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Logos
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Buttons
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utils
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Make Brush
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Misc.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ru">
      <listitem><para>
        Текстуры<!--в интерфейсе всё еще 'шаблоны'-->
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Темы Web-страниц
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Эмблемы
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Кнопки
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Утилиты
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Создать кисть
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Разное
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem><para>
        图案
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        网页主题
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        徽标
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        按钮
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        工具
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        制作画笔
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        杂项
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


  <variablelist lang="en">

    <varlistentry><term>Patterns</term>
      <listitem><para>
        You will find all kinds of pattern-generating scripts
        here. Generally, they are quite useful because you can add many
        arguments to your own patterns.
      </para>
      <para>
        We'll take a look at the Land script. In this script you have to
        set the image/pattern size, and specify what levels of random to
        use for your land creation. The colors used to generate the land
        map are taken from the currently selected gradient in the
        gradient editor. You must also supply values for the level of
        detail, land and sea height/depth and the scale. Scale refers to
        the scale of your map, just as in an ordinary road map, 1:10
        will be typed as 10. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Web Page Themes</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Here is clearly a practical use for scripts. By creating a
        script for making custom text, logos, buttons arrows, etc., for
        your web site, you will give them all the same style and
        shape. You will also be saving a lot of time, because you don't
        have to create every logo, text or button by hand. 
      </para>
      <para>
        You will find the Gimp.org theme under the Web page theme
        submenu. If you want to create your own theme, this script
        will serve as an excellent template that you can modify to
        create a theme for your web site. 
      </para>
      <para>
    Most of the scripts are quite self-explanatory, but here are
    some hints: 
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          Leave all strange characters like ' and " intact.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Make sure that the pattern specified in the script exists.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Padding refers to the amount of space around your text.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          A high value for bevel width gives the illusion of a higher button.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          If you type TRUE for "Press", the button will look pushed down.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Choose transparency if you don't want a solid background. If
          you choose a solid background, make sure it is the same
          color as the web page background. 
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Logos</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Here you will find all kinds of logo-generating scripts. This
        is nice, but use it with care, as people might recognize your
        logo as being made by a known Gimp script. You should rather
        regard it as a base that you can modify to fit your needs. The
        dialog for making a logo is more or less the same for all such
        scripts:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          In the Text String field, type your logo name, like Frozenriver.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          In the Font Size text field, type the size of your logo in pixels.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          In the Font text field, type the name of the font that you
          want to use for your logo. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          To choose the color of your logo, just click on the color
          button. This brings up a color dialog. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          If you look at the current command field, you can watch the
          script run. 
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Make Buttons</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Under this headline you'll find a script that makes beveled
        buttons. The script has a dozen parameters or so, and most of
        them are similar to those in the logo scripts. You can
        experiment with different settings to come up with a button you
        like. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <!-- warning: not present anymore in gimp > 2.2 -->
    <varlistentry><term>Utils</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Under Utils you will find a small but nice script: the Fontmap
          script, which makes an image of your fonts. You will have to
          type the names of the fonts you want displayed in the Fonts
          text field. 
        </para>
        <para>
          The Custom gradient script creates an image of the current
          custom gradient in the gradient editor. This can be useful if
          you want to pick colors from a gradient as in a palette. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
 
    <varlistentry><term>Misc.</term> <!-- warning: changed 2006-08-03 -->
      <listitem>
	<para>
          Under Misc. you'll find scripts that can be quite useful, but
	  aren't suitable for the other submenus. An example is the Sphere
	  script. You will have to set the radius in pixels to determine
	  the sphere size. The lighting angle is where at the sphere you
	  point the spotlight. This value also has an impact on the sphere
	  shadow. If you don't want a shadow, you just have remove the tick
	  on the "shadow" checkbox. The last thing you have to select is
	  background color, and the color of your sphere.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <!-- warning: not present anymore in gimp > 2.2 -->
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Make Brush</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This script lets you make your own custom rectangular/circular
          brushes, with or without feathered (blurred) edges. The script
          will automatically store your brush in your personal brush
          directory. You just have to press refresh in the Brush
          Selection dialog to use your newly created brush. 
       </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>


  <variablelist lang="fr">

    <varlistentry><term>Motifs</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Vous trouverez là toutes sortes de scripts générateurs de motifs.
      </para>
      <para>
        Prenons par exemple le script Land. Dans ce script, vous devez 
        régler la taille de l'image/motif, et spécifier quels niveaux de 
        hasard vous désirez pour votre création. Les couleurs utilisées 
        pour générer la carte du paysage sont prises dans le dégradé 
        actif. Vous devez aussi préciser le niveau de détails, la 
        hauteur/profondeur de la terre et de la mer ainsi que l'échelle.
        L'échelle se réfère à l'échelle de votre carte, comme dans une 
        carte de géographie, le 1/10è étant indiqué 10.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Thèmes de pages Web</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Il y a là un usage très pratique des scripts. En réalisant 
        vous-même des scripts pour créer des textes sur mesure, des 
        logos, des boutons-flèches...etc, vous leur donnerez à tous 
        un même style. Et vous économiserez beaucoup de temps puisque 
        vous n'aurez pas à les créer à la main.
      </para>
      <para>
        Vous trouverez le thème Gimp.org dans le sous-menu pages Web. 
        Si vous voulez créer votre propre thème, ce script vous servira 
        de modèle.
      </para>
      <para>
        La plupart des scripts n'ont pas besoin d'explication. Voici 
        néanmoins quelques conseils:
      </para> 
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          Laissez intacts les caractères étranges comme  '  et  ". 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Assurez-vous que le motif spécifié dans le script existe. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Remplissage (padding) se réfère à l'importance de l'espace 
          vide autour de votre texte. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Une forte valeur de biseau (bevel) donne l'illusion d'un 
          bouton plus haut. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Si vous donnez la valeur TRUE (Vrai) à «Press», le bouton 
          aura l'aspect enfoncé. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Choisissez la transparence si vous ne voulez pas avoir un 
          fond plein. Si vous choisissez un fond plein, veillez à ce 
          qu'il soit de la même couleur que le fond de votre page Web. 
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Logos</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Vous trouverez là des scripts pour générer des logos. C'est bien,
        mais on pourra voir que votre logo a été fait avec un script 
        Gimp connu. Voyez-les plutôt comme une base que vous pouvez 
        modifier pour créer quelque chose d'original. La boîte de 
        dialogue est à peu près la même dans tous ces scripts: 
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          Dans le champ Chaîne de texte (Text String), tapez le nom de 
          votre logo. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Dans le champ taille de police (Font Size), tapez la taille de 
          votre logo en pixels. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Dans le champ Police (Font), tapez le nom de la police, tapez 
          le nom de la police que vous voulez utiliser. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Pour choisir la couleur de votre logo, cliquez simplement sur 
          le bouton couleur, ce qui ouvrira une fenêtre de choix de 
          couleur. 
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Si vous regardez le champ de commande courant, vous pouvez voir 
          le script agir. 
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Fabriquer des boutons</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Sous cette tête de chapitre, vous trouverez un script qui crée 
        des boutons en relief avec biseau. Il possède une douzaine de 
        paramètres dont la plupart ressemblent à ceux des scripts de 
        logo. Expérimentez par vous-même. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Utils</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Sous Utils, vous trouverez un bien joli petit script: le script 
        Fontmap, qui fait une image de vos polices. Vous devrez taper le 
        nom des polices que vous voulez afficher dans le champ texte 
        Fonts (Polices).
      </para>
      <para> 
        Le script Custom gradient (dégradé sur mesure) crée une image 
        du dégradé sur mesure de l'Éditeur de dégradés. Ce peut être 
        utile si vous voulez prélever des couleurs dans le dégradé 
        comme dans une palette. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Misc.</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Sous Misc. (Divers), vous trouverez des scripts qui peuvent 
        être utiles mais ne peuvent figurer dans les autres sous-menus. 
        Par exemple le script Sphère. Vous aurez à fixer le rayon de la 
        sphère en pixels. L'angle d'éclairage détermine la position de 
        la source de lumière éclairant la sphère, ce qui agit aussi sur 
        l'ombre de la sphère. Si vous ne voulez pas d'ombre, entrez la 
        valeur FALSE. Enfin, choisissez la couleur de la sphère et du 
        fond. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Créer une brosse</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Ce script vous permet de créer votre propre brosse rectangulaire 
        ou circulaire, avec ou sans bords adoucis. Le script sauvegardera 
        automatiquement votre brosse dans votre répertoire des brosses 
        personnel. Il vous suffit alors de cliquer sur Rafraîchir dans le 
        dialogue de sélection des brosses pour pouvoir utiliser la brosse. 
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist lang="it">

    <varlistentry><term>Motivi</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Qui si trovano tutti i tipi di script utili per la generazione di
          motivi. Sono molto utili in quanto è possibile personalizzarli
          inserendo molti argomenti.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Diamo un'occhiata allo script Paesaggio. In questo script è
          necessario impostare la dimensione dell'immagine/motivo e
          specificare il livello di casualità da usare la la creazione
          dell'immagine della landa. I colori usati per generare la mappa
          della terra vengono presi dal gradiente attualmente selezionato
          nell'editor del gradiente. È necessario anche fornire i valori
          del livello di dettaglio, altezza della terra e profondità del
          mare e la scala. La scala si riferisce alla scala della mappa,
          come in una normale carta stradale; 1:10 sarà scritto come 10.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Temi per pagine web</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Ecco un uso pratico per gli script. Fare uno script per creare
          testo personalizzato, logotipi, pulsanti frecce, ecc. per il
          proprio sito web è un modo pratico per mantenere coerente lo
          stile del sito e contemporaneamente risparmiare molto tempo in
          queste operazioni ripetitive.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Nel sottomenu dei temi per le pagine web si troverà anche il tema
          gimp.org. Se si desidera creare un proprio tema, questo script è
          un eccellente modello personalizzabile per creare il tema del
          proprio sito. 
	</para>
	<para>
	  Molti degli script sono auto-documentati ma ecco un po' di
	  suggerimenti: 
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
              Lasciare tutti quegli strani caratteri come ' e " come sono.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Controllare che il motivo specificato nello script esista.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Lo riempimento si riferisce alla quantità di spazio attorno al
            testo.
          </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Un valore alto di spessore smussatura dà l'illusione di un
              pulsante in rilievo.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Se si imposta la casella di "premuto", il pulsante
              avrà l'effetto premuto.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Scegliere la trasparenza se non si vuole uno sfondo pieno. Se
              si sceglie lo sfondo pieno, assicuratevi che sia dello stesso
              colore dello sfondo della pagina web.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>Logotipi</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Qui si trovano tutti i tipi di script per la generazione di
          logotipi. Simpatico ma da usare cum grano salis, dato che è
          facile che la gente riconosca che il logo è stato fatto con un
          comune script GIMP. È meglio considerarli come una base
          modificabile per soddisfare le proprie esigenze dopo una adeguata
          personalizzazione. La finestra di dialogo per la generazione di
          un logotipo è più o meno la stessa per tutti gli script:
	</para>
	<orderedlist>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Nel campo di testo insterire il nome del logotipo, come
              Fiumeghiacciato.
          </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Nel campo della dimensione del carattere, inserire la
              dimensione del logo in pixel.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Nel campo del carattere, inserire il nome del font che si
              intende utilizzare per il logotipo.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Per scegliere il colore del logo, fare clic sul pulsante del
            colore. L'operazione porterà in primo piano la finestra di
            selezione del colore. 
          </para>
	</listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Se si guarda il campo del comando corrente è possibile
            osservare l'andamento dello script durante l'esecuzione.
          </para>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>Pulsanti</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Sotto quest'intestazione si troveranno gli script che servono per
          generare automaticamente immagini di pulsanti in rilievo. Gli
          script hanno dozzine di parametri e molti sono simili o
          equivalenti a quelli presenti negli script dei
          logotipi. Sperimentate tranquillamente fino ad ottenere il
          pulsante desiderato.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <!-- warning: not present anymore in gimp > 2.2 -->
    <varlistentry><term>Utilità</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Sotto la voce Utilità si troverà un piccolo ma utile script: lo
          script della mappa caratteri, che crea un'immagine di esempio dei
          caratteri specificati.
	  È necessario indicare il nome dei font che si vuole
          visualizzare nel campo di testo apposito. Verrà creata un
          immagine contenente il nome del font con vicino un'esempio di resa.
        </para>
        <para>
	  Lo script del gradiente personalizzato crea un'immagine del
          gradiente personalizzato corrente presente nell'editor dei
          gradienti. Utile se si vuole prelevare dei colori dal gradiente
          come si fa per le tavolozze.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
 
    <varlistentry><term>Varie.</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Sotto la voce Varie si trovano script molto utili che non
          rientrano i nessuna delle categorie suindicate. Un esempio è lo
          script Sfera. È necessario inserire il raggio in pixel per
          impostare la dimensione della sfera. L'angolazione della luce è
          dove si punta il faro sulla sfera. Questo valore ha conseguenze
          anche sull'ombra della sfera. Se non si desidera un'ombra basta
          togliere la spunta alla casella "ombra". Gli ultimi parametri da
          impostare sono il colore di primo piano e quello dello sfondo
          della sfera.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <!-- warning: not present anymore in gimp > 2.2 -->
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Crea pennello</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Questo script permette di creare pennelli rettangolari o
          circolari personalizzati, con o senza bordi sfumati. Lo script
          automaticamente memorizza il pennello nella cartella personale
          dei pennelli di GIMP. Una volta creato basta premere il pulsante
          "Aggiorna pennelli", presente nella finestra di selezione dei
          pennelli, per usare il nuovo pennello appena creato.
       </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>


  <variablelist lang="ko">

    <varlistentry><term>Patterns</term>
      <listitem><para>
        이곳에는 패턴 생성 스크립트들이 모여있다. 여러가지 인자들을 
        첨가해서 다양한 패턴을 생성할 수 있다.
      </para>
      <para>
        Land 스크립트를 보면, 이미지/패턴 크기, 그리고 Land 생성에 필요한
        임의 레벨값을 설정해야 한다. Land map 생성에 사용되는 색상은 
        그라디언트 편집기에서 선택된 그라디언트를 사용하게 된다. 그리고
        land 의 높이, sea 의 깊이, 스케일 등의 구체적인 값들도 정해줘야 
        한다. 스케일은 맵의 배율로 1:10 인 경우 10을 넣어주면 된다.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Web Page Themes</term>
      <listitem><para>
        실제적으로 스크립트를 사용할 수 있는 부분이다. 웹사이트에서는 
        텍스트, 로고, 화살표 버튼 따위가 통일될 필요성이 있는데 이럴 때에
        스크립트를 이용해 만들면 된다. 그리고 이를 저장해 두었다가 필요할
        때에 불러내어 만들면 로고, 텍스트, 버튼 따위를 매번 새로 만들지
        않아도 된다.
      </para>
      <para>
        Web page theme의 하위 메뉴를 보면 Gimp.org 테마를 볼 수 있다.
        이곳에 있는 스크립트가 제공하는 템플릿을 이용하면 근사한 웹사이트용
        테마를 만들 수 있을 것이다.
      </para>
      <para>
        대부분의 스크립트들은 자체적인 설명을 가지고 있다.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          ' 와 " 같은 특수 문자는 모두 제거한다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          스크립트에 명시된 패턴이 존재하는지 확인한다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          패딩은 텍스트 주변의 공간에 따라 결정된다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          베벨 높이의 높은 값은 그 상위 버튼의 환영(幻影)을 만든다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          "Press" 항목에 TRUE 를 입력하면 눌려진 버튼이 생성된다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          짙은 배경을 원치 않는다면 투명도를 선택하면 된다. 만약 짙은 
          배경을 사용한다면 그것이 웹페이지 배경과 같은지 확인해야 한다.
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Logos</term>
      <listitem><para>
        여기엔 로고 제작과 관련된 스크립트들이 모여 있다. 이것은 꽤 
        유용하지만 조심해서 써야 한다. 그것은 유명한 김프 스크립트로 만든
        것이 티날 수도 있기 때문이다. 따라서 원하는 형태로 만들기 위한
        기본틀 정도로 생각하는 것이 좋다. 로고 제작을 위한 모든 스크립트가 
        제공하는 대화상자는 거의 비슷한 형태를 취하고 있다.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          문자열 입력란에는 Frozenriver처럼 로고 이름을 입력한다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          폰트 크기 입력란에는 로고의 크기를 픽셀단위로 입력한다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          폰트 입력란에는 로고에 사용하려고 하는 폰트의 이름을 입력한다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          로고의 색상은 색버튼을 클릭하면 나타나는 색 대화상자에서 
          선택한다.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          현재 명령행을 통해 스크립트가 진행되는 과정을 볼 수 있다.
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Make Buttons</term>
      <listitem><para>
        이 항목 아래에 있는 스크립트들은 경사진 버튼을 만들기 위한 
        것들이다. 많은 인수값들이 있지만, 그 대부분은 로고 스크립트와 
        비슷하다. 이 값들을 잘 조정하면 원하는 버튼을 만들 수 있다.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Utils</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Utils 항목 아래에는 작지만 훌륭한 스크립트인 폰트맵 스크립트가 
          있다. 이것은 폰트 이미지를 만드는 스크립트로 폰트 입력란에 폰트 
          이름을 입력해야 한다.
        </para>
        <para>
          사용자 그라디언트 스크립트는 그라디언트 편집기에 있는 기존 
          그라디언트의 이미지를 생성한다. 이는 색상표와 같은 그라디언트에서
          색상들을 추출해낼 때 유용하다.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
 
    <varlistentry><term>Misc.</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Misc. 항목 아래에는 다른 하위메뉴들과 비슷하진 않지만 굉장히 유용한
        스크립트들이 있다. 예를 들어 Sphere 스크립트에서 반지름(픽셀) 
        란에는 구체의 크기, 조명(각도) 란에는 빛이 비추는 각도를 넣어준다.
        조명(각도) 의 값은 구체의 그림자에도 관여한다. 그리고 이제 
        마지막으로 배경색과 구의 색상을 정해주면 멋진 구체가 만들어진다.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Make Brush</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          이 스크립트는 페더가 들어간 다양한 다각형/원형의 브러쉬를 만들기
          위한 것이다. 여기서 만든 브러쉬는 자동적으로 사용자 브러쉬 
          디렉토리로 저장이 된다. 따라서 브러쉬를 만들고 브러쉬 선택 
          대화상자를 새로 고침하기만 하면 새 브러쉬를 볼 수 있다.
       </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist lang="ru">

    <varlistentry><term>Текстуры</term>
      <listitem><para>
        Здесь вы найдете все скрипты, генерирующие текстуры. 
        Вообще, они довольно полезны, поскольку вы можете добавить 
        множество аргументов к своим текстурам.
      </para>
      <para>
        Рассмотрм скрипт "Земля". В этом скрипте вы должны установить 
        размер изображения/текстуры, и задать уровень случайности, 
        используемый для создания земли. Используемые для генерации 
        карты цвета взяты из текущего выбранного градиента в редакторе 
        градиентов. Вы также должны установить значения для уровня 
        детализации, высоту/глубину земли и моря, также как в обычной 
        дорожной карте, 1:10 представляется как 10.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Темы Web-страниц</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Вот это очевидное практическое применение скриптов. 
        Создавая скрипт для создания текста, эмблем, кнопок-указателей, 
        и т.д. вы даёте всем им одинаковый стиль и форму. Вы также 
        сохраняете массу времени, поскольку вам не нужно создавать 
        каждую эмблему, текст или кнопку вручную.
      </para>
      <para>
        Вы найдёте тему Gimp.org в подменю тем web-страниц. 
        Если вы желаете создать свою собственную тему, 
        этот скрипт может послужить вам отличным шаблоном, 
        модифицируя который вы можете создать тему для своего 
        сайта.
      </para>
      <para>
	Большинство скриптов достаточно самодокументированы, но вот 
	несколько подсказок:
      </para>
       <itemizedlist>
       <listitem><para>
          Оставьте все странные символы, такие как ' и " нетронутыми.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Удостоверьтесь, что указанная в скрипте текстура существует.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Заполнение определяет колчиество пространства вокруг 
          вашего текста.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Большое значение ширины скоса создаст иллюзию более высокой 
          кнопки.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Если вы отметите пункт "нажатая", кнопка будет выглядеть нажатой.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Выберите прозрачность если не хотите сплошной фон. 
          Если вы выберите сплошной фон, удостоверьтесь, что 
          это такой же цвет как и у фона веб страницы.
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Эмблемы</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Здесь вы найдёте все типы генерирующие логотипы скриптов. 
        Это хорошо, но используйте их с предосторожностью, поскольку люди 
        могут узнать вашу эмблему, как сделанную известным скриптом GIMP. 
        Вы должны скорее расценивать это как основу, которую вы можете 
        изменить в соответствии вашим потребностями. Диалог создания эмблем 
        более или менее такой же как и для всех подобных скриптов:
       </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          В поле ввода текста введите имя вашей эмблемы, например, Frozenriver.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          В поле ввода размера шрифта введите размер вашей эмблемы в пикселах.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          В поле ввода текста введите имя шрифта, который вы 
          хотите использовать для вашей эмблемы.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Для выбор цвета вашей эмблемы просто щёлкните по кнопке 
          выбора цвета. Это вызовет диалог выбора цвета.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Если вы посмотрите на поле выполнения текущей команды<!--FIXME?-->, 
          вы увидите, что скрипт запущен.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Make Buttons</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Под этим заголовком вы найдёте скрипт,  создающий выпуклые
	  кнопки. Скрипт имеет  приблизительно дюжину параметров, и
	  большинство из них подобно тем, что описаны в скриптах 
	  создания эмблем. Вы можете экспериментировать с  различными
	  параметрами настройки,  чтобы получить кнопку, которую вам
	  нравится.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term>Утилиты</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Здесь вы найдёте небольшие, но приятные скрипты: скрипт 
          "Карта шрифта", который создаёт изображение с вашими 
          шрифтами. Вы должны ввести названия шрифов, которые вы 
          хотите видеть в поле отображения шрифтов.
        </para>
        <para>
          Скрипт "Отобразить градиент" создаёт изображение текущего 
          выбранного градиента в редакторе градиента. Это может быть 
          полезным, если вы хотите получить цвета из градиента как из 
          палитры.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
 
    <varlistentry>
    <term>Разное</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        В разном вы найдёте скрипты, которые могут быть вполне 
        полезны, но которые не подходят для других подменю. 
        В качестве примера представлен скрипт "Сфера". 
        Вы должны установить радиус в пискелах, определяющий 
        размер сферы. Угол освещения задаёт центр освещения 
        сферы. Это значение также влияет на тень сферы. 
        Если вам не нужна тень, вы должны убрать 
        соответствующую отметку. Последняя вещь, которую вы 
        должны выбрать это цвет фона и цвет вашей сферы.
      </para>
     </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
      <term>Создать кисть</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         Этот скрипт позволяет вам создать свою  собственную
	 прямоугольную/круглую кисть,  с размытыми краями или без.
	 Скрипт  автоматически сохранить созданную кисть в  вашу
	 персональную директорию кистей. Для  использования вашей вновь
	 созданной кисти  вам нужно будет просто нажать кнопку 
         "Обновить" в диалоге выбора кистей. 
       </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist lang="zh_CN">

    <varlistentry><term>图案</term>
      <listitem><para>
        这里有生成图案的所有脚本，它们是很有用的可以对您的图案添加很多参数。
      </para>
      <para>
        以凹凸地图脚本为例，您需要设置图像/图案尺寸和随机种子数,以及从渐变编
        辑器中选取生成凹凸地图颜色的渐变，另外必须设定细节等级，地面和海洋的
        高度/深度和缩放，缩放就是地图的比例，和普通的道路地图中的一样，1:10
        就输入 10。
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>网页主题</term>
      <listitem><para> 这里是一些关于脚本的实际应用。通过一个创建自定义文字，
        徽标，按钮箭头等的脚本，可以给您的网页统一的风格和样式。它也可以给您
        节约很多时间，因为不用自己手动创建每一个徽标，文字和图标。
      </para>
      <para>
        在网页主题子菜单下的 Gimp.org 给您创建自己的主题提供一个完美的模板，
        通过修改它就可以创建自己的网站主题。
      </para>
      <para>
	大部分脚本都很容易理解其用法，不过这里有些有用的提示：
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          保留完整的像 ' 和 " 一样的奇怪字符。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          确认脚本中使用的图案是存在的。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          衬垫指文字周围空格的数量。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          一个高的“斜面宽度”值体现一个更高的按钮。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          勾选“按下”，按钮就好像被按下一样。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          如果不想要一个纯色背景就要选择透明。使用纯色背景时要确保它和网页背景颜色相同。
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>徽标</term>
      <listitem><para> 这里是生成徽标的所有脚本。它们很不错，不过要注意，人
        们可能会发现您的徽标是由大家都知道的 GIMP 脚本创建的。最好把它们作为
        您修改和满足需要的模板。对于所有的这些脚本其对话框都很相似：
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>
          在文字区域，输入徽标的名字，如 Frozenriver。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          在字体大小区域，输入您徽标的像素大小。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          在字体区域，输入您徽标要使用的字体。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          要给您的徽标选择颜色，点击颜色按钮，会出现一个颜色对话框。
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          您可以在当前命令区域看到脚本在运行。
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>按钮</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  这里可以找到产生斜面按钮的脚本。该脚本有非常多参数，
          其中大部分都和徽标脚本中的相同。您可以体验不同参数产生的按钮。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>工具</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
          在工具下有一个简单但很好的脚本：字体表脚本，它生成字体的图像，您需
          要在文字区域输入所要显示的字体名字。
	</para>
	<para>
          自定义渐变脚本创建在渐变编辑器中当前自定义渐变的图像，这样您可以很
          方便地像从从渐变中拾取颜色，就像从色板中一样。  
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>杂项</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  在杂项下是一些很有用但不在其它子菜单中的脚本。比如球体脚本，您需要
	  设置半径的像素大小。光照角度是点光源指向球体的位置，该对球体阴影也有影
	  响。如果您不想要阴影，就不要勾选“阴影”。最后要选取背景颜色和球体颜色。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>制作画笔</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  通过这些脚本可以创建矩形/椭圆，是否带羽化(模糊)边缘的自定义画笔。
          它们会自动将创建的画笔保存到个人画笔目录中，您只需要在画笔选择对话框
          中刷新它们就能使用这些新建的画笔了。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect lang="en;fr;it;ko;ru;zh_CN">
    <title lang="en">Image-Dependent Scripts</title>
    <title lang="fr">Scripts lancés depuis une image</title>
    <title lang="it">Script immagine dipendenti</title>
    <title lang="ko">이미지 의존형 스크립트</title>
    <title lang="ru">Зависящие от изображения скрипты</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">依赖图像的脚本</title>
    <para lang="en">
      These are scripts that perform operations on an existing
      image. In many ways they are like the plug-ins in the Filters
      menu. The following script groups are installed by default: 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Il y a des scripts qui opèrent des transformations à partir
      d'une image existante. Souvent ils agissent ou ressemblent
      à des greffons installés dans le menu Filtres.
      Ces scripts sont rangés par défaut selon les catégories suivantes :
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Questi sono script che eseguono delle operazioni su un'immagine
      esistente. In molti versi questi agiscono come fossero dei plug-in
      del menu filtri. Il seguente gruppo di script viene installato
      insieme a GIMP: 
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      이곳의 스크립트들은 기존 이미지에 작업을 실행하기 위한 것들이다.
      따라서 필터 메뉴에 있는 플러그인과 많은 부분이 닮아 있다. 다음 
      스크립트 그룹들은 기본적으로 설치되는 것들이다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
       Эти скрипты выполняют операции на существующем изображении. 
       В большинстве методов они сходны с плагинами из меню фильтров. 
       Следующие группы скриптов устанавливаются по умолчанию: 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这些脚本对现有图像进行操作。它们在很多方面就像是滤镜菜单中的插件。默认
      安装了下列组的脚本：
    </para>

    <!-- warning: modified 2006-08-03 -->
    <!-- warning: not present in gimp > 2.2 -->
    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem><para>
        Alchemy
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Alpha to logo
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Animators
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Decor
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Render
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Selection
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Shadow
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Stencil Ops
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utils
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="fr">
      <listitem><para>
        Décor
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Modifier
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Animateurs
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Pochoirs (Stencil ops)
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Alchimie
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Ombre
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Rendu
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utilitaires
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Sélection
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <!-- warning: not present in gimp > 2.2 -->
    <itemizedlist lang="it">
      <listitem><para>
        Alchimia
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Alfa a logotipo
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Animatori
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Decorazioni
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Ombre
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Render
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Selezione
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Stencil Ops
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utilità
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ko">
      <listitem><para>
        Decor
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Modify
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Animators
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Stencil Ops
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Alchemy
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Shadow
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Render
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Utils
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Selection
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="ru">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Декор
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Алхимия
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Аниматоры
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Трафарет
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Алхимия
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Тень
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Визуализация
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Утилиты
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Выделение
       </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem><para>
        装饰
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        动画
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Stencil Ops
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        炼金术
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        阴影
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        绘制
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        工具
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        选区
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <variablelist lang="en">
      <varlistentry><term>Stencil Ops</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Here, you'll find two scripts: Carve-It and Chrome-It, which
          can render some truly nice artistic effects on grayscale
          images. 
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Drop Shadow</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Drop Shadow will cast a shadow behind your selected
          object. It has three important parameters. X and Y offset
          determine where the shadow will be placed in relation to the
          selected object. Offset is measured in pixels. High values
          make the shadow look like it's far away, and low values will
          make it look closer to the object. The blur value is also
          important, because a shadow that is cast far from the object
          has a higher blur level. 
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Perspective Shadow</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Perspective Shadow has a very important parameter: the
          perspective angle. If this angle is set to 0 or 180, there
          will be no shadow, because the script assumes that the object
          has no thickness. This also means that this script looks fine
          in certain angles, but unnatural in others. The other
          parameters are quite self-explanatory. You'll get more blur if
          the horizon is far away, and the shadow length is the length
          in relation to the selected object. 
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>   

    <variablelist lang="fr">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Pochoirs (Stencil Ops)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Contient deux scripts: Carve-it (Sculpter) et Chrome it
            (Chromer), qui donnent un bel effet artistique sur les
            images en niveaux de gris. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Ombre portée (Drop Shadow)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ombre portée projètera une ombre derrière l'objet
            sélectionné.  Il dispose de trois paramètres importants: Les
            décalages (offset) X et Y déterminent où l'ombre sera placée
            par rapport à l'objet sélectionné. Ils sont mesurés en
            pixels. Les fortes valeurs allongeront l'ombre et les
            faibles valeurs la raccourciront. Le flou est important, car
            une ombre étendue est floue. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Ombre en Perspective (Perspective Shadow)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Un paramètre important: l'angle de perspective. Si cet angle
            est égal à O ou à 180, il n'y aura pas d'ombre, car le
            script suppose alors que l'objet n'a pas d'épaisseur. cela
            signifie aussi que certains angles donneront un bel effet et
            que d'autres auront un effet déplorable. Les autres
            paramètres n'ont pas besoin d'explication. Vous aurez plus
            de flou si l'horizon est lointain et la longueur d'ombre est
            la longueur en rapport avec l'objet sélectionné. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>   

    <variablelist lang="it">
      <varlistentry><term>Stencil Ops</term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Qui si possono trovare due script: Scolpiscilo e Cromalo, che
            effettuano degli effetti veramente interessanti su immagini in
            scala di grigi.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Crea ombra</term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Crea ombra creerà un'ombra dietro l'oggetto
            selezionato. Possiede tre importanti parametri: gli spostamenti
            in X e in Y che determinano dove verrà posta l'ombra
            relativamente all'oggetto selezionato. Lo spostamento è
            misurato sempre in pixel. Valori molto alti fanno sembrare
            l'ombra molto distante mentre valori piccoli la fanno sembrare
            vicina all'oggetto. Il valore di sfocatura è anche molto
            importante dato che un'ombra molto distante da un oggetto in
            genere dovrebbe avere un'ombra molto sfocata.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Prospettiva</term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Il comando ombre/prospettiva ha un parametro molto importante:
            l'angolo di prospettiva. Se questo angolo è impostato tra 0 e
            180 gradi, non ci sarà ombra, dato che lo script assume che
            l'oggetto non abbia spessore. Ciò significa anche che questo
            script funzionerà bene per certi angoli ma non troppo naturale
            per altri. Gli altri parametri sono abbastanta
            auto-espliciti. L'ombra sarà molto più sfocata se l'orizzonte è
            distante e la lunghezza dell'ombra è relativa alla dimensione
            dell'oggetto selezionato.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>   

    <variablelist lang="ko">
      <varlistentry><term>Stencil Ops</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Carve-It 과 Chrome-It 스크립트는 회색톤 이미지에 근사한 예술 
          효과를 만들어준다.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Drop Shadow</term>
        <listitem><para>
          드롭 쉐도우는 선택한 물체에 그림자를 만들어 준다. 여기에는 세 
          가지 중요한 인수가 있는데, X, Y 오프셋 값은 선택된 물체의 
          어느쪽에 그림자를 만들지 결정하게 되며 오프셋 단위는 픽셀이다.
          높은 값은 그림자가 멀리 떨어진 듯 보이게 되며, 낮은 값은 물체에
          가깝게 있는 것처럼 보이게 된다. 그리고 블루어 값도 중요한데 이는
          블루어 값이 높을수록 그림자가 멀리 떨어진 느낌을 주기 때문이다.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>Perspective Shadow</term>
        <listitem><para>
          원근 그림자에서 가장 중요한 인수는 원근 각도이다. 각도가 0 에서
          180 의 값을 가질때에는 물체에 두께가 없다고 가정되어 그림자가 
          생기지 않는다. 이 말은 제대로 된 각도에서는 비록 자연스럽지는 
          않지만 좋은 그림자를 만들어 준다라는 것이다. 다른 인수값들은
          굳이 설명히 필요하지 않을 것이다. 블루어 값을 증가시키면 
          수평선이 점차 멀어지게 되고, 그림자 길이는 선택된 물체에 대한
          상대적인 길이이다.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist lang="ru">
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Трафарет</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Здесь вы найдёте два скрипта: "Вырезать" и "Хромировать", 
          которые могут отрисовывать кое-какие действительно хорошие 
          эффекты на изображениях в градациях серого. 
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Падающая тень</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          "Падающая тень" создаст тень позади выбранного вами объекта. 
          Существует три важных параметра. Смещение по оси X и Y 
          определяет расположение тени по отношению к 
          выбранному объекту. Смещение измеряется в пикселах. 
          Большое значение создаст видимость тени на большом 
          расстоянии, небольшое значение создаст видимость 
          тени ближе к объекту. Радиус размывания также важен, 
          поскольку находящаяся на удалённом расстоянии от объекта 
          тень имеет больший уровень размытия. 
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Перспектива</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          "Перспектива" имеет один очень важный параметр: 
          угол перспективы. Если угол установлен на 0 или 180, тени 
          не будет, поскольку скрипт предполагает, что объект не имеет 
          никакой толщины. Также это означает, что результат работы 
          скрипта выглядит прекрасно с определёнными значениями угла, 
          и неестественно с другими. Остальные параметры 
          весьма очевидны. Вы получите больше размытое 
          пятно, если горизонт будет далеко, 
          и длина тени это длина относительно выбранного объекта.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist lang="zh_CN">
      <varlistentry><term>Stencil Ops</term>
        <listitem><para>
          这里有两个滤镜： Carve-It 和 Chrome-It，它们能在灰度图像上绘制非常艺术的效果。
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>投影</term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
            投影将在您选取物体后面生成阴影。它有三个重要的参数。位移 X 和 Y
            决定阴影相对于选取物体的位置，位移的单位是像素。高值使阴影看上去
            非常远，低指则使它和物体更近。模糊半径值也比较重要，因为一个表现
            为离物体较远的阴影有一个高的模糊等级。
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>透视阴影</term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
            透视阴影有一个非常重要的参数：透视角度。该脚本假设物体没有厚度，
            因此该值为 0 或 180，则没有阴影。这也表明该脚本在某些角度看上去
            不错，但在其它角度就不自然。其它的参数都容易看懂。水平太远就会更
            加模糊，阴影长度就是相对于选取物体的长度。
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>   
  </simplesect>
</sect1>
