<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-concepts-selection' lang="cs;en;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Výběr</title>
  <title lang="en">The Selection</title>
  <title lang="fr">La Sélection</title>
  <title lang="it">La selezione</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">选区</title>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Při manipulaci s obrázkem je často pořeba upravit jen jeho část.
    V Gimpu se proto taková část před úpravou <emphasis>vybere</emphasis>.
    Ke každému obrázku je připojen tzv. <emphasis>výběr</emphasis>.
    Většina, nikoliv však všechny, operací v Gimpu se provádí pouze
    na vybraných částech obrázku.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Often when you operate on an image, you only want part of it to be
    affected.  In Gimp, you make this happen by
    <emphasis>selecting</emphasis> that part.  Each image has a
    <emphasis>selection</emphasis> associated with it.  Most, but not
    all, Gimp operations act only on the selected portions of the
    image.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Souvent, quand vous travaillez sur une image, vous voulez que 
    seule une partie en soit affectée. Vous le faites en <emphasis>
    sélectionnant</emphasis> cette partie. Beaucoup d'opérations dans 
    Gimp ne portent que sur des sélections.    
  </para>
  <para lang='it'>
    Spesso quando si opera su di un'immagine si desidera lavorare solo su
    parte di essa. In Gimp basta <emphasis>selezionare</emphasis> questa parte.
    Ogni immagine ha una <emphasis>selezione</emphasis> associata ad essa.
    Molte, ma non tutte, le operazioni di Gimp lavorano solo sulla porzione
    selezionata dell'immagine.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当对一个图像处理时，您常常只想处理其中的一部分。在 GIMP 中，通过<emphasis>选择</emphasis>那部分来实现。每个图像上都有一个相关的<emphasis>选区</emphasis>。大部分，但不是全部的 GIMP 操作只对图像选择部分进行操作。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Jak oddělit strom od pozadí?
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    V mnoha situacích je vytvoření správného a kvalitního výběru
    nejdůležitějším a klíčovým momentem celé grafické práce. Často je také
    úkolem nejobtížnějším, vyžadujícím nejvíce zkušeností. Představme si,
    že z obrázku výše chceme oddělit strom od pozadí a vložit ho do jiného
    obrázku. K tomu je zapotřebí vytvořit výběr obsahující celý strom alke nic
    jiného. Protože tvar stromu je složitý a na mnoha místech je těžké odlišit
    ho od pozadí, není to jednoduchý úkol.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          How would you isolate the tree?
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    There are many, many situations where creating just the right selection is
    the key to getting the result you want, and often it is not very easy to
    do.  For example, in the above image, suppose I want to cut the tree out
    from its background, and paste it into a different image.  In order to do
    this, I need to create a selection that contains the tree and nothing but
    the tree.  It is difficult because the tree has a very complex shape, and
    in several spots is hard to distinguish from the objects behind it.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Comment allez-vous isoler l'arbre?
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    Nombreux sont les cas où une sélection est indispensable mais 
    n'est pas facile à réaliser. Par exemple, dans l'image ci-contre, 
    supposons que nous voulions séparer l'arbre de son fond et le 
    coller dans une autre image. Pour cela, nous devons créer une 
    sélection qui isole l'arbre et seulement l'arbre. Ce n'est pas 
    facile car il a une forme très complexe et, en plusieurs points, 
    on le distingue mal des objets situés derrière lui .
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fog-tree-example.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          如何把这个树独立出来？
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    这有很多，很多的情形，创建正确的选区是获取您所有结果的关键，常常这并不容易办到。比如，在右边的图像中，我准备将树从背景中剪切出来，并粘贴到其它的图像中。为了达到这个目的，我需要创建一个只包含树而没有其它任何东西的选区。这就比较困难，因为树有一个非常复杂的形状，而且在某些地方与其后的物体很难区分。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Obvyklý způsob zobrazení výběru pomocí přerušované čáry,
          tzv. „pochodujících mravenců“.
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    Velmi důležité je pochopit následující skutečnost: Výběr se obvykle
    zobrazuje jako přerušovaná čára ohraničující vybranou oblast. Z toho
    se dalo usuzovat, že výběr je jakási nádoba, uvnitř které jsou vybrané
    oblasti a mimo kterou jsou oblasti nevybrané. Tato představa výběru
    je v mnoha případech použitelná, ale není správná.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Selection shown as usual with dashed line
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    Now here is a very important point, and it is crucial to
    understand this.  Ordinarily when you create a selection, you see
    it as a dashed line enclosing a portion of the image.  The idea
    you could get from this is that the selection is a sort of
    container, with the selected parts of the image inside, and the
    unselected parts outside.  This concept of the selection is okay
    for many purposes, but it is not really correct.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Sélection présentée avec sa ligne pointillée.
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
      Un point très important, et qu'il est crucial de comprendre. 
      Quand vous créez une sélection, elle est entourée d'une ligne en 
      pointillés qui englobe donc une partie de l'image. Vous pourriez 
      penser que la sélection est une sorte de réceptacle avec la 
      partie sélectionnée de l'image à l'intérieur et la partie non 
      sélectionnée à l'extérieur. Cette idée est valable dans de 
      nombreux cas, mais elle n'est pas vraiment correcte.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          选区通常用虚线表示
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    现在这是非常重要的地方了，弄明白这点是至关重要的。通常的，当创建一个选区，您会发现它是一条虚线环绕在图像一部分上。您可能决定选区好像一种容器，图像选择的部分在内，未选择部分在外。这种关于选区的观点在许多目的中没有问题，但它并不是完全正确的。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Výběr je ve skutečnosti implementován jako <emphasis>kanál</emphasis>.
    Z technického hlediska je tedy totožný s barevnými kanály či alfa kanálem
    obrázku. Výběr tedy pro každý pixel obrázku definuje hodnotu v rozsahu
    0 (nevybraný) až 255 (zcela vybraný). Výhodou tohoto přístupu je
    skutečnost, že některé pixely mohou být <emphasis>částečně
    vybrané</emphasis>, tedy jim je přiřazena některá z hodnot mezi 0 a 255.
    Často jsou plynulé přechody mezi vybranými a nevybranými oblastmi
    nenahraditelné.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Actually the selection is implemented as a
    <emphasis>channel</emphasis>.  In terms of its internal structure,
    it is identical to the red, green, blue, and alpha channels of an
    image.  Thus, the selection has a value defined at each pixel of
    the image, ranging between 0 (unselected) and 255 (fully
    selected).  The advantage of this approach is that it allows some
    pixels to be <emphasis>partially selected</emphasis>, by giving
    them intermediate values between 0 and 255.  As you will see,
    there are many situations where it is desirable to have smooth
    transitions between selected and unselected regions.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    En fait, la sélection est mise en œuvre comme un <emphasis>canal
    </emphasis>. Sa structure est identique à celle des canaux rouge, 
    vert, bleu et alpha d'une image. Chaque pixel de la sélection 
    possède ainsi une valeur définie entre 0 (non sélectionné) et 255 
    (pleinement sélectionné). Vous comprenez ainsi que certains pixels 
    peuvent être <emphasis>partiellement sélectionnés</emphasis>. Et 
    vous verrez que dans de nombreuses situations, il est souhaitable 
    d'avoir une transition douce entre les régions sélectionnées et 
    non sélectionnées.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    准确地说，选区是作为一个<emphasis>通道</emphasis>来实现的。在其内部结构方面，它与图像的红色，绿色，蓝色和 alpha通道完全相同。因此，选区中有一个定义每个图像像素的值，从 0 (未选中)到 255 (完全选中)。这种方式的优点是，它允许一些像素被<emphasis>部分选中</emphasis>，其值在 0 到 255 之间。正如您所见的，这有许多需要在选中和未选中区域间有个平滑的过渡的情况。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Co tedy znamená ona přerušovaná čára plná mravenců?
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    What, then, is the dashed line that appears when you create a
    selection?
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Mais alors, que signifie la ligne pointillée qui entoure la sélection?
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    哪怎么当您创建一个选区时，虚线就出现了？
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Jedná se o <emphasis>konturu</emphasis> dělící oblasti více než z poloviny
    vybrané od oblastí vybraných méně než z poloviny.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    It is a <emphasis>contour line</emphasis>, dividing areas that are
    more than half selected from areas that are less than half
    selected.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    C'est une <emphasis>ligne de contour</emphasis> qui sépare les 
    zones sélectionnées à plus de 50% de celles sélectionnées à moins 
    de 50%.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    那是一个<emphasis>轮廓线</emphasis>，它区分被选中多于半个像素的区域和被选中少于半个像素的区域。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='cs'>
          Stejný výběr v režimu rychlé masky
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    Vždy, když se podíváte na přerušovanou čáru ohraničující výběr, měli byste
    si uvědomit, že ukazuje pouze část informace. Pokud chcete výběr vidět
    se všemi podrobnostmi, je nejjednodušší přepnout se do režimu rychlé
    masky kliknutím na tlačítko v levém dolním rohu okna obrázku. Výběr je v
    režimu rychlé masky zobrazen jako průsvitný závoj zakrývající nevybrané
    části obrázku. Vybrané oblasti nejsou zahaleny vůbec. Nad částečně
    vybranými oblastmi je závoj úměrně zeslabený.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Same selection in QuickMask mode
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    You should always bear in mind, when looking at the dashed line
    that represents the selection, that it only tells you part of the
    story.  If you want to see the selection in complete detail, the
    easiest way is to click the QuickMask button in the lower left
    corner of the image window.  This causes the selection to be shown
    as a translucent overlay atop the image.  Selected areas are
    unaffected; unselected areas are reddened.  The more completely
    selected an area is, the less red it appears.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          La même sélection en mode Masque rapide.
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    Vous devez toujours avoir à l'esprit, en regardant la ligne 
    pointillée qui représente la sélection, qu'elle ne vous raconte 
    pas toute l'histoire. Si vous voulez voir tous les détails d'une 
    sélection, le plus facile est de cliquer sur bouton Masque Rapide 
    en bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image. La sélection apparaît alors 
    comme un masque transparent, rouge par défaut, recouvrant l'image: 
    les zones sélectionnées ne sont pas recouvertes et les zones 
    sélectionnées sont plus ou moins rouges en fonction de leur degré 
    de sélection.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask.png' format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          在快速蒙板模式下的同一个选区
        </para>
      </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    您需要一直牢记，当您看到表现选区的虚线时，它只告诉您部分信息。如果您想了解选区的完全细节，最简单的方法就是点击图像窗口左下角的快速蒙板按钮。它使选区好像被蒙上一层半透明的遮盖。选中的区域没有受影响，而非选中区域则呈红色。越完全选中的区域，显示的红色越少。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Režim rychlé masky je podrobně popsán dále  Pokud si při čtení této
    kapitoly vše zkoušíte v Gimpu, přepněte se zpátky z režimu rychlé masky
    (klikněte znovu na tlačítko, kterým jste rychlou masku zapnuli),
    protože mnoho funkcí funguje v režimu rychlé masky jinak.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    QuickMask mode, and its uses, are described in detail below.
    Meanwhile, if you are following this discussion by trying things
    out in Gimp, you should know that many operations work differently
    in QuickMask mode, so go ahead and toggle it off again for now (by
    clicking the QuickMask button once more).
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le Masque rapide et son utilisation sont décrits en détail plus 
    loin. Cependant, si vous lisez ce texte tout expérimentant dans 
    Gimp, vous devez savoir dès à présent que de nombreuses opérations 
    se déroulent différemment en mode Masque Rapide. Aussi, quittez le 
    Masque rapide en cliquant à nouveau sur son icône avant de 
    continuer.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    快速蒙板模式，及其使用，下面有详细描述。同时，如果您跟随该讨论并在 Gimp 中尝试，您会了解与许多操作在快速蒙板中工作方式不同，因此现在将其切换为关闭(再次点击快速蒙板按钮)。
  </para>

  <formalpara lang='cs'>
    <title>Feathering</title>
    <para>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png'
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang='cs'>
              Stejný výběr v režimu rychlé masky po prolnutí
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      Ve výchozím nastavení vytvářejí základní nástroje pro výběr, např.
      nástroj Výběr obdélníku, ostře ohraničené výběry. Pixely uvnitř
      čárkované hranice jsou zcela vybrané, pixely vně jsou zcela nevybrané.
      Ověřit si to můžete přepnutím do režimu rychlé masky – uvidíte jasně
      ohraničený obdélník bez závoje obklopený rovnoměrně červeně zahaleným
      okolím. Ve volbách tohoto nástroje je však možnost zaškrtnutí volby
      <guilabel>Prolnout okraje</guilabel>, která způsobí, že vytvořené výběry
      budou plynule přecházet do okolí. Nastavený <guilabel>Poloměr</guilabel>
      určuje velikost těchto přechodů.
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara lang='en'>
    <title>Feathering</title>
    <para>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png'
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang='en'>
              Same selection in QuickMask mode after feathering
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      With the default settings, the basic selection tools, such as the
      Rectangle Select tool, create sharp selections.  Pixels inside the
      dashed line are fully selected, and pixels outside completely
      unselected.  You can verify this by toggling QuickMask: you see a
      clear rectangle with sharp edges, surrounded by uniform red.  In the
      Tool Options, however, is a checkbox called "Feather".  If you enable
      this, the tool will instead create graduated selections.  The feather
      radius, which you can adjust, determines the distance over which the
      transition occurs.
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara lang='fr'>
    <title>Adoucir</title>
    <para>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png'
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Même sélection en Mode Masque rapide après adoucissement
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      Avec les réglages par défaut, les outils de sélection de base, 
      telle la Sélection Rectangulaire, créent des sélections à bords 
      tranchés, nets. Les pixels à l'intérieur du contour pointillé 
      sont complètement sélectionnés et ceux à l'extérieur ne le sont 
      pas du tout. Vous pouvez le vérifier en activant le Masque 
      Rapide: vous verrez un rectangle clair avec des bords nets, 
      entouré d'un rouge uniforme. Dans les Options de l'outil, vous 
      trouverez la case à cocher «Adoucir». Si vous la cochez, l'outil 
      créera des sélections à bords gradués. Le rayon d'adoucissement, 
      que vous pouvez ajuster, détermine la largeur sur laquelle la 
      transition s'opérera. 
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
    <title>羽化</title>
    <para>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png'
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              羽化后在快速蒙板模式下的同一个选区
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      默认设置下，基本的选择工具如矩形选择工具，生成锐利的选区。虚线内的像素被完全选中，而其外的像素则完全未选中。您可以通过切换快速蒙板来验证：您看到一个清晰带锐利边缘的矩形，并被统一的红色包围。而在工具选项有个“边缘羽化”勾选框。如果您勾选它，改工具将生成有层次的选区。羽化半径则可以用来调节在什么距离上进行过渡。
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Pokud máte po ruce Gimp, vyzkoušejte si to s nástrojem Výběr obdélníku
    a pak se přepněte do režimu rychlé masky. Uvidíte, že okraj jasného
    obdélníku je rozmazaný.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    If you are following along, try this out with the Rectangle Select
    tool, and then toggle QuickMask.  You will now see that the
    clear rectangle has a fuzzy edge.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Si vous me suivez en expérimentant, faites un essai avec l'outil 
    de sélection Rectangulaire, activez le Masque Rapide, et voyez que 
    le rectangle clair a maintenant des bords flous.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果您沿着上面内容下来，可以用矩形选择工具来实践，然后切换到快速蒙板模式。您现在将看到带有一个模糊边界的清晰的矩形。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Prolínání je velmi užitečné při vyjímání objektu a jeho vkládání na jiné
    místo, neboť zlepšuje splývání objektu s okolím.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Feathering is particularly useful when you are cutting and
    pasting, in helping the pasted object to blend smoothly and
    unobtrusively with its surroundings.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Adoucir est particulièrement utile lors du copier-coller, 
    permettant d'introduire un objet qui se fond progressivement dans 
    son environnement.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当剪切和粘贴后，羽化特别有用，它可以使被粘贴的物体平滑而不引人注意地和周围环境混合在一起。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Výběr lze s nevybranými oblastmi prolnout kdykoliv, i tehdy, pokud byl
    vytvořen s ostrými okraji. Slouží k tomu příkaz
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Výběr</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Prolnout</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> z nabídky okna obrázku.
    Otevře se tak dialog, ve kterém lze nastavit velikost prolnutí.
    Lze učinit i opak, tedy změnit prolínající se neostrý výběr na
    výběr typu „vše nebo nic“. K tonu slouží příkaz
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Výběr</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Zaostřit</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> ze stejné nabídky.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Actually, it is possible to feather a selection at any time, even
    if it was originally created as a sharp selection.  You can do
    this from the image menu, by choosing 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Feather</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    This brings up a dialog that allows you to set the feather
    radius.  You can do the opposite--sharpen a graduated
    selection into an all-or-nothing selection--by choosing  
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Sharpen</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Il est possible d'Adoucir une sélection n'importe quand, même si 
    elle a été créée avec un bord dur, net, tranché.Vous pouvez le 
    faire en choisissant 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Sélection</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Adoucir</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    Cela ouvre une fenêtre de dialog vous permettant de régler le 
    rayon. Vous pouvez faire l'inverse, durcir les bords flous d'une 
    sélection, en choisissant
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Sélection</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Augmenter la netteté</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para> 
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    实际上，在任何时候羽化一个选区是可能的，甚至最开始创建的是一个锐利的选区。通过在图像菜单中选取
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>选择</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>羽化</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>。
    会弹出一个允许您设定羽化半径的对话框。也能干相反的--锐化一个有层次的选区为一个边界分明的选区--通过选取
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>选择</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>锐化</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para lang='cs'>
      Pro technicky založené čtenáře: prolnutí se provádí aplikací Gausova
      rozostření na kanál výběru, s nastaveným poloměrem rozostření.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      For technically oriented readers: feathering works by applying a
      Gaussian blur to the selection channel, with the specified
      blurring radius.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Pour les lecteurs intéressés par la technique: Adoucir agit par 
      application d'un flou Gaussien sur le canal de la sélection, selon 
      le rayon spécifié.
    </para> 
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      对于面向技术的读者：羽化实质上是对选区通道使用选定模糊半径的高斯模糊操作。
    </para>
  </note>

  <!--Saving selections-->

</sect2>
