<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-21 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2008-04-03 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2007-05-14 j.h added "Make a solid BG transparent"
  2007-04-04 alex falappa: fixes in italian language
  2006-09-06 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-07-23 manuelq: added spanish translation
  2006-05-02 Dust: added Korean translation
  2006-03-31 j.h: changed "making a selection transparent"
  2006-01-13 lexa: added translation for de an made file docbook compliant
  2005-11-28 lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures
  050905: Added Making a selection semi-transparente
-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-selection">
  <title>The Selection</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Selections</primary>
    <secondary>Concepts</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Often when you operate on an image, you only want part of it to be
    affected. In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you make this happen by
    <emphasis>selecting</emphasis>
    that part. Each image has a <emphasis>selection</emphasis>
    associated with it. Most, but not all, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> operations
    act only on the selected portions of the image.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>How would you isolate the tree?</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/fog-tree-example.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    There are many, many situations where creating just the right selection is
    the key to getting the result you want, and often it is not easy to
    do. For example, in the above image, suppose I want to cut the tree out
    from its background, and paste it into a different image. To do
    this, I need to create a selection that contains the tree and nothing but
    the tree. It is difficult because the tree has a complex shape, and
    in several spots is hard to distinguish from the objects behind it.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Selection shown as usual with dashed line.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/select-outline.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    Now here is a very important point, and it is crucial to understand this.
    Ordinarily when you create a selection, you see it as a dashed line
    enclosing a portion of the image. The common, not entirely accurate,
    idea you could get from this, is that
    the selection is a sort of container, with the selected parts of the image
    inside, and the unselected parts outside. Although this concept of
    selection is okay for many purposes, it is not entirely correct.
  </para>
  <para>
    Actually the selection is implemented as a <emphasis>channel</emphasis>.
    In terms of its internal structure, it is identical to the red, green,
    blue, and alpha channels of an image. Thus, the selection has a value
    defined at each pixel of the image, ranging between 0 (unselected) and 255
    (fully selected). The advantage of this approach is that it allows some
    pixels to be <emphasis>partially selected</emphasis>,
    by giving them intermediate values between 0 and 255. As you will see,
    there are many situations where it is desirable to have smooth transitions
    between selected and unselected regions.
  </para>
  <para>
    What, then, is the dashed line that appears when you create a selection?
  </para>
  <para>
    The dashed line is a <emphasis>contour line</emphasis>, dividing areas
    that are more
    than half selected from areas that are less than half selected.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Same selection in Quick Mask mode.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/select-outline-qmask.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    While looking at the dashed line that represents the selection, always
    remember that the line only tells part of the story. If you want to see the
    selection in full detail, the easiest way is to click the
    <link linkend="gimp-image-window-quick-mask-button">Quick Mask button</link>
    in the lower left corner of the image window. This causes the selection to
    be shown as a translucent overlay atop the image. Selected areas are
    unaffected; unselected areas are reddened. The more completely selected an
    area is, the less red it appears.
  </para>
  <para>
    Many operations work differently in Quick Mask mode, as mentioned in the
    <link linkend="gimp-image-window-quick-mask-overview"
    >Quick Mask overview</link>.
    Use the Quick Mask button in the lower left corner of the image window to
    toggle Quick Mask mode on and off.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Same selection in Quick Mask mode after feathering.</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/select-outline-qmask-feather.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 id="gimp-concepts-selection-feathering">
    <title>Feathering</title>
    <para>
      With the default settings, the basic selection tools, such as the
      Rectangle Select tool, create sharp selections. Pixels inside the dashed
      line are fully selected, and pixels outside completely unselected. You
      can verify this by toggling Quick Mask: you see a clear rectangle with
      sharp edges, surrounded by uniform red.
      Use the <quote>Feather edges</quote> checkbox in the Tool Options to
      toggle between graduated selections and sharp selections.
      The feather radius, which
      you can adjust, determines the distance over which the transition
      occurs.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are following along, try this with the Rectangle Select tool,
      and then toggle Quick Mask. You will see that the clear rectangle has
      a fuzzy edge.
    </para>
    <para>
      Feathering is particularly useful when you are cutting and pasting, so
      that the pasted object blends smoothly and unobtrusively with its
      surroundings.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is possible to feather a selection at any time, even if it
      was originally created as a sharp selection. Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Feather</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      from the main menu to open the Feather Selection dialog. Set the
      feather radius and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sharpen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      to do the opposite&mdash;sharpen a graduated selection into an
      all-or-nothing selection.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        For technically oriented readers: feathering works by applying a
        Gaussian blur to the selection channel, with the specified blurring
        radius.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-concepts-selection-transparent">
    <title>Making a Selection Partially Transparent</title>
    <para>
      You can set layer opacity, but you cannot do that directly for a
      selection. It is quite useful to make the image of a glass
      transparent. Use the following methods to set the layer opacity:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          For simple selections, use the Eraser tool with the desired opacity.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          For complex selections: use
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Float</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          to create a floating selection. This creates a new layer with
          the selection called <quote>Floating Selection</quote>
          (<xref linkend="gimp-selection-float"/>).

          Set the opacity slider in the Layers dialog to the desired opacity.
          Then anchor the selection: outside the selection, the mouse pointer
          includes an anchor. When you click while the mouse pointer includes
          the anchor, the floating selection
          disappears from the Layers dialog and the selection is at the right
          place and partially transparent (anchoring works this way only if a
          selection tool is activated: you can also use the Anchor Layer
          command in the context menu by right clicking on the selected layer
          in the Layers dialog).
        </para>
        <para>
          And, if you use this function frequently:
          <keycombo action="press">
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>C</keycap>
          </keycombo> to copy the selection,
          <keycombo action="press">
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>V</keycap>
          </keycombo> to paste the clipboard as a floating selection, and
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>New Layer…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice> to turn the selection into a new layer.
          You can adjust the opacity before, or after creating the new layer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Another way: use
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Mask</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Add Layer Masks…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          to add a layer mask to the layer with the
          selection, initializing it with the selection. Then use a brush with
          the desired opacity to paint the selection with black, i.e. paint it
          with transparency. Then <menuchoice><guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Mask</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Apply Layer Mask</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>. See <xref linkend="gimp-layer-mask"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          To <emphasis>make the solid background of an image
          transparent</emphasis>, add an Alpha channel, and use the Magic
          Wand to select the background. Then, use the Color Picker
          tool to select the background color, which becomes the foreground
          color in Toolbox. Use the Bucket Fill tool with the selected color.
          Set the Bucket Fill mode to <quote>Color Erase</quote>, which erases
          pixels with the selected color; other pixels are partially erased
          and their color is changed.
        </para>
        <para>
          The simplest method is to use
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Clear</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>, which gives complete transparency to a selection.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
