<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">


<!-- section history:
  2007-09-30 lexa: threw away all content that is not valid for 2.4 anymore
  2006-09-06 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-12-20 added italian content by ciampix
  2005-12-12 reviewed and added de screenshots by lexa
  2005-11-28 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<!-- FIXME: cs en fr it ko nl zh_CN Review needed! -->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-setup" lang="cs;en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect1info lang="de;fr;ko;it;no">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="it">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-09-30</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-11-23</date>
        <authorinitials>kost</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect1info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">První spuštění Gimpu</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Starting GIMP the first time</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">GIMP das erste Mal starten</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Prima esecuzionde di GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">김프 처음 시작하기</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl"><acronym>GIMP</acronym> de eerste keer instellen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Å starte GIMP for første gong</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Запуск GIMP в первый раз</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">首次启动 GIMP</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">GIMP : premier démarrage</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>prvotní nastavení</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Setup</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Einstellungen</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl"><primary>Instellen</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Installation</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>L'installazione</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>설치</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Installering</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Инсталляция</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>设置</primary></indexterm>


  <para lang="cs">
    Při prvním spuštění vás GIMP provede řadou kroků, ve kterých je potřeba
    nastavit základní volby a adresáře. Během tohoto procesu se ve vašem
    domovském adresáři vytvoří podadresář
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>
    <footnote>
      <para>
        Číslice ve jménu adresáře představují první dvě čísla verze Gimpu.
      </para>
    </footnote>. Všechna provedená nastavení se ukládají do tohoto adresáře.
    Pokud adresář smažete nebo přejmenujete, provede vás GIMP při dalším
    spuštění těmito kroky znovu a adresář znovu vytvoří. Toho můžete využít,
    pokud si chcete vyzkoušet nějaké nastavení, aniž byste si poškodili svou
    vyladěnou instalaci, nebo naopak tehdy, pokud jste ji již natolik
    poškodili, že je třeba ji vytvořit znovu.
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    The first time you run GIMP, it goes through a series of steps to set up
    options and directories. This process creates a subdirectory of your home
    directory called <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>.
    All of the information about the choices you make here goes into that
    directory. If you later remove that directory, or rename it as something
    like <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4.bak</filename>,
    then the next time you start GIMP, it will go through the whole setup
    sequence again, creating a new
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>
    directory. You can exploit this if you want to explore the effect of
    different choices without destroying your existing installation, or if you
    have screwed things up so badly that your existing installation needs to
    be nuked.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Durch den ersten Start von <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    wird ein neuer Ordner in ihrem Benutzerverzeichnis eingerichtet. Dieser
    Ordner heißt <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>
    <footnote>
      <para>
        Die Endung des Ordners ist versionsabhängig. Analog zur
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Version 2.4 wird der Ordner auch automatisch
        <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename> genannt.
      </para>
    </footnote>
    und enthält alle Ihre persönlichen Einstellungen, Pinselformen,
    Muster, Farbpaletten und andere Dinge, die Sie für Ihre Arbeit mit GIMP
    benötigen. Sollten Sie diesen Ordner verschieben oder löschen, wird GIMP
    beim nächsten Start diesen Ordner wieder anlegen. Nützlich kann dies sein,
    wenn Sie verschiedene Einstellungen ausprobieren und das Programm wieder
    auf Vorgabewerte zurücksetzen möchten. Bedenken Sie dabei, dass alle Ihre
    <emphasis>eigenen</emphasis>
    Pinselformen, Muster oder Paletten ebenso gelöscht werden.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    La première fois que vous lancez GIMP, il part dans une série d'étapes
    pour fixer les options et les répertoires. Ce processus crée un
    sous-répertoire dans votre dossier personnel appelé «.gimp-2.4». Toute
    l'information sur les choix que vous faites va dans ce répertoire. Si,
    plus tard, vous supprimez ce répertoire, ou si vous le renommez en
    «.gimp-2.4.bak» par exemple, toute la séquence d'installation reprendra
    recréant un nouveau répertoire .gimp-2.4. Vous pouvez exploiter cette
    astuce pour explorer l'effet de choix différents sans détruire votre
    installation existante, ou si vous avez raté vos choix d'installation.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    La prima volta che si esegue GIMP si deve passare attraverso una
    serie di passi che servono alla configurazione di opzioni e
    cartelle. Questo procedimento crea una sottocartella nella
    cartella dell'utente con il seguente nome: <filename
    class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>.
    Tutte le informazioni sulle scelte effettuate vengono memorizzate
    in questa cartella speciale. Se si elimina la cartella o la si
    rinomina per esempio in questo modo, <filename
    class="directory">.gimp-2.4.bak</filename>, al prossimo avvio di
    GIMP ripartirà la sequenza di configurazione, creando una nuova cartella
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>. È possibile
    ricorrere a questo metodo per sperimentare l'effetto di scelte
    differenti senza distruggere una installazione esistente o se si è
    fatto un tale pasticcio da non riuscire più a rimettere le cose a
    posto e si rende necessario rifare l'installazione.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    김프를 처음 사용하려면 디렉토리와 설정 등을 정하는 몇가지 과정을 거쳐야
    합니다. 이 과정에서 홈디렉토리에
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename> 라는 디렉토리가
    생성되며, 설치 과정 중의 모든 선택에 대한 내용이 이 디렉토리에
    저장됩니다. 따라서 차후에 이 디렉토리를 삭제하거나,
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4.bak</filename> 라는 식으로 이름을
    바꾸게 되면, 김프 시작시에 새로운
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename> 디렉토리를 만들며 설치
    과정을 다시 반복하게 됩니다. 기존의 세팅을 망치지 않고 새로운 세팅을
    시도해보고 싶다던가, 기존의 세팅에 문제가 있어 세팅만 바꿔야한다면 이
    디렉토리를 제거하거나 이름을 변경하여 새로운 설치 과정을 진행하면
    됩니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    De eerste keer dat u <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opstart zal deze bepaalde
    mappen aanmaken en opties instellen. In dit proces wordt in uw
    gebruikersmap een deelmap met de naam <filename
    class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename> aangemaakt.  <footnote> <para> Het
    einde van de mapnaam is versie-afhankelijk, als u dus de oude
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> versie 2.0 gebruikt wordt aan de map de naam
    <filename class="directory">gimp-2.0</filename> gegeven.  </para>
    </footnote> Alle keuze's in de instellingen die u maakt worden in deze
    deelmap opgeslagen. Indien u deze map verwijderd of hernoemd in iets als:
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4.bak</filename>, dan wordt deze
    instelprocedure de volgende keer dat u GIMP opstart weer doorlopen en
    wordt er weer een nieuwe deelmap  <filename
    class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename> aangemaakt.  U kunt hier gebruik
    van maken als u wilt weten wat de gevolgen van de verschillende keuze's
    zijn of indien u uw instellingen een zodanige puinhoop zijn geworden dat
    het handiger is ze te vervangen door de beginwaarden.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Første gongen du tar <acronym>GIMP</acronym> i bruk, går programmet
    gjennom fleire steg for å setje opp diverse opsjonar og filkatalogar.
    Mellom anna blir det laga ein underkatalog til hovudkatalogen. Denne
    blir kalla <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>. All
    informasjonen om dei ulike innstillingane du gjer blir lagra her. Dersom
    du fjernar denne mappa, eller gir ho eit nytt namn, vil
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gå gjennom oppstartsprosedyrane på nytt neste
    gong, og lage ei ny mappe med namnet
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>.
    Du kan utnytte dette dersom du ønskjer å utforske ulike innstillingar
    utan å øydeleggje det eksisterande oppsettet, eller at du hamnar så
    ettertrykkeleg i suppa at alt må gjerast om att.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    При первом запуске GIMP, он предпринимает несколько шагов для инсталляции
    настроек и папок. Этот процесс создаёт подпапки в вашей домашней папке
    под названием <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>. Вся
    информация о ваших выборах сохраняется здесь. Если вы позже удалите эту
    папку или переименуйте её в, например,
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4.bak</filename>, тогда GIMP пройдёт
    через весь процесс заново, создавая новую папку
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>. Вы можете использовать
    это для проверки разных выборов и настроек, не удаляя всю инсталляцию или
    для восстановления инсталляции, если существующая слишком сломана.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    您第一次启动 GIMP 时，要通过一系列步凑来设置选项和目录。该进程在您的个人目录创建一个子目录“.gimp-2.4”。所有您在这里做的选择信息都在那个目录里。当您以后移除那个目录，或重命名为其它名字，比如“.gimp-2.4.bak”，下次启动 GIMP 时将会重新整个设置过程，创建新的“.gimp-2.4”目录。您可以通过这样来探寻不同选项的效果而不会损害您现有安装，或由于现有安装已经一团糟需要重新开始。
  </para>


  <sect2 lang="cs;en;de;fr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="cs">Konečně…</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Finally . . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Es kann los gehen...</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Finalement . . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Infine . . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">마지막으로 . . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Eindelijk . . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Til slutt . . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Наконец. . .</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">最终...</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="cs">
      Takže máte GIMP nainstalovaný a nakonfigurovaný a jste
      připraveni ho použít. Jen několik rad, než doopravdy začnete:
      Ve výchozím nastavení se po každém spuštění Gimpu otevře okno s
      tipem. Tipy obsahují velmi užitečné rady, na které jen těžko
      přijdete pouhým experimentováním. Pokud vás ruší, můžete je
      vypnout, vyplatí se však věnovat jim pozornost. Můžete si je
      číst kdykoliv pomocí příkazu
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Nápověda</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tip dne</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. Zadruhé, pokud s vámi GIMP při práci přestane
      komunikovat nebo se prostě nepohodnete, může vám pomoci část
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Řešení problémů</link>.
      Příjemné chvíle s Gimpem!
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      Just a couple of suggestions before you start, though: First, when you
      run GIMP, by default it shows a "tip" each time it starts up. These tips
      tell you things that are very useful but not easy to learn by
      experimenting, so they are worth paying attention to. If you find it too
      distracting to look at them each time you start, you can disable them;
      but please go through them when you have the chance: for your
      convenience, you can read them at any time using the menu command
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tips</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Second, if at some point you are trying to do something, and GIMP
      seems to have suddenly stopped functioning, the section
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Getting Unstuck</link>
      may help you out. Happy Gimping!
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Bevor Sie sich in Ihr Vergnügen stürzen, kurz noch zwei Hinweise: Nach
      jedem Start des Programms werden Ihnen Tipps über Funktionen und
      Vorgehensweisen angezeigt, die Ihnen bei der täglichen Arbeit nützlich
      sein könnten. Sollten Sie gerade erst in das Thema Bildbearbeitung oder
      in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      einsteigen, schauen Sie sich die Tipps an, bevor Sie sie in den
      Einstellungen abstellen. Die Tipps können Sie auch manuell unter
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tipps</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      anschauen. Sollten Ihnen während der Arbeit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      <quote>einfrieren</quote>, geben wir Ihnen unter
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Problemlösungen</link>
      Hilfe, um in diesem Fall genau das Richtige zu tun.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Aber jetzt erst einmal: <emphasis>Happy GIMPing!</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Ora GIMP è installato e configurato e siete pronti per partire. Solo un
      paio di suggerimenti prima di lasciarvi andare: primo, GIMP è
      preimpostato per mostrarvi un suggerimento ad ogni avvio. Questi
      suggerimenti mostrano cose che sono molto utili ma difficili da imparare
      sperimentando, perciò si consiglia di non disabilitarli. Se proprio li
      trovate fastidiosi potete eliminarli ma ricordate che potete sempre
      consultarli in qualsiasi momento e si consiglia caldamente di farlo
      spesso tramite il comando da menu
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Aiuto</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Suggerimenti del giorno</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Secondo, se stavate provando qualcosa e sembra che GIMP abbia
      improvvisamente smesso di funzionare, la lettura della sezione
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Come sbloccarsi</link>
      può essere molto utile. Buon lavoro con GIMP!
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      이제 김프 설치 및 설정을 완료하고 사용할 준비를 끝냈습니다.
      하지만 김프를 사용하기 전에 필요한 몇 가지 조언이 있습니다. 첫째,
      김프를 실행할 때마다 기본값으로 "팁"이 보여지게 됩니다. 이 팁들은
      쉽게 배울 수 없는 유용한 팁들을 보여주므로 매 시작시마다
      보여지도록 놓아두는 편이 좋습니다. 하지만 이런 팁이 뜨는 것이
      싫다면, 해당 기능을 중지시킬 수 있습니다. 그리고 필요할 때는
      언제든지
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tips</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      메뉴를 통해 팁들을 볼 수 있습니다. 두번째, 특정 지점에 어떤
      작업을 하려고 할때, 갑자기 김프의 기능이 중지된 것처럼 보일때가
      있습니다. 그럴때는
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">문제 해결</link>
      섹션을 보면 도움을 받을 수 있을 것입니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Nu u <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ingesteld heeft, kunt u de wereld
      van beeldbewerking gaan verkennen. Voor u verder gaat hebben we
      nog de volgende twee tips: Iedere keer dat u het programma
      start verschijnt er een venster met een tip. Deze tips geven u
      nuttige informatie waar u waarschijnlijk niet met eenvoudig
      experimenteren achtergekomen was.  Dus het is nuttig eens wat
      aandacht aan deze adviezen te schenken, voor u het tonen ervan
      uitvinkt. U kunt ze ook via een menu nog eens een keer opvragen
      via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Hulp</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tip van de dag</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Als de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> tijdens het gebruik niet meer op uw
      acties reageert. Kunt er in het hoofdstuk <link
      linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Vastlopen oplossen</link>
      aanwijzingen vinden om dit probleem op te lossen.  Maar voor nu
      wensen we u veel plezier met <quote>Gimpen</quote>.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Nå er altså <acronym>GIMP</acronym> installert og sett opp slik
      du ønskjer det. Klar til bruk. Bare eit par tips før du
      går i gang. Kvar gong du opnar <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, vil
      det kome opp eit <quote>Dagens tips</quote>. Desse tipsa fortel
      ting om <acronym>GIMP</acronym> som det ikkje alltid er så lett
      å finne ut av bare på eige hand ved prøving og feiling, så dei
      er vel verd tida du bruker på dei. Du kan likevel ta bort desse
      tipsa dersom du finn dei distraherande, men du bør likevel
      studera dei når du får sjanse til det, for din eigen del.
      Tipsa kan hentast fram igjen ved å bruke menykommandoen
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Hjelp</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Dagens tips</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Dersom du prøver å gjere eitt eller anna og det ser ut til at
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ikkje vil meir, eller oppfører seg på ein
      uventa måte, kan det verre eit forsøk å lese kapitlet<link
      linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Avstressing</link> før
      du gir heilt opp.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Lykke til med gimpinga di!
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Несколько советов до того, как вы начнёте. Во первых, по умолчанию,
      GIMP показывает подсказку при каждой загрузке. Эти подсказки объясняют
      разные полезные вещи, которым трудно научиться эксперимертированием. Если
      вам этого не надо, их можно отключить. Но пройдитесь по ним хоть раз: они
      находятся в меню
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Справка</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Подсказки</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Во-вторых, если вы время какой-нибудь операции GIMP зависнет, обратитесь к
      главе
      <!--link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck"-->Выход из зависания<!--/link-->
      Приятного пользования.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      现在您安装和配置完GIMP，准备使用了。不过在您开始之前这里有两个建
      议：首先，但您每次启动 GIMP时，默认显示一个“每日提示”。这些提示
      告诉您一些非常有用但不容易靠实践来发现的东西，因此注意看下是有价
      值的。您也能关闭它，如果您认为看这些很心烦。不过当有机会时请看一
      遍它们：为方便起见，您能在任何时候来阅读它们，使用菜单命令
      <menuchoice> <guimenu>帮助</guimenu> <guimenuitem>每日提示
      </guimenuitem> </menuchoice>。第二，如果在某处您尝试干一些事，而
      GIMP 好像突然停止响应了，<link
      linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">不要抓狂</link>章节也许能帮
      助您。快乐 Gimping！
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Ça y est ! GIMP est installé et configuré. Deux suggestions avant de
      vous lancer. La première : chaque fois que vous démarrez GIMP, une
      astuce est affichée par défaut. Ces astuces vous apprennent des choses
      très utiles et pas facile à acquérir par une expérimentation
      personnelle. Elles méritent attention. Si vous les trouvez gênantes,
      vous pouvez les désactiver. Vous pourrez toujours les lire en utilisant
      la commande
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Aide</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Conseil du jour</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      La seconde : Si, à un moment, GIMP paraît bloqué, la section
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Comment se débloquer</link>
      peut vous aider à vous tirer d'affaire. Bon Gimping !
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>