<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-09-30 lexa: threw away all content that is not valid for 2.4 anymore
  2006-09-06 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-12-20 added italian content by ciampix
  2005-12-12 reviewed and added de screenshots by lexa
  2005-11-28 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<!-- FIXME: cs it ko nl zh_CN Review needed! -->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-setup">
  <title>
    <phrase>Starting GIMP the first time</phrase>
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Setup</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    The first time you run GIMP, it goes through a series of steps to set up
    options and directories. This process creates a subdirectory of your home
    directory called <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>.
    All of the information about the choices you make here goes into that
    directory. If you later remove that directory, or rename it as something
    like <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4.bak</filename>,
    then the next time you start GIMP, it will go through the whole setup
    sequence again, creating a new
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.4</filename>
    directory. You can exploit this if you want to explore the effect of
    different choices without destroying your existing installation, or if you
    have screwed things up so badly that your existing installation needs to
    be nuked.
  </para>
  <sect2>
    <title>
      <phrase>Finally . . .</phrase>
    </title>
    <para>
      Just a couple of suggestions before you start, though: First, when you
      run GIMP, by default it shows a "tip" each time it starts up. These tips
      tell you things that are very useful but not easy to learn by
      experimenting, so they are worth paying attention to. If you find it too
      distracting to look at them each time you start, you can disable them;
      but please go through them when you have the chance: for your
      convenience, you can read them at any time using the menu command
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Help</guimenu><guimenuitem>Tips</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
      Second, if at some point you are trying to do something, and GIMP
      seems to have suddenly stopped functioning, the section
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Getting Unstuck</link>
      may help you out. Happy Gimping!
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
