<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2015-12-18 j.h Fix bug #675745: developp text toolbox elements
  2012-03-18 j.h: created
 -->
<sect1 id="gimp-text-management">
  <title>Text Management</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Text</primary>
    <secondary>Editing text</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <!--FOR TRANSLATORS: this file is a reshaping of the old
    text.xml file. A large part can be copy-pasted-->

  <para>
    Text is managed with the Text tool. This tool creates a new layer containing
    the text, above the current layer in the Layers dialog, with the size of the
    text box. Its name is the beginning of the text.
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Example of a text item</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/text-example.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          Example of a text item, showing the boundary of the text layer.
          (Font: Utopia Bold)
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/text-example-2.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>
          The Layers dialog, with the text layer above the layer which was
          current.
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
    Text can be edited directly on canvas. A text tool box, which shows up on
    top of the canvas above the text box, allows you to quickly change some of
    the text characteristics.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      The settings you change in this on canvas dialog only apply to the parts
      of the text that are selected, or any new text you type after the current
      cursor position.
    </para>
  </note>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/using/text-toolbar.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <caption>
      <para>
        As soon as you click on the canvas with the Text tool, you get a closed
        text box and a semi-transparent tool box just above.
      </para>
    </caption>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
    Text tool options are described in <xref linkend="gimp-tool-text"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="text-area">
    <title>Text Area</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Text Area</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      You can start typing text at once. The text box will enlarge gradually.
      Press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to add a new line.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also <emphasis role="bold">enlarge the text box</emphasis> by
      click-and-dragging, as you do with selections. The box size appears then
      in the <link linkend="gimp-image-window-status-bar">status bar</link> at
      the bottom of the image:
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/text-area-size.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      To <emphasis role="bold">edit text</emphasis>, you must, first, select the
      part you want to edit by click-and-drag, or
      <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>arrow keys</keycap></keycombo> and
      then use the options of the <xref linkend="gimp-text-toolbox"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Instead of using the on-canvas text editing, you can use the text editor
      dialog described in <xref linkend="gimp-text-editor-dialog"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can <emphasis role="bold">move the text</emphasis> on the image using
      the Move tool: you must click on a character, not on the background.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can <emphasis role="bold">edit the text later</emphasis>, if the text
      layer still exists and has not been modified by another tool (see below):
      make the text layer active in the<link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layer
      dialog</link>, select the Text tool and click on the text in the image
      window.
    </para>

      <sect3 id="entering-unicode-characters">
      <title>Entering Unicode Characters</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Text</primary>
        <secondary>Entering Unicode characters</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Entering Unicode characters</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        It can be useful to enter characters that are not easily available on
        your keyboard. How you enter these Unicode characters depends on your
        Operating System.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Linux</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can enter Unicode characters with the keyboard shortcut
              <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>U</keycap>
              </keycombo>
              followed by the hexadecimal number of the desired character and
              then pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>macOS</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Use the Character Viewer, shortcut
              <keycombo>
                <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Cmd</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap>
              </keycombo>
              to find and insert symbols, or enable the Unicode Hex Input
              keyboard in Keyboard settings. With the Unicode Hex Input active,
              hold the <keycap>Option</keycap> key and type the character's
              hexadecimal code to insert it.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Windows</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you know the number of the character, you can
              enter that character by pressing and holding the left
              <keycap>Alt</keycap> followed by the number using the numbers on
              the keypad, and then releasing the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key.
              This only works for a limited set of characters.
            </para>
            <para>
              Alternatively you can select a character or emoji by opening a
              dialog using the shortcut
              <keycombo>
                <keycap>Windows-key</keycap><keycap>.</keycap>
              </keycombo>.
              By default emojis are shown, but you can change that to symbols
              using the tabs at the top, and then further select a category
              with the tabs at the bottom.
            </para>
            <para>
              The third option is by opening the
              <productname>Character Map</productname> application that
              is part of Windows and select the desired character from there.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>
        Of course this feature is more useful for entering special (even exotic)
        characters, provided that the required glyphs for these characters are
        supplied by the selected font &mdash; only few fonts support Klingon.
        ;-)
      </para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/enter-unicode-char4.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Unicode 0x47 (<quote>G</quote>), 0x2665, 0x0271, 0x03C0
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="managing-text-layer">
    <title>Managing Text Layer</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Managing Text Layer</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      You can operate on a text layer in the same ways as any other layer,
      but doing so often means giving up the ability to edit the text
      without losing the results of your work.
    </para>
    <para>
      To understand some of the idiosyncrasies of text handling, it may help
      for you to realize that a text layer contains more information than
      the  pixel data that you see: it also contains a representation of the
      text in a text-editor format. You can see this in the text-editor
      window that pops  up while you are using the Text tool. Every time you
      alter the text, the image layer is redrawn to reflect your changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Now suppose you create a text layer, and then operate on it in some
      way that does not involve the Text tool: rotate it, for example.
      Suppose you then come back and try to edit it using the Text tool. As
      soon as you  edit the text, the Text tool will redraw the layer,
      wiping out the results of the operations you performed in the
      meantime.
    </para>
    <para>
      Because this danger is not obvious, the Text tool tries to protect you
      from it. If you operate on a text layer, and then later try to edit
      the text, a message pops up, warning you that your alterations will be
      undone, and giving you three options:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>edit the text anyway;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>cancel;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          create a new text layer with the same text as the existing layer,
          leaving the existing layer unchanged.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <figure>
      <title>Warning lose modifications</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/text-warning.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
        </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-text-toolbox">
    <title>Text Toolbox</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Text Toolbox</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <figure>
      <title>Text Toolbox</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/text-toolbar.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You get this box, which overlays canvas, as soon as you click on canvas with
      the Text Tool. It allows you to edit text directly on canvas.
    </para>
    <para>
      Apart from the usual text formatting features like font family, style and
      size selectors you get numeric control over baseline offset and kerning, as
      well as the ability to change text color for a selection.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Change font of selected text</emphasis>:
          as soon as you start editing the default font name, a drop-down
          list appears, allowing you to select a font.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Change size of selected text</emphasis>:
          self-explanatory.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Bold, Italic, Underline, Strikethrough
          </emphasis>: self-explanatory.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Change baseline of selected text</emphasis>:
          "In European typography and penmanship, baseline is the line upon
          which most letters "sit" and below which descenders extend"
          (Wikipedia). In HTML, there are several kinds of baselines
          (alphabetic, ideographic, bottom…). Here, consider that baseline
          is "bottom" and determines the place for descenders. The default
          baseline "0" gives place for descenders. You can use it to
          increase space between two lines only, while <quote>Adjust line
          spacing</quote> in tool options increases space between all lines.
        </para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Default Baseline</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/text-default-baseline.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Default baseline marked with a red line.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Change kerning of selected text</emphasis>:
          "In typography, kerning… is the process of adjusting the spacing
          between characters in a proportional font." (Wikipedia). You will
          probably use this setting to adjust letter spacing of a selected
          part of text.
        </para>
        <para>
          Let us look at a selected text (zoomx800 to see pixels):
        </para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Example of Selected Text</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/text-selected-example.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/text-selected-dialog.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
          We can see that the Sans font is a proportional font: letters
          widths are different, and <quote>T</quote> glyph comes over
          the <quote>e</quote>. Letters widths are marked with thin
          vertical lines and left borders of letter width cover
          preceding letters by one pixel. Now we set <quote>Change
          kerning of selected text</quote> to 2 pixels:
        </para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Example of Text Kerning</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/text-kerning-example.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/text-kerning-dialog.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
          Blank spaces, 2 pixels wide, are added between all selected
          characters and letter widths are preserved. If no text is
          selected, a blank space is added at the place of the mouse
          pointer between two characters.
        </para>
        <para>
          Here is a comparison with the <guilabel>Adjust letter spacing</guilabel>
          option of the <link linkend="gimp-tool-text">Text tool</link>:
        </para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Example of Text Spacing</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/text-spacing-example.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/toolbox/text-selected-dialog.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>
          The option applies to the whole text, not only to the selected
          text. Blank spaces are added inside letters widths and
          letter widths are not respected.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can also use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>arrow keys</keycap>
          </keycombo> to change baseline offset and kerning.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Change color of selected text</emphasis>:
          this command opens a color dialog where you choose a color for
          the selected text.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Clear style of selected text</emphasis>:
          using this command, you can get rid of all new settings you
          applied to the selected text.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="text-context-menu">
    <title>Text Context Menu</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Context Menu</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      The context menu can be brought up by right-clicking on text.
      It is somewhat different from that of the Text Editor dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      The context menu offers the following options:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-cut"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-copy"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-paste"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-delete"/>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Cut</guilabel>, <guilabel>Copy</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Paste</guilabel>, <guilabel>Delete</guilabel>: these commands work
          with selected text. Except for <guilabel>Paste</guilabel>, they are disabled
          as long as no text is selected. <guilabel>Paste</guilabel> is enabled when
          the clipboard contains text.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-open-text-file"/>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Open text file…</guilabel>: this command opens a file
          dialog where you can select a text file. The contents of this file
          will be opened in the current text layer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-clear"/>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Clear</guilabel>: this command deletes all the text,
          selected or not.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="gimp-text-tool-text-to-path">
        <para>
          <guilabel>Text to Path</guilabel>: this command creates a
          path from the outlines of the current text. The result is not
          evident. You have to open the Paths dialog and make path visible.
          Then select the Path tool and click on the text. Every letter
          is  now surrounded with a path component. So you can modify
          the shape of letters by moving path control points.
        </para>
        <para>
          This command is similar to
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Text to Path</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Text to path applied</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-to-path1.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Nothing appears.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Path made visible</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-to-path2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Path made visible in Path tab. Path appears
                as a red border around text.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Path tool activated</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-to-path3.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Path tool activated; click on path.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="gimp-text-tool-text-along-path">
        <para>
          <guilabel>Text along path</guilabel>:
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Text along Path</primary>
          </indexterm>
        </para>
        <para>
          This option is enabled only if a
          <link linkend="gimp-using-paths">path</link> exists. When your
          text is created, then create or import a path and make it active.
          If you create your path before the text, the path becomes
          invisible and you have to make it visible in the Paths dialog.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Text along path</guilabel> command is also available
          from the <guimenuitem>Layer</guimenuitem> menu in the main menu.
        </para>
        <para>
          The commands <guimenuitem>Discard Text Information</guimenuitem>,
          <guimenuitem>Text to Path</guimenuitem>, and <guimenuitem>Text
          along Path</guimenuitem> only appear in the
          <guimenuitem>Layer</guimenuitem> menu if a text layer is selected.
        </para>
        <para>
          Select the <guimenuitem>Text along Path</guimenuitem> option. The
          text is wrapped along the path. Letters are represented with their
          outline. Each of them is a component of the new path that
          appears in the <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths
          dialog</link>.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            You can change the direction that the text is wrapped around the
            path by <link linkend="gimp-path-path-tool-reverse-stroke">reversing
            the stroke direction</link> when editing the path with the
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path Tool</link>.
            In the same way you can change at which anchor
            <link linkend="gimp-path-path-tool-shift-start">stroking starts</link>.
          </para>
        </note>
        <figure>
          <title><quote>Text along Path</quote> example</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/text-along-path.png"
              format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/text-path.png"
              format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
          By converting a text item to a selection or a path, you can fill it,
          stroke the outlines, transform it, or generally apply the whole panoply
          of GIMP tools to get interesting effects.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-direction-ltr"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-direction-rtl"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-direction-ttb-rtl"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-direction-ttb-rtl-upright"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-direction-ttb-ltr"/>
        <anchor id="gimp-text-tool-direction-ttb-ltr-upright"/>
        <para>
          <guilabel>From left to right</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>From right to left</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Vertical, right to left (mixed orientation)</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Vertical, right to left (upright orientation)</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Vertical, left to right (mixed orientation)</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Vertical, left to right (upright orientation)</guilabel>:
          These commands let you adjust the writing direction of the text.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
