<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- Version History:
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-01-29: fixed Korean translation by Dust
  2006-09-06: added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02: added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-02-17: added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-09-03: Addition en;fr at file end
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-concepts-toolbox" lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;hr;it;ko;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">

  <sect2info lang="de;es;fr;ko;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2006-07-15</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">romanofski</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="es">2006-11-22</date>
        <authorinitials lang="es">manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="fr">2006-03-27</date>
        <authorinitials lang="fr">j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="ko">2007-02-15</date>
        <authorinitials lang="ko">Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="no">2006-09-06</date>
        <authorinitials lang="no">KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">The Main Toolbox</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Panel nástrojů</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Das Werkzeugfenster</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">La caja de herramientas</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">La boîte à outils principale</phrase>
    <phrase lang="hr">Glavna Alatna kutija</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">La finestra strumenti</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">기본 도구 상자</phrase>
    <phrase lang="nl">Het Gereedschapsvenster</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Verktøyskrinet</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Панель инструментов</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">主工具箱</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Panel nástrojů</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Werkzeugfenster</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Caja de herramientas</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="hr"><primary>Alatna kutija</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Strumenti</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>도구상자</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl"><primary>Gereedschapsvenster</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Verktøyskrinet</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Панель инструментов</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>工具箱</primary></indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Screenshot of the Toolbox</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Panel nástrojů GIMPu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Das GIMP-Werkzeugfenster</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        Captura de pantalla de la caja de herramientas
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Capture d'écran de la Boîte à outils</phrase>
      <phrase lang="hr">Snimka ekrana Alatne kutije</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Schermata degli strumenti</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구상자의 모습</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Afbeelding van het gereedschapsvenster</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Verktøyskrinet</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Панель инструментов</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">工具箱的屏幕截图</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;es;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/cs/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/de/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="hr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/hr/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/it/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ko">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/ko/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="nl">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/nl/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/no/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/using/zh_CN/toolbox-description.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Main Toolbox is the heart of GIMP. It is the only part of the
    application that you cannot duplicate or close. Here is a quick tour of
    what you will find there.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Panel nástrojů je srdcem Gimpu. Je to jediná část aplikace, kterou
    nemůžete zdvojit nebo naopak zavřít. Zavření Panelu nástrojů totiž znamená
    ukončení celého Gimpu. V této části je stručně popsáno, co v Panelu
    nástrojů najdete.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeugfenster ist das Herzstück von <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
    Es ist das einzige Fenster, von dem alle anderen Dialogfenster der
    Applikation abhängig sind. Hier nun eine kurze Beschreibung der
    Bereiche des Werkzeugfensters.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    La caja de herramientas es el corazón del GIMP. Es la única parte de la
    aplicación que no puede aparecer duplicada y que no puede cerrarse.
    Daremos un breve vistazo de lo que encontrará en ella.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    La boîte à outils est le cœur de GIMP. C'est la seule partie de
    l'application que vous ne pouvez ni dupliquer ni fermer. Voici un rapide
    aperçu de ce que vous y trouverez.
  </para>
  <para lang="hr">
    Glavna alatna kutija je srce Gimpa. To je jedini dio aplikacije koji ne
    možete duplicirati ili zatvoriti. Evo kratkog opisa što sve u njoj možete
    naći.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    Het Hoofdgereedschapsvenster is het hart van <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, het
    is het enige onderdeel van het programma dat u niet kunt sluiten of
    verdubbelen binnen een uitvoering van het programma. Hier volgt een korte
    beschrijving van de aanwezige onderdelen.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    La finestra principale degli strumenti è il cuore di GIMP. È l'unica parte
    dell'applicazione che non è possibile duplicare o chiudere. Di seguito una
    veloce panoramica del suo contenuto.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    기본 도구 상자는 김프의 핵심이므로 복사하거나 닫을 수 없는 유일한 
    부분입니다. 다음은 도구 상자에 대한 개괄적인 설명입니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Verktøyskrinet er hjartet til <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Dette er den
    einaste applikasjonen du ikkje kan kopiera eller lukke. Her er ein rask
    gjennomgang av kva du kan finne i skrinet.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Панель инструментов это сердце <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Это единственная
    часть приложения, которую вы не можете cдублировать или закрыть. Вот
    небольшое описание того, что вы здесь найдёте.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    主工具箱是 GIMP 的心脏。它是程序中唯一不能被复制和关闭的部分。下面是一个简短的介绍。
  </para>

  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      In the Toolbox, as in most parts of GIMP, moving the mouse on top
      of something and letting it rest for a moment will usually bring
      up a "tooltip" message that may help you understand what the thing
      is or what you can do with it.  Also, in many cases you can press
      the <keycap>F1</keycap> key to get help about the thing that is
      underneath the mouse.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Pokud v Panelu nástrojů, nejdůležitější části Gimpu, nad nějakou částí
      zastavíte ukazatel myši a necháte ho chvíli v klidu, objeví se obvykle
      „nástrojový tip“, který vám pomůže zjistit, k čemu daná část slouží a
      jak ji použít. V mnoha případech také můžete získat plnohodnotnou
      nápovědu k objektu, na který ukazuje myš, stisknutím klávesy
      <keycap>F1</keycap>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Im Werkzeugfenster, wie auch in Dialogen oder Menüs, können Sie sich von
      GIMP kurze Erklärungen geben lassen. Bewegen Sie hierzu den Mauszeiger
      über eine Schaltfläche und verharren Sie dort mit der Maus einige
      Sekunden. Die Minihilfe wird automatisch eingeblendet. Außerdem können
      Sie <keycap>F1</keycap>
      drücken, um den Hilfebrowser zu öffnen, der Ihnen eine ausführlichere
      Seite der Onlinehilfe mit einer Beschreibung der aktuellen Schaltfläche
      oder Funktion anzeigt.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      En la caja de herramientas, como en la mayor parte de la interfaz del
      GIMP, al llevar el ratón sobre algún elemento y dejarlo allí por un
      momento hace aparecer un mensaje descriptivo que le puede ayudar a
      entender lo que es o lo que se puede hacer con el mismo.  Además, en
      muchos casos, puede presionar la tecla <keycap>F1</keycap> para obtener
      ayuda sobre el elemento que se encuentra debajo del cursor.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Dans la boîte à outils, comme dans la plupart des autres dialogues du
      GIMP, placer et maintenir la souris sur un élément fait généralement
      apparaître une information sur l'outil qui vous aide à comprendre ce
      qu'est cet élément et ce qu'il vous permet de faire. De plus, dans la
      plupart des cas, vous pouvez presser la touche <keycap>F1</keycap>
      pour obtenir de l'aide sur ce qui est sous la souris.
    </para>
    <para lang="hr">
      U alatnoj kutiji kao i u većini drugih dijaloga Gimpa ako stavite i
      zadržite kursor iznad određenog elementa pojaviti će se informacija o
      tom elementu što vam pomaže u razumijevanju elementa i što sve s njime
      možete napraviti. Osim toga, u većini slučajeva, možete pritisnuti
      tipku <keycap>F1</keycap> i čime aktivirate pomoć za element koji se
      nalazi ispod kursora.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      In het gereedschapsvenster kunt u, zoals in de meeste onderdelen van
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, de muis enige tijd op een onderdeel ervan laten
      rusten om een "gereedschap-tip" te laten verschijnen. Deze vertelt u de
      naam van het onderliggende ding en legt in het kort uit wat u er mee
      kunt doen. In veel gevallen kunt u ook door op de
      <keycap>F1</keycap>-toets te drukken hulp krijgen over hetgeen zich op
      dat moment onder de muiscursor bevindt.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Nella finestra degli strumenti, come in molte altre parti di GIMP,
      muovendo il puntatore del mouse sopra una parte di essa e
      lasciandocelo per un tempo minimo provocherà la visualizzazione di un
      breve messaggio di descrizione, un "suggerimento", che potrà aiutare
      nella comprensione della funzione del particolare strumento al quale
      si sta puntando. Allo stesso modo, premendo il
      tasto <keycap>F1</keycap> si ottiene la visualizzazione della parte
      del manuale che riguarda l'argomento puntato dal mouse.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      김프의 다른 부분과 마찬가지로 도구 상자의 특정 부분에 마우스 커서를
      올려놓고 잠시 기다리면, 해당 부분에 대한 간단한 설명과 사용법이 
      "도움말" 로 뜹니다. 또 원하는 부분에 마우스 커서를 올려놓고 
      <keycap>F1</keycap> 키를 누르면 조금 더 상세한 도움말을 볼 수 
      있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      I verktøyskrinet, som i det meste av <acronym>GIMP</acronym> elles,
      kan du la musepeikaren kvile ei lita stund over eitt eller anna, og det
      vil til vanleg dukke opp ei lita melding som fortel kva dette er og kva
      det kan brukast til. I mange tilfelle kan du også trykke
      <keycap>F1</keycap>-tasten for å få meir hjelp om det som er under
      musepeikaren.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      В панели инструментов, как и в большинстве элементов  интерфейса
      GIMP, помещение курсора мыши поверх какого-либо  элемента с
      задержкой на мгновенье обычно вызывает  "подсказку", которая может
      помочь понять действие или  назначение этого элемента. Также в
      большинстве случаев для получения  помощии по данному элементу вы
      можете нажать клавишу <keycap>F1</keycap>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      像 GIMP 中其它部分一样，移动鼠标到工具箱中的组件上，然后等一会常常会显
      示“工具提示”，它们帮助您了解这些是什么和您能用它们干嘛。大部分情况下，
      您也可以按 <keycap>F1</keycap> 获得当前在您鼠标下组件的相关帮助。
    </para>
  </tip>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Toolbox Menu:</emphasis>
        This menu is special:  it contains some commands that cannot
        be found in the menus that are attached to images.  (Also some
        that can.)  These include commands for setting preferences,
        creating certain types of dialogs, etc.  The contents are
        described systematically in the <link
        linkend="gimp-tools-menu">Toolbox Menu</link> section.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Nabídka Panelu nástrojů:</emphasis>
        Tato nabídka je zvláštní tím, že některé z příkazů, které obsahuje
        nejsou dostupné z nabídek obrázků. Patří mezi ně příkazy pro
        nastavení předvoleb, vytvoření určitých dialogů atd.
        Nabídka je podrobně a systematicky popsána v části <link
        linkend="gimp-tools-menu">Nabídka Panelu nástrojů</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Werkzeugfenstermenü:</emphasis>
        Das Spezielle an diesem Menü ist, dass es Funktionen enthält, die Ihnen
        ausschließlich im Werkzeugfenster und nicht im Bildfenster zur
        Verfügung stehen. Insbesondere finden Sie in diesem Menü eine große
        Menge von Funktionen, um Bilder zu öffnen, zu laden oder neu zu
        erzeugen. Weitere Informationen finden Sie im
        <xref linkend="gimp-tools-menu" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Menú de la caja de herramientas:</emphasis>
        Este menú es especial: contiene algunos comandos que no se hallan en
        los menús correspondientes a las imágenes (además de algunos que sí se
        hallan en ellos).  Éstos incluyen comandos para ajustar las
        preferencias, crear ciertos tipos de diálogos, etcétera.  Su contenido
        se describe sistemáticamente en la sección <link
        linkend="gimp-tools-menu">menú de la caja de herramientas</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Le menu de la boîte à outil :</emphasis>
        Ce menu est particulier : il contient des commandes que l'on ne
        retrouve pas dans les menus des fenêtres image (et d'autres qui y
        sont). Il s'agit des commandes qui permettent de paramétrer les
        préférences, de créer certain type de dialogues, etc... Leurs contenus
        sont systématiquement décrits dans la section
        <link linkend="gimp-tools-menu">Menu de la boîte à outils</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="hr">
        <emphasis>Izbornik alatne kutije:</emphasis> ovaj izbornik je
        specijalan: većinu komandi koje on sadrži nemožete naći u drugim
        izbornicima povezanima sa slikom. Radi se o komandama podešavanja,
        komandama za kreiranje određenih tipova dijaloga itd … Njihov
        sadržaj je detaljno opisan u poglavlju Izbornik alatne kutije
        <!--<link linkend="gimp-tools-menu">-->Toolbox Menu<!--</link>-->.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Gereedschapsvenster menu:</emphasis>
        Dit is een speciaal menu; het bevat enkele functies die nergens
        anders, in menu's die met afbeeldingen verbonden zijn, te vinden zijn.
        We hebben het hier over mogelijkheden om voorkeuren in te stellen,
        bepaalde soorten dialoogvensters maken enzovoorts. Al deze zaken
        worden volledig uitgebreid uitgelegd on het hoofdstuk over het
        <!-- PENDING: nl link linkend="gimp-tools-menu" -->Gereedschapsvenster
        menu<!--/link-->.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Menu strumenti:</emphasis> Questo menu è speciale:
        contiene alcuni comandi che si non possono trovare nei menu
        associati alle immagini (per lo meno non tutti). Tra questi ci sono
        i comandi per impostare le preferenze, per creare alcuni tipi di
        finestre, ecc. I contenuti di questo menu sono descritti in maniera
        esaustiva nella sezione <link linkend="gimp-tools-menu">Menu
        strumenti</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>도구상자 메뉴:</emphasis>
        이 메뉴는 조금 특별해서 이미지 창에 있는 메뉴에서는 찾을 수 없는
        몇 가지 메뉴들을 가지고 있습니다. 그것은 기본 설정, 새로운 대화상자
        생성 등으로 자세한 내용은
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-tools-menu">도구상자 메뉴</link>
         --> 도구상자 메뉴 섹션에 소개되어 있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Menyen for verktøyskrinet:</emphasis> Denne menyen er noe
        spesiell. Han inneheld ein del kommandoar som ikkje finst i dei andre
        menyane i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Dette gjeld mellom anna menyen for
        å setje diverse innstillingar for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, lage ulike
        typar dialogboksar osv. Dette er nærare omtala i avsnittet om
        <link linkend="gimp-tools-menu">menyen for verktøyskrinet</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Меню панели инструментов:</emphasis> Это меню особое:
        оно содержит некоторые команды,  которые не найти в прикрепяемых
        к изображению меню. ( А также некоторые дублируемые) Здесь
        включены команды  для настроек, создания определенных типов
        диалогов, и т.д.  Содержание систематически описано в разделе
        <!--PENDING: ru link linkend="gimp-tools-menu"-->Меню панели инструментов
        <!--/link-->
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>工具箱菜单：</emphasis> 该菜单比较特殊：它有很多命令在图像
        上的菜单那儿无法找到。(而有些能找到。)它们包括设置首选项，生成特定的
        对话框等命令。这些内容在<link linkend="gimp-tools-menu">工具箱目录
        </link>有系统的描述。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Tool icons:</emphasis> These icons are buttons which
        activate tools for a wide variety of purposes: selecting parts of
        images, painting on them, transforming them, etc.  The <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">Toolbox Introduction</link>
        section gives an overview of how to work with tools, and each tool is
        described systematically in the <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox">Tools</link> chapter.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Ikony nástrojů:</emphasis>
        Tyto ikony jsou tlačítky pro aktivaci nástrojů Gimpu, které slouží
        k nejrůznějším účelům: výběru částí obrázku, malování, transformacím
        a mnoha dalším. V části <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">Úvod do panelu nástrojů</link>
        jsou popsány obecné základy práce s nástroji, v kapitole <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox">Nástroje</link> jsou jednotlivé nástroje
        systematicky a podrobně popsány.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Werkzeugsymbole:</emphasis>
        Durch einen Mausklick auf eines dieser Symbole aktivieren Sie das
        symbolisierte Werkzeug. GIMP stellt Ihnen verschiedenste Werkzeuge aus
        den Kategorien <quote>Auswahlwerkzeug</quote>,
        <quote>Malwerkzeug</quote>, <quote>Transformationswerkzeug</quote>
        und <quote>Sonstiges</quote> zur Verfügung. Weitere Informationen
        über die GIMP Werkzeuge und wie Sie mit diesen Arbeiten können
        finden Sie im <xref linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Iconos de herramientas:</emphasis>
        Estos iconos activan herramientas que sirven a una variedad de
        propósitos: seleccionar partes de imágenes, pintar sobre ellas,
        transformarlas, entre otras cosas.  En la sección de <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">introducción a la caja de
          herramientas</link> se da un repaso general al empleo de las
        herramientas, y cada una se describe sistemáticamente en el capítulo
        <link linkend="gimp-toolbox">Herramientas</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Les icônes outils :</emphasis>
        Ces icônes sont des boutons qui activent les outils permettant
        de multiples choses : sélectionner des parties d'image, les peindre,
        les transformer, etc... La section
        <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">La Boîte à outils</link>
        donne un aperçu du fonctionnement des outils, et chaque outil est
        décrit dans le chapitre <link linkend="gimp-toolbox">Outils</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="hr">
        <emphasis>Ikone alati:</emphasis> ove ikone su zapravo gumbi koji
        aktiviraju alate za razne svrhe: selektiranje dijelova slike,
        slikanje, vršenje raznih promjena na slici, itd … Poglavlje Upute
        za Alatnu kutiju <!--<link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">-->Toolbox
        Introduction<!--</link>--> daje vam pregled kako raditi s alatima,
        a svaki je alat posebno i detaljno opisan u poglavlju Alati
        <!--<link linkend="gimp-toolbox">Tools</link>-->.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Gereedschapspictogrammen:</emphasis> deze pictogrammen
        activeren de gereedschappen met verschillende functies: Het selecteren
        van delen van afbeeldingen, ze anders inkleuren, ze van vorm
        veranderen enzovoorts. Het hoofdstuk <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">Inleiding in het
          gereedschapsvenster</link> geeft een overzicht van de mogelijkheden
        die de verschillende gereedschappen bieden, ieder gereedschap zal
        ook uitgebreid in het hoofdstuk <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox">gereedschappen</link> beschreven worden.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Icone strumenti:</emphasis> queste icone sono pulsanti
        che attivano strumenti per gli scopi più vari: selezionare parti di
        immagini, disegnarle, trasformarle, ecc. La sezione <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">Introduzione agli
        strumenti</link> fa una panoramica su come lavorare con gli
        strumenti mentre ogni strumento viene descritto in dettaglio nel
        capitolo <link linkend="gimp-toolbox">Strumenti</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>도구 아이콘:</emphasis>
        이 아이콘들은 그림의 일부를 선택하거나, 칠하거나 변형시키는 등의 
        다양한 목적을 위한 도구들을 사용하기 위한 것입니다. 도구들의 
        간단한 사용법은
        <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">도구상자 소개</link>
        섹션에 있고, 각 도구들에 대해서는
        <link linkend="gimp-toolbox">도구들</link> 장에 상세히 소개되어 
		있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Verktøyikona:</emphasis> Dette er ikon som også er knappar
        for å aktivera verktøy for eit uttal føremål: velje ut deler av
        biletet, male på biletet, omforme bileta osv. Du finn meir om dette
        i avsnittet <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">Verktøyskrinet</link>.
        Her finn også eit oversyn over korleis du kan arbeide med verktøya.
        Kvart verktøy er nærare omtala i kapitlet om 
        <link linkend="gimp-toolbox">verktøya</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Пиктограммы инструментов:</emphasis> Эти пиктограммы
        являются кнопками, которые активируют инструмены для разнообразных
        действий: выделение частей изображений, рисования, преобразования,
        и т.п. Раздел <link linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">
        Введение в панель инструментов
        </link>  описывает принципы работы с инструментами. Каждый
        инструмент описан в разделе <link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox">Инструменты</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>工具图标：</emphasis> 这些图标是开启那些完成各种各样功能工
        具的按钮；在图像上选择，在上面涂画和变换它们等。<link
        linkend="gimp-toolbox-introduction">使用工具</link>这部分有如何使用
        这些工具的概述，每个工具在<link linkend="gimp-toolbox">工具</link>章
        节都有系统地描述。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Foreground/Background colors:</emphasis>
        The color areas here show you GIMP's current foreground and background
        colors, which come into play in many operations. Clicking on either
        one of them brings up a color selector dialog that allow you to change
        to a different color. Clicking on the double-headed arrow swaps the
        two colors, and clicking on the small symbol in the lower left corner
        resets them to black and white.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Barva popředí a pozadí:</emphasis>
        Barevné plochy představují aktuální barvu popředí a barvu pozadí
        Gimpu. Tyto barvy jsou používány při mnoha operacích. Kliknutím na
        jednu z barevných ploch se otevře dialog pro výběr barvy, který
        umožňuje aktivní barvu popředí nebo pozadí změnit. Kliknutím na
        zahnutou oboustrannou šipku se obě barvy vzájemně prohodí. Kliknutím
        na černobílou ikonku vlevo dole se barva pozadí nastaví na bílou a
        barva popředí na černou, tedy na výchozí hodnoty.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Vordergrund-/Hintergrundfarbe:</emphasis>
        Der Farbbereich des Werkzeugfensters zeigt die aktuelle Vorder-
        und Hintergrundfarbe, die von verschiedenen Dialogen benutzt wird.
        Durch Klicken auf eines der beiden Schaltflächen öffnet sich der
        Farbdialog. Mit dem Pfeil lassen sich die Farben jeweils
        vertauschen. Um die Farben auf die Voreinstellungswerte Schwarz
        und Weiß zurückzusetzen, benutzen Sie das kleine
        <quote>Schwarz/Weiß</quote> Symbol links unten.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Colores de frente y fondo:</emphasis>
        Estas áreas muestran los colores de frente y fondo actuales del GIMP,
        los cuales entran en juego en numerosas operaciones.  Al hacer clic
        sobre cualquiera de los dos hace aparecer un diálogo, que le permite
        cambiarlo a un color diferente.  Si hace clic sobre la flecha de dos
        puntas, los dos colores se alternan.  Y si hace clic sobre el pequeño
        símbolo de la esquina inferior izquierda, los colores se reestablecen
        a blanco y negro.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>Couleurs de premier et d'arrière-plan :</emphasis>
        Les aires de couleurs vous montrent les couleurs de premier plan et
        d'arrière plan actuelles, elles interviennent dans de nombreuses
        opérations. Cliquer sur l'une d'entre elles fera apparaître un
        dialogue de choix des couleurs qui vous permettra de la changer.
        Cliquer sur la double-flèche interchange les deux couleurs, et cliquer
        sur le petit symbole dans le coin en bas à gauche réinitialise
        le noir et le blanc.
      </para>
      <para lang="hr">
        <emphasis>Boje prednjeg i stražnjeg plana: </emphasis>
        Boje koje možete vidjeti na slici su boje izabrane prema osnovnim
        vrijednostima programa. One dolaze u igru u mnogim operacijama.
        Kliknite na jednu od njih i otvoriti će se izbornik boja, ako pak
        dvaput kliknete na strelicu sa dva smjera boje će zamijeniti mjesta.
        Klik na mali simbol u donjem lijevom uglu ponovno vraća boje na
        njihovo početno mjesto.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Voorgrond/Achtergrond kleuren:</emphasis>
        De gekleurde vlakken alhier tonen de huidige voor- en
        achtergrondkleuren die <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gebruikt in
        verschillende bewerkingen. Als u op een ervan klikt verschijnt er een
        venster waarin u een kleur kunt selecteren om de huidige mee te
        vervangen. Als u op de dubbelle pijl klikt verwisselt u de beide
        kleuren en met een klik op het kleine symbool in de linker onderhoek
        zet u ze weer terug naar zwart en wit.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Colori di primopiano/sfondo:</emphasis> queste aree di
        colore mostrano i colori di primopiano e di sfondo correnti di
        GIMP; colori che entrano in gioco in molte operazioni.  Facendo
        clic su uno di questi si attiva una finestra di selezione colore
        che permette di selezionare altri colori. Facendo clic sulla
        doppia freccia invece si ottiene lo scambio dei due colori e
        facendo clic sul piccolo simbolo presente nella parte in basso a
        sinistra li si reimposta ai valori predefiniti rispettivamente
        di nero e bianco.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>전경색/배경색:</emphasis>
        이 부분은 김프의 현재 전경색과 배경색을 보여줍니다. 각 부분을 
        클릭하면 색상 선택 대화상자가 나타나고 그곳에서 다른 색상으로 
        변경할 수 있습니다. 그리고 양방향 화살표를 클릭하면 두 색상을 
        맞바꿀 수 있으며, 좌하단의 조그만 심볼을 클릭하면 기본값인 검정색과
        흰색으로 초기화할 수 있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Forgrunns-/bakgrunns-fargar:</emphasis>  Fargerutene her
        syner gjeldande forgrunnsfarge (strekfarge) og bakgrunnsfarge.
        Klikkar du på ei av fargerutene, dukkar det opp ein fargeveljar som
        gir deg høve til å endre fargen som er i bruk. Klikk på den doble
        pila og dei to fargane bytter plass. Klikk på symbolet i nedre,
        venstre hjørnet for å setje fargane til svart og kvit.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Цвета фона/переднего плана:</emphasis> Область выбора
        цвета показывает текущий выбранный вами цвет  переднего плана и
        фона, который применяется во многих операциях.  Щелчок по одному
        из них вызовет выборщик цветов, который позволяет  вам
        установить другой цвет. Щелчок по двунаправленной стрелке
        поменяет местами два цвета, щелчок по небольшому символу  в
        нижнем левом углу сбросит их в черный и белый цвета.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>前景/背景色：</emphasis> 该颜色区域显示 GIMP 当前的前景和
        背景色，它们在许多操作中都有用。点它们中任何一个都会跳出颜色选择对话
        框。点击双头箭头标志会交换它们的颜色，而点左下角的小标志会重置为黑白
        色。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Brush/Pattern/Gradient</emphasis>
        The symbols here show you <acronym>GIMP's</acronym>
        current selections for: the Paintbrush, used by all tools that allow
        you to paint on the image ("painting" includes operations like erasing
        and smudging, by the way); for the Pattern, which is used in filling
        selected areas of an image; and for the Gradient, which comes into
        play whenever an operation requires a smoothly varying range of
        colors. Clicking on any of these symbols brings up a dialog window
        that allows you to change it.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Stopa, Vzorek a Přechod</emphasis>
        Ikony v této části zobrazují aktivní stopu (kterou používají kreslící
        nástroje, mezi které se řadí i nástroje pro gumování či rozmazávání),
        aktivní vzorek (který se používá pro vyplňování částí obrázku) a
        aktivní přechod (který se používá tehdy, když nějaká operace vyžaduje
        plynule přecházející škálu barev). Kliknutím na kteroukoliv z těchto
        ikon se otevře dialogové okno, umožňující změnu stopy, vzorku či
        přechodu.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Pinsel/Muster/Verlauf:</emphasis>
        Diese Miniaturbilder zeigen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>s
        aktuell ausgewählten Pinsel, Muster und Farbverlauf. Der Pinsel kann
        sowohl zum Zeichnen im herkömmlichen Sinn benutzt werden, als auch zum
        Radieren und Verschmieren.
        <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">Malwerkzeuge</link>
        benutzen nicht nur Pinseleinstellungen. Auch Muster werden
        beispielsweise durch den
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Fülleimer</link>
        benutzt, um Flächen mit dem ausgewählten Muster zu füllen. Der Verlauf
        kommt ins Spiel, wenn man viele Farben braucht, um eine bestimmten
        Bildbereich zu füllen. Durch Klicken auf eines dieser Miniaturbilder
        erreichen Sie den jeweiligen Dialog, um entweder einen neuen Pinsel,
        Verlauf oder ein neues Muster auszuwählen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Brocha, patrón y degradado</emphasis>
        Estos símbolos muestran las opciones actuales para: <emphasis>la
          brocha</emphasis> que emplean todas las herramientas que le permiten
        pintar sobre la imagen (recuerde que "pintar" incluye a operaciones
        como borrar y difuminar); <emphasis>el patrón</emphasis> empleado al
        rellenar las áreas seleccionadas de una imagen; y <emphasis>el
          degradado</emphasis>, el que entra en juego cuando una operación
        requiere una variación suave por un rango de colores.  Al hacer clic
        sobre cualquiera de estos símbolos aparece una ventana de diálogo que
        le permite cambiarlo.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Ces symboles vous montrent la sélection actuelle de
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        pour: la brosse, utilisée par tous les outils qui permettent de
        dessiner sur l'image ("dessiner" est pris au sens large et inclut
        les opérations telles que le gommage et le barbouillage) ; le motif,
        utilisé pour remplir des aires sélectionnées d'une image ; et le
        dégradé, qui intervient dès qu'une opération nécessite une douce
        transition de couleurs. Un clic sur l'un de ces symboles affichera
        le dialogue permettant d'en changer.
      </para>
      <para lang="hr">
        <emphasis>Kistovi/Motivi/Gradijenti: </emphasis>
        Simboli koji su vidljivi na slici prikazuju trenutnu
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> selekciju: za Kist, a koriste se za sve
        alate kojima možete crtati (“crtanje” uključuje i operacije
        brisanja ili zamićuvanja); Motivi se koriste za punjenje
        selektiranih zona slike, a Gradijente za operacije koje zahtjevaju
        lagani prijelaz iz jedne u drugu boju. Klik na bilo koji od ovih
        ikona otvara prozor dijaloga u kojem možete mijenjati različite
        opcije.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Penseel/Patroon/Verloop</emphasis>
        De symbolen hier illustreren de huidige selectie voor het verfpenseel:
        dit wordt gebruikt door alle gereedschappen waarmee u in de afbelding
        kunt tekenen. (Onder tekenen worden trouwens ook bewerkingen als
        uiwissen en uitsmeren geschaard). Voor het patroon: dat wordt gebruikt
        bij het vullen van geselecteerde delen van afbeeldingen; En voor het
        verloop dat van belang is als een bewerking een geleidelijk
        kleurverloop nodig heeft. Als u op een van deze drie symbolen klikt
        opent u een dialoogvenster waarin u de huidige instellingen naar
        behoefte kunt veranderen.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Pennello/Motivo/Gradiente</emphasis> i simboli mostrano
        la selezione corrente di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> per: il pennello,
        usato da tutti gli strumenti per disegnare sull'immagine (il
        "disegno" include operazioni tipo cancellare e sfumare); per il
        Motivo, usato nel riempimento delle aree selezionate di
        un'immagine; e per il gradiente che entra in gioco quando
        un'operazione abbisogna di un'insieme di colori variabile con
        continuità. Facendo clic su ognuno di questi simboli porta in primo
        piano una finestra di dialogo che permette di cambiarli.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>붓/무늬/그라디언트</emphasis>
        여기에는 현재 선택된 도구들의 상태를 보여줍니다. : 이미지에 색칠을 
        할 수 있는 모든 도구(지우기나 문지르기도 포함), 이미지의 선택된 
        부분을 채우데 사용되는 무늬, 색상을 부드럽게 변화시키는 작업에 
        사용하는 그라디언트 등. 이 버튼들을 클릭하면 각각의 대화상자가 
        나타나는데, 그 대화상자에서 원하는 것으로 바꿀 수 있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Pensel/Mønsterelement/Fargeovergangar</emphasis>
        Symbola her viser gjeldande val for desse. Penselen blir brukt av
        alle verktøya som du kan male på biletet med. (<quote>Maling</quote>
        i dette tilfellet inkluderer også visking og å gjere biletet meir
        utydeleg). Mønsterelementet blir brukt for å fylle utvalde område på
        biletet. Fargeovergangen blir brukt kvar gong eit verktøy har behov for
        gradvise overgangar mellom farger eller fargenyansar. Klikk på kvart
        av symbola for å få opp dialogvindauget som gir deg høve til å
        endra innstillingane.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Киcть/Текстура/Градиент</emphasis>
        Расположенные здесь значки показывают текущие выбранные элементы
        <acronym>GIMP'а</acronym>,
        такие как: кисть, используемую всеми инструментами, позволяющими
        рисовать по изображению ("рисование", кстати, включает в себя такие
        операции как стирание и размазывание); текстуру, используемую для
        заливки выделенных областей изображения; и градиент, который
        применяется когда необходимо создать плавный цветовой переход. Щелчок
        по любому из этих значков вызовет диалоговое окно позволяющее изменить
        данный элемент.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>画笔/图案/渐变：</emphasis> 这些标志显示 GIMP 当前选取的：
        画笔，能被所有在图像上涂画的工具所使用(这里的“涂画”操作包括擦除和涂
        抹等)；图案，在填充所选区域时使用；渐变，当操作需要一组平滑渐变的颜
        色是起作用。点击任何的这些标志将弹出允许您改变它的对话框窗口。
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Active Image:</emphasis> (This is a new feature in GIMP
        2.2) In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you can work with many images at
        once, but at any given moment, one of them is the <quote>active
        image</quote>. Here you find a small iconic representation of the
        active image. Clicking on it brings up a dialog with a list of all
        the currently open images, allowing you to make a different one
        active if you want to. (Clicking on the window where the image is
        displayed will accomplish the same thing, though.)
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        <emphasis>Aktivní obrázek:</emphasis>
        (Toto je nová vlastnost Gimpu 2.2.) V Gimpu můžete pracovat s mnoha
        obrázky současně, ale v každém okamžiku je pouze jeden z nich aktivní.
        V této části Panelu nástrojů je aktivní obrázek zobrazen v podobě
        ikony. Kliknutím na ní se otevře dialog se seznamem všech právě
        otevřených obrázků. Pomocí tohoto seznamu je možné aktivovat jiný
        obrázek, ale snadněji toho lze dosáhnout prostým kliknutím na okno
        požadovaného obrázku.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Aktives Bild:</emphasis> Wenn Sie in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        mit vielen Bildern arbeiten, gibt es immer genau eines, auf welchem
        Sie Operationen ausführen können. Das aktive oder aktuelle Bild
        zeigt Ihnen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        in diesem Bereich als Miniaturbild an. Klicken Sie auf dieses
        Miniaturbild, öffnet <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        einen Dialog, der Ihnen alle derzeit geöffneten Bilder anzeigt.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        <emphasis>Imagen activa:</emphasis>
        (ésta es una nueva capacidad del GIMP 2.2) En el
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, puede trabajar con muchas imágenes a la vez,
        pero en cada momento, una de ellas es la <quote>imagen activa</quote>.
        Aquí puede encontrar una representación en miniatura de la imagen
        activa.  Al hacer clic sobre ella aparece un diálogo con una lista de
        todas las imágenes actualmente abiertas, que le permite seleccionar
        una para convertirla en la imagen activa (es lo mismo que hacer clic
        sobre la ventana de la imagen que se desea hacer activa).
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <emphasis>L'image active</emphasis>: Nouvelle fonctionnalité
        apparue dans GIMP 2.2. Dans <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, vous pouvez
        travailler avec plusieurs images en même temps, mais à chaque
        instant, l'une d'entre elle est <quote>l'image active</quote>.
        Vous trouverez ici une représentation miniature de cette image.
        Cliquer sur elle ouvrira un dialogue listant toutes les images
        actuellement ouvertes, vous permettant de changer l'image active si
        vous le désirez (Bien sûr, on peut aussi rendre une image active en
        cliquant sur la fenêtre de l'image).
      </para>
      <para lang="hr">
        <emphasis>Aktivna slika:</emphasis>
        (ovo je novi element u GIMP 2.2). U <acronym>Gimpu</acronym>
        možete u isto vrijeme raditi sa nekoliko slika, međutim samo jedna od
        njih može biti “aktivna slika”. Ova nova ikona prikazuje tu aktivnu
        sliku. Klik na nju otvara dijalog sa listom svih otvorenih slika što
        vam pruža mogućnos promjeniti aktivnu slike ukoliko to želite. (Klik
        na prozor aktivne slike postići će isti rezultat).
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        <emphasis>Actieve afbeelding:</emphasis>
        (Dit is een nieuwe mogelijkheid in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-2.2) In
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        kunt u meerdere afbeeldingen tegelijkertijd ge-opend hebben, er kan er
        echter maar een tegelijk actief zijn. Op deze plaats kunt u een kleine
        weergave van de actieve afbeelding vinden. Als u er op klikt komt er
        een lijst met alle geopende afbeeldingen tevoorschijn en kunt u een
        andere activeren. (Door op het afbeeldingsvenster van de betreffende
        afbeelding te klikken bereikt u op vaak eenvoudiger wijze ook
        hetzelfde.)
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <emphasis>Immagine attiva:</emphasis> (questa è una nuova
        caratteristica in GIMP 2.2) In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, puoi
        lavorare con molte immagini contemporaneamente, ma solo una per
        volta è l'"immagine attiva". Qui si può vedere una poccola icona
        rappresentante l'immagine attiva. Facendo clic su di essa si apre
        una finestra con un'elenco delle immagini aperte che consente di
        renderne una qualunque l'immagine attiva (anche se si ottiene lo
        stesso risultato facendo clic direttamente sulla finestra che si
        desideri divenga quella attiva).
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <emphasis>활성화된 이미지:</emphasis>
        (김프 2.2의 새로운 기능) <acronym>김프</acronym> 에서는 한번에 여러
        이미지들을 작업할 수 있습니다. 하지만 그러할지라도 어느 한 순간에는
        한 이미지만 "활성화된 이미지" 가 될 것입니다. 그 활성화된 이미지의
        미리보기가 이곳에 표시됩니다. 이것을 클릭해서 대화상자를 호출하면
        현재 열려있는 이미지들의 리스트가 나타나므로 이중 하나를 선택해
        활성화시킬 수 있습니다(활성화시키려는 이미지의 창을 직접 선택해도 
        됩니다).
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <emphasis>Aktivt bilete:</emphasis>
        Dette er nytt frå og med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2. I
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> kan du arbeide med mange bilete samstundes,
        men bare eitt av dei er til ei kvar tid aktivt. Her finn du ein
        miniatyr av det aktive biletet. Klikkar du på miniatyren, kjem det
        opp ei liste over alle dei opne bileta slik at du kan velje kva bilete
        du vil arbeide med. Du kan oppnå det same ved å klikka direkte på
        det vindauget du ønskjer å opna.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        <emphasis>Активное изображение:</emphasis> (Это новая
        возможность в GIMP 2.2) В  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> вы можете
        работать с многими  изображениями одновременн, но в любой момент
        только  одно из них является "активным изображением".
        Здесь вы найдёте представление уменьшённой копии   активного
        изображения в виде пиктограммы.  Щелчок по ней вызовет диалог со
        списком всех открытых  на данный момент изображений, позволяя
        вам при желании  изменить активное изображение. (Щелчок по окну
        изображения  делает тоже самое)
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        <emphasis>活动图像：</emphasis> (这是 GIMP 2.2 版本的新特性)您能在
        GIMP 中同时在多个图像上工作，但是在给定的时刻，只能有一个是“活动图像
        ”。在这这个小图标就就指出活动图像。点击它会弹出一个您当前打开的所有
        文件的列表的对话框，允许按您所愿指定活动图像。(虽然点击图像显示的窗
        口将完成同样的事。)
      </para>

      <note lang="en;cs;de;es;ko;nl;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
        <para lang="en">
          The "Active Image" preview is disabled by default. If you want it,
          you can enable it in the
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Toolbox Preferences</link> tab.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Náhled aktivního obrázku v Panelu nástrojů je ve výchozím nastavení
          zakázán. Pokud ho chcete používat, můžete ho povolit v
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">
            Předvolbách Panelu nástrojů
          </link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Diese Funktion ist in den GIMP Standardeinstellungen deaktiviert.
          Sie können diese im Dialog <link
          linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Einstellungen Werkzeugfenster</link>
          einschalten.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          La previsualización de la imagen activa se encuentra desactivada de
          fábrica.  Si desea tenerla, puede activarla en las <link
          linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">preferencias de la caja de
            herramientas</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="nl">
          Dit pictogram met de actieve afbeelding staat standaard niet
          getoond. Als u het in beeld wilt hebben kunt u het in het tabblad
          met <!--link
          linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox"XXX_NL-->Gereedschapsvoorkeuren<!--/link-->
          aanzetten.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          L'anteprima dell'"immagine attiva" è normalmente disabilitata. Se
          si vuole è possibile abilitarla nella linguetta delle <link
          linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Preferenze degli strumenti</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ko">
          "활성화된 이미지" 의 미리보기는 기본적으로는 보여지지 않습니다.
          따라서 보기를 원할 경우 
		  <!-- PENDING: ko <link  linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox"> 도구상자 설정</link> --> 
		  도구상자 설정 탭을 통해 설정해야 합니다.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Dersom det aktive vindauget ikkje er synleg, kan du henta det fram
          med menyen
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">innstillingar</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          Просмотр "активного изображения" по умолчанию отключен.
          Если хотите его активировать, можете сделать это на
          странице <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Настройки
          панели инструментов</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          “活动图像”预览默认是关闭的，不过您可以通过
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">工具箱首选项</link>
          页来改变它。
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <note lang="en;de;es;fr;hr;it;ko;nl;no;ru">  <!--Added 050903-->
    <para lang="en">
      At every start, GIMP selects a tool (the brush), a color, a brush and
      a pattern by default, always the same. If you want GIMP to select the
      last tool, color, brush and pattern you used when quitting your
      previous session, check the <guilabel>Save input device settings
        on exit</guilabel> in
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-input-devices">Preferences/Input
        Devices</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Bei jedem Start von GIMP wird das Standardwerkzeug mit der
      Standardfarbe, der Standardpinselspitze und dem Standardmuster
      aktiviert. Wenn Sie es bevorzugen, dass GIMP mit der zuletzt verwendeten
      Einstellung startet, können Sie dies im Dialog
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Einstellungen</link>
      im Punkt <guilabel>Gerätestatus beim Beenden speichern</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Cada vez que se inicia el GIMP, se coloca una herramienta (el pincel),
      un color, una brocha y un patrón predeterminados.  Si desea que el GIMP
      seleccione los últimos usados, active la opción "Guardar la
      configuración del dispositivo de entrada al salir" en
      Preferencias/Dispositivos de entrada.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      À chaque démarrage, GIMP sélectionne par défaut un outil (le pinceau),
      une couleur, une pointe de brosse et un motif, toujours les mêmes. Si
      vous voulez que GIMP sélectionne l'outil, la couleur, la pointe de
      brosse et le motif utilisés quand vous avez quitté la session
      précédente, cochez l'option <quote>Enregistrer l'état des
      périphériques en quittant</quote> dans Préférences/Périphériques
    </para>
    <para lang="hr">
      Pri svakom otvaranju GIMP izabire jedan alat (kist), jednu boju, jedna
      kist i motiv prema već unaprijed određenim osnovnim vrijednostima, a
      koje su uvijek iste. Ukoliko želite da GIMP izabere alat, boju i motiv
      koji ste koristili prethodni put, provjerite "Set input device
      settings on exit" u Preferences/Ulazni uređaji.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ad ogni avvio, GIMP seleziona uno strumento (il pennello), un colore,
      un pennello e un motivo predefiniti; sempre gli stessi. Se si vuole
      che GIMP selezioni l'ultimo strumento, colore, pennello e motivo
      utilizzati prima di uscire dalla precedente sessione, controllate la
      voce "All'uscita salva lo stato dei dispositivi di ingresso" in
      Preferenze/Dispositivi di ingresso.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      매 시작때마다 김프는 도구, 색상, 붓, 무늬 등을 기본값으로 
      설정합니다. 그러므로 마지막에 사용했던 값들을 그대로 유지시키고 
      싶다면, "기본 설정 - 입력 장치" 에서 "마칠 때 입력 장치 설정 저장" 에
      체크해야 합니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Iedere keer wanneer u <acronym>GIMP</acronym> opstart, staat
      hetzelfde gereedschap (het penseel), kleur, penseel en patroon
      ge-activeerd. Als u wilt dat <acronym>GIMP</acronym> met het werktuig
      en de instellingen van de laatste keer dat u het programma afgesloten
      heeft opstart moet u <guilabel>"<accel>A</accel>pparaatinstellingen
      opslaan bij verlaten ..."</guilabel> in het
      <guimenu>Voorkeuren</guimenu>/<guisubmenu>Invoerapparaten</guisubmenu>-menu
      aanvinken.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> startar alltid opp med dei same verktøya aktive.
      Dersom du heller vil starte opp med dei verktøya du brukte sist økt,
      kan du gå inn i menyen <link
      linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">innstillingar</link> i hovudmenyens
      <guimenu>Innstillingar</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Inndataeiningar</guisubmenu>
      <guisubmenu>Lagra innstillingar for inndataeiningar ved
        avslutning</guisubmenu>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      При каждом запуске GIMP выбирает инструмент (кисть), цвет, кисть и
      текстуру по умолчанию, всегда те же самые. Чтобы GIMP выбирал последний
      активный инструмент, цвет, кисть и текстуру с предыдущей сессии,
      необходимо выбрать параметр <quote>Сохранить настройки устройства ввода
      на выходе</quote> в <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">диалоге
      настроек</link>.
    </para>
  </note>

</sect2>
