<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- Version History:
  
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-concepts-toolbox">
  <title>The Toolbox</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>Screenshot of the Toolbox</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/toolbox-description.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Toolbox is the heart of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. 
    Here is a quick tour of what you will find there.
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      In the Toolbox, as in most parts of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, moving the
      mouse over something and letting it rest for a moment, usually displays
      a <quote>tooltip</quote> that describes the thing. Short cut keys are
      also frequently shown in the tooltip. In many cases, you can hover the
      mouse over an item and press the <keycap>F1</keycap> key to get help
      about the thing that is underneath the mouse.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
    By default, only the Foreground/Background Colors area is visible. You
    can add the Brush/Pattern/Gradient area and Active Image area through
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Toolbox</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>:
    <xref linkend="prefs-tools-config"/>.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis>The GIMP logo:</emphasis> At the top of the toolbox, you can
        click-drag-and-drop images from a file browser into this area or into
        the tool icons to open the images. You can hide this logo by unchecking 
        the <guilabel>Show GIMP logo</guilabel> option in the
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Toolbox Preferences</link>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Tool icons:</emphasis> These icons are buttons which
        activate tools for a wide variety of purposes: selecting parts of
        images, painting an image, transforming an image, etc.
        <xref linkend="gimp-toolbox"/> gives an overview of how to work with
        tools, and each tool is described systematically in the
        <link linkend="gimp-tools">Tools</link> chapter.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Foreground/Background colors:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        The color area shows <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s current foreground
        and background colors, which are used for painting, filling, and
        many other operations.
        Clicking on either one of them brings up a color selector dialog
        that allows you to change to a different color.
      </para>
      <para>
        Clicking on the small symbol in the lower left corner resets the
        foreground and background colors to black and white. Pressing the
        <keycap>D</keycap> key has the same effect.
      </para>
      <para>
        Clicking on the double-headed arrow symbol swaps the foreground and
        background colors. Pressing the <keycap>X</keycap> key has the same
        effect.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Brush/Pattern/Gradient:</emphasis>
        The symbols here show you <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
        current selections for: the Paintbrush, used by all tools that allow
        you to paint on the image (<quote>painting</quote> includes
        operations like erasing and smudging, by the way); for the Pattern,
        which is used in filling selected areas of an image; and for the
        Gradient, which comes into play whenever an operation requires a
        smoothly varying range of colors. Clicking on any of these symbols
        brings up a dialog window that allows you to change it.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Active Image:</emphasis> In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you
        can work with many images at once, but at any given moment, only one
        image is the <quote>active image</quote>. Here you find a small
        iconic representation of the active image. Click the icon to display
        a dialog with a list of the currently open images, click an
        image in the dialog to make it active. Usually, you click an
        image window in multi-window mode, or an image tab in single-window
        mode, to make it the active image.
      </para>
      <para>
        <!-- TODO: Remove when Xorg has become irrelevant in favor of Wayland:
        https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/wayland/wayland-protocols/-/issues/89 -->
        <indexterm>
          <primary>XDS</primary>
        </indexterm>
        If you use <acronym>GIMP</acronym> on a Unix-like operating system with
        the X Window System, you can also drag and drop the thumbnail to an
        enabled <link linkend="bibliography-online-xds">XDS file manager</link>
        to directly save the corresponding image.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <note>
    <para>
      At every start, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> selects the brush, color, pattern 
      you used when quitting your previous session because the <guilabel>Save 
      input device settings on exit</guilabel> in
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-input-devices">Preferences/Input Devices</link>,
      is checked by default. If you uncheck it, GIMP will use a color, a
      brush and a pattern by default, always the same. 
    </para>
  </note>
</sect2>
