<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-concepts-undo' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Undoing</title>
  <title lang="cs">Vracení změn</title>
  <title lang="fr">Annuler</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">撤消</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="cs">Obrázky</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Image</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">图像</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Undo</secondary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Vracení změn</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Annuler</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">撤消</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang='en'>
    Almost anything you do to an image in GIMP can be undone.  You can
    undo the most recent action by choosing
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Undo</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    from the image menu, but this is done so frequently that you
    really should memorize the keyboard shortcut,
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Z</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Téměř vše, co s obrázkem v Gimpu provedete, lze vrátit zpět.
    Poslední akci vrátíte zpět volbou
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Upravit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Zpět</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    z nabídky obrázku. Budete to ale pravděpodobně dělat tak často, že se
    vyplatí zapamatovat si klávesovou zkratku
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Z</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Presque tout ce que vous pouvez faire sur une image dans Gimp peut 
    être annulé. Vous pouvez annuler la dernière opération en choisissant 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Éditer</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Annuler</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    dans le menu image, mais vous aurez à le faire si souvent qu'il vous 
    faut mémoriser le raccourci clavier 
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Z</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    几乎可以撤消在 GIMP 中对一个图像所做的任何操作。要撤消最近的操作，选择图像菜单中的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>编辑</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>撤消</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> 
    不过由于经常使用它，有必要记住其快捷键，
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Z</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    Undoing can itself be undone.  After having undone an action, you
    can <emphasis>redo</emphasis> it by choosing
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Redo</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    from the image menu, or use the keyboard shortcut,
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Y</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    It is often helpful to judge the effect of an action by repeatedly
    undoing and redoing it.  This is usually very quick, and does not
    consume any extra resources or alter the undo history, so there is
    never any harm in it.
  </para>
  <para lang='cs'>
    Vrátit zpět lze i vracení, Pokud jste nějakou akci vrátili zpět, můžete
    ji provést <emphasis>znovu</emphasis> volbou
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Upravit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Znovu</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    z nabídky obrázku nebo použít klávesovou zkratku
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Y</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    Občas je výhodné posoudit vliv nějaké akce jejím opakovaným vracením a
    znovuprováděním. Je to obvykle velmi rychlé a nespotřebovává zvláštní
    zdroje ani paměť historie změn, takže se není čeho obávat.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Annuler peut lui-même être annulé. Après avoir annulé une action, vous 
    pouvez en effet la <emphasis>Refaire</emphasis> en choisissant
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Éditer</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Refaire</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    dans le menu image, ou en utilisant le raccourci
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Y</keycap>
    </keycombo>.
    Il est souvent utile de juger de l'effet d'une action en l'annulant et 
    en la refaisant plusieurs fois. C'est habituellement très vite fait et 
    cela ne consomme pas de mémoire ni ne modifie l'historique. Vous 
    pouvez donc l'utiliser sans danger.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    撤消本身也能被撤消。在撤消一个动作后，您也能<emphasis>重做</emphasis>它，选择在图像菜单中的
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>编辑</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>重做</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    ，或使用快捷键,
    <keycombo>
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      <keycap>Y</keycap>
    </keycombo>。
    通过反复地撤消和重做一个动作，对判断其效果常常是非常有用的。这通常是非常快捷，不会耗费任何多余资源，而且也不会更改撤消历史，因此这样做没有任何坏处。
    </para>

  <caution lang='en'>
    <para>
    If you undo one or more actions and then operate on the image in
    any way except by using Undo or Redo, it will no longer be possible
    to redo those actions:  they are lost forever.  The solution to
    this, if it creates a problem for you, is to duplicate the image
    and then operate on the copy.  (<emphasis>Not</emphasis> the
    original, because the undo/redo history is not copied when you
    duplicate an image.)
    </para>
  </caution>
  <caution lang='cs'>
    <para>
    Pokud vrátíte zpět jednu nebo více operací a a pak s obrázkem provedete
    další operaci s výjimkou Zpět/Znovu, jsou operace nenávratně ztraceny;
    již je nebude možné obnovit pomocí funkce Znovu. Řešením může být
    duplikování obrázku a práce s jeho kopií. (<emphasis>Nikoliv</emphasis>
    originálem, protože historie změn se při duplikování obrázku
    nekopíruje.)
    </para>
  </caution>
  <caution lang='fr'>
    <para>
    Si vous avez annulé une ou plusieurs actions et qu'ensuite vous 
    faites autre chose qu'Annuler ou Refaire, il ne sera plus possible 
    de Refaire vos actions annulées: elles sont à jamais perdues. La 
    solution, si cela vous pose problème, est de dupliquer l'image et 
    de travailler sur la copie. <emphasis>Pas</emphasis> sur 
    l'original, car l'historique Annuler/Refaire n'est pas copié quand 
    vous dupliquez l'image.
    </para>
  </caution>
  <caution lang="zh_CN">
    <para> 
    当您撤消一个或多个命令后，又对图像进行了除撤消或重做以外的操作，那么您就不可能再重做这些操作了：它们永远地丢失了。如果您觉得这样不妥，解决方法就是先复制图像，然后在其拷贝上进行操作。(<emphasis>不是</emphasis>原图像，因为在复制图像时，重做/撤消历史不会被拷贝。)
    </para>
  </caution>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Pokud často vracíte a či obnovujete mnoho změn najednou, bude se vám lépe
    pracovat s dialogem <link linkend='gimp-undo-dialog'>Historie změn</link>.
    Jedná se o dokovatelný dialog zobrazující náhled všech změn v historii a
    umožňující mezi jednotlivými body histrorie přecházet jednoduchým
    klikáním.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    If you often find yourself undoing and redoing many steps at a
    time, it may be more convenient to work with the <link
    linkend='gimp-undo-dialog'>Undo History dialog</link>, a
    dockable dialog that shows you a small sketch of each point in the
    Undo History, allowing you to go back or forward to that point by
    clicking. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Si vous devez revenir plusieurs pas en arrière dans vos 
    annulations, au lieu de répéter Ctrl-Z utilisez plutôt l'
    <link linkend='gimp-undo-dialog'>Historique d'Annulation</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    假如您每次常常重做或撤消很多步，这时也许使用<link linkend='gimp-undo-dialog'>撤消历史对话框</link>更加方便。它是一个显示撤消历史中各点的概要的可停靠对话框，允许您通过点击来后退或前进到某点。
  </para>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Historie změn je součástí obrázku, proto je udržována pro každý obrázek
    zvlášť. Gimp každému obrázku pro tento účel vyhradí určité množství
    paměti. Na stránce Předvoleb <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Prostředí</link> můžete toto množství
    paměti nastavit. Existují dvě důležité volby: <emphasis>minimální počet
    kroků zpět</emphasis>, které Gimp dodrží bez ohledu na množství paměti,
    a <emphasis>maximální paměť vracení</emphasis>, po jejímž naplnění začne
    Gimp zapomínat nejstarší bodu z historie.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Undo is performed on an image-specific basis:  the "Undo History"
    is one of the components of an image.  GIMP allocates a certain
    amount of memory to each image for this purpose.  You can
    customize your Preferences to increase or decrease the amount,
    using the <link
    linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Environment</link> page of the
    Preferences dialog.  There are two important variables:  the
    <emphasis>minimal number of undo levels</emphasis>, which GIMP
    will maintain regardless of how much memory they consume, and the
    <emphasis>maximum undo memory</emphasis>, beyond which GIMP will
    begin to delete the oldest items from the Undo History.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'Historique d'annulation est spécifique de chaque image. Gimp 
    alloue une certaine quantité de mémoire à chaque image dans ce 
    but. Vous pouvez personnaliser vos Préférences pour changer ce 
    montant en utilisant la page <link 
    linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Environnement</link> du 
    dialogue Préférences. Il y a là deux variables importantes: le 
    <emphasis>Nombre de niveaux d'annulations</emphasis>, que Gimp 
    assurera quelle que soit la quantité de mémoire consommée et la 
    <emphasis>Mémoire maxima d'annulation</emphasis>, marquant la 
    limite au-delà de laquelle Gimp commencera à supprimer les 
    éléments les plus anciens de l'historique.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    撤消是基于特定的一个图像操作的：“撤消历史”是一个图像的组成部分。GIMP 要给每个图像分配一定的内存来达到该目的。您能够定制您的首选项来增加或减少其数量，在首选项对话框中的<link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>环境</link>页有两个重要的参数：<emphasis>最小撤消次数</emphasis>--不管耗费多少内存都要保证，和<emphasis>最大撤消内存</emphasis>--超过这个值，GIMP 会从撤消历史中删除旧的记录。
  </para>

  <note lang='en'>
    <para>
      Even though the Undo History is a component of an image, it is not
      saved when you save the image using GIMP's native XCF format,
      which preserves every other image property.  When the image is
      reopened, it will have an empty Undo History.
    </para>
  </note>
  <note lang='cs'>
    <para>
      Přestože je historie změn součástí obrázku, není s ním ukládána ani do
      nativního XCF formátu, který zachovává všechny ostatní vlastnosti
      obrázku. Znovuotevřený orbázek má historii prázdnou.
    </para>
  </note>
  <note lang="fr">
    <para>
    Même si l'Historique d'annulation est un composant de l'image, il 
    n'est pas sauvegardé quand vous enregistrez une image au format 
    XCF, qui pourtant préserve toutes les autres propriétés de 
    l'image. Quand l'image est réouverte, l'historique d'annulation 
    est vide.
    </para>
  </note>

  <note lang="zh_CN">
    <para>
      虽然撤消历史是一个图像的组成部分，但是在用 GIMP 的内建 XCF 格式保存图像时不会保存该信息，而其它的图像属性都将保留。当图像被重新打开时，它的撤消历史为空。
    </para>
  </note>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Implementace historie změn je v Gimpu poměrně složitá. Mnoho operací
    vyžaduje velmi málo paměti v historii změn (např. změna viditelnosti
    vrstvy), takže jich můžete provádět velmi mnoho, než je začne Gimp
    zapomínat. Některé operace (příkladem je opět změna viditelnosti vrstvy)
    se <emphasis>komprimují</emphasis>, takže pokud je učiníte několikrát
    přímo za sebou, budou reprezentovány pouze jedním bodem v historii změn.
    Některé jiné operace však mohou zpotřebovat velké množství paměti v
    historii změn. Příkladem je většina filtrů: prtože jsou implementovány
    jako zásuvné moduly, nemá Gimp možnost zjistit, co skutečně s obrázkem
    udělaly. Proto se v historii změn ukládá celý obsah vrstvy před i po
    použití filtru. Takových operací lze proto v historri změn uložit jen
    relativně málo.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    The implementation of Undo by GIMP is rather sophisticated.  Many
    operations require very little Undo memory (e.g., changing
    visibility of a layer), so you can perform long sequences of them
    before they drop out of the Undo History.  Some operations
    (changing layer visibility is again an example) are
    <emphasis>compressed</emphasis>, so that doing them several times
    in a row produces only a single point in the Undo History.
    However, there are other operations that may consume a lot of undo
    memory.  Most filters are examples of this:  because they are
    implemented by plug-ins, the GIMP core has no really efficient way
    of knowing what they have changed, so it has no way to implement
    Undo except by memorizing the entire contents of the affected
    layer before and after the operation.  You might only be able to
    perform a few such operations before they drop out of the Undo
    History. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    La mise en œuvre d'Annuler par Gimp est assez perfectionnée. 
    Beaucoup d'opérations ne requièrent que peu de mémoire (p.e 
    changer la visibilité d'un calque). Certaines sont comprimées, si 
    bien qu'en les répétant plusieurs fois de suite, leur 
    représentation dans le dialogue de l'historique peut se réduire à 
    un point. Mais d'autres opérations peuvent consommer beaucoup de 
    mémoire. C'est le cas des greffons: étant externes, le cœur de 
    Gimp ne peut pas savoir ce qui a changé en eux et doit mémoriser 
    l'ensemble du calque affecté avant et après l'opération. 
    Avec eux vous ne pourrez effectuer qu'un nombre réduits 
    d'annulations avant qu'elles ne soient rejetées de l'Historique 
    d'annulation.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 撤消的实现是相当复杂的。只需要很多的撤消内存来保留需要操作(比如改变一个图层的可见性)，因此在记录被从撤消历史中删除之前，可以保持一个很长的操作序列。许多操作(再次以改变图层可见性为例)被<emphasis>压缩</emphasis>了，所以连续多次地执行它们只在撤消历史中产生单独的一个点。尽管如此，还是有其它的操作可能耗费大量的撤消内存。比如说大部分的滤镜：它们由插件实现，GIMP 核心没有知道它们改变了什么的真正有效方法，因此它就不得不记住操作前后被影响图层的全部内容。您可能在记录被从撤消历史中删除之前只能执行很少的这种操作。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='cs'>Nevratné operace</title>
    <title lang='en'>Things that cannot be Undone</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Ce qui ne peut pas être annulé</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">不能被撤消的东西</title>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Většina operací měnících obrázek lze vrátit zpět. Operace, které
      obrázek nemění, ale většinou vrátit nejdou. Patří mezi ně uložení
      obrázku do souboru, duplikování obrázku, zkopiírování jeho části do
      schránky atd. Patří mezi ně také většina operací, které mění zobrazení
      obrázku,a le nikoliv obrazová data. Nejdůležitějším příkladem je
      přibližování (zoom). Existují ovšem i výjimky: lze vrátit přepínání
      rychlé masky, i když to nijak neovlivňuje obrazová data.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      Most actions that alter an image can be undone.  Actions that do
      not alter the image generally cannot be.  This includes
      operations such as saving the image to a file, duplicating the
      image, copying part of the image to the clipboard, etc.  It also
      includes most actions that affect the image display without
      altering the underlying image data.  The most important example
      is zooming.  There are, however, exceptions:  toggling QuickMask
      on or off can be undone, even though it does not alter the image
      data. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Toutes les actions qui modifient une image peuvent être Annulées. 
      Celles qui ne la modifient pas ne le peuvent pas. Cela concerne 
      les des opérations telles que enregistrer, dupliquer une image, 
      copier une partie de l'image dans le presse-papier...etc. Cela 
      concerne aussi la plupart des actions qui affectent l'affichage 
      sans modifier l'image elle-même. L'exemple le plus important en 
      est le zoom. Mais il y a des exceptions: la bascule du Masque 
      Rapide peut être Annulée, bien qu'elle ne modifie pas l'image.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      大部分修改一个图像的动作能被撤消，而那些没有修改图像的动作一般就不能。这些操作包括保存图像到一个文件，复制图像和拷贝图像部分等。它还包括大部分影响图像显示但没有修改其图像数据的动作。最重要的例子就是图像比例的缩放。不过也要例外：虽然切换快速蒙板开启或关闭没有修改图像数据，但它能被撤消。
    </para>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Existuje několik důležitých operací, které mění obrazová data,
      ale přesto je nelze vrátit zpět:
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      There are a few important actions that do alter an image but
      cannot be undone:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Inversement, il y a des opérations qui modifient l'image et qui 
      pourtant ne peuvent pas être Annulées:
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      下面是一些最重要的动作，它们修改一个图像但不能被撤消：
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Zavření obrázku</term>
        <term lang='en'>Closing the image</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Fermeture d'une image</term>
        <term lang='zh_CN'>关闭图像</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='cs'>
            Historie změn je součástí obrázku, proto, pokud je obrázek uzavřen
            a jím používané zdroje uvolněny, historie změn se ztratí. Proto se,
            pokud nebyl obrázek od poslední změny uložen, Gimp zeptá, zda
            zavření obrázku myslíte skutečně vážně. (Toto chování lze změnit
            na stánce <link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Prostředí</link>
            dialogu Předvolby; pokud tak učiníte, berete na sebe zodpovědnost
            za případné nechtěné zavření neuloženého obrázku.)
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            The Undo History is a component of the image, so when the
            image is closed and all of its resources are freed, the Undo
            History goes along.  Because of this, unless the image has not
            been modified since the last time it was saved, GIMP always
            asks you to confirm that you really want to close it.  (You
            can disable this in the <link
            linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Environment</link> page of
            the Preferences dialog; if you do, you are assuming
            responsibility for thinking about what you are doing.)
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            L'historique d'annulation est un composant d'une image,
            ainsi quand l'image est fermée l'historique d'annulation
            est également clos. Gimp demande une confirmation
            si vous fermez une image qui contient des modifications
            non enregistrées. Il est possible de supprimer cette
            confirmation au chapitre 
            <link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>Environnement</link>
            des Préférences (mais c'est de votre responsabilité de
            savoir ce que vous faites).
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            撤消历史是图像的组成部分，因此当图像被关闭时，其所有资源都被释放，撤消历史也一样。正因为这样，GIMP 总是要您确认是否真想关闭图像，除非在最近一次保存图像后没有被修改。(您能够通过首选项对话框的<link linkend='gimp-prefs-environment'>环境</link>页来关闭该提示；您要这样做时请先想清楚。)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Navrácení obrázku</term>
        <term lang='en'>Reverting the image</term>
        <term lang='fr'>Revenir à l'image</term>
        <term lang='zh_CN'>恢复图像</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='cs'>
            <emphasis>Navrácení</emphasis> znamená obnovení obrázku starší
            uloženou verzí ze souboru. Gimp tak ve skutečnosti činmí zavřením
            stávajícího obrázku a jeho novým otevřením, proto je historie změn
            ztracena. Proto, pokud jsou v obrázku neuložené změny, požádá Gimp
            o potvrzení.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            "Reverting" means reloading the image from file.  GIMP
            actually implements this by closing the image and creating a
            new image, so the Undo History is lost as a consequence.
            Because of this, if the image is unclean, GIMP always asks you
            to confirm that you really want to revert the image.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            Cela veut dire recharger l'image depuis le fichier. Gimp 
            réalise cela en fermant l'image et en créant une nouvelle 
            image. L'Historique d'Annulation est donc perdu. C'est 
            pourquoi Gimp vous demande toujours de confirmer si vous 
            tenez vraiment à revenir à l'image.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            “恢复”表示从文件重新读取图像。GIMP 实际上是通过关闭图像并打开一个新图像来实现的，因此其撤消历史将丢失。所以，当图像“不干净”时，GIMP 总是要您确认是否真想恢复图像。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='cs'>Části operací</term>
        <term lang='en'>"Pieces" of actions</term>
        <term lang='fr'>"Parties" d'actions</term>
        <term lang='zh_CN'>动作的“片段”</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='cs'>
            Některé nástroje vyžadují pro své použití celou komplexní řadu
            akcí, ale umožňují vrátit jen celou tuto řadu jako celek, nikoliv
            její jednotlivé části. Například inteligentní nůžky vyžadují
            vytvoření uzavřené křivky klikáním na více bodů v obrázku a
            následné kliknutí do vymezené oblasti pro vytvoření výběru. Nelze
            však vracet jednotlivá kliknutí, příkaz Zpět vás vrátí na začátek,
            před použití nůžek. Jiným příkladem je textový nástroj, který
            neumožňuje vracet jednotlivá písmeny či změny formátování. Příkaz
            Zpět v vás opět vrátí na začátek, před použití textového nástroje.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            Some tools require you to perform a complex series of
            manipulations before they take effect, but only allow you to
            undo the whole thing rather than the individual elements.
            For example, the Intelligent Scissors require you to create
            a closed path by clicking at multiple points in the image,
            and then clicking inside the path to create a selection.
            You cannot undo the individual clicks:  undoing after you
            are finished takes you all the way back to the starting
            point.  For another example, when you are working with the
            Text tool, you cannot undo individual letters, font changes,
            etc.:  undoing after you are finished removes the newly
            created text layer.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            Certains outils vous obligent à réaliser une série complexe 
            de manipulations avant de prendre effet, mais ne vous 
            autorisent à annuler que l'ensemble de l'action et non ses 
            éléments individuels. 
            Par exemple, les Ciseaux Intelligents vous demandent de 
            créer un chemin fermé en cliquant en plusieurs points de 
            l'image. Vous ne pouvez pas annuler les clics individuels, 
            mais seulement l'ensemble de la sélection une fois réalisée. 
            Un autre exemple concerne l'outil Texte: vous ne pouvez pas 
            annuler les lettres individuelles, les changements de 
            police...etc, mais seulement le calque de Texte une fois 
            créé. 
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            一些工具在它们起作用之前要求您做一系列复杂的处理，不过只能撤消全部而不是单个步凑。比如，智能剪刀要求您通过点击图像中的多个点产生一个闭合的路径，然后再通过在路径内部点击创建一个选区。您无法撤消单独的点击：在您完成后撤消将使全部回到起始点。再比如，当使用文字工具时，您无法撤消单独的文字，改变字体等：完成后撤消会删除新建的文字图像。
          </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Filtry a další operace prováděné skripty či zásuvnými moduly lze vracet
      stejně jako operace prováděné jádrem Gimpu, ale pouze v případě, že jsou
      správně napsány a správně používají funkce Gimpu pro historii změn.
      Pokud nejsou napsány správně, mohou poškodit historii změn tak, že nelze
      vrátit ani operaci provedenou filtrem, ani operace předchozí. Zásuvné
      moduly i skripty dodávané přímo s Gimpem pracují spolehlivě, nicméně to
      samozřejmě nelze zaručit u zásuvvných modulů a skriptů z jiných zdrojů.
      I v případě, že je zásuvný modul napsán správně, může jeho zrušení během
      práce znamenat poškození historie změn. Proto je lépe běžící zásuvné
      moduly nepřerušovat, není-li to skutečně nezbytné.
    </para>
    <para lang='en'>
      Filters, and other actions performed by plugins or scripts, can
      be undone just like actions implemented by the GIMP core, but
      this requires them to make correct use of GIMP's Undo
      functions.  If the code is not correct, a plugin can potentially
      corrupt the Undo History, so that not only the plugin but also
      previous actions can no longer properly be undone.  The plugins
      and scripts distributed with GIMP are all believed to be set up
      correctly, but obviously no guarantees can be given for plugins
      you obtain from other sources.  Also, even if the code is
      correct, canceling a plugin while it is running can sometimes
      leave the Undo History corrupted, so it is best to avoid this
      unless you have accidentally done something whose consequences
      are going to be very harmful.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les actions réalisées à l'aide de filtres, de greffons ou de 
      scripts peuvent être annulées comme celles du cœur de Gimp, à 
      condition que leur code soit correct, et qu'ils sachent utiliser 
      les fonctions d'annulation de Gimp. C'est généralement le cas 
      pour les greffons et les scripts fournis avec Gimp, mais aucune 
      garantie ne peut être assurée pour ceux d'autre origine. Le 
      risque est alors une altération de l'Historique d'annulation. 
      C'est également le cas si vous interrompez un greffon en cours.  
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      滤镜，和其它由插件或脚本执行的操作能像通过 GIMP 核心实现的动作一样地被撤消，不过这需要它们正确使用 GIMP 的撤消函数。如果代码不正确，一个插件有潜在破坏撤消历史的可能，到时不光是该插件而且以前的动作都不能被正确地撤消。所有由 GIMP 贡献的插件和脚本都可以认为是被正确设置的，而从其它地方得到的插件就显然没有保证。同时，即使代码正确，在运行一个插件时取消掉它有时也会破坏撤消历史，所以除非是不小心所做的其结果将非常严重，最好避免这样做。
    </para> 
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
