<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-10-17 ude: moved here from menus/plug-in-c-astretch.xml ('en','de')
  2007-06-09 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-02-22 KoSt: added no
  2006-09-05 Example added by j.h; text revised by scb
  2005-11-11 split of from layer-colors.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-c-astretch" lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-17</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-17</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-21</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-11-17</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="xx">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-MM-DD</date>
        <authorinitials>N.N.</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Stretch Contrast</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Kontrastspreizung</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Reducir el contraste</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Étendre le contraste</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Ampliamento contrasto</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Strekk kontrast</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">拉伸对比度</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Colors</primary>
    <secondary>Stretch contrast</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Stretch Contrast</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Contrast</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Farben</primary>
    <secondary>Kontrastspreizung</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Kontrastspreizung</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <!--TODO es: update indexterm-->
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Gestión de los colores</secondary>
    <tertiary>Reducir el contraste</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Reducir el contraste</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Contraste</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Couleurs</primary>
    <secondary>Étendre le contraste</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Étendre le contraste</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Contraste</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Colori</primary>
    <secondary>Ampliamento contrasto</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Ampliamento contrasto</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Contrasto</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Fargar</primary>
    <secondary>Strekk kontrast</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Strekk kontrast</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Stretch Contrast</guimenuitem> command automatically
    stretches the histogram values in the active layer. For each channel
    of the active layer, it finds the minimum and maximum values and uses
    them to stretch the Red, Green and Blue histograms to the full contrast
    range. The bright colors become brighter and the dark colors become
    darker, which increases the contrast.
    This command produces a somewhat similar effect to the
    <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalize</link> command, except that
    it works on each color channel of the layer individually. This usually
    leads to color shifts in the image, so it may not produce the desired
    result. <quote>Stretch Contrast</quote> works on layers of RGB,
    Grayscale and Indexed images. Use <quote>Stretch Contrast</quote> only
    if you want to remove an undesirable color tint from an image which
    should contain pure white and pure black.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    This command is also similar to the
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Color Balance</link>
    command, but it does not reject any of the very dark or very bright
    pixels, so the white might be impure.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando werden die einzelnen Farben Rot, Grün und Blau so
    weit wie möglich zwischen dem kleinstmöglichen und dem größtmöglichen
    Wert gestreckt. Dadurch werden helle Farben heller und dunkle Farben
    dunkler, was den Kontrast erhöht. Damit können Sie einen ähnlichen
    Effekt erzielen wie mit dem <link
    linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalisieren</link>, mit dem Unterschied,
    dass die <quote>Automatische Kontrastspreizung</quote> auf jeden Kanal
    der Ebene wirkt und nicht nur auf die Helligkeitswerte.  Daraus
    resultieren gelegentlich leichte Farbverschiebungen, welche zu einem
    unerwünschten Ergebnis führen können.  Im Unterschied zum <link
    linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Weißabgleich</link> werden die extrem
    hellen oder dunklen Punkte nicht von der Berechnung ausgenommen, so dass
    das Weiß unter Umständen nicht völlig rein ist.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Sie sollten dieses Kommando nur verwenden, wenn Sie einen unerwünschten
    Farbton in einem Bild haben, das nur Schwarz und Weiß enthalten sollte.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    El comando <guimenuitem>Reducir el contraste</guimenuitem> reduce,
    automaticamente, el valor del histograma de la capa activa. Para cada
    canal de la capa activa, encuentra los valores mínimo y máximo y los usa
    para reducir los histogramas rojo, verde y azul a un rango lleno de
    contraste. Los colores claros se vuelven más claros y los oscuros más
    oscuros, lo que incrementa el contraste. Este comando produce un efecto
    similar al comando <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normalizar</link>,
    excepto que trabaja sobre cada canal  de color de la capa de manera
    individualmente. A veces, esto produce cambios de color en la imagen, así
    que puede producir resultados no deseados.
    <quote>Reducir el contraste</quote> funciona sobre capas de imágenes RGB,
    en escala de grises e indexadas. Use <quote>Reducir el contraste</quote>
    solo si quiere suprimir un tinte de color no deseado de la imagen, la
    cual debería contener blanco y negro puro.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Este comando es, tembién, similar al comando 
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Balance de blanco</link>,
    pero no deshecha píxeles muy claros o muy oscuros, con lo que el blanco
    podría no ser puro.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Ce greffon réalise un étalement automatique du contraste dans
    l'histogramme du calque actif. Pour chaque canal de l'image, il trouve
    les valeurs minimum et maximum. Il utilise ces valeurs pour étaler les
    histogrammes individuels sur l'étendue de l'intervalle de contraste. Les
    couleurs claires deviennent donc plus claires et les couleurs sombres
    plus sombres, d'où augmentation du contraste.
    L'action de cette commande ressemble à celle du greffon
    <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normaliser</link>, mais elle
    agit sur chaque canal de couleur de façon séparée si bien que des
    aberrations de couleurs peuvent survenir et que le résultat recherché
    n'est pas obtenu. Elle agit sur les trois types d'image : RVB, Indexée,
    Niveaux de gris. N'utilisez cette commande que si vous souhaitez
    supprimer une teinte indésirable sur ce qui devrait être un blanc pur ou
    un noir pur.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande ressemble beaucoup à la nouvelle commande
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Balance des Couleurs</link>. Mais
    contrairement à cette dernière, les quelques pixels très noirs ou très
    clairs ne sont pas éliminés, si bien que le blanc créé n'est pas aussi
    pur.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>ampliamento contrasto</guimenuitem> allarga
    automaticamente i valori di istogramma nel livello attivo. Per ogni
    canale del livello attivo, esso trova i valori massimo e minimo e li
    usa per allargare gli istogrammi di rosso, verde e blu al campo di
    contrasto massimo. I colori più chiari diventano più chiari ancora e
    quelli più scuri diventano ancora più scuri, in poche parole, aumenta
    il contrasto. Questo comando produce un effetto simile in qualche modo
    al comando <link linkend="plug-in-normalize">normalizzazione</link>,
    eccetto che esso lavora su ogni canale di colore di ogni livello in
    maniera individuale. Ciò porta spesso a spostamenti di colore
    nell'immagine, che potrebbero non portare all'effetto
    desiderato. <quote>Ampliamento contrasto</quote> lavora su livelli
    di immagini RGB, in scala di grigi e indicizzate. Usare
    l'<quote>ampliamento contrasto</quote> solo se si desidera rimuovere
    una tinta di colore non desiderata da un'immagine che dovrebbe
    contenere solo valori puri di bianco e nero.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Questo comando somiglia anche al comando <link
    linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">bilanciamento del bianco</link>,
    ma esso non rigetta nessun pixel troppo scuro o troppo chiaro, per
    cui il bianco potrebbe non essere perfetto.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Strekk kontrast</guimenuitem> strekker
    automatisk histogramverdiane for det aktive laget. Kommandoen finn
    maksimums- og minimumsverdiane for kvar kanal og bruker desse for å
    strekke histogramma for raud, grøn og blå til fullt kontrastområde.
    Lyse fargar blir lysare og mørke fargar mørkare. Dermed aukar
    kontrasten. Kommandoen liknar på kommandoen <link
    linkend="plug-in-normalize">Normaliser</link>, men verkar individuelt
    på kvar fargekanal. Svært ofte blir det tilført eit fargeskifte i
    biletet. <quote>Strekk kontrast</quote> arbeider på biletlag i alle
    fargemodus, altså både RGB, gråskala og indeksert. Kommandoen blir
    helst brukt for å fjerne fargestikk i bilete som eigentleg skulle
    innehalde rein kvit eller rein svart.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen er også nokså lik kommandoen
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-white-balance">Kvitbalanse</link>, men
    fjernar ikkje noen av dei svært mørke eller svært lyse pikslane.
    Dermed kan du risikera ein urein kvitfarge.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This command can be accessed from an image menubar as 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>olors</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>tretch Contrast</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>arben</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>utomatisch</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>K</accel>ontrastspreizung</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <!--TODO es: check menuentries-->
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>olores</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Reducir el contra<accel>s</accel>te</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image 
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Coule<accel>u</accel>rs</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Étendre le <accel>c</accel>ontraste</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Questo comando è disponibile dalla barra del menu immagine
          tramite 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>olori</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Ampliamento
            contra<accel>s</accel>to</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fargar</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Strekk kontrast</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en"><quote>Stretch Contrast</quote> Example</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Ein Beispiel für die automatische Kontrastspreizung
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo de <quote>Reducir el contraste</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        Exemple de <quote>Étendre le Contraste</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Esempio di <quote>ampliamento
      contrasto</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Strekk kontrast</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Original image</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Originalbild</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Original</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Image d'origine</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Immagine originale</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Originalbiletet</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alice.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The layer and its Red, Green and Blue histograms before
            <quote>Stretch Contrast</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die aktive Ebene und die zugehörigen Histogramme für den roten,
            blauen und grünen Kanal.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            La capa activa y su histograma de color rojo, verde y azul, antes
            de <quote>Reducir el contraste</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert, Bleu avant traitement.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il livello e i suoi istogrammi di rosso, verde e blu, prima del
            comando <quote>ampliamento contrasto</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå før
            bruk av <quote>Strekk kontrast</quote>.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Image after the command</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Bild nach Konstrastspreizung</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Imagen después del comando</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Image Traitée</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Immagine dopo il comando</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Biletet etter bruk av filteret</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/c-stretch.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The layer and its Red and Green and Blue histograms after
            <quote>Stretch Contrast</quote>.
            The pixel columns do not reach the right end of the histogram
            (255) because of a few very bright pixels, unlike
            <quote>White Balance</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Histogram stretching creates gaps between the pixel columns,
            giving it a striped look.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Die Histogramme des roten, blauen und grünen Kanals nach Anwendung
            der Konstrastspreizung.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            La capa activa y su histograma de color rojo, verde y azul,
            después de <quote>Reducir el contraste</quote>. La columnas del
            píxel no alcanzan el final derecho del histograma (255) por unos
            pocos píxeles muy claros, al contrario que 
            <quote>Balance de blanco</quote>. 
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Estirar el histograma crea vacios entre las columnas de los
            píxeles dando una vista rayada.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert, Bleu après traitement.
            Les colonnes de pixels n'atteignent pas l'extrémité droite de
            l'histogramme (255), contrairement à Balance des Blancs.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            L'étalement des histogrammes crée des vides entre les colonnes de
            pixels, lui donnant un aspect strié.
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Il livello e i suoi istogrammi di rosso, verde e blu dopo il
            comando <quote>ampliamento contrasto</quote>.  Le colonne di
            pixel non raggiungono l'estrema destra dell'istogramma (255) a
            causa dell'esistenza di pochi pixel molto luminosi,
            diversamente dal comnando <quote>bilanciamento del
            bianco</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            L'ampliamento degli istogrammi crea dei "buchi" tra le colonne
            di pixel che ne danno il caratteristico aspetto a strisce.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå etter
            bruk av <quote>Strekk kontrast</quote>. Til skilnad frå
            <quote>Kvitbalanse</quote> rekk ikkje pikselkolonna heilt ut
            til høgresida av histogrammet (255) på grunn av svært få lyse
            pikslar.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Strekkinga av histogrammet lagar opningar mellom kolonnene. Difor
            stripene.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
