<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-10-17 ude: moved here from menus/plug-in-color-enhance.xml ('en','de')
  2007-06-09 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-02-22 KoSt: added no
  2006-09-05 text rewritten by scb;  example added by j.h
  2005-11-11 split of from layer-colors.xml by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-color-enhance" lang="en;de">
  <sect2info role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-10-17</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-17</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="xx">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-MM-DD</date>
        <authorinitials>N.N.</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Color Enhance</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Farbverbesserung</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Realzar color</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Renforcer les couleurs</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Aumento del colore</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Fargeforbetring</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">颜色增强</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Colors</primary>
    <secondary>Color enhance</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Color Enhance</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Farben</primary>
    <secondary>Farbverbesserung</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbverbesserung</primary></indexterm>

  <!--TODO es fr it no: update indexterm-->
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Gestión de los colores</secondary>
    <tertiary>Realzar color</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Realzar color</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Gérer les couleurs</secondary>
    <tertiary>Renforcer les couleurs</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Renforcer les Couleurs</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Lagmenyen</primary>
    <secondary>Fargeforbetring</secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Color Enhance</guimenuitem> command increases the
    saturation range of the colors in the layer, without altering
    brightness or hue. It does this by converting the colors to HSV space,
    measuring the range of saturation values across the image, then
    stretching this range to be as large as possible, and finally
    converting the colors back to RGB. It is similar to <link
    linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Stretch Contrast</link>, except that it
    works in the HSV color space, so it preserves the hue.  It works on
    layers from RGB and Indexed images. If the image is Grayscale, the menu
    entry is insensitive and grayed out.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Mit diesem Kommando können Sie den Wertebereich der Farbsättigung in der
    aktiven Ebene erhöhen. Dabei werden weder die Farbwerte noch die
    Helligkeit verändert. Dies geschieht, indem die Ebene in das
    HSV-Farbmodell überführt wird und dann das Histogramm des
    Farbsättigungskanals optimiert wird. Hiernach wird die Ebene in das
    RGB-Farbmodell zurückgewandelt. Das Kommando ist ähnlich wie <link
    linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Kontrastspreizung</link>, nur dass es im
    HSV-Farbraum operiert und daher den Farbton bewahrt. Dieses Kommando kann
    auf Graustufenbildern nicht ausgeführt werden (da wäre ja auch nicht
    sonderlich viel an der Farbsättigung anzupassen).
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    El comando <guimenuitem>Realzar color</guimenuitem> incementa el rango de
    la saturación de los colores en la capa, sin alterar la luminosidad o la
    tonalidad. Hace esto convirtiendo los colores al espacio HSV, midiendo el
    rango de los valores de saturación de la imagen, estirando este rango
    tanto como sea posible, y, finalmente, volviendo a convertirlos al RGB.
    Es similar a <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Reducir contraste</link>,
    excepto que funciona en el espacio de color HSV, para preservar la
    tonalidad. Funciona sobre capas en imágenes RGB e indexadas. Si la imagen
    está en escala de grises, la entrada del menú está deshabilitada y en
    gris claro.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Cette commande accroît automatiquement la saturation des plages colorées
    du calque actif sans altérer la teinte ni la luminosité. Agit en
    convertissant les couleurs dans l'espace TSV, mesurant l'intervalle des
    valeurs de saturation sur l'image et étendant cet intervalle aussi
    largement que possible, et finalement re-transformant les couleurs dans
    l'espace RVB. Cette commande fonctionne avec les calques des images RVB et
    les images Indexées, mais pas avec les images en niveaux de gris.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>aumento del colore</guimenuitem> incrementa il
    valore di saturazione dei colori nel livello, senza alterarne la
    luminosità o la tonalità. L'operazione avviene convertendo i colori
    nello spazio HSV, misurando il campo dei valori di saturazione
    nell'immagine, per poi allargarne l'estensione al massimo possibile, ed
    infine convertendo nuovamente i colori nello spazio RGB. È simile a
    <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">ampliamento contrasto</link>, eccetto
    per il fatto che lavora nello spazio di colore HSV in modo da
    preservare il valore di tonalità. È in grado di lavorare su livelli di
    immagini RGB e indicizzate. Se l'immagine è in scala di grigi, la voce
    del menu viene resa con un colore pallido e disabilitata.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Fargeforbetring</guimenuitem> aukar
    metningsområdet for fargane i laget, utan å forandra lysverdi og kulør.
    Dette blir gjort ved å konvertere fargane til HSV-systemet og måle
    området for metningsverdiane i biletet for så å strekke dette området
    så mykje som råd er. Deretter blir biletet konvertert tilbake til RGB
    igjen.  Kommandoen liknar på <link linkend="plug-in-c-astretch">Strekk
    kontrast</link>, men sidan han arbeider i HSV-modus, blir kuløren ikkje
    endra. <quote>Fargeforbetring</quote> verkar på lag i fargemodus RGB og
    indekserte bilete.  Er biletet i gråskala, er kommandoen uverksam.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “颜色增强”增加图层中颜色的饱和度范围，而不改变亮度和色调。它先将图像转变
    为 HSV 空间，衡量图像中的饱和度值范围，然后尽量扩大该范围，最后再将颜色
    转变回 RGB。它只能在 RGB 和索引图像的图层上使用。当图像为灰度时，该菜单
    项不可用。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>olors</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>olor Enhance</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Das Kommando kann aus dem Bildfenster erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>F</accel>arben</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>utomatisch</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>arbverbesserung</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <!--TODO es fr it no: check menuentries-->
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>olores</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Realzar <accel>c</accel>olor</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image 
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Coule<accel>u</accel>rs</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Renforcer les cou<accel>l</accel>eurs</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando dalla barra del menu
          immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>C</accel>olori</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Aumento del <accel>c</accel>olore</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du har tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Fargar</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Fargeforbetring</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该命令在图像菜单的
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>颜色</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>自动</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>颜色增强</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en"><quote>Color Enhance</quote> example</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Ein Beispiel für die Farbverbesserung
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo de <quote>Realzar color</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        Exemple de <quote>Renforcer les couleurs</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Esempio di <quote>aumento del colore</quote></phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Fargeforbetring</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Color Enhance</quote> example (Original image)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Originalbild</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Original</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Exemple de <quote>Renforcer les couleurs</quote> (Image d'origine)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di <quote>aumento del colore</quote> (immagine originale)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Originalbiletet</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/alice.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
  
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The active layer and its Red, Green and Blue
            histograms before <quote>Color Enhance</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die aktive Ebene und ihre Histogramme des roten, blauen und
            grünen Kanals.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            La capa activa y su histograma de color rojo, verde y azul, antes
            de <quote>Realzar color</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque actif et ses histogrammes Rouge, Vert,
            Bleu avant traitement.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il livello attivo e i suoi istogrammi del colore rosso, verde e
            blu, prima dell'operazione di <quote>aumento del colore</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå før
            bruk av <quote>Fargeforbetring</quote>.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Color Enhance</quote> example (Image after the command)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Bild nach Farbverbesserung</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Exemple de <quote>Renforcer les couleurs</quote> (Image traitée)
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di <quote>aumento del colore</quote> (immagine dopo
          l'esecuzione del comando)
        </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Fargeforbetring</quote>
      </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/menus/color-enhance.png" 
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
  
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The active layer and its Red, Green and Blue histograms after
            <quote>Color Enhance</quote>.  The result may not always be
            what you expect.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Histogramme des roten, blauen und grünen Kanals nach der
            Farbverbesserung. Das Ergebnis muss nicht unbedingt so sein, wie
            erwartet.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            La capa activa y su histograma de color rojo, verde y azul,
            después de <quote>Realzar color</quote>. El resultado puede no
            ser el esperado. 
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le calque après traitement. Cette commande ne
            fournit pas toujours le résultat escompté.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il livello attivo ed i suoi istogrammi del colore rosso, verde
            e blu, dopo la trasformazione <quote>aumento del
            colore</quote>.  Il risultato potrebbe non essere sempre ciò
            che ci si aspetta.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Det aktive laget og histogrammet for raud, grøn og blå etter
            bruk av <quote>Fargeforbetring</quote>. Resultatet blir ikkje
            alltid slik du kanskje vente det.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
