<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  
-->
<!-- id is still used by GIMP, do not change! -->
<sect2 id="gimp-layer-equalize">
  <title>Equalize</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Colors</primary>
    <secondary>Equalize</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Equalize</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Equalize</guimenuitem>
    command automatically adjusts the brightness of colors across the active
    layer so that the histogram for the Value channel is as nearly flat as
    possible, that is, so that each possible brightness value appears at about
    the same number of pixels as every other value. You can see this in the
    histograms in the example below, in that pixel colors which occur
    frequently in the image are stretched further apart than pixel colors
    which occur only rarely. The results of this command can vary quite a bit.
    Sometimes <quote>Equalize</quote>
    works very well to enhance the contrast in an image, bringing out details
    which were hard to see before. Other times, the results look very bad. It
    is a very powerful operation and it is worth trying to see if it will
    improve your image. It works on layers from RGB and Grayscale images. If
    the image is Indexed, the menu entry is disabled.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <para>
      You can access this command from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Auto</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Equalize</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title><quote>Equalize</quote> example</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Original image</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/colors/auto/alice.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The active layer and its Red, Green, Blue histograms before
            <quote>Equalize</quote>.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title>Image after the command</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/colors/auto/equalize.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The active layer and its Red, Green, Blue histograms after
            treatment.
          </para>
          <para>
            Histogram stretching creates gaps between pixel columns giving it
            a striped look: colors that occur frequently are stretched.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
  
</sect2>
