<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-randomize-hurl' lang="en;cs;fr">
  <title lang="en">Hurl</title>
  <title lang="cs">Výpadky</title>
  <title lang="fr">Jeter</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Noise</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Hurl</tertiary>

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Šum</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">Výpadky</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Bruit</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Jeter</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-noise-hurl.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-noise-hurl.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-noise-hurl.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Noise</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>H</accel>url</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Šum</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Výpadky</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Bruit</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>J</accel>eter</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      The Hurl filter changes each affected pixel to a random color, so it
      produces real <emphasis>random noise</emphasis>. All color channels,
      including an alpha channel (if it is present) are randomized. All
      possible values are assigned with the same probability. The original
      values are not taken into account. All or only some pixels in an active
      layer or selection are affected, the percentage of affected pixels is
      determined by the <guilabel>Randomization (%)</guilabel> option.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr Výpadky přiřadí všem ovlivněným pixelům zcela náhodnou barvu,
      vytváří tak skutečný <emphasis>náhodný šum</emphasis>. Náhodná hodnota
      je přiřazena všem barevným kanálům, včetně případného alfa kanálu.
      Všechny možné hodnoty mají stejnou pravděpodobnost přiřazení, originální
      hodnoty pixelů se neberou v potaz. Filtrem jsou ovlivněny všechny nebo
      jen některé pixely z aktivní vrstvy či výběru, jejich podíl je určen
      volbou <guilabel>Náhodnost (%)</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Jeter change au hasard la couleur des pixels affectés, et
      produit un véritable <emphasis>bruit aléatoire</emphasis>. Tous les
      canaux de couleur sont rendus aléatoires, ainsi que le canal alpha (s'il
      est présent). La même probabilité est assignée à toutes les valeurs
      possibles, et les valeurs d'origine ne sont pas prises en compte. La
      quantité de pixels affectés dans un calque actif ou dans une sélection
      est déterminée par l'option <guilabel>Aléa (%)</guilabel>.
    </para> 
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Random Seed</term>
        <term lang="cs">Hnízdo náhodných čísel</term>
        <term lang="fr">Graine aléatoire</term>
        <listitem>

          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Random Seed</guilabel> controls randomness of hurl.
            If the same random seed in the same situation is used, the filter
            produces exactly the same results. A different random seed
            produces different results. Random seed can be entered manually
            or generated randomly by pressing <guibutton>New Seed</guibutton>
            button.
          </para>
          <para lang='en'>
            When the <guilabel>Randomize</guilabel> option is checked, random
            seed cannot be entered manually, but is randomly generated each
            time the filter is run. If it is not checked, the filter remembers
            the last random seed used.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Hnízdo náhodných čísel</guilabel> určuje náhodné
            vlastnosti výpadků. Pokud je ve stejné situaci použito stejné
            hnízdo, výsledky filtru jsou stejné. Použití jiného hnízda
            způsobí odlišné výsledky. Hnízdo lze zadat ručně nebo náhodně
            vygenerovat tlačítkem <guibutton>Randomizovat</guibutton>.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Je-li zaškrtnuta volba <guilabel>Randomizovat</guilabel>, nelze
            hnízdo náhodných čísel zadávat ručně, ale je náhodně generováno
            při každém použití filtru. V opačném případě si filtr pamatuje
            poslední použité hnízdo náhodných čísel.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            <guibutton>Graine aléatoire</guibutton> contrôle le caractère 
            aléatoire du déplacement des pixels. Si la même graine aléatoire
            est utilisée dans la même situation, le filtre produira les mêmes
            résultats. Un graine aléatoire différente produira des résultats
            différents. Une graine aléatoire peut être fournie manuellement,
            ou générée au hasard en pressant le bouton <guibutton>Nouvelle
            Graine</guibutton>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Lorsque l'option <guilabel>Aléatoire</guilabel> est cochée, la
            graine aléatoire ne peut plus être fournie manuellement, elle est
            générée aléatoirement à chaque fois que le filtre est utilisé. Si
            elle n'est pas cochée, le filtre se souvient de la dernière graine
            aléatoire utilisée.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Randomization (%)</term>
        <term lang="cs">Náhodnost (%)</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aléa (%)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guibutton>Randomization</guibutton> slider represents the
            percentage of pixels of the active layer or selection which will
            be hurled. The higher value, the more pixels are hurled.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Posuvník <guibutton>Náhodnost</guibutton> nastavuje podíl pixelů
            v obrázku, které budou postiženy výpadky. Vyšší hodnota znamená
            více výpadků.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guibutton>Aléa</guibutton> représente le pourcentage
            de pixels de la sélection ou du calque actif qui peuvent être
            affectés par le filtre.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Repeat</term>
        <term lang="cs">Opakování</term>
        <term lang="fr">Répétition</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Repeat</guilabel> slider represents the number
            of times the filter will be applied. In the case of the Hurl
            filter it is not verfy useful, because the same results can be
            obtained faster just by using a higher <guilabel>Randomization
            (%)</guilabel> value.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Posuvník <guibutton>Opakování</guibutton> určuje počet aplikací
            filtru. V případě filtru výpadky nemá valného smyslu, neboť
            stejného výsledku lze dosáhnout rychleji použitím vyšší hodnoty
            pro <guilabel>Náhodnost (%)</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guibutton>Répétition</guibutton> représente le nombre
            de fois où le filtre sera appliqué. Dans le cas du filtre Jeter,
            ce curseur n'est pas particulièrement utile puisqu'on peut
            obtenir le même résultat plus rapidement, en choisissant une
            valeur plus grande pour <guilabel>Aléa (%)</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
