<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2005-12-08 <simplesect> replaced by <sect3> by lexa
  050930 de replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
  050826 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<!-- TODO: RGB Noise in Gimp-2.4 -->
<sect2 id="plug-in-noisify" lang="en;es;cs;de;fr;it;ru">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-19</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-04</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-19</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Scatter RGB</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Roztřepení RGB</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Streue RGB</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Ruido RGB</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Dispersion RVB</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Dispersione RGB</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Разбросать RGB</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Noise</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Scatter RGB</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>filtry</primary>
    <secondary>Šum</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Roztřepení RGB</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Rauschen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Streue RGB</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Filtro</primary>
    <secondary>Ruido</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Ruido RGB</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtre</primary>
    <secondary>Bruit</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Dispersion RVB</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary>
    <secondary>Disturbo</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Dispersione RGB</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Фильтр</primary>
    <secondary>шум</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Разбросать RGB</primary></indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="cs;ru">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/filters-noise-noisify.png"
                format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="es">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/es/filters-noise-noisify.png"
                format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="it">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/it/filters-noise-noisify.png"
                format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Přehled</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Filterwirkung</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Generalidades</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;fr;it;ru">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Example of applying the Noisify filter
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          v.l.n.r.: Originalbild, Streue RGB angewandt
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Exemple d'application du filtre Dispersion RVB
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di applicazione del filtro Dispersione RGB
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Изображение до и после применения фильтра <quote>Разбросать
            RGB</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"
                    format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/examples/noise-taj-scatter-rgb.jpg"
                    format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Noise</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>catter RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Scatter RGB filter adds a normally distributed noise to a layer or a
      selection. It uses the RGB color model to produce the noise (noise is
      added to red, green and blue values of each pixel). A normal
      distribution means, that only slight noise is added to the most pixels
      in the affected area, while less pixels are affected by more extreme
      values. (If you apply this filter to an image filled with a solid grey
      color and then look at its histogram, you will see a classic bell-shaped
      Gaussian curve.)
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The result is very naturally looking noise.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter does not work with indexed images.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Obrázek</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Šum</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Roztřepení RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Roztřepení RGB přidává do aktivní vrstvy nebo výběru šum s normálním
      rozložením. Šum je vytvářen v RGB barevném modelu, tj. je přidáván k
      červené, zelené a modré hodnotě každého pixelu. Normální rozložení
      znamená, že většina pixelů je šumem pozměněna jen málo, zatímco menší
      množství pixelů více. (Pokud se tento filtr aplikuje na obrázek vyplněný
      šedou barvou, histogram výsledného obrázku vypadá jako klasická
      zvonovitá Gaussova křivka.)
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Výsledkem aplikace tohoto filtru je velmi přirozeně vypadající šum.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter fügt zu einer Ebene oder einer Auswahl normalverteiltes
      Rauschen hinzu. Das RGB-Farbmodell wird benutzt, um das Rauschen zu
      erzeugen. Dabei wird ein Rauschanteil zu den Rot- Blau- und Grünanteilen
      jedes Pixels hinzugefügt. Normalverteilt bedeutet, dass die meisten
      Pixel mit einem geringen und nur wenige Pixel mit einem grossen
      Rauschanteil versehen werden. Wenn Sie dieses Filter auf eine einfarbig
      graue Fläche anwenden würden, könnten Sie im Histogramm eine klassische
      glockenförmige Gaußkurve sehen.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Ergebnis dieses Filters ist ein sehr natürlich wirkendes Rauschen.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter funktioniert nicht bei indizierten Bildern.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Este filtro se encuentra en
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtros</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Ruido</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>uido RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El filtro de Ruido RGB añade un ruido distribuido de forma normal a una
      capa o selección. El modelo de color RGB se usa para producir el ruido
      (el ruido añade los valores de rojo, verde y azul a cada píxel). Una
      distribución normal significa que sólo ruido leve es añadido a la
      mayoría de los píxeles del área afectada, y menos píxeles son afectados
      por los valores extremos. (Si aplicas este filtro a una imagen coloreada
      por un gris sólido y después miras el histograma, verás la clásica curva
      de la campana de Gauss.)
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El resultado es un ruido muy natural.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      On accède à ce filtre par le menu d'image en suivant
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Bruit</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Dispersion RVB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre dispersion RVB ajoute un bruit distribué de façon «normale» à
      un calque ou à une sélection. Il utilise le mode de couleur RVB pour
      produire le bruit (le bruit est ajouté aux valeurs de rouge, de vert et
      de bleu de chaque pixel). «Distribution normale» signifie qu'un léger
      bruit est ajouté à la plus grande partie des pixels et un bruit fort à
      moins de pixels (si vous appliquez ce filtre à une image remplie d'un
      gris uniforme et vous examiniez son histogramme, vous verrez une
      classique courbe de Gauss en cloche.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le résultat est un brouillage de l'image. Vous pouvez l'utiliser pour
      donner un aspect de grain de pellicule photographique ou dans une
      oeuvre pointilliste.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre ne marche pas sur les images indexées.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le nom anglais de ce filtre est <quote>Noisify</quote>
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro si trova nel menu immagine:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filt<accel>r</accel>i</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dist<accel>u</accel>rbo</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>ispersione RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il filtro Dispersione RGB aggiunge un disturbo uniformemente distribuito
      ad un livello o ad una selezione. Sfrutta il modello di colore RGB per
      produrre il disturbo (si aggiungono piccole quantità alle componenti
      rossa, verde e blu di ciascun pixel). Una distribuzione uniforme
      significa che solo una leggera quantità di disturbo è aggiunta alla
      maggior parte dei pixel nell'area selezionata, soltanto pochi pixel
      risultano disturbati da valori più elevati (se si applica questo filtro
      ad una immagine completamente grigia e poi si guarda il suo istogramma
      dei colori si osserverà una classica curva gaussiana a forma di
      campana).
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il risultato è un disturbo molto naturale.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр находится в меню
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Фильтры</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Шум</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Разбросать RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Фильтр Разбросать RGB добавляет нормально распределённый шум к слою или
      выделению. Он использует цветовую модель RGB чтобы добавить шум к
      каналам красного, зелёного и синего каждой подверженной точки.
      Нормальное распределение означает, что только небольшие изменения
      добавляются к большинству точек, и большие изменения - к меньшиству.
      Если применить этот фильтр к серому изображению, то его
      гистограмма будет выглядеть как классическая колоколообразная кривая
      Гаусса.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Результат фильтра - естественно выглядящий шум.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 lang="de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Filteraufruf</phrase>
    </title>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter lässt sich über das Menü
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>R</accel>auschen</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Streue <accel>R</accel>GB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      im Bildfenster aufrufen.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;fr">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Scatter RGB</quote> filter options
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften für das Filter <quote>Streue RGB</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Options du filtre <quote>Dispersion RVB</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/scatter-RGB-options.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/de/options-noise-scatter-rgb.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/fr/scatter-RGB-options.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="cs">Náhled</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="es">Vista previa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <term lang="it">Anteprima</term>
        <term lang="ru">Просмотр</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This preview displays interactively changes before they are
            applied to the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Náhled zobrazuje interaktivně změny dříve, než jsou skutečně
            aplikovány do obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Vorschau zeigt Ihnen einen Ausschnitt des Bildes, so wie das
            Bild aussehen würde, wenn Sie den Filter mit den aktuellen
            Einstellungen ausführen würden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            La vista previa muestra los cambios de forma interactiva antes de
            ser aplicados a la imagen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cet aperçu affiche en temps réel le résultat des modifications
            apportées avant qu'elles ne soient appliquées à l'image.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questa anteprima mostra interattivamente i cambiamenti prima che
            essi vengano applicati all'immagine.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Окно просмотра обновляется по мере изменения параметров.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Correlated noise</term>
        <term lang="cs">Korelovaný šum</term>
        <term lang="de">Korreliertes Rauschen</term>
        <term lang="es">Ruido correlativo</term>
        <term lang="fr">Bruit en corrélation</term>
        <term lang="it">Disturbo correlato</term>
        <term lang="ru">Согласованный шум</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When checked, this radio button makes sliders R, G and B to move
            all together. The same relative noise will be added to all
            channels in each pixel, so the hue of pixels does not change much.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs"></para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--CHECK: de  it doesn't work that way for me, please doublecheck -->
            Wenn diese Eigenschaft aktiviert ist, haben werden die drei
            Schieberegler für Rot, Grün und Blau alle den gleichen Wert haben.
            Das gleich relative Rauschen wird damit auf alle Kanäle jedes
            Pixels angewendet. Daher ändert sich der Farbton der Pixel nicht
            sehr.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Cuando está activa esta casilla, hace que los deslizadores R, G y
            B se muevan a la vez. El mismo ruido relativo se añadirá a todos
            los canales en cada píxel, y de esta forma conseguir que no cambie
            mucho la tonalidad de los píxeles.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Quand cette option est cochée, un algorithme de <quote>bruit
            corrélé</quote> est appliqué au résultat : l'histogramme est
            étalé, le contraste renforcé.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se selezionato, questo radio button fa muovere i cursori R, G e B
            in sincrono. La stessa quantità di disturbo verrà applicata a
            tutti i canali di ogni pixel cosicchè la tinta di ciascun pixel
            non subirà eccessive variazioni.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При выборе этого параметра ползунки RGB будут изменятся
            одновременно при изменении одного из них. Таким образом шум
            применится ко всем каналам одинаково, и тон точек не сильно
            изменится.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Independent RGB</term>
        <term lang="es">RGB Independiente</term>
        <term lang="cs">Nezávislé RGB</term>
        <term lang="de">Unabhängige RGB Kanäle</term>
        <term lang="fr">R, V, B indépendants</term>
        <term lang="it">RGB indipendenti</term>
        <term lang="ru">Независимый RGB</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When this radio button is checked, you can move each RGB sliders
            separatly.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Si esta casilla está activa, puedes mover cada deslizador RGB de
            forma independiente.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud tato volba není aktivní, pohybují se všechny posuvníky
            společně a do všech kanálu bude přidán stejný relativní šum.
            Zachová se tak vyvážení barev.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <!--CHECK: de  it doesn't work that way for me, please doublecheck -->
            Wenn diese Eigenschaft aktiviert ist, können die Schieberegler
            unabhängig voneinander bewegt werden.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Quand ce bouton radio est coché, les trois curseurs RVB sont
            indépendants.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se questo radio button è selezionato si può muovere ciascun
            cursore RGB separatamente.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При выборе этого параметра ползунки RGB можно изменить отдельно.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Red, Blue, Green and Alfa Sliders</term>
        <term lang="cs">Posuvníky Červená, Zelená, Modrá a Alfa</term>
        <term lang="de">Rot, Blau, Grün, Alpha</term>
        <term lang="es">Deslizadores Rojo, Azul, Verde y Alfa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Curseurs Rouge Vert Bleu</term>
        <term lang="it">Cursori Rosso, Blu, Verde e Alfa</term>
        <term lang="ru">Красный, зелёный, синий и альфа</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            These slidebars and adjacent input boxes allow to set noise level
            (0.00 - 1.00) in each channel. Alpha channel is only present, if
            your layer holds such a channel. In case of a grayscale image, a
            <guilabel>Grey</guilabel>
            is shown instead of color sliders.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The value set by these sliders actually determine the standard
            deviation of the normal distribution of applied noise. The used
            standard deviation is a half of the set value (where 1 is the
            distance between the lowest and highest possible value in a
            channel).
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Tyto posuvníky a odpovídající přírůstková pole pole určují
            množství šumu v každém kanálu (v rozsahu 0.00 - 1.00). Alfa kanál
            je zobrazen jen tehdy, pokud je ve vrstvě přítomen. V případě
            obrázku ve stupních šedi jsou barevné posuvníky nahrazeny
            posuvníkem
            <guilabel>Šedá</guilabel>
            .
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Zde nastavené hodnoty ve skutečnosti udávají standardní odchylku
            normálního rozložení aplikovaného šumu. Použitá odchylka je
            polovinou nastavené hodnoty (kde 1 odpovídá vzdálenosti mezi
            nejnižší a nejvyšší možnou hodnotou v kanálu).
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesen Schiebereglern und den zugeordneten Eingabefeldern
            können Sie das Rauschniveau im Bereich 0,00 bis 1,00 einstellen.
            Der Alphakanal wird nur angezeigt, wenn das Bild über einen
            solchen verfügt. Falls das Bild ein Graustufenbild ist, wird an
            Stelle der RGB-Felder <guilabel>Grau</guilabel> angezeigt.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Der Wert, der durch die Schieberegler eingestellt wird ist die
            Standardabweichung von der Normalverteilung des aufgebrachten
            Rauschens. Die benutzte Standardabweichung ist die Hälfte des hier
            eingetragenen Wertes. Dabei ist 1 der Abstand zwischen dem
            höchsten und dem niedrigsten möglichen Wert in einem Kanal.
          </para>
          <tip lang="de">
            <para lang="de">
              Falls sich der letzte Abschnitt für Sie nach einer Vorlesung in
              Statistik anhört, so liegen Sie nicht ganz falsch. Sollten Sie
              dabei kein Wort verstanden haben, so macht das gar nichts.
              Betrachten Sie die Einstellung einfach als Menge des durch das
              Filter aufgetragenen Rauschens und experimentieren Sie ein
              bisschen mit den Werten.
            </para>
          </tip>

          <para lang="es">
            Estos deslizadores y los valores junto a estos permite establecer
            el nivel de ruido (0.00 - 1.00) en cada canal. El canal alfa está
            presente, si la capa lo contiene. En caso de ser una imagen en
            escala de grises, un
            <guilabel>Gris</guilabel>
            se muestra en vez de los deslizadores de colores.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            El valor de estos deslizadores determina la desviación estándar de
            la distribución normal del ruido aplicado. El uso de la desviación
            estándar es la mitad del valor elegido (donde 1 es la distancia
            entre el menor y mayor valor posible en el canal).
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Ces curseurs, et les boîtes de saisie adjacentes, permettent de
            fixer le niveau de bruit (de 0 à 1) dans chaque canal. Le canal
            Alpha n'est présent que si votre image possède un tel canal.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La valeur fournie par ces curseurs détermine en fait la déviation
            standard de la distribution normale du bruit appliqué. La
            déviation standard utilisée est la moitié de la valeur fixée où 1
            est la distance entre les valeurs minimale et maximale d'un
            canal).
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Questi cursori e le caselle di immissione adiacenti permettono di
            impostare il livello di disturbo (0.00 - 1.00) per ciascun canale.
            il canale alfa è presente solo se il livello corrente contiene
            tale canale. Nel caso di un'immagine in scala di grigi, viene
            mostrata una etichetta
            <guilabel>Grigio</guilabel>
            invece dei cursori dei colori.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il valore impostato da questi cursori in realtà determina la
            deviazione standard della distribuzione uniforme con cui è
            applicato il disturbo. La deviazione standard applicata è pari
            alla metà del valore impostato (dove 1 è la distanza tra il valore
            più basso e quello più alto in un canale).
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Эти ползунки и поля ввода позволяют определить уровень шума для
            каждого канала (от 0 до 1). Канал альфа показан только если
            текущий слой его содержит. Для серого изображения показан
            параметр <guilabel>Серый</guilabel> вместо цветных каналов.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Значение, установленное этими ползунками, определяет стандартное
            отклонение нормального распределения применяемого шума.
            Используемое значение отклонения составляет половину
            установленного значения. Значение 1 соответствует диапазону между
            наименьшим и наибольшим значениями канала.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
