<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-noisify' lang="en;cs;fr">
  <title lang="en">Scatter RGB</title>
  <title lang="cs">Roztřepení RGB</title>
  <title lang="fr">Dispersion RVB</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Noise</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Scatter RGB</tertiary>

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Šum</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">Roztřepení RGB</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Bruit</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Dispersion RVB</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-noise-noisify.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-noise-noisify.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-noise-noisify.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in the image window menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Noise</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>catter RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Scatter RGB filter adds a normally distributed noise to a layer or a
      selection. It uses the RGB color model to produce the noise (noise is
      added to red, green and blue values of each pixel). A normal
      distribution means, that only slight noise is added to the most pixels
      in the affected area, while less pixels are affected by more extreme
      values. (If you apply this filter to an image filled with a solid grey
      color and then look at its histogram, you will see a classic bell-shaped
      Gaussian curve.)
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The result is very naturally looking noise.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Obrázek</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Šum</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Roztřepení RGB</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Roztřepení RGB přidává do aktivní vrstvy nebo výběru šum s normálním
      rozložením. Šum je vytvářen v RGB barevném modelu, tj. je přidáván
      k červené, zelené a modré hodnotě každého pixelu. Normální rozložení
      znamená, že většina pixelů je šumem pozměněna jen málo, zatímco menší
      množství pixelů více. (Pokud se tento filtr aplikuje na obrázek vyplněný
      šedou barvou, histogram výsledného obrázku vypadá jako klasická
      zvonovitá Gaussova křivka.)
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Výsledkem aplikace tohoto filtru je velmi přirozeně vypadající šum.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à 
      <guimenuitem>Image&gt;Filtres/Bruit/<accel>B</accel>rouiller</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Brouiller renforce, pour des pixels choisis au hasard dans le calque actif ou la
      sélection, la couleur d'un ou plusieurs canaux, créant l'analogue d'un «bruit» surajouté 
      dans le domaine du son, ce qui aboutit à brouiller l'image.
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="cs">Náhled</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This preview displays interactively changes before they are
            applied to the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Náhled zobrazuje interaktivně změny dříve, než jsou skutečně
            aplikovány do obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cet aperçu affiche en temps réel le résultat des modifications
            apportées avant qu'elles ne soient appliquées à l'image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Correlated noise</term>
        <term lang="cs">Korelovaný šum</term>
        <term lang="fr">fixme</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Independent RGB</term>
        <term lang="cs">Nezávislé RGB</term>
        <term lang="fr">Indépendant RGB</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If this checkbox is not checked, sliders for <guilabel>Red</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Green</guilabel> and <guilabel>Blue</guilabel> channels
            below move together and the same relative noise will be added to all
            channels in each pixel, so the hue of pixels does not change much.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud tato volba není aktivní, pohybují se všechny posuvníky
            společně a do všech kanálu bude přidán stejný relativní šum.
            Zachová se tak vyvážení barev.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si cette case n'est pas cochée, les trois curseurs seront solidaires et le même bruit sera 
            ajouté aux trois canaux, de telle sorte que la balance des couleurs de l'image sera conservée.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Red, Blue, Green and Alfa Sliders</term>
        <term lang="cs">Posuvníky Červená, Zelená, Modrá a Alfa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Curseurs Rouge Vert Bleu</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            These slidebars and adjacent input boxes allow to set noise
            level (0.00 - 1.00) in each channel. Apha channel is only present,
            if your layer holds such a channel. In case of a greyscale image,
            a <guilabel>Grey</guilabel> is shown instead of color sliders.
          </para>
          <para>
            The value set by these sliders actually determine the standard
            deviation of the normal distribution of applied noise. The used
            standard deviation is a half of the set value (where 1 is the
            distance between the lowest and highest possible value in a
            channel).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="cs">
          <para>
            Tyto posuvníky a odpovídající přírustková pole pole určují množství
            šumu v každém kanálu (v rozsahu 0.00 - 1.00). Alfa kanál je zobrazen
            jen tehdy, pokud je ve vrstvě přítomen. V případě obrázku ve stupních
            šedi jsou barevné posuvníky nahrazeny posuvníkem
            <guilabel>Šedá</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Zde nastavené hodnoty ve skutečnosti udávají standardní odchylku
            normálního rozložení aplikovaného šumu. Použitá odchylka je
            polovinou nastavené hodnoty (kde 1 odpovídá vzdálenosti mezi
            nejnižší a nejvyšší možnou hodnotou v kanálu).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem lang="fr">
          <para>
            Ces curseurs, et les boîtes de saisie adjacentes, permettent de fixer le niveau de bruit 
            (de 0 à 1) dans chaque canal. Le canal Alpha n'est présent que si votre image possède un tel 
            canal. Dans le cas d'une image en niveau de gris, le canal Rouge représente le Gris et le canal 
            Vert représente l'Alpha.
          </para>
          <para>
            En ajoutant de la couleur à un pixel, la valeur peut dépasser 255. Dans ce cas une valeur 
            négative est ajoutée et la couleur diminue, ce qui peut amener un changement de couleur quand 
            la valeur du canal concerné devient inférieure à celle de l'un ou l'autre canal.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
