<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-01-13 j.h update to v2.10
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-filter-noise-rgb">
  <title>RGB Noise</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Noise</secondary>
    <tertiary>RGB Noise</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>RGB Noise</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example of applying the <quote>RGB Noise</quote> filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/noise/taj-rgb-noise.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>RGB Noise</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The RGB Noise filter adds a normally distributed noise to a layer or a
      selection. It uses the RGB color model to produce the noise (noise is
      added to red, green and blue values of each pixel). A normal
      distribution means, that only slight noise is added to the most pixels
      in the affected area, while less pixels are affected by more extreme
      values. (If you apply this filter to an image filled with a solid gray
      color and then look at its histogram, you will see a classic bell-shaped
      Gaussian curve.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The result is very naturally looking noise.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the main menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Noise</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>RGB Noise…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>RGB Noise</quote> filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/noise/RGB_Noise-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Presets</term>
        <term><quote>Input Type</quote></term>
        <term>Clipping</term>
        <term>Blending Options</term>
        <term>Preview</term>
        <term>Merge filter</term>
        <term>Split view</term>
        <listitem>
          <xi:include href="../about-common-features.xml"/>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Correlated noise</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Noise may be additive (uncorrelated) or multiplicative (correlated
            - also known as speckle noise). When checked, every channel value
            is multiplied by a normal distributed value. So the noise
            depends on the channel values: a greater channel value leads to
            more noise, while dark colors (small values) tend to remain dark.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Independent RGB</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this radio button is checked, you can move each RGB slider
            separately. Otherwise, the sliders R, G and B will be replaced by
            a single slider Value. The same relative noise will then be added
            to all channels in each pixel, so the hue of pixels does not change
            much.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Linear RGB</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Operate on linearized RGB color data.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Gaussian distribution</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use a gaussian noise distribution. When unchecked, a linear noise 
            distribution is used instead.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Red</term>
        <term>Green</term>
        <term>Blue</term>
        <term>Alpha</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These slidebars and adjacent input boxes allow to set noise level
            (0.00&nbsp;-&nbsp;1.00) in each channel.
          </para>
          <para>
            The value set by these sliders actually determine the standard
            deviation of the normal distribution of applied noise. The used
            standard deviation is a half of the set value (where 1 is the
            distance between the lowest and highest possible value in a
            channel).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Random seed</term>
        <term>New Seed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option controls the randomness of the filter.
            The <guilabel>Random seed</guilabel> box lets you manually enter
            a seed for the randomization algorithm used. You can also generate
            a random seed by pressing the <guibutton>New Seed</guibutton>
            button. If the same random seed is used in the same situation,
            the filter produces exactly the same results. A different random
            seed produces different results.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
