<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-10-23 ude: moved here from filters/color/map/sample_colorize.xml ('en','de')
  2007-07-11 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-04-01 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-08-22 de added by axel.wernicke
  2005-08-30 de replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-sample-colorize">
  <title>Sample Colorize</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Colors</primary>
    <secondary>Sample Colorize</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Sample Colorize</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Example for the <quote>Sample Colorize</quote> filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/color-taj-sample-colorize.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>Sample Colorize</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      This filter allows you to colorize old black-and-white images by mapping
      a color source image or a gradient against it.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the main menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Map</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sample Colorize</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Options of the <quote>Sample Colorize</quote> filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/colors/map/samplecolorize.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The filter window is divided into two parts: Destination on the left,
      Sampling on the right.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Destination</term>
        <term>Sample</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By default, displayed image previews reproduce the image you
            invoked the filter from.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>The sample</guilabel> can be the whole preview, or a
            selection of this preview. With the drop list, you can select
            another sample-image among the names of images present on
            your screen when you called the filter. If you choose
            <guilabel>From Gradient</guilabel> (or <guilabel>From Inverse
            Gradient</guilabel>), the selected gradient in Gradient Dialog
            (or its inverse) will be the sample. It will be displayed into
            the gradient bar below the sample preview. The sampling preview
            is grayed out and two cursors allow you to select the gradient
            range that will be applied to the image or selection.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Destination</guilabel> is, by default, the source
            image. The drop list displays the list of images present on your
            screen when you evoked the filter and allow you to select
            another destination image. If there is a selection in this
            image, it will be grayscale, else the whole preview will be
            grayscale.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show selection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option toggles between the whole image and the selection,
            if it exists.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option toggles between colors and grayscale.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Input levels</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Three input boxes and three sliders allow to fix importance of
            dark tones, mid tones and light tones. Result appears
            interactively in destination preview.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Output levels</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Two input boxes and two sliders act the same: they limit the
            color range which will be applied to destination image. You can
            choose this range accurately. Result appears interactively in
            destination preview.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hold intensity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this option is checked, the average light intensity of
            destination image will be the same as that of source image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Original intensity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this option is checked, the In levels intensity settings will
            not be taken in account: original intensity will be preserved.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Get Sample Colors</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you click on this button, the gradient bar below the
            sample preview displays colors of the sample. If your sample
            holds few colors, transitions may be abrupt. Check
            <guilabel>Smooth samples</guilabel> option to improve them.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Use subcolors</guilabel> is more difficult to
            understand. Let's say first that in a grayscale image there is
            information only for Value (luminosity, more or less light). In a
            RGB  image, each pixel has information for the three colors and
            Value. So, pixels with different color may have the same Value.
            If this option is checked, colors will be mixed and applied to
            Destination pixels having that Value. If it is unchecked, then
            the dominating color will be applied.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
