<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-12-10 ude: adapted 'no' guides text for 'en','de'
  2007-10-23 kost: added 'no'
  2007-09-12 lexa: encapsulated images in figures
  2007-05-24 ude: options section rewritten for de
  2007-05-12 ude: added translation of new text
  2007-05-01 Pierre :  main modifications;  new text and images created
  2007-01-05 lexa: added de translation
  2006-12-27 created by j.h
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-imagemap">
  <title>Image Map</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Web</secondary>
    <tertiary>Clickable image</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image Map</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    In Web sensitive images are frequently used to get some effects when
    defined areas are enabled by the pointer. Obviously the most used effect
    is a dynamic link to another web page when one of the sensitive areas is
    clicked on. This <quote>filter</quote> allows you to design easily
    sensitive areas within an image. Applications for website design have this
    as a standard function. In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you can do this in a
    similar way.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      This plug-in lets you design graphically and friendly all areas you
      want to delimit over your displayed image. You get the relevant part
      of html tags that must be merged into the right place in your page html
      code. You can define some actions linked to these areas too.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is a complex tool which is not completely described here
      (it works about like Web page makers offering this function). However
      we want to describe here some of the most current handlings. If you
      want, you can find a more complete description in Grokking the GIMP
      with the
      link <xref linkend="bibliography-online-grokking-gimp-imagemap"/>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the main menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Web</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Image Map…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The window is a small one, but you can magnify it.
      The main useful areas are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          completely on the left are vertically displayed icons, one for
          pointing, three for calling tools to generate various shape areas,
          one to edit zone properties, and finally one to erase a selected
          zone; you can call these functions from the Mappings menu,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          just on the right is your working area where you can draw all the
          shapes areas you want with the relevant tools,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          on the right is displayed an icon vertical set; its use is obvious
          but a help pop-up gives you some information about each function,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          finally, even on the right is a display area, as a property list of
          the created areas. A click on one item of the list selects
          automatically the corresponding shape in the working area.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Image Map filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/web/imagemap.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Image map window</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect4>
      <title>The Menu Bar</title>
      <para>
        The menu bar is similar to the main menu, only a few menus
        or menu entries are different:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>File</term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Save</term>
                <term>Save As</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Contrary to other filters, this plug-in doesn't make an
                    image but a text file. So you must save your work in a
                    text format.
                  </para>
                  <tip>
                    <para>
                      With
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Source</guimenuitem>
                      </menuchoice>
                      you can preview this text file content.
                    </para>
                  </tip>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Open</term>
                <term>Open recent</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    In the plug-in you can open the saved text file. The
                    areas defined in your file will be loaded and
                    overdisplayed; if the displayed image is not the
                    original one or not with the same size,
                    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will ask you for adapting the
                    scale.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Edit</term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Edit area info</term>
                <listitem>
                  <figure>
                    <title>Editing an image map area</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata format="PNG"
                          fileref="images/filters/web/imagemap-area.png"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </figure>
                  <para>
                    In the settings dialog you can edit the area information
                    of a selected area. This dialog will pop up automatically
                    whenever you create a new area.
                    <!--CHECK: If you are opening the HTML file from the pull
                      down menu only the file name is added. You have to add
                      the path manually.  In the tag JavaScript you may add
                      functions for onMouseover, onMouseout etc.-->
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>View</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This menu offers you special functions:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Area List</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Here you can hide or show the selection area.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Source…</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Here you see the raw data as you would save it to or read
                    it from a file.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Color</term>
                <term>Gray</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    You can select the image mode here and work with a
                    Grayscale display.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Mappings</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You will seldom use this menu, since you can more easily access
              selection tools by clicking on icons on the left of the working
              area.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Arrow</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The arrow here represents the Move tool. When activated
                    tool is selected, you can select and move an area on the
                    image.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    With a polygon, you can use the arrow to move one of
                    the red points. Right-click on a segment between two
                    red points to open a pop-up menu that offers, with
                    several others, the possibility to add a new point. If
                    you right-click on a red point, you can remove it.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Rectangle</term>
                <term>Circle</term>
                <term>Polygon</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    These tools let you create various shape areas: click on
                    the image, move the pointer, and click again.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Edit Map Info…</term>
                <listitem>
                  <figure>
                    <title>Editing the image map data</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata format="PNG"
                          fileref="images/filters/web/imagemap-info.png"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </figure>
                  <para>
                    With this simple dialog you can enter some items, which
                    will be written to the resulting output file; either as
                    comments (<guilabel>Author</guilabel>,
                    <guilabel>Description</guilabel>)
                    or as attribute values of the HTML tags
                    (<guilabel>Image name</guilabel>,
                    <guilabel>Title</guilabel>,
                    <guilabel>Default URL</guilabel>).
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tools</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>With the <quote>Tools</quote> menu
              you can create guides and even regularly spaced rectangular areas.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Grid</term>
                <term>Grid Settings…</term>
                <listitem>
                  <figure>
                    <title>Grid options</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata format="PNG"
                          fileref="images/filters/web/imagemap-grid.png"/>
                      </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </figure>
                  <para>
                    Here you can enable and disable the image grid or
                    configure some grid properties.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Use GIMP Guides…</term>
                <term>Create Guides…</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The guide lines are created at the border of the image but
                    can be moved around by clicking on the red squares on each
                    line something similar to the GIMP guide lines. By using
                    the guides you are able to create active rectangles in the
                    image.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Create guides</term>
                <listitem>
                  <figure>
                    <title>Guide options</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata format="PNG"
                          fileref="images/filters/web/imagemap-guides-options.png"/>
                      </imageobject>
                      <caption>
                        <para>The guide options</para>
                      </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                  </figure>
                  <para> 
                    Instead of creating geometrical shapes to select the
                    active areas you may use an array of rectangles, each
                    representing an active area, by clicking on the
                    <quote>Create guides</quote>. In the menu popping
                    up you set the width and height of the rectangles, the
                    space between them, the number of rows and 
                    columns, and the upper and left startpoint for the array.
                    All measures are in pixels. If you are not satisfied with
                    the result you may adjust each rectangle by moving the
                    red squares as usual.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
      <title>The Tool Bar</title>
      <para>
        Most entries here are just shortcuts for some functions already
        described. Exceptions:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Move Area to Front</term>
          <term>Move Area to Bottom</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Here you can move an area entry to the bottom or top
              of the area list.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
      <title>The Working Area</title>
      <figure>
        <title>The Working Area</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/filters/web/imagemap-draw.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        In the main area of the image map window, on the left side, you will
        find your working area where you can draw all the shapes areas you
        want with the relevant tools.
      </para>
      <para>
        Beside the working area there are vertically displayed icons, one for
        pointing, three for calling tools to generate various shape areas, one
        to edit zone properties, and finally one to erase a selected zone; you
        can call these functions from the Mappings menu too.
      </para>
      <caution>
        <para>
          Note that the areas should not overlap.
        </para>
      </caution>
    </sect4>

    <sect4>
      <title>The selection area</title>
      <para>
        On the right is a display area, as a property list of the created
        areas. A click on one item of the list selects automatically the
        corresponding shape in the working area, then you can modify it.
      </para>
      <para>
        Beside the display is an icon vertical set; its use is obvious
        but a help pop-up gives you some information about each
        function.
      </para>
      <para>
        Unfortunately, the arrow symbols for moving a list entry up or down do
        not work here.
        <!--You can use <guiicon>Move to Front</guiicon> or
        <guiicon>Send to Back</guiicon> in the tool bar instead. Or you can
        activate the arrow tool and open the context menu of a selected area,
        with menu items <guimenuitem>Move Up</guimenuitem> and
        <guimenuitem>Move Down</guimenuitem>.-->
        But of course you carefully avoided to create overlapping areas, so
        you do not use these functions at all.
      </para>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
