<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-gradmap' lang="en;cs;fr">
  <title lang="en">Gradient Map</title>
  <title lang="cs">Mapování z přechodu</title>
  <title lang="fr">Application de dégradé</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Color</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Gradient Map</tertiary>

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Barvy</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">Mapování z přechodu</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtres</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Couleurs</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Dégradé</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/filters/examples/gradmap-example.png'
          format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>

       <caption lang="en">
         <para>
           Example of Gradient Mapping.  Top: Original image.  Middle: a
           gradient.  Bottom: result of applying the gradient to the
           original image with the Gradient Map filter.
        </para>
       </caption>
       <caption lang="cs">
         <para>
           Příklad mapování z přechodu. Nahoře: původní obrázek. Uprostřed:
           přechod. Dole: výsledek použití přechopdu na původní obrázek pomocí
           filtru Mapování z přechodu.
        </para>
       </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    This filter uses the current gradient, as shown in the
    Brush/Pattern/Gradient area of the Toolbox, to recolor the active
    layer or selection of the image to which the filter is applied. To
    use it, first choose a gradient from the <link
    linkend="gimp-gradient-dialog">Gradients Dialog</link>.  Then
    select the part of the image you want to alter, and activate the
    filter by choosing
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Colors</guisubmenu>
      <guisubmenu>Map</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Gradient Map</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    from the image menu.   The filter runs automatically, without
    showing any dialog or requiring any further input.   It uses image
    color intensities (0 - 255), mapping the darkest pixels to
    the left end color from the gradient, and the lightest pixels to
    the right end color from the gradient. Intermediate values are set
    to the corresponding intermediate colors. 
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Tento filtr používá aktuální přechod zobrazený v indikační oblasti panelu
    nástrojů k přebarvení aktivní vrstvy nebo výběru obrázku. Nejprve zvolte
    vhodný přechod z dialogu <!--FIXCS<link
    linkend="gimp-gradient-dialog">-->Přechody<!--</link>-->. Pak vyberte část
    obrázku, na kterou chcete mapování použít a aktivujte filtr volbou
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Barvy</guisubmenu>
      <guisubmenu>Mapa</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Mapování z přechodu</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    z nabídky obrázku. Filtr běží automaticky, bez zobrazení konfiguračního
    dialogu. Pracuje s jasem (0-255) jednotlivých pixelů obrázku, nejtmavším
    přiřadí barvu ze začátku přechodu, nejsvětlejším barvu z konce přechodu.
    Mezilehlým hodnotám jsou přiřazeny barvy z odpovídajících částí přechodu.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Ce filtre applique les couleurs du dégradé de la Boîte à Outils à la 
    sélection ou au calque actif. Avant de l'utiliser, vous devezchoisir un 
    dégradé dans l' <link linkend="gimp-gradient-editor-dialog">Éditeur de 
    Dégradés</link> (clic dans la zone du Dégrade en bas à droite de la 
    Boîte à Outils ou Dialogues>Dégradés), puis application du dégradé en 
    activant le filtre
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Couleurs</guisubmenu>
      <guisubmenu>Carte</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Application de dégradé</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>. 
    Le filtre agit immédiatement, sans passer par une fenêtre de dialogue. 
    Il utilise les intensités 
    de couleur (0 - 255) de votre image et fait correspondre les pixels les 
    plus sombres de l'image à la couleur la plus à gauche du dégradé et les 
    pixels les plus vifs à la couleur la plus à droite du dégradé. Les 
    pixels de valeur intermédiaire prennent la couleur intermédiaire 
    correspondante dans le dégradé.
    </para>

</sect2>
