<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-09-17 aprokoudine: fixed bugs
  2008-01-11 j.h: updated to v2.4 'en;fr'
  2007-06-04 kost: added 'no'
  2007-06-14 alex falappa: updated italian translation
  2007-04-29 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2007-02-23 note added to Key Modifiers by j.h
  2006-06-07 added link to path concept by j.h
  2006-02-15 en;fr revised by j.h
  2005-12-06 replaced sect3 by sect3 by lexa
  2005-12-06 replaced informalfigure by figure by lexa
  2005-08-14 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-path">
  <title>Paths</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Path</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Paths</primary>
    <secondary>Tool</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Bézier's curve</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title>Paths tool</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/toolbox-path.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The Paths tool allows to create complex selections called Bézier Curves, a
    bit like Lasso but with all the adaptability of vectorial curves. You can
    edit your curve, you can paint with your curve, or even save, import, and
    export the curve. You can also use paths to create geometrical figures.
    Paths have their own dialog box:
    <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Dialog</link>.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>You can get this tool in several ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In the image menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paths</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic
              fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-path-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>
          in Toolbox,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          or by using the <keycap>B</keycap> keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Key modifiers (Defaults)</title>
    <note>
      <para>
        Help messages pop up at the bottom of the image window to help you
        about all these keys.
      </para>
    </note>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This key has several functions depending on context. See Options
            for more details.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> ; <keycap>Alt</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Three modes are available to work with the Paths tool:
            <guilabel>Design</guilabel>,<guilabel>Edit</guilabel>
            and <guilabel>Move</guilabel>.  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key
            toggles between Design and Edit.  <keycap>Alt</keycap> (or
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>)
            key toggles between Design and Move.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Path</quote> tool options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/path-tool-options.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Normally, tool options are displayed in a window attached under the
      Toolbox as soon as you activate a tool. If they are not, you can access
      them from the image menu bar through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Windows</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tool Options</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> which opens the option window of the selected tool.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Design Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By default, this tool is in <guilabel>Design</guilabel> mode.
            You draw the path by clicking successively. You can move
            control points by clicking on them and dragging them. Between
            control points are segments.
          </para>
          <para>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/path-stroke.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Numbers are steps to draw a two segments straight path.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </para>
          <para>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/path-curve.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Curved segments are easily built by dragging a segment or a
                  new node. Blue arrows indicate curve. Two little handles
                  appear that you can drag to bend the curve.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </para>
          <tip>
            <para>
              To quickly close the curve, press <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              key and click on the initial control point. In previous
              versions, clicking inside a closed path converted it into
              Selection. Now, you can use the <guibutton>Create
              selection from path</guibutton> button or
              <guiicon>
                <inlinegraphic
                  fileref="images/dialogs/stock-selection-16.png"/>
              </guiicon>
              the <emphasis>Path to Selection</emphasis> button
              in the Path Dialog.
            </para>
          </tip>
          <tip>
            <para>
              When you have two handles, they work symmetrically by
              default.  Release the pressure on the mouse button to move
              handles individually. The <keycap>Shift</keycap> key will
              force the handles to be symmetrical again.
            </para>
          </tip>
          <para>Several functions are available with this mode:</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Add a new node</emphasis>:
            If the active node (a small empty circle after clicking on a node)
            is at the end of the path, the mouse pointer is a '+' sign and a new
            node is created, linked to the previous one by a segment. If the
            active node is on the path, the pointer is a square and you can
            create a new component to the path. This new component is
            independent from the other, but belongs to the path as you can see
            on the Path dialog. Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            forces the creation of a new component.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Move one or several nodes</emphasis>: On a node,
            the mouse pointer becomes a 4-arrows cross. You can click
            and drag it.
            You can select several nodes by <keycap>Shift</keycap> and
            click and move them by click and drag.
            Pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt
            </keycap></keycombo> allows to move all the path, as a
            selection.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Modify handles</emphasis>: You have to Edit a node
            before. A handle appears. Drag it to bend the curve.
            Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> toggles to symmetric handles.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Modify segment</emphasis>: When the mouse pointer
            goes over a segment, it turns to a 4-arrows cross. Click-and-drag
            it to bend the segment. As soon as you move, handles appear
            at both ends of the segment. Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            key toggles to symmetric handles.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edit Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> performs functions which are not
            available in <guilabel>Design</guilabel> mode. With this
            mode, you can work only on the existing path.  Outside, the
            pointer is a small crossed circle (on the whole image if
            there is no path!) and you can do nothing.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Add a segment between two nodes</emphasis>: Click
            on a node at one end of the path to activate it. The pointer is
            like a union symbol. Click on an other node to link both
            nodes. This is useful when you have to link unclosed
            components.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Remove a segment from a path</emphasis>: While pressing
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            key combination, point to a segment. Pointer turns to -.
            Click to delete the segment.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Add a node to a path</emphasis>: point to a
            segment. Pointer turns to +. Click where you want to place
            the new control point.
          </para>
          <para><emphasis>Remove a node</emphasis>: While pressing
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            key combination, point to a node. Pointer turns
            to -. Click to delete the node.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Add a handle to a node</emphasis>: Point to a
            node. Pointer turns to small hand. Drag the node: handle
            appears.
            Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> toggles to symmetric
            handles.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Remove a handle from a node</emphasis>: While pressing
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            key combination, point to a handle. The pointer
            doesn't turn to the expected - and remains a hand. Click
            to delete the handle.
          </para>
          <caution>
            <para>
              No warning before removing a node, a segment or a handle.
            </para>
          </caution>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Move Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Move</guilabel> mode allows to move one or all
            components of a path. Simply click on the path and drag it.
          </para>
          <para>
            If you have several components, only the selected one is moved. If
            you click and drag outside the path, all components are moved.
            Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            key toggles to move all components also.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Polygonal</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option, segments are linear only. Handles are not
            available and segments are not bent when moving them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Create selection from path</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This button allows creation of a selection that is based on
            the path in its present state. This selection is marked with
            the usual "marching ants". Note that the path is still present:
            current tool is still path tool and you can modify this path without
            modifying the selection that has become independent. If you
            change tool, the path becomes invisible, but it persists in
            Path Dialog and you can re-activate it.
          </para>
          <para>
            If the path is not closed, GIMP will close it with a straight line.
          </para>
          <para>
            As the help pop-up tells, pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            when clicking on the button will add the new selection to an
            eventually pre-existent. Pressing the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> will
            subtract the selection from the pre-existent and the
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            key combination will intersect the two selections.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stroke path</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In previous versions, you could access to this command
            only by the Edit sub-menu in the Image Menu. Now you can
            access to it also via this button. See
            <xref linkend="gimp-path-stroke"/> and
            <xref linkend="gimp-using-paths"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      See the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-paths"><quote>Path</quote>
      </link>concept.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
