<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2018-10-27 j.h: update to v2.10
  2008-09-17 aprokoudine: fixed bugs
  2008-01-11 j.h: updated to v2.4 'en;fr'
  2007-02-23 note added to Key Modifiers by j.h
  2006-06-07 added link to path concept by j.h
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-path">
  <title>Paths</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Paths</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Paths</primary>
    <secondary>Tool</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Bézier curve</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    The Paths tool allows to create complex selections called Bézier Curves, a
    bit like the Free Selection tool but with all the adaptability of vectorial
    curves. You can edit your curve, you can paint with your curve, or even
    save, import, and export the curve. You can also use paths to create
    geometrical figures. Paths have their own dialog box:
    <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Dialog</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    See the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-paths">Path</link> concept.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paths</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-path.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the <keycap>B</keycap> keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <note>
      <para>
        Help messages pop up at the bottom of the image window to help you
        about all these keys.
      </para>
    </note>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This key has several functions depending on context. See Options
            for more details.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> ; <keycap>Alt</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Three modes are available to work with the Paths tool:
            <guilabel>Design</guilabel>,<guilabel>Edit</guilabel>
            and <guilabel>Move</guilabel>.  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key
            toggles between Design and Edit.  <keycap>Alt</keycap> (or
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>)
            key toggles between Design and Move.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-paths.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Normally, tool options are displayed in a window attached under the
      Toolbox as soon as you activate a tool. If they are not, you can access
      them from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Windows</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tool Options</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> which opens the option window of the selected tool.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edit Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Design</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  By default, this tool is in <guilabel>Design</guilabel> mode.
                  You draw the path by clicking successively. You can move
                  control points by clicking on them and dragging them. Between
                  control points are segments.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/tool-options/path-stroke.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para>
                        Numbers are steps to draw a two segments straight path.
                      </para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/tool-options/path-curve.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para>
                        Curved segments are easily built by dragging a segment or a
                        new node. Blue arrows indicate curve. Two little handles
                        appear that you can drag to bend the curve.
                      </para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                </para>
                <tip>
                  <para>
                    To quickly close the curve, click on the initial control point.
                    If you want to reposition the start node, hold <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                    and click to deselect the end node, then move the start node.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    You can use the
                    <guibutton>Selection from Path</guibutton> button or
                    <guiicon>
                      <inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                          <imagedata
                            fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-selection.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
                        </imageobject>
                      </inlinemediaobject>
                    </guiicon>
                    the <emphasis>Path to Selection</emphasis> button
                    in the Paths dialog to convert the path to a Selection.
                  </para>
                </tip>
                <tip>
                  <para>
                    When you have two handles, they work symmetrically by
                    default.  Release the pressure on the mouse button to move
                    handles individually. The <keycap>Shift</keycap> key will
                    force the handles to be symmetrical again.
                  </para>
                </tip>
                <para>Several functions are available in Design mode:</para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Inserting a new node</emphasis>:
                  When you press <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and hover the mouse pointer
                  over the existing path, the mouse pointer changes to the '+'
                  sign. Clicking will create a new path node in the hovered point
                  of the path.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Moving one or several nodes</emphasis>: On a node,
                  the mouse pointer becomes a 4-arrows cross. You can click
                  and drag it.
                  You can select several nodes by <keycap>Shift</keycap> and
                  click and move them by click and drag.
                  Pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt
                  </keycap></keycombo> allows to move all the path, as a
                  selection.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Modifying handles</emphasis>: You have to Edit a node
                  first. A handle appears. Drag it to bend the curve.
                  Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> toggles to symmetric handles.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Modify segment</emphasis>: When the mouse pointer
                  moves over a segment, it turns to a 4-arrows cross. Click and drag
                  it to bend the segment. As soon as you move it, handles appear
                  at both ends of the segment. Pressing the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
                  key toggles to symmetric handles.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Adding a new subpath</emphasis>:
                  When you press <keycap>Shift</keycap> and hover the mouse pointer
                  outside the existing path, the mouse pointer starts displaying
                  a square. Clicking will start a subpath that isn't connected
                  to other curves, but is considered a part of the path.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Edit (Ctrl)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> performs functions which are not
                  available in <guilabel>Design</guilabel> mode. With this
                  mode, you can work only on the existing path. When the mouse
                  pointer is not on the path, the pointer changes to a small crossed
                  circle and you can not do any path editing.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Add a segment between two nodes</emphasis>: Click
                  on a node at one end of the path to activate it. The pointer is
                  like a union symbol. Click on an other node to link both
                  nodes. This is useful when you have to link unclosed
                  components.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Remove a segment from a path</emphasis>: While pressing
                  <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
                  key combination, point to a segment. The mouse pointer turns to a
                  "-" sign. Click to delete the segment.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Add a node to a path</emphasis>: point to a
                  segment. Pointer turns to "+"". Click where you want to place
                  the new control point.
                </para>
                <para><emphasis>Remove a node</emphasis>: While pressing
                  <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
                  key combination, point to a node. Pointer turns
                  to "-"". Click to delete the node.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Add a handle to a node</emphasis>: Point to a
                  node. Pointer turns to small hand. Drag the node: handle
                  appears.
                  Pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> toggles to symmetric
                  handles.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Remove a handle from a node</emphasis>: While pressing
                  <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
                  key combination, point to a handle. The pointer
                  doesn't turn to the expected "-"" and remains a hand. Click
                  to delete the handle.
                </para>
                <caution>
                  <para>
                    There is no warning before removing a node, segment or a handle.
                  </para>
                </caution>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Move (Alt)</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Move</guilabel> mode allows to move one or all
                  components of a path. Simply click on the path and drag it.
                </para>
                <para>
                  If you have several components, only the selected one is moved. If
                  you click and drag outside the path, all components are moved.
                  Pressing the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key toggles between moving all
                  components and selected components only.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Polygonal</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this option, segments are linear only. Handles are not
            available and segments are not bent when moving them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Selection from Path</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This button allows creation of a selection that is based on
            the path in its present state. This selection is marked with
            the <link linkend="glossary-marching-ants"><quote>marching ants</quote>
            </link>. Note that the path is still present:
            the current tool is still the path tool and you can modify this
            path without modifying the selection that has become independent.
            If you change tools, the path becomes invisible, but it persists in
            the <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths Dialog</link> and you
            can re-activate it.
          </para>
          <para>
            If the path is not closed, GIMP will close it with a straight line.
          </para>
          <para>
            As the help pop-up tells, pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            when clicking on the button will add the new selection to an
            already existing one. Pressing <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> will
            subtract the selection from the pre-existing selection, and the
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
            key combination will intersect the two selections.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fill path</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This lets you fill an enclosed path with a solid color or
            pattern.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stroke path</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            See
            <xref linkend="gimp-path-stroke"/> and
            <xref linkend="gimp-using-paths"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

    <sect3>
    <title>Context Menu</title>
    <para>
      When right-clicking on path elements, like anchors or segments, a
      context menu will appear, the contents of which depends on the item
      you clicked on. The following commands may be shown in the context menu.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-path-path-tool-delete-anchor">
        <term>Delete Anchor</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command deletes the selected anchor and connects the segments
            before and after it.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-path-path-tool-shift-start">
        <term>Shift Start</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command shifts the start anchor to the selected anchor. The
            start anchor is where stroking starts. The start anchor has a
            pointy side indicating the stroking direction. This can be
            useful when you want to wrap
            <link linkend="gimp-text-tool-text-along-path">Text along Path</link>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Shifting the start anchor on open strokes may insert a new segment
            connecting the previous endpoints, and removes the segment leading
            into the new start anchor.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-path-path-tool-insert-anchor">
        <term>Insert Anchor</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command adds a new anchor on the selected spot on the segment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-path-path-tool-delete-segment">
        <term>Delete Segment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This command deletes the selected segment. This will create an
            opening in your path.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-path-path-tool-reverse-stroke">
        <term>Reverse Stroke</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This reverses the direction of the stroke. The shape of the start
            anchor will reflect the direction of the stroke. The pointy side
            is the direction it will go to when stroking.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
