<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2018-10-27 j.h: update to v2.10
  2015-12-12 j.h fix bug #675745: add on-canvas editor
  2012-03-18 j.h: update to v2.7
  2009-07-09 ude: added scroll wheel tip (#585823),
                  fixed "entering special chars" (#580532)
  2009-03-09 j.h: updated to v2.6
  2008-01-05 j.h: updated to v2.4.
  2006-06-17 added note for special characters by j.h
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-text">
  <title>Text</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Text</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Text</primary>
    <secondary>Tool</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The Text tool adds text to your image in a new layer. Text can be edited
    directly on canvas. A text tool editor, which shows up on top of the canvas
    above the text box, allows you to quickly change some of the text
    characteristics (for selected text or newly typed text only).
  </para>
  <para>
    As soon as you type your text, the text box appears on the canvas in a rectangular
    frame. If you draw the rectangular frame first, the text is automatically
    adapted to the frame size. You can enlarge this frame as you do with
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">rectangular selections</link>.
  </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/using/text-toolbar.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  <para>
    Right clicking
    on the text opens a context menu that allows you to copy, cut, paste, open
    a text file, change text orientation, and other text related commands.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can also use a separate Text Editor window by checking the
    <guilabel>Use editor window</guilabel> option in the Tool Options dialog.
    You can also use the <emphasis>Text Options dialog</emphasis> to change
    the font, color and size of your text, and justify it, interactively.
  </para>
  <para>
    In this chapter, tool options will be described. To know how to use the
    Text tool, please refer to <link linkend="gimp-text-management">text
    management</link>.
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Text</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-text.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the <keycap>T</keycap> keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-text.png"
format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Normally, tool options are displayed in a window attached under the
      Toolbox as soon as you activate a tool. If they are not, you can access
      them from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Windows</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tool Options</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> which opens the option window of the selected tool.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Font</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Click on the fonts button <guibutton>A&alpha;</guibutton> to open
            the font selector of this tool, which offers you a list of
            installed X fonts.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <para>
              At the bottom of the font selector you find some icons which
              act as buttons for:
            </para>
            <listitem>
              <para>resizing the font previews,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                selecting <emphasis>list view</emphasis> or <emphasis>grid
                view</emphasis>,
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                opening the <link linkend="gimp-font-dialog">font
                dialog</link>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            Choose a font from the installed fonts. When you select a font it
            is interactively applied to your text.
          </para>
          <tip>
            <!--cf. bug #585823 (2009-06-15)-->
            <para>
              You can use the scroll wheel of your pointing device (usually
              your mouse) on the fonts button in order to quickly change the
              font of your text (move the pointer on the fonts button, and
              don't click, just use the wheel button).
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This control sets the size of the font in any of several
            selectable units.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use editor window</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use an external editor window for text editing instead of
            direct-on-canvas editing.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show on-canvas editor</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Show a text tool editor on top of the canvas above the text box,
            which allows you to quickly change some of the text characteristics
            (for selected text or newly typed text only).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Antialiasing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When enabled, this will render the text with much smoother edges and
            curves. This is achieved by slight blurring and merging of the
            edges. This option can radically improve the visual appearance of
            the rendered typeface. Caution should be exercised when using
            anti-aliasing on images that are not in RGB color space.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hinting</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Uses the index of adjustment of the font to modify characters in
            order to produce clear letters in small font sizes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Color of the text that will be drawn next. Defaults to black.
            Selectable from the color picker dialog box that opens when the
            current color sample is clicked.
          </para>
          <tip>
            <para>
              You can also click-and-drag the color from the Toolbox color
              area onto the text.
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Style</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Style</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            This allows you to select how to style the text. The following
            choices are available.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Filled</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The inside of each character is filled with a solid color
                  defined by the <guilabel>Color</guilabel> option.
                  This is the default.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Outlined</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The edges of each character are painted based on the settings
                  below, and the inside is left transparent.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Outlined and filled</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  A combination of the above two settings. The inside of each
                  character is painted using the fill color.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <variablelist>
            <title>Outline Options</title>
            <para>
              Settings for <guilabel>Outlined</guilabel> and
              <guilabel>Outlined and filled</guilabel>.
            </para>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Solid color</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If this is selected, the outline is painted in the solid
                  color chosen here. To choose a color click the color button.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Pattern</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If this is selected, the outline is filled with the
                  pattern chosen here. To choose a pattern click the button
                  showing the current pattern, or start typing a name in the
                  text field next to it; it will show patterns starting with
                  the letters you entered.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Patterns work best with larger size outlines. This can be
                  set by changing <guilabel>Line width</guilabel>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Antialiasing</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Curves and lines at an angle may look jagged. When enabled,
                  this setting makes this smoother.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Line width</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  This sets the width of the text outline. By default, this is
                  measured in pixels, but you can select a different measurement
                  unit from the drop-down list.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Cap style</term>
              <term>Join style</term>
              <term>Miter limit</term>
              <term>Dash pattern</term>
              <term>Dash preset</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  See <link linkend="gimp-path-stroke-styles">Path stroking
                  styles</link>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Justify</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Justify</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Causes the text to be justified according to any of four rules
            selectable from the associated icons.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Indent</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Indent</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Controls the indent spacing from the left margin, for the first
            line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Adjust line spacing</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Line spacing</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            Controls the spacing between successive lines of text. This
            setting is interactive: it appears at the same time in image text.
            The number is not the space between lines itself, but how many
            pixels must be added to or subtracted from this space (the value
            can be negative).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Adjust letter spacing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Controls the spacing between letters. Also in this case the number
            is not the space itself between letters, but how many pixels must
            be added to or subtracted from this space (the value can be
            negative).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Box</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Concerns the text box. The associated drop-down list offers two
            options:
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Dynamic</emphasis>: default option. The size
            of the text box increases as you type. Text may go out of the
            image. You have to press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key to add a
            new line. The indent option indents all lines. If you increase the
            box size, the option turns to "Fixed".
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Fixed</emphasis>: you must enlarge the text
            box first. Else, usual shortcuts are active! The text is limited
            by the right side of the box and continues on next line. This is
            not true new line: you must press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key
            to add a real new line. The text may go out the lower border of the
            image. The indent option works on the first line only.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Language</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The text language may have an effect on the way the text is
            rendered. If you enter a letter in this field, you get a list
            of all available languages whose names begin with this letter.
            Select the language in which you are entering your text.
          </para>
          <para>
            Right clicking on this field opens the context menu which allows
            you to paste language names from the clipboard.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-text-editor-dialog">
    <title>Text Editor</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Editor</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>The Text Editor</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/text-editor-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      This text editor is only available if the
      <guilabel>Use editor window</guilabel>
      option is checked in Tool Options.
    </para>
    <para>
      As soon as you start writing, a Text layer is created in the Layer
      Dialog. On an image with such a layer (the image you are working on, or
      a <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> image), you can resume
      text editing by activating this text layer then clicking on it (double
      click). Of course, you can apply to this text layer the same functions
      you use with other layers.
    </para>
    <para>
      To add another text to your image click on a non-text layer: a new Text
      Editor will appear and a new text layer will be created. To pass from a
      text to another one activate the corresponding text layer and click on
      it to activate the editor.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <title>The Text Editor options</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Text</primary>
        <secondary>Load from file</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        All these options are also in the text context menu.
      </para>
      <para>
        Vertical text (top-to-bottom writing) is supported and particularly
        useful for East-Asian writing systems, but also for anyone wishing to
        design fancy vertical text.
      </para>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Load text from file</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Text can be loaded from a text file by clicking the folder icon in
            the text editor. All the text in the file is loaded.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Clear all text</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Clear all the text.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>From left to right</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option causes text to be entered from left to right, as
            is the case with most Western languages and may Eastern
            languages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>From right to left</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option allows text to be entered from right to left, as is
            the case with some Eastern languages, such as Arabic (illustrated
            in the icon).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Vertical, right to left (mixed orientation)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Text is written top-to-bottom in columns, from right to left, and
            is rotated 90° clockwise.
          </para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-orientation-RLM.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Vertical, right to left (upright orientation)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Text is written top-to-bottom in columns, from right to left,
            upright.
          </para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-orientation-RLU.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Vertical, left to right (mixed orientation)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Text is written top-to-bottom in columns, from left to right, and
            is rotated 90° clockwise.
          </para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-orientation-LRM.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Vertical, left to right (upright orientation)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Text is written top-to-bottom in columns, from left to right,
            upright.
          </para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/toolbox/text-orientation-LRU.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use selected font</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Default doesn't use the font you have selected in the Options
            dialog. If you want to use it, check this option.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              See also <xref linkend="gimp-using-text"/>
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
