<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-11-30 informalfigure replaced by figure by lexa
  050815 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
  -->
<sect2 id='gimp-tool-bucket-fill' lang="de;en;es;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="de;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-08-15</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-05-31</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title lang="en">Bucket Fill</title>
  <title lang="de">Füllen (Fülleimer)</title>
  <title lang="es">Relleno de cubeta</title>
  <title lang="fr">Remplissage</title>
  <title lang="it">Riempimento colore</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">油漆桶填充</title>
  
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Bucket Fill</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Bucket Fill</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary>
    <secondary>Füllen (Fülleimer)</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Füllen (Fülleimer)</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Herramientas</primary>
    <secondary>Relleno</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Relleno</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Outils</primary>
    <secondary>Remplir</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Remplissage (Outil)</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Pot de peinture</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary>
    <secondary>Riempimento colore</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Riempimento colore</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>工具箱</primary>
    <secondary>填充</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;zh_CN">Toolbox Fill</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Riempimento colore</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Das Dialogfenster des Werkzeuges<quote>Füllen</quote>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        La herramienta de Relleno en la Caja de herramientas
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">L'outil <quote>Remplissage</quote> dans la Boîte à 
      outils
      </phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-fill.png'
                   format="PNG" lang='en;es'/>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-fill.png'
                   format="PNG" lang="de" />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-fill.png'
                   format="PNG" lang='fr' />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-fill.png'
                   format="PNG" lang='it' />
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-fill.png'
                   format="PNG" lang='zh_CN' />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    This tool fills a selection with the current foreground color. If
    you Shift+click and use the Bucket tool, it will use the
    background color instead. Depending on how the tool options are
    set, the Bucket Fill tool will either fill the entire selection,
    or only parts whose colors are similar to the point you click on.
    The tool options also affect the way transparency is handled.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The amount of fill depends on what Fill Threshold you have
    specified. The fill threshold determines how far the fill will
    spread (similar to the way in which the magic wand works). The
    fill starts at the point where you click and spreads outward until
    the color or alpha value becomes <quote>too different</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    When you fill objects in a transparent layer (such as letters in a
    text layer) with a different color than before, you may find that
    a border of the old color still surrounds the objects. This is due
    to a low fill-threshold in the Bucket Fill options dialog. With a
    low threshold, the bucket tool won't fill semi-transparent pixels,
    and they will stand out against the fill because they have kept
    their original color. If you want to fill areas that are totally
    transparent, you have to choose right-click|Select|Select All, and
    make sure that the layer's <quote>Keep Transparency</quote> button (in
    the Layers dialog) is unchecked. If the Keep Transparency button is
    checked, only the opaque parts of the layer will be filled, and if
    you don't use the Select All command, only the opaque
    <quote>island</quote> that you clicked on will be filled.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Füllen</quote> oder Fülleimer wird benutzt, um
    Bildbereiche mit der Vordergrundfarbe zu füllen. Wenn Sie bei der
    Anwendung des Werkzeuges die Taste <keycap>Shift</keycap> gedrückt halten,
    wird zum Füllen die aktuelle Hintergrundfarbe verwendet. Für die Füllart
    stehen Vorder-, und Hintergrundfarbe, sowie Muster zur Auswahl. Gerade
    beim Füllen von grösseren Bildbereichen, kann es sehr hilfreich sein, 
    ähnliche Farben mit zu füllen. Das Werkzeug kann darüberhinaus auch die
    Transparenz von Bildteilen beeinflussen.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die Grösse der gefüllten Bildteile hängt wesentlich vom eingestellten
    Schwellwert ab. Mit diesem können Sie beeinflussen, wie weit sich die
    eingefüllte Farbe verteilt. Dies funktioniert ähnlich wie beim Werkzeug
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-fuzzy-select">Zauberstab</link>. Das Füllen
    beginnt an dem Pixel auf den Sie das Werkzeug durch Klicken anwenden und
    breitet sich von dort aus, bis die Bildfarbe oder der Wert des Alphakanals
    <quote>zu verschieden</quote> werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Wenn Sie Objekte auf einer transparenten Ebene (Beispielsweise Buchstaben
    auf einer Textebene) mit einer neuen Farbe füllen, kann es passieren, dass
    die alte Farbe immernoch am Rand des Objektes erscheint. Die Ursache
    dafür ist ein niedriger Schwellwert des Werkzeuges. Mit einem geringen
    Schwellwert füllt das Werkzeug halbtransparente Pixel nicht und diese
    behalten daher ihre alte Farbe. Wenn Sie Bereiche füllen wollen, welche
    komplett transparent sind, wählen Sie den Menüeintrag
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu><accel>A</accel>uswahl</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>lles</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    und stellen Sie sicher, dass die Eigenschaft
    <guilabel>Transparenz erhalten</guilabel> (zu finden im Ebenendialog)
    angeschaltet ist. Ist diese Eigenschaft ausgeschaltet, werden nur die
    nichttransparenten Bereiche der Ebene gefüllt, und wenn Sie vergessen
    den Befehl <quote>Alles auswählen</quote> auszuführen, wird nur die
    bedeckte <quote>Insel</quote> auf die Sie geklickt haben, gefüllt.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    Esta herramienta rellena la selección con el color de frente
    actual.  Si realizas la operación manteniendo la tecla Shift
    presionada, se usará el color de fondo.  Dependiendo de cómo se
    hayan colocado las opciones, la herramienta rellenará la selección
    entera, o sólo las partes que tengan un color cercano al del punto
    en donde hagas clic.  Las opciones también afectan la forma en que
    la transparencia es tratada.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    La cantidad de relleno depende del Umbral de relleno que hayas
    especificado.  El umbral de relleno determina qué tan lejos se
    esparcirá el color (es similar a la forma en que trabaja la
    selección difusa).  El relleno empieza en el punto en que haces
    clic y se esparce hasta que el valor del color o del alfa se
    vuelve <quote>demasiado diferente</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Cuando rellenas objetos en una capa transparente (como letras en
    una capa de texto) con un color diferente al anterior, puedes
    encontrar que todavía queda un borde del color antigüo alrededor
    de los objetos.  Esto se debe a que hay un bajo umbral de relleno
    colocado en el diálogo de opciones del Relleno de cubeta.  Con un
    umbral bajo, el relleno de cubeta no llenará pixeles
    semi-transparentes, y se notará la diferencia con el área rellena
    porque conservarán su color.  Si quieres llenar áreas que son
    completamente transparentes, debes seleccionar
    clic-derecho|Seleccionar|Todos, y asegurarte que el botón
    <quote>Mantener transparencia</quote> (en el Diálogo de capas)
    esté desactivado.  Si el botón se encontrara activado, sólo las
    partes opacas de la capa serán llenadas, y si no utilizas el
    comando Seleccionar todos, sólo la <quote>isla opaca</quote> en la
    que hagas clic será rellenada.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil Remplissage (Pot de peinture) est utilisé pour remplir des 
    plages d'un calque ou d'une sélection avec une couleur ou un motif. La 
    couleur est versée et s'étale à partir du point cliqué jusqu'à 
    rencontrer des pixels dont la couleur dépasse un seuil donné. 
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    Quand vous remplissez des objets dans un calque transparent (par 
    exemple des lettres dans un calque de texte) avec une couleur 
    différente de la couleur d'origine des objets, vous pouvez avoir 
    une bordure de la couleur ancienne qui entoure les objets. C'est 
    dû au choix d'un seuil trop bas dans le dialogue des options de 
    l'outil Remplissage. Avec un seuil bas, l'outil ne remplira pas 
    les pixels semi-transparents d'une bordure adoucie. Si vous 
    voulez remplir des surfaces complètement transparentes, vous 
    devez sélectionner tous les calques par un clic droit sur le 
    dialogue des calques et vous assurer que l'option <quote>Garder
    la transparence</quote> de ce dialogue n'est pas cochée. Si l'option
    <quote>Garder la transparence</quote> n'est pas activée, seules les
    parties opaques du calque seront remplies et si vous n'utilisez pas la
    commande Tout Sélectionner, seuls les <quote>îlots</quote> opaques sur
    lesquels vous avez cliqué seront remplis.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="it">
    Questo strumento riempie una selezione con il corrente 
    colore di primo piano. Se si tiene premuto Ctrl mentre si fa 
    clic sarà usato il colore di sfondo. A seconda delle opzioni
    scelte, lo strumento riempirà l'intera selezione o solo le parti
    i cui colori sono simili al punto in cui si è fatto clic.
    Altre opzioni riguardano il modo in cui è gestita la trasparenza.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    L'ammontare del riempimento dipenderà dal valore scelto in
    soglia. La soglia di riempimento determina quanto lontano 
    si diffonderà il riempimento (in maniera simile a come avviene 
    per la selezione fuzzy). Il riempimento inizia nel punto in cui 
    si fa clic e si diffonde finché il valore del colore o della trasparenza
    diventa "troppo diverso".
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Quando si riempiono oggetti su un livello trasparente (come le 
    lettere in un livello di testo) con un colore diverso dal preesistente, 
    si può riscontrare la presenza di un leggero bordo del colore 
    precedente che circonda gli oggetti. Questo fenomeno è dovuto
    ad una soglia di riempimento troppo bassa nella finestra delle opzioni
    dello strumento riempimento colore. Con una soglia bassa, lo 
    strumento non riempirà i pixel semitrasparenti che emergeranno 
    contro il riempimento poiché hanno  mantenuto il loro colore originale.
    Se si vogliono riempire le aree che sono totalmente trasparenti
    si deve scegliere: tasto destro del mouse | seleziona | seleziona tutto,
    e assicurarsi che la casella "mantieni trasparenza" (nella finestra
    di dialogo livelli) non sia spuntata. Se la casella "mantieni 
    trasparenza" è spuntata, solo le parti opache del livello saranno 
    riempite e se non si usa il comando seleziona tutto, solo l'"isola" 
    opaca su cui si è fatto clic sarà riempita.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该工具用当前前景色填充一个选区。按住 Shift 并点击油漆桶工具，则会用背景色填充。油漆桶填充工具根据选项设置，决定是填充整个选区还是仅仅是和您点击处颜色相近的区域。工具选项也能控制其透明度。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    填充量由您设定的填充阈值决定。填充阈值决定填充的扩展程度。填充将从您点的地方开始向外扩展直到颜色或 alpha 值变得“很不相同”为止。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    当填充带有透明图层的物体(比如文字图层上的字母)时，您可能发现物体周围仍然有以前的颜色。这是因为油漆桶填充工具选项中的阈值太低了。由于低阈值,油漆桶填充工具无法填充吧半透明像素，这些带有以前颜色的像素就很明显。当您要填充完全透明的区域时，可以右键|选择|全部,并确保图层对话框中该图层的“保持透明部分”勾选框没有勾上。如果勾选保持透明部分，就只有图层的不透明部分会被填充，要是没用全选命令，则只有您点击处的不透明“岛屿”会被填充。
  </para>  
  
  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Activate Tool</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="es">Activar la herramienta</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activer l'outil</title>
    <title lang="it">Attivazione dello strumento</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>

  <itemizedlist lang="en">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The Bucket Fill can be called in the following
        order, from the image-menu:
        <guimenuitem><accel>T</accel>ools</guimenuitem>/
        <guimenuitem><accel>P</accel>aint
          Tools</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>B</accel>ucket
          Fill.</guimenuitem> 
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        The Tool can also be called by clicking the tool icon:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  
              <para lang="de">
                      Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten das Werkzeug <quote>Füllen</quote>
    zu aktivieren:
              </para>
  <itemizedlist lang="de">
    <listitem>
                              <para>
                                      Über das Menü
                                      <menuchoice>
                                              <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>alwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
                                  <guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>üllen</guimenuitem>
                                      </menuchoice>
                                      im Bildfenster,
                              </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                              <para>
                                      Mit einen Mausklick auf das Symbol
                    <guiicon>
                                              <inlinemediaobject>
                                                      <imageobject>
                                                              <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fill.png"></imagedata>
                                                      </imageobject>
                                              </inlinemediaobject>
                                      </guiicon>
                                      im Werkzeugfenster, sowie
                              </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                              <para>
                                      Über das Tastenkürzel
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>.
                              </para>
                      </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist lang="es">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        El relleno de cubeta puede ser activado siguiendo el menú de
        imagen en el siguiente orden:
        <guimenuitem><accel>H</accel>erramientas</guimenuitem>/
        <guimenuitem>Herramientas de
        <accel>p</accel>intura</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>elleno.</guimenuitem>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        La herramienta también puede activarse clicando en el ícono:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist lang="fr">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        L'outil Remplissage peut être appelé à partir du menu-image 
        et de la barre de menus de la fenêtre d'image:
        <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
        <guimenuitem>Outils de d<accel>e</accel>ssin</guimenuitem>
        /<guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>emplissage</guimenuitem> 
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        L'outil peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône 
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        dans la Boîte à outils. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <itemizedlist lang="it">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Lo strumento riempimento colore  può essere invocato dal menu 
        immagine seguendo questo ordine:
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>S<accel>t</accel>rumenti</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu><accel>D</accel>isegno</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>iempimento colore</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        Lo strumento può essere attivato anche facendo clic su 
        questa icona:
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
               <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        按如下步骤启动油漆桶填充工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>涂画工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>油漆桶填充工具</guimenuitem>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        也可以点工具图标：
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3>
  <title lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</title>
  <title lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</title>
  <title lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (por defecto)</title>
  <title lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</title>
  <title lang="it">Tasti modificatori (Predefiniti)</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</title>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Shortcut</term>
      <term lang="de">Tastenkürzel</term>
      <term lang="es">Atajo de teclado</term>
      <term lang="fr">Raccourcis clavier</term>
      <term lang="it">Scorciatoia</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">快捷键</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The <keycombo> <keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>b</keycap>
          </keycombo> keys will change the active tool to Bucket 
          Fill.
        </para>
        
        <para lang="de">
          Die Tastenkombination 
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            <keycap>B</keycap>
          </keycombo>
            aktiviert das Werkzeug <quote>Füllen</quote>.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          Las teclas <keycombo> <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          <keycap>b</keycap> </keycombo> cambiarán la herramienta
          activa al Relleno de cubeta.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          La combinaison de touches <keycombo> <keycap>Maj</keycap>
          <keycap>b</keycap> </keycombo> Sélectionnera l'outil de
          Remplissage.
        </para>
        
        <para lang="it">
          I tasti <keycombo> <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> <keycap>b</keycap>
          </keycombo> cambiano lo strumento attivo in riempimento colore
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycombo> <keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>b</keycap> </keycombo>将转到油漆桶填充工具。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en;es"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
      <term lang="de"><keycap>Strg</keycap></term>
      <term lang="fr"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
      <term lang="it"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
      <term lang="zh_CN"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          toggles the use of BG Color Fill or FG Color Fill on the fly.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Mit der <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste lässt sich leicht
          zwischen der Vordergrund- oder Hintergrundfarbe, als
          Füllart wechseln.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> cambia el uso del color de fondo o del
          color de frente.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          bascule de la couleur de remplissage premier plan à la couleur
          d'arrière-plan et inversement.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> commuta, al volo, l'uso del colore di sfondo 
          con quello di primo piano e viceversa.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 快速切换前景色填充和背景色填充。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en;es"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
      <term lang="de"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
      <term lang="fr"><keycap>Maj</keycap></term>
      <term lang="it"><keycap>maiusc</keycap></term>
      <term lang="zh_CN"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          toggles the use of Fill Similar Color or Fill Whole Selection on
          the fly.
        </para>          
        <para lang="de">
          Schaltet die Eigenschaft <quote>Beeinflusster Bereich</quote>
          zwischen <guilabel>Ähnliche Farben</guilabel> und <guilabel>Ganze
          Auswahl füllen</guilabel> um.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          <keycap>Shift</keycap> cambia el uso de Rellenar colores
          similares a Rellenar la selección completamente.
        </para>          
        <para lang="fr">
          bascule de l'option Remplir la couleur similaire à Remplir toute
          la Sélection et inversement.
        </para>         
        <para lang="it">
          Il tasto <keycap>maiusc</keycap> scambia al volo l'area di 
          riempimento tra l'intera selezione e quella con colori simili.
        </para>          
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycap>Shift</keycap> 快速切换填充相近的颜色还是整个选区。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>

<sect3>
  <title lang="en">Options</title>
  <title lang="de">Eigenschaften</title>
  <title lang="es">Opciones</title>
  <title lang="fr">Options</title>
  <title lang="it">Opzioni</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
  
  <figure lang="de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Eigenschaften für das Werkzeug <quote>Füllen</quote>
      </phrase>
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-fill.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Overview</term>
      <term lang="de">Übersicht</term>
      <term lang="es">Descripción</term>
      <term lang="fr">Vue d'ensemble</term>
      <term lang="it">Descrizione</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">概述</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The available tool options for the Fill Tool can be accessed
          by
          double clicking the Fill Tool icon.
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Die Werkzeugeinstellungen für das Werkzeug lassen
          sich durch einen Doppelklick auf das Symbol 
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          anzeigen.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Las opciones disponibles para la herramienta de Relleno
          pueden ser accedidas realizando doble clic en su ícono.
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On obtient les options disponibles pour l'outil 
          Remplissage par un double clic sur l'icône  de 
          cet outil.
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para> 
        <para lang="it">
           Le opzioni disponibili per lo strumento riempimento colore 
           possono essere raggiunte con un doppio clic sull'icona dello 
           strumento stesso:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                 <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          双击油漆桶填充工具图标可以得到可用的工具选项。
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fill.png' />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>  
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
      <term lang="de">Deckkraft</term>
      <term lang="es">Opacidad</term>
      <term lang="fr">Opacité</term>
      <term lang="it">Opacità</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">不透明度</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The Opacity slider sets the transparency level for the 
          fill. A higher opacity setting results in a more opaque 
          fill and a lower setting results in a more transparent fill.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Mit dem Schieberegler können Sie die Deckkraft des
          Werkzeuges einstellen. Der Regler kann Werte zwischen 100 (voller)
          und 0 (keiner) Deckkraft annehmen. 
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          El control de opacidad asigna el nivel de transparencia para
          el relleno.  Un nivel de opacidad alto resulta en un relleno
          más opaco y un nivel bajo resulta en un relleno más
          transparente.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le curseur Opacité règle le niveau de transparence du 
          remplissage. Plus l'opacité est élevée et plus le 
          remplissage est opaque et inversement.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          La barra orizzontale opacità imposta il livello di 
          trasparenza per il riempimento. Un livello più alto renderà
          il riempimento più opaco, mentre uno più basso lo 
          renderà più trasparente.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          不透明度滑条设置填充的透明程度。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Mode</term>
      <term lang="de">Modus</term>
      <term lang="es">Modo</term>
      <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
      <term lang="it">Modalità</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">模式</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          The Mode dropdown list provides a selection of paint 
          application modes. A list of these modes can be found in the 
          <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossary</link>. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Die verfügbaren Modi verändern die Art und Weise, wie
          die Pixel auf die Ebene gezeichnet werden. Ähnlich den Modi
          der Ebenen, repräsentieren die Füllmodi eine Überblendung mit der
          ausgewählten Füllfarbe (-muster) und der zu füllenden Ebene. Mehr
          über die Modi, die <acronym>GIMP</acronym> zur Verfügung stellt,
          finden Sie im <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossar</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="es">
        <para>
          La lista desplegable Modo permite seleccionar uno de los
          modos de aplicación de la pintura.  Una lista de estos modos
          se encuentra en el <link
          linkend='glossary-modes'>glosario</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          La liste déroulante Mode fournit une sélection des modes 
          d'application de la peinture. Une liste de ces modes se 
          trouve dans le 
          <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossaire</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="it">
        <para>
          Il menu a tendina modalità fornisce una selezione di
          modalità di colore. Una lista di queste modalità possono
          essere trovate nel 
          <link linkend='glossary-modes'>glossario</link>. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          模式下拉列表提供一系列涂画应用模式。术语表中右这些模式的列表。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry lang="en;es;fr;it;zh_CN">
      <term lang="en">Pattern</term>
      <term lang="es">Patrón</term>
      <term lang="fr">Motif</term>
      <term lang="it">Motivi</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">图案</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This dropdown list allows the user to select one of many
          fill patterns to use on the next fill operation.  The manner
          in which the list is presented is controlled by the four
          buttons at the bottom of the selector.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Esta lista desplegable permite seleccionar uno de muchos
          patrones de relleno para ser usado en la siguiente
          operación.  La manera en que la lista es presentada es
          controlada por cuatro botones en la parte inferior del
          selector.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Vous indique le motif courant. En cliquant dans la fenêtre 
          de présentation des motifs adjacente, vous développez 
          la liste des motifs et vous pouvez en choisir un autre.
          Les boutons situés en bas de cette liste permettent 
          d'afficher différemment cette liste: les bulles d'aide sont 
          claires.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Questo menu a tendina consente all'utente di selezionare
          uno dei tanti motivi da usare nella successiva operazione 
          di riempimento. Il modo in cui la lista si presenta è controllata 
          dai pulsanti presenti in basso nel menu stesso.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该下拉列表让用户在众多的图案中选择一个应用于下次填充操作。列表下部的四个按键可以控制列表显示方式。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Fill Type</term>
      <term lang="de">Füllart</term>
      <term lang="es">Tipo de relleno</term>
      <term lang="fr">Type de remplissage</term>
      <term lang="it">Modalità di riempimento</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">填充类型</term>

      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> provides three fill types: <guilabel>FG
            Color Fill</guilabel>, <guilabel>BG Color Fill</guilabel> and
          <guilabel>Pattern Fill</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>FG Color Fill</guilabel> sets the fill color to the
          currently selected foreground color.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>BG Color Fill</guilabel> sets the fill color to the
          currently selected background color.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Pattern Fill</guilabel> sets the fill color to the
          currently selected pattern.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> stellt drei verschiedene Füllarten zur
          Verfügung: Füllen mit der <guilabel>Vordergrundfarbe (VG)
          </guilabel>, <guilabel>Hintergrundfarbe (HG)</guilabel> und 
          einem <guilabel>Muster</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Bei aktivierter Einstellung <guilabel>VG-Farbe</guilabel>, wird
          die nächste Füllung mit der aktuellen Vordergrundfarbe ausgeführt.
        </para>
        <para>
          Ähnlich verhalten sich die zwei weiteren Einstellungen. So lässt
          sich bei aktivierter Einstellung <guilabel>HG-Farbe</guilabel> mit
          der Hintergrundfarbe und bei aktivem <guilabel>Muster</guilabel>,
          mit dem ausgewählten Muster füllen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="es">
        <para>
          El <acronym>Gimp</acronym> proporciona tres tipos de
          relleno: <guilabel>Relleno con color de frente</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Relleno con color de fondo</guilabel> y
          <guilabel>Relleno con patrón</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para>
          El <guilabel>Relleno con color de frente</guilabel> asigna
          el color de frente actual al color del relleno.</para>
        <para>
          El <guilabel>Relleno con color de fondo</guilabel> asigna el
          color de fondo actual al color del relleno.
        </para>
        <para>
          El <guilabel>Relleno con patrón</guilabel> asigna el patrón
          actualmente seleccionado al color del relleno.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> fournit trois types de remplissage:
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Remplissage par couleur de PP</guilabel> utilise la
          couleur de premier plan pour remplir.
          en cours.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Remplissage avec couleur d'AP</guilabel> utilise la
          couleur d'arrière-plan, ou couleur de fond, pour remplir.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Remplissage par Motif</guilabel> utilise le motif 
          en cours pour remplir.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="it">
        <para>
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> consente tre tipologie di
          riempimento: <guilabel>Riempimento colore di primo piano</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Riempimento colore di sfondo</guilabel> e
          <guilabel>Riempimento a motivo</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Riempimento colore di primo piano</guilabel> 
          imposta il colore di riempimento al colore di primo piano
          attualmente selezionato.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Riempimento colore di sfondo</guilabel> 
          imposta il colore di riempimento al colore di sfondo 
          attualmente selezionato.
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Riempimento a motivo</guilabel> imposta il colore
          di riempimento al motivo attualmente selezionato.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>提供三种填充类型：<guilabel>前景色填充</guilabel>, <guilabel>背景色填充</guilabel>和<guilabel>图案填充</guilabel>。
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>前景色填充</guilabel>用当前选取的前景色做为填充颜色。
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>背景色填充</guilabel>用当前选取的背景色做为填充颜色。
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>图案填充</guilabel>用当前选取的图案做为填充颜色。
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Affected Area</term>
      <term lang="de">Beeinflusster Bereich</term> 
      <term lang="es">Área afectada</term>
      <term lang="fr">Aire affectée</term>
      <term lang="it">Area coinvolta</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">影响区域</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
       <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Fill similar colors</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This is the default setting: the tool fills the area with a
                color near the pixel onto you have clicked. The color
                similarity is defined by a brightness threshold, that you
                can set by a value or by a cursor position.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Fill whole selection</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This option makes GIMP fill a preexistent selection or the
                whole image. A quicker approach to do the same thing could
                be to click and drag the foreground, background or pattern
                color, leaving it onto the selection.
              </para> 
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Ähnliche Farben füllen</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Das Füllwerkzeug kann nicht nur eine Farbe ersetzen
                (füllen), sondern auch Farben die sich nur wenig in der
                Helligkeit unterscheiden und somit ähnlich sind. Die
                Ähnlichkeit der Farben lässt sich mit dem Schwellwert
                einstellen.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Ganze Auswahl füllen</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Füllt eine bestehende Auswahl oder das ganze Bild.
              </para> 
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="es">
       <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Rellenar colores similares</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Ésta es la opción por defecto: la herramienta rellena
                el área que tenga el color parecido al pixel en que
                hayas clicado.  La similitud del color es definida por
                el umbral de brillo, que puedes cambiar dando un valor
                o dando una posición del cursor.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Rellenar la selección completamente</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Esta opción hace que el <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
                rellene toda la selección existente.  Si no hay una
                selección definida se rellena toda la imagen. Una
                alternativa más rápida para realizar la misma tarea
                consiste en arrastrar el color de frente, de fondo o
                el patrón hasta la selección.
              </para> 
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Remplir les couleurs similaires</guilabel>: 
            C'est l'option par défaut: l'outil remplit l'aire ayant 
            une couleur similaire à celle du pixel cliqué. La 
            similarité de couleur est définie par un seuil de 
            différence de luminosité réglé par le curseur Seuil. 
            </para>
            <para>
            En pressant la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> on bascule sur 
            l'option Remplir toute la sélection.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guilabel>Remplir toute la sélection</guilabel>: Avec 
              cette option, la sélection active (ou l'ensemble de 
              l'image si pas de sélection) est complètement remplie 
              par la couleur. Une façon plus directe de réaliser la 
              même chose est de cliquer-glisser la couleur de premier 
              ou d'arrière-plan, ou le motif, jusque sur le calque ou 
              la sélection.
            </para> 
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="it">
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Riempi i colori simili</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                È l'opzione predefinita: lo strumento riempie l'area avente
                un colore simile a quella del pixel su cui si è fatto
                clic. La similitudine del colore è definita da una soglia
                di differenza di luminosità, specificabile tramite un valore
                oppore tramite il cursore.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Riempi intera selezione</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Riempie una selezione preesistente oppure l'immagine
                intera. Un modo più diretto di realizzare la stessa
                operazione è di fare clic e trascinare, il colore dal primo
                piano o dallo sfondo oppure il motivo, fino alla selezione.
              </para> 
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          FIXME
        </para>
      </listitem>  
    </varlistentry>  

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Finding Similar Colors</term>
      <term lang="de">Ähnliche Farben finden</term>
      <term lang="es">Buscando colores similares</term>
      <term lang="fr">Recherche de couleurs similaires</term>
      <term lang="it">Trova colori simili</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">寻找相近的颜色</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          Under this section you can find two options:
        </para> 
        <para>
          The option <guilabel>Fill Transparent Areas</guilabel> 
          offers the possibility of filling areas with low opacity.
        </para> 
        <para>
          The option <guilabel>Sample Merged</guilabel> toggles the
          sampling from all layers. If Sample Merged is active, fills 
          can be made on a lower layer, while the color information 
          used for threshold checking is located further up. Simply 
          select the lower level and ensure that a layer above is 
          visible for color weighting.
        </para>
        <para>
          The Threshold slider sets the level at which color weights 
          are measured for fill boundaries. A higher setting will 
          fill more of a multi colored image and conversely, a lower 
          setting will fill less area.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Unter <guilabel>Ähnliche Farben finden</guilabel> sind drei
          Einstellungen untergebracht: <guilabel>Transparente Bereiche
          füllen</guilabel>, <guilabel>Vereinigung abtasten</guilabel> und
          der <guilabel>Schwellwert</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Transparente Bereiche füllen</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Diese Einstellung bietet die Möglichkeit auch transparente
                Bereiche, die keine oder nur eine geringe Deckkraft besitzen
                zu füllen.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Vereinigung abtasten</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Durch diese Einstellung ist es möglich, den Auswahlbereich
                zu beeinflussen, den das Füllwerkzeug selektiert. Wenn
                dieses Kontrollkästchen aktiviert ist, wird die Auswahl von
                allen sichtbaren Ebenen beeinflusst. Weitere Informationen
                zu <link linkend='glossary-samplemerge'>Vereinigung abtasten
                </link> bietet das Glossar.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Schwelle</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Der Schieberegler <guilabel>Schwelle</guilabel> bietet Ihnen die
                Möglichkeit, den Schwellwert einzustellen. Es werden bei niedrigem 
                Schwellwert (0) keine ähnlichen Farben mit in die Füllung
                einbezogen. Je höher der Schwellwert, desto mehr umliegende Farben
                werden mit in die Füllung einbezogen. Bei ausgewähltem Maximalwert
                von 255, wird die gesamte Ebene gefüllt.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="es">
        <para>
          Bajo esta sección puedes encontrar dos opciones:
        </para> 
        <para>
          La opción <guilabel>Rellenar áreas transparentes</guilabel>
          ofrece la posibilidad de rellenar áreas con baja opacidad.
        </para> 
        <para>
          La opción <guilabel>Muestra combinada</guilabel> activa el
          muestreo para todas las capas.  Si esta opción se encuentra
          activa, el relleno puede hacerse sobre una capa más baja,
          mientras la información de color usada para determinar el
          área de relleno está en las capas superiores.  Simplemente
          selecciona la capa baja y asegúrate que una capa superior
          esté visible.
        </para>
        <para>
          El control de Umbral determina el nivel en que el peso del
          color es mesurado para rellenar el espacio.  Un nivel alto
          rellenará área de una imagen con color más variado, mientras
          que un nivel bajo rellenará menos área.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          <guilabel>Remplir les régions transparentes</guilabel>: 
          Cette option permet de remplir aussi les régions plus ou 
          moins transparentes.
        </para>
        <para>
          Avec l'option <guilabel>Echantillonner sur tous les calques
          </guilabel>, la couleur choisie pour chaque pixel est la 
          couleur vue effectivement dans l'image, c-à-d qu'elle  est 
          la combinaison des couleurs de ce pixel dans les différents 
          calques composant l'image, à condition bien sûr qu'ils 
          soient suffisamment transparents. Le seuil s'applique alors 
           aux différents calques.
        </para>
        <para>
          Le curseur Seuil fixe l'intensité de couleur à partir duquel 
          la couleur cessera de diffuser lors du remplissage. Avec un 
          seuil élevé, le remplissage sera plus étendu qu'avec un 
          seuil moindre.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="it">
        <para>
          In questa sezione ci sono due opzioni:
        </para> 
        <para>
          L'opzione <guilabel>riempi aree trasparenti</guilabel>
          offre la possibilità di riempire aree con bassa opacità.
        </para> 
        <para>
          L'opzione <guilabel>campiona a video</guilabel> imposta
          il campionamento da tutti i livelli. Se campiona a video è attivo,
          i riempimenti possono essere effettuati su un livello sottostante,
          mentre le informazioni sul colore usate per la soglia sono 
          locate più in alto. In parole povere si può selezionare un livello
          più basso e assicurarsi che un livello superiore sia visibile
          per il peso colore.
        </para>
        <para>
          La barra orizzontale soglia imposta il livello al quale i
          pesi colore sono misurati per i confini del riempimento.
          Una impostazione più elevata riempirà una parte 
          maggiore di una immagine multicolore e, per contro,
          una impostazione più bassa riempirà di meno l'area.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          <guilabel>位样合并</guilabel>选项切换是否从所有图层中取样。当勾选位样合并，填充能在一个更下面的图层进行，同时被用作阈值检查的颜色信息位于更上面。简单地选中更下面图层并确保在其上面的一个图层其颜色深度是可见的。
        </para>
        <para>
          阈值滑条设定填充边缘所使用颜色重量级别。高值将填充一个多色图像更多的区域，而低值则填充更少的区域。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
