<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<!-- 050523 de reviewed by axel.wernicke -->
<sect2 id='gimp-tool-convolve' lang="cs;en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="cs">Změna ostrosti</title>
  <title lang="en">Convolve (Blur/Sharpen)</title>
  <title lang="de">Verknüpfen (Weichzeichnen/Schärfen)</title>
  <title lang="fr">Goutte d'eau</title>  <!--050505-->
  <title lang="zh_CN">卷积工具(模糊/锐化)</title>

  <indexterm lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
    <primary lang="cs">Panel nástrojů</primary>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à outils</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具箱</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Změna ostrosti</secondary>
    <secondary lang="en">Convolve</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Goutte d'eau</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">卷积</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Schärfen</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Weichzeichnen</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary>
    <secondary>Schärfen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary>
    <secondary>Weichzeichnen</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='cs'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='en'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='zh_CN'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-blur.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="cs">
          Ikona náístroje Změna ostrosti v Panelu nástrojů
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Convolve tool icon in the Toolbox
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Das Werkzeug <quote>Verknüpfen</quote> im Werkzeugfenster.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          L'outil Goutte d'eau dans la Boîte à outils.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          工具箱中卷积工具图标
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroj Změna ostrosti používá stopu k lokálnímu zaostření nebo rozostření
    obrázku. Rozostřování pomocí tohoto nástroje se může hodit například ke
    změkčení objektu, který z obrázku příliš výrazně vystupuje. Prorozostření
    celé vrstvy nebo jjeí velké části je vhodnější použít některý z <link
    linkend='filters-blur'>filtrů pro rozostření</link>. Směr tahu nástroje
    nemá žádný efekt. Pro rozmázávání ve směru tahu nástroje se používá
    nástroj Rozmazávání. <!--FIXCS-->
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The Convolve tool uses the current brush to locally blur or
    sharpen your image. Blurring with it can be useful if some element
    of your image stands out too much, and you would like to soften
    it. If you want to blur a whole layer, or a large part of one,
    you will probably be better off using one of the <link
    linkend='filters-blur'>Blur Filters</link>.  The direction of a
    brushstroke has no effect:  if you want directional blurring, use
    the Smudge tool.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    <!-- de TODO: insert link to sharpen filter -->
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Verknüpfen</quote> ist geeignet, um kleine 
    Bildbereiche gezielt zu weichzuzeichnen oder zu schärfen. Wollen Sie
    jedoch große Bereiche oder gar das ganze Bild weichzeichnen oder schärfen,
    ist die Verwendung der Filter zum
    <link linkend='filters-blur'>Weichzeichnen</link> oder Schärfen
    komforabler. Die Richtung, in die der Pinselstrich ausgeführt wird, hat
    keinen Einfluss auf das Ergebnis. Wenn Sie gerichtet weichzeichnen
    möchten, verwenden Sie besser das
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-smudge">Verschmieren</link> Werkzeug.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil Goutte d'eau utilise le pinceau courant pour rendre flous 
    ou plus nets les contours contenus dans votre image. Il est utile 
    pour rendre floue une petite zone de l'image. Mais pour agir sur 
    de plus grandes zones, mieux vaut utiliser l'un des <link 
    linkend='filters-blur'>Filtres de flou</link>. En outre, il n'a 
    pas d'effet directionnel; pour cela, utilisez l'outil Barbouiller.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    卷积工具用当前画笔模糊或锐化您的图像。模糊在当您的图像中某些元素过于明显，需要柔化它们时非常有用。假如要模糊整个图层或其大部分，此时最好使用<link linkend='filters-blur'>模糊滤镜</link>。笔划的方向对模糊没有影响：要想得到有方向的模糊，使用涂抹工具。
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    V režimu zaostřování pracuje nástroj zvyšováním kontrastu <!--FIXME-->
    v místě aplikace stopy. Mírné zaostření může být užitečné, ale přílišné
    přeostření tímto nástrojem může vytvořit šum. Lepší bývá použití
    některého z filtrů <link linkend='filters-enhance'>Vylepšení</link>,
    obzvláště <link linkend='plug-in-unsharp-mask'>Rozostřit masku</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    In "Sharpen" mode, the tool works by increasing the contrast where
    the brush is applied.  A little bit of this may be useful, but
    overapplication will produce noise.  Some of the <link
    linkend='filters-enhance'>Enhancement Filters</link>, particularly
    the <link linkend='plug-in-unsharp-mask'>Unsharp Mask</link>, do a
    much cleaner job of sharpening areas of a layer.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Im <quote>Schärfen</quote> Modus bewirkt das Werkzeug eine
    Kontrasterhöhung in dem Bereich in dem es angewendet wird. Ein bisschen
    davon kann ganz hilfreich sein, aber wenn Sie es zu stark anwenden, wird
    ein meist unerwünschtes Rauschen auftreten. Hier leisten die
    <quote>Verbessern Filter</quote>, speziell <quote>Unscharf
    Maskieren</quote>, wesentlich <!-- de PENDING: <link
    linkend='filters-enhance'>Verbessern</link> Filter, speziell --> <!-- de
    PENDING: <link linkend='plug-in-unsharp-mask'>Unscharf Maskieren</link>,
    wesentlich --> bessere Arbeit und führen zu saubereren Ergebnissen.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    En mode «Augmenter la netteté», l'outil travaille en augmentant le
    contraste là où il passe. L'utiliser un peu peut être utile, mais
    n'insistez pas, sous peine de voir apparaître un bruit parasite. Certains
    des <link linkend='filters-enhance'>Filtres d'amélioration</link>, et
    particulièrement le filtre <link linkend='plug-in-unsharp-mask'>Renforcer
    la Netteté</link> qui réalise un travail plus soigné sur des plages d'un
    calque.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    “锐化”模式中，笔刷工具增加其笔划经过像素的对比度。少量的锐化比较有用，而过多则会产生噪音。许多<link linkend='filters-enhance'>增强滤镜</link>，特别是<!-- <link linkend='plug-in-unsharp-mask'> -->虚光蒙板都是更标准地锐化图层中的区域。
  </para>

  <tip lang="cs;en;de;fr;zh_CN">
    <para lang="cs">
      Lepší nástroj pro zaostřování lze vytvořit pomocí Razítka.
      Nejprve je potřeba duplikovat vrstvu, na které chcete pracovat,
      a aplikovat na vytvořenou kopii zaostřovací filtr, například Masku
      rozostření. Pak je nutno aktivovat Razítko a v jeho volbách nastavit
      zdroj na obrázek a sledování jako registrující. Krytí je třeba
      nastavit na rozumnou hodnotu, například 10. Pak je nutné kliknout
      s podrženou klávesou <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> na kopii vrstvy, čímž se
      z ní stane zdrojový obrázek. Malováním na původní vrstvu se pak
      zaostřená verze postupně aplikuje do originální.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can create a more sophisticated sharpening brush using the
      Clone tool.  To do this, start by duplicating the layer you want
      to work on, and run a sharpening filter, such as Unsharp Mask,
      on the copy.  Then activate the Clone tool, and in its Tool
      Options set Source to "Image source" and Alignment to
      "Registered".  Set the Opacity to a modest value, such as 10.
      Then Ctrl-click on the copy to make it the source image.  If you
      now paint on the original layer, you will mix together, where
      the brush is applied, the sharpened version with the unsharpened
      version.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sie erhalten ein wesentlich raffinierteres Malwerkzeug zum Schärfen,
      indem Sie das Werkzeug <quote>Klonen</quote> verwenden. Hierzu
      duplizieren Sie zunächst die Ebene auf der Sie arbeiten wollen, führen
      dann einen Schärfefilter auf der Kopie aus. Im nächsten Schritt
      aktivieren Sie das Werkzeug <quote>Klonen</quote> mit den Eigenschaften
      Quelle: Bild; Ausrichtung: Registriert; Deckkraft: niedrig, etwa 10. Mit
      einem <keycap>Strg</keycap>-Mausklick auf die Kopie der Ebene legen Sie
      die Quelle fest. Wenn Sie nun auf der Originalebene zeichnen, klonen Sie
      die geschärften Bildbereiche in das Original.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez créer une brosse efficace pour améliorer la netteté en
      utilisant l'outil Cloner. Pour cela, commencez par dupliquer le calque
      sur lequel vous voulez travailler et appliquez le filtre Renforcer la
      netteté sur cette copie. Activez alors l'outil Cloner et, dans ses
      options, réglez la Source sur «Image Source» et l'Alignement sur
      «Enregistrer». Fixez l'Opacité à une valeur faible, par exemple 10.
      Ctrl-cliquez sur la copie pour en faire l'image source. Si alors vous
      peignez sur le calque original, vous mélangerez, là ou la brosse est
      appliquée, la version nette et la version floue.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      用克隆工具能产生更加复杂的锐化。首先复制准备对其进行处理的图层，然后对副本使用一个锐化滤镜，如虚光蒙板。接着开启克隆工具，在其工具选项中设置“源”为“图像源”而“对齐”为“记录”，再给克隆工具的不透明度一个适当值，比如 10。最后 Ctrl-点击副本使其为源图像。现在对原始图层进行涂画，锐化部分和未锐化部分就会混合在一起。
    </para>
  </tip>

  <para lang='cs'>
    Rozostřování i zaostřování pracuje inkrementálně: opakovaná aplikace
    nástroje na jedno místo efekt postupně zesiluje. Přeběh umožňujue
    nastavit, jak rychle se změny akumulují. Krytí na druhou stranu omezuje
    množství rozostření aplikovatelné jedním tahem štětce, bez ohledu na to,
    kolikrát přejde přes jedno místo.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Both blurring and sharpening work incrementally:  moving the brush
    repeatedly over an area will increase the effect with each
    additional pass.  The Rate control allows you to determine how
    quickly the modifications accumulate.  The Opacity control,
    however, can be used to limit the amount of blurring that can be
    produced by a single brushstroke, regardless of how many passes
    are made with it.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Beide Modi, sowohl <quote>Weichzeichnen</quote> alsauch
    <quote>Schärfen</quote>, arbeiten verstärkend. Wenn Sie einen Bildbereich
    mehrfach überstreichen wird jedesmal die Wirkung des Werkzeuges neu
    angewendet und damit verstärkt. Mit der <guilabel>Deckkraft</guilabel>
    können Sie diese Verstärkung beschränken. Die Eigenschaft
    <guilabel>Rate</guilabel> bestimmt wie schnell die maximale Stärke mit der
    das Werkzeug auf einen einzelnen Bereich wirken kann erreicht wird.
  </para>
  <para lang='fr'>
    Le délayage et le renforcement de la netteté travaillent tous deux de
    façon incrémentielle: passer et repasser la brosse au même endroit
    augmente l'effet de l'outil à chaque fois. La vitesse d'évolution de
    l'effet peut être réglée grâce au Contrôle de Taux. Le curseur d'Opacité
    permet de limiter l'importance de cette sommation.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    模糊和锐化会累加：在某个区域反复移动画笔时，每一次移动都增加其效果。“比率”控制这些修改的累积有多快。而不透明度可以用作限制每一笔模糊的程度，不管这一笔反复移动了多少次。
  </para>
    
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</title>
    <title lang="en">How to Activate</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</title> 
    <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>

    <para lang='cs'>
      Nástroj Změna ostrosti lze aktivovat z nabídky okna obrázku
      volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Nástroje</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Kreslící nástroje</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Změna ostrosti</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      nebo kliknutím na ikonu nástroje
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/blur.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> v Panelu nástrojů;
      nebo klávesovou zkratkou <keycap>V</keycap> (ve výchozím nastavení).
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Convolve tool can be activated from an image menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Convolve</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; 
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon 
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/blur.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>V</keycap>.
    </para>

		<para lang="de">
			Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten das Werkzeug
			<quote>Verknüpfen</quote> zu aktivieren:
		</para>
    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Über das Menü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>alwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>V</accel>erknüpfen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          im Bildfenster,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Mit einen Mausklick auf das Symbol
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/blur.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          im Werkzeugfenster, sowie
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Über das Tastenkürzel <keycap>V</keycap>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil Goutte d'eau est appelé à partir de la barre de menus de 
      l'image par 
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Outils de d<accel>e</accel>ssin</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Goutte d'<accel>e</accel>au</guimenuitem>. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      Il peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône 
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/blur.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à outils.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La touche <keycap>V</keycap> activera l'outil Goutte d'eau.
    </para>

    <para lang='zh_CN'>
      卷积工具在图像菜单的：
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>工具</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>涂画工具</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>卷积</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;也可以点工具图标：
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/blur.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;或使用快捷键 <keycap>V</keycap>。
    </para>

  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy</title>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Standardeinstellungen)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de contrôle</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键</title>

    <para lang='cs'>
      V části <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Přehled nástrojů používajících
      stopy</link> jsou popsány modifikační klávesy společné pro všechny
      nástroje používající stopy.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      See the <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Brush Tools
      Overview</link> for a description of key modifiers that have the
      same effect on all brush tools.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang='cs'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Podržení klávesy <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>přepíná mezi rozostřovacím a
          zaostřovacím režimem; přepíná nastavení zobrazené ve volbách
          nástroje.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang='en'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Holding down the Ctrl key toggles between Blur and Sharpen
          modes; it reverses the setting shown in the Tool Options. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 

    <itemizedlist lang='de'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Strg</keycap>:
          Mit der <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste, lässt sich zwischen den Modi
          <quote>Weichzeichnen</quote> und <quote>Schärfen</quote> umschalten.
          Der jeweilige Modus bleibt erhalten, solange Sie die
          Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap> gedrückt halten.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 

    <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Ctrl permet de basculer entre le mode Flou 
          et le mode Augmenter la netteté. Le mode ainsi obtenu 
          restera actif tant que durera l'appui sur Ctrl.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 

    <itemizedlist lang='zh_CN'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 在模糊和锐化模式间切换。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="cs">Volby nástroje</title>
    <title lang="en">Tool Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Einstellungen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-convolve.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-convolve.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-convolve.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-convolve.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-convolve.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="cs">
            Volby nástroje Změna ostrosti
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Tool Options for the Convolve tool
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Die Eigenschaften des Werkzeuges <quote>Verknüpfen</quote>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les options de l'outil Goutte d'eau
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            卷积工具的工具选项
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <note lang="cs;en;fr;zh_CN">
      <para lang='cs'>
        V kapitole <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Přehled nástrojů
        používajících stopy</link> jsou popsány volby společné většině
        nebo všem těmto nástrojům.
      </para>
      <para lang='en'>
        See the <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Brush Tools
        Overview</link> for a description of tool options that apply to
        many or all brush tools.
      </para>
      <para lang='fr'>
        Voyez <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Fonctions communes des 
        outils</link> pour une description des fonctions communes.   
      </para>  
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        关于许多或所有笔刷工具共用工具选项的描述请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>笔刷工具简介</link>。
      </para>
    </note>

    <variablelist>

    <varlistentry lang="de">
      <term lang="de">
        Deckkraft; Pinsel(-form); Druckempfindlichkeit; Verblassen;
        Harte Kanten
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <note lang="de">
          <para>
            Diese Eigenschaften sind bei allen Malwerkzeugen von
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vorhanden und daher in einem separaten
            Abschnitt <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Allgemeine
            Eigenschaften</link> beschrieben.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="cs">Druh změny ostrosti</term>
      <term lang="en">Convolve Type</term>
      <term lang="de">Verknüpfungsart</term>
      <term lang="fr">Type de circonvolution</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">卷积类型</term>

      <listitem lang='cs'>
        <para><!--FIX every lang -->
          V režimu <guilabel>Rozostření</guilabel> dotyk stopy způsobuje
          splývání dotčených pixelů se sousedními pixely, zvyšuje tedy
          vzájemnou podobnost pixelů v ovlivněné oblasti. V režimu
          <guilabel>Zaostření</guilabel> se naopak rozdílnost pixelů a
          kontrast ve stopou ovlivněné oblasti zvyšuje. Ať je v dialogu zvolen
          jakýkoliv režim, lze přepínat při práci (ale nikoliv v průběhu
          jednoho tahu nástrojem) pomocí klávesy <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Blur</emphasis> mode causes each pixel affected by
          the brush to be blended with neighboring pixels, thereby increasing the
          similarity of pixels inside the brushstroke area.
          <emphasis>Sharpen</emphasis> mode causes each pixel to
          become more different from its neighbors than it previously
          was:  it increases contrast inside the brushstroke area.
          Whatever setting you choose here, you can reverse it
          on-the-fly by holding down the Ctrl key.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Die Verknüpfungsart gibt den Standardmodus des Werkzeuges an. So
          erlaubt das Werkzeug, zwischen <guilabel>Weichzeichnen</guilabel>
          und <guilabel>Schärfen</guilabel> zu wählen. Der jeweils andere
          Modus lässt sich durch gedrückt halten der <keycap>Strg</keycap>
          Taste einschalten.
        </para>
        <para>
          Im <guilabel>Weichzeichnen</guilabel> Modus, werden die Farben
          ineinander verwischt. So entsteht von der weichgezeichneten
          Region ein verschwommener Eindruck. Damit lässt sich ein weicher
          Übergang zwischen Farben erreichen, der aber auch etwas dunkler
          ausfallen kann.
        </para>
        <para>
          Bei ausgewähltem <guilabel>Schärfen</guilabel> Modus,
          werden ähnliche Farben vereint. So entsteht ein
          Eindruck der Schärfe. Bei übermässiger Anwendung
          kann der Werkzeugmodus zu ungewünschten Ergebnissen
          führen, da Pixel zerstreut werden und scharfgezeichnete
          Kanten zerfranst wirken.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          Le mode <guilabel>Flou</guilabel> dilue les couleurs l'une 
          dans l'autre: à chaque passage, le pinceau mélange 
          les pixels colorés. Le résultat est une transition en 
          douceur entre les couleurs, mais qui est toujours plus foncée 
          que les couleurs d'origine. On a l'impression d'un effet de 
          délayage des couleurs, comme si on passait de l'eau sur une 
          gouache, ce qui explique probablement l'icône Goutte d'eau.
        </para>
        <para>
          Le mode <guilabel>Augmenter la netteté</guilabel> oblige les 
          pixels de couleurs voisines à converger. En l'utilisant 
          judicieusement, on peut rendre les bords plus nets, mais une 
          application répétée aboutit à un aspect de floculation 
          disgracieux.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='zh_CN'>
        <para>
          <emphasis>模糊</emphasis>模式使被笔刷经过的像素与其周围像素相混合，因此增加了笔划中像素的相似性。而<emphasis>锐化</emphasis>模式使像素与其周围像素更加不同：即增加了笔划中像素的对比度。无论设定如何，都可以通过按下 Ctrl 键快速交换它们。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="cs">Přeběh</term>
      <term lang="en">Rate</term>
      <term lang="de">Rate</term>
      <term lang="fr">Taux</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">比率</term>
      <listitem lang='cs'>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Přeběh</guilabel> nastavuje
          intenzitu efektu změny ostrosti.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='en'>
        <para>
          The <guilabel>Rate</guilabel> slider sets the strength of the
          convolve effect.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='de'>
        <para>
          Der Schieberegler zur Einstellung der <guilabel>Rate</guilabel> gibt
          an, mit welcher Stärke das Werkzeug angewendet wird. So findet
          bei einer geringen Rate (0) keine Weichzeichnung/Schärfe
          statt. Bei einer hohen Rate (100) verschwimmen die Farben im
          Weichzeichnen Modus ineinander umso mehr. Ebenso verhält es
          sich im Schärfen-Modus, nur dass entsprechend mehr
          ähnliche Farben zusammengefasst werden.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          Le curseur <guilabel>Taux</guilabel> règle la force de 
          l'outil Goutte d'eau. Cet outil agit de façon 
          incrémentielle: l'effet se cumule à chaque passage. Le Taux 
          permet de régler la quantité d'effet à chaque passage 
          tandis que le curseur Opacité règle le maximum d'effet 
          total.  
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang='zh_CN'>
        <para>
          <guilabel>比率</guilabel>设置卷积效果的强烈程度。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</simplesect>
</sect2>


