<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-07-24 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-06-15 en;fr: changed Ctrl and Shift sections by j.h
  2006-02-17 en;fr: added section for Space bar by j.h
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050516 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-select" lang="de;cs;en;es;fr;nl;zh_CN;it">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;fr;nl">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-15</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2005-05-16</date>
        <authorinitials>a.w</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-15</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="nl">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-09</date>
        <authorinitials>rvw</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>
  
  <title lang="en">Common Features</title>
  <title lang="cs">Společné vlastnosti</title>
  <title lang="de">Allgemeine Eigenschaften</title>
  <title lang="es">Características en común</title>
  <title lang="fr">Fonctions communes</title>
  <title lang="nl">Algemene Eigenschappen</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">基本特性</title>
  <title lang="it">Funzioni comuni</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selections</primary>
    <secondary>Common Features</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Panel nástrojů</primary>
    <secondary>Výběr</secondary>
    <tertiary>Vlastnosti</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Auswahl</primary>
    <secondary>Allgemeine Eigenschaften</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Selecciones</primary>
    <secondary>Características en común</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélections</primary>
    <secondary>Fonctions communes</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Selezioni</primary>
    <secondary>Funzioni comuni</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="nl">
    <primary>Selecties</primary>
    <secondary>Algemene eigenschappen</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>工具箱</primary>
    <secondary>选择</secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <para lang="en">
    Selection tools are designed to select regions from images or layers so
    you can work on them without affecting the unselected areas. Each tool has
    its own individual properties, but the selection tools also share a number
    of options and features in common. These common features are described
    here; the variations are explained in the following sections for each tool
    specifically. If you need help with what a <quote>selection</quote>
    is in GIMP, and how it works, see
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Selection</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroje pro výběr jsou určeny k vybírání částí obrázku či vrstev tak,
    abyste na nich mohli pracovat, aniž byste ovlivnili nevybrané části. Každý
    nástroj má své zvláštní unikátní vlastnosti, ale jednotlivé nástroje pro
    výběr také řadu společných vlastností a voleb sdílí. Tyto společné
    vlastnosti jsou popsány v této kapitole, zatímco zvláštnosti jednotlivých
    nástrojů jsou jsou popsány v následujících částech. Pokud potřebujete
    vysvětlit, co to vlastně v Gimpu výběr je, přečtěte si kapitolu
    <!-- FIXME: cs <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection"> --> Výběr.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Als Auswahl wird in in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ein definierter, beliebig
    geformter Bereich eines Bildes bezeichnet. Weitere Informationen hierzu
    finden Sie im Kapitel Auswahl. Die Arbeit mit
    <!-- de PENDING <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Auswahl</link> -->
    einer Auswahl ermöglicht es Ihnen Werkzeuge und Filter nur auf den
    ausgewählten Bereichen des Bildes wirken zu lassen. GIMP stellt Ihnen
    verschiedene Auswahlwerkzeuge zur Verfügung, mit deren Hilfe Sie leicht
    solche Bereiche festlegen können. Dabei verfügt jedes Auswahlwerkzeug
    einerseits über spezielle Eigenschaften, andererseits haben aber auch alle
    Auswahlwerkzeuge bestimmte allgemeine Eingenschaften. In diesem Abschnitt
    werden zunächst diese allgemeinen Eigenschaften beschrieben.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    Las herramientas de selección están diseñadas para seleccionar
    regiones de las imágenes o de las capas, y así poder trabajar en
    ellas sin que las áreas no seleccionadas se vean afectadas.  Cada
    herramienta tiene sus propiedades individuales, pero las
    herramientas de selección además comparten una cantidad de
    características en común.  Éstas son descriptas aquí, mientras que
    las variaciones se explican en las próximas secciones para cada
    herramienta en particular.  Si necesita ayuda sobre qué es una
    <quote>selección</quote> en el GIMP, y cómo funciona, diríjase a
    la sección sobre <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">selección</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Les outils de sélection servent à sélectionner des zones dans l'image de
    façon à travailler dessus sans affecter la partie non sélectionnée de
    l'image. Chaque outil a ses propres caractéristiques mais les outils de
    sélection ont en commun un certain nombre d'options. Ces options communes
    sont décrites ici; les variations seront expliquées pour chaque outil en
    particulier. Si vous avez besoin de savoir ce qu'est une sélection et
    comment ça marche, voyez
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Sélection</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Gli strumenti di selezione sono progettati per selezionare delle zone di
    immagini o di livelli in modo che si possa lavorare senza compromettere le
    aree non selezionate. Ogni strumento ha le sue proprietà particolari, ma
    gli strumenti di selezione condividono alcune opzioni e funzioni comuni.
    Qui vengono descritte queste caratteristiche comuni; le varianti vengono
    spiegate nelle sezioni seguenti specificatamente per ogni strumento. Se si
    ha bisogno di aiuto per sapere cosa sia una "selezione" in GIMP, e su come
    funzioni, vedere
    <!-- PENDING: it link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection" -->selezioni<!--/link-->.
  </para>

  <para lang="nl">
    Selectie gereedschappen zijn ontworpen om gebieden uit afbeelding of lagen
    te selecteren zodat u op deze kan werken zonder de niet geselecteerd delen
    te beinvloeden. Ieder gereedschap heeft zijn eigen individuele
    eigenschappen, maar de selectie gereedschappen delen ook een aantal
    eigenschappen en mogelijkheden. Deze gedeelde mogelijkheden zijn hier
    beschreven; de variaties worden voor elk gereedschap specifiek behandeld
    in de volgende secties. Mocht u op dit moment nog meer informatie behoeven
    omtrent het begrip <quote>selectie</quote> en de betekenis ervan in De
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, kijkt u dan vooral nog eens bij
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">De selectie</link>
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    选区工具被用作在图像或图层上选取区域，可以对其进行处理而不会影响非选中区域。每个工具都有自己独立的属性，但是选择工具也共用一些选项和特性。这里介绍下这些特性；各个工具单独的章节指出其略微的不同。如果想对 GIMP 中的“选择”获取更多的帮助，请看“使用 GIMP”这章的选区小节。
  </para>


  <para lang="en">There are six selection tools:</para>
  <para lang="cs">Existuje šest nástrojů pro výběr:</para>
  <para lang="de">Es gibt sechs Auswahlwerkzeuge:</para>
  <para lang="es">Hay seis herramientas de selección:</para>
  <para lang="fr">Il y a six outils de sélection:</para>
  <para lang="it">Ci sono sei strumenti di selezione:</para>
  <para lang="nl">Er zijn zes selectie gereedschappen:</para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">有六种选择工具：</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Rectangle Select</para>
      <para lang="cs">Výběr obdélníku</para>
      <para lang="de">Rechteckige Auswahl</para>
      <para lang="es">Selección rectangular</para>
      <para lang="fr">Sélection rectangulaire</para>
      <para lang="it">Selezione rettangolare</para>
      <para lang="nl">Rechthoekigselectie</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">矩形选择</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Ellipse Select</para>
      <para lang="cs">Výběr elipsy</para>
      <para lang="de">Elliptische Auswahl</para>
      <para lang="es">Selección elíptica</para>
      <para lang="fr">Sélection elliptique</para>
      <para lang="it">Selezione ellittica</para>
      <para lang="nl">Ovale selectie</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">椭圆选择</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Free Select (the Lasso)</para>
      <para lang="cs">Volný výběr (Laso)</para>
      <para lang="de">Freie Auswahl</para>
      <para lang="es">Selección libre (el lazo)</para>
      <para lang="fr">Sélection à main levée (le Lasso)</para>
      <para lang="it">Selezione libera (il lazo)</para>
      <para lang="nl">Vrije selectie (de Lasso)</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">自由选择(套索)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Select Contiguous Regions (the Magic Wand)</para>
      <para lang="cs">Přibližný výběr (Kouzelná hůlka)</para>
      <para lang="de">Zauberstab</para>
      <para lang="es">Seleccionar regiones continuas (la varita mágica)</para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Sélection de régions contiguës (La Baguette magique)
      </para>
      <para lang="it">Seleziona regioni contigue (la bacchetta magica)</para>
      <para lang="nl">Selecteer aaneengesloten gebieden (de Toverstaf)</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">选择邻近区域(魔术棒)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Select by Color</para>
      <para lang="cs">Podle barvy výběru</para>
      <para lang="de">Auswahl nach Farbe</para>
      <para lang="es">Seleccionar por colores</para>
      <para lang="fr">Sélection par couleur</para>
      <para lang="it">Seleziona per colore</para>
      <para lang="nl">Op-kleur-selectie</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">按颜色选择</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Select Shapes from Image (Intelligent Scissors)</para>
      <para lang="cs">Inteligentní nůžky</para>
      <para lang="de">Magnetische Auswahl</para>
      <para lang="es">
        Seleccionar figuras de la imagen (tijeras inteligentes)
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">Ciseaux intelligents</para>
      <para lang="it">
        Seleziona forme dall'immagine (forbici intelligenti)
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Semi-automatisch selecteren (Intelligente Scharen)
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">从图像中选择形状(智能剪刀)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>



  <para lang="en">
    In some ways the Path tool can also be thought of as a selection tool: any
    closed path can be converted into a selection. It also can do a great deal
    more, though, and does not share the same set of options with the other
    selection tools.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Cesty jsou v mnoha ohledech podobné a daly by se také považovat za nástroj
    pro výběr: každá uzavřená cesta se dá převést na výběr. Cesty ale umí i
    mnoho dalších věcí a nesdílí s nástroji pro výběr stejnou základní sadu
    voleb.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Auch das Pfadwerkzeug kann als ein Auswahlwerkzeug betrachtet werden, da
    jeder geschlossene Pfad in eine Auswahl konvertiert werden kann. Da das
    Pfadwerkzeug neben der Erstellung einer auswahl aber noch viele weitere
    Anwendungsmöglichkeiten bietet, zählt es nicht zu den primären
    Auswahlwerkzeugen und wird in einem eigenen
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Kapitel</link> beschrieben.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    De alguna manera las rutas también pueden pensarse como una
    herramienta de selección: toda ruta cerrada puede convertirse en
    una selección.  A pesar de esto, usarlas puede llevar un gran
    trabajo, y no comparten el mismo conjunto de opciones con las
    otras herramientas de selección.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    D'une certaine façon, on peut voir l'outil Chemins comme un outil de 
    sélection puisque tout chemin fermé peut être transformé en sélection. 
    Il peut aussi faire beaucoup de choses, différentes de ce que font les 
    vrais outils de sélection.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    In un certo senso anche lo strumento "tracciati" può essere inteso come
    uno strumento di selezione: ogni tracciato chiuso può essere convertito in
    una selezione. Anche se esso può fare molto di più e non condivide con gli
    altri strumenti di selezione lo stesso insieme di opzioni.
  </para>
  <para lang="nl">
    Het Pad gereedschap kan op een bepaalde manier ook beschouwd worden als
    een Selectie gereedschap: elk gesloten pad kan geconverteerd worden naar
    een selectie. Het Pad gereedschap kan echter veel meer, en heeft ook niet
    dezelfde eigenschappen als de andere Selectie gereedschappen. Het Pad 
    gereedschap wordt beschreven in een eigen
    <!-- TODO: nl :<link linkend="gimp-tool-path">-->hoofdstuk<!--</link>-->.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    某种一样上，路径也可以认为是一种选择工具：任何闭合路径能被转换为一个选区。甚至还有更多的功能，虽然它和其它选择工具不共用一套选项。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy (Výchozí)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (por omisión)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Toetsencombinaties (Standaard instellingen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tasti modificatori (predefiniti)</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The behavior of selection tools is modified if you hold down the
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>, and/or
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> keys while you use them.  
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Chování nástrojů pro výběr lze ovlivnit stlačením klávesy
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap> a/nebo
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> během jejich používání.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Verhalten der Auswahlwerkzeuge verändert sich, wenn Sie eine der
      drei Tasten <keycap>Strg</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>,
      und/oder <keycap>Alt</keycap> während der Arbeit mit dem Werkzeug
      gedrückt halten.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El comportamiento de las herramientas de selección se modifica
      su presiona las teclas
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>, y/o
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> mientras las utiliza.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le comportement des outils de sélection est modifié si vous appuyez 
      sur les touches <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>, 
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> pendant leur utilisation.
    </para>
    <para lang="nl">
      Het gedrag van de Selectie gereedschappen veranderd als u de 
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap> en/of 
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> toetsen ingedrukt houdt tijdens het gebruik
      van de Selectie gereedschappen.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      当按住 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap> 或 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 的同时使用选择工具将改变它们的行为。
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il comportamento degli strumenti di selezione cambia se mentre li
      usate tenete premuti i tasti <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>,
      <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>, e/o <keycap>Alt</keycap>.  
    </para>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        Advanced users find the modifier keys very valuable, but novice users
        often find them confusing. Fortunately, it is possible for most
        purposes to use the Mode buttons (described below) instead of modifier
        keys.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Pokročilí uživatelé považují modifikační klávesy za velmi užitečné,
        ale začátečníci je často považují za matoucí. Naštěstí je pro většinu
        účelů možno používat místo těchto kláves tlačítka pro přepínání režimu
        (viz níže).
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Tastenkürzel ermöglichen einen schnellen Zugriff auf verschiedene
        Eigenschaften der Auswahlwerkzeuge. Sie werden gern und häufig von
        fortgeschrittenen Benutzern verwendet, Einsteiger finden Tastenkürzel
        hingegen gelegentlich verwirrend. Glücklicherweise können sie die
        meisten Eigenschaften der Werkzeuge auch per Mausklick verändern.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Los usuarios avanzados encuentran que las teclas modificadoras
        son muy valiosas, pero los novatos a menudo las encuentran
        confusas.  Afortunadamente, es posible utilizar los botones de
        modo (que se describen debajo) en lugar de las teclas
        modificadoras, para la mayoría de los propósitos.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les utilisateurs expérimentés aiment bien les touches de contrôle,
        mais les novices les trouvent compliquées. Heureusement, il est
        possible la plupart du temps d'utiliser les boutons Mode (décrits plus
        bas) à la place de ces touches.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Gli utenti avanzati ritengono importante l'uso dei tasti modificatori,
        ma agli utenti alle prime armi possono creare confusione.
        Fortunatamente, nella maggior parte dei casi è possibile usare al loro
        posto i pulsanti di modalità (descritti in seguito).
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Gevorderde gebruikers waarderen de sneltoetsen zeer, maar voor
        beginners zijn ze vaak verwarrend. Gelukkig zijn de eigenschappen vaak
        ook aan te passen via knoppen in het Gereedschaps venster in plaats
        van de sneltoetsen te gebruiken. Het aanpassen via de knoppen wordt
        zometeen besproken.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        高级用户认为上面的控制键非常有价值，而新手觉得它们让人迷惑。幸运的是，也可以用模式按钮(下面有描述)代替控制键来完成大多数功能。
      </para>
    </note>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;nl"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <term lang="cs"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Strg</keycap></term>
        <term lang="es"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <term lang="it"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <term lang="zh_CN"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"> <!--changed 060615-->
            When creating a selection, holding down the 
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key can have two different actions
            according to the way you use it:
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Podržení <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> během tvorby výběru může mít dva
            důsledky najednou. První závisí na konkrétním použitém nástroji:
            nastudujte si popisy jednotlivých nástrojů. Druhý efekt je ale
            všem společný: přepne nástroj do odečítacího režimu, takže vybraná
            oblast je <emphasis>odečtena</emphasis> od stávajícího výběru.
            Pokud chcete využít jen této možnosti, ale nikoliv efektu
            závislého na konkrétním nástroji, uvolněte tlačítko
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> dříve než <mousebutton>tlačítko
            myši</mousebutton>. Tak zůstane aktivní odečítací režim, nikoliv
            však efekt závislý na konkrétním nástroji.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie während der Verwendung eines Auswahlwerkzeuges die Taste
            <keycap>Strg</keycap> gedrückt halten, wird dies zwei Auswirkungen
            haben. Zum Einen wird der Startpixel als Mittelpunkt der Auswahl
            benutzt, dass heisst um diesen Mittelpunkt wird die Auswahl
            erstellt. Alternativ wird der Startpixel als rechte, untere Ecke
            benutzt, um die Auswahl zu erstellen. Zum Anderen wird der
            Auswahlmodus auf Subtrahieren gesetzt. Sollte nur eine der
            Funktionen gewünscht sein, so können Sie die
            <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste vor der
            <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> loslassen. Dies wird dazu
            führen, dass die Auswahl im Subtraktionsmodus durchgeführt wird,
            die werkzeugabhängige Funktion aber nicht zum Einsatz kommt.
          </para>
		  <para lang="es">
            Al crear una selección, mantener presionada la tecla
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> puede resultar en dos acciones
            diferentes, de acuerdo a la forma en que la utilices:
		  </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Lors de la création d'une sélection, la touche
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> peut avoir deux actions différentes selon
            la façon dont vous l'utilisez:
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> premuto mentre create una
            selezione può avere simultaneamente due effetti.  Il primo
            effetto è variabile a seconda dello strumento che state
            usando: per questo vedi la documentazione dei singoli
            strumenti.  Il secondo effetto è comune a tutti gli
            strumenti di selezione: imposta lo strumento in modalità di
            sottrazione, in modo che la zona che tracciate venga
            <emphasis>sottratta</emphasis> dalla selezione preesistente.
            Se volete che avvenga solo una di queste azioni, dovete
            rilasciare il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> prima di
            rilasciare il <mousebutton>pulsante del mouse</mousebutton>.
            Così facendo lascierete la selezione in modalità di
            sottrazione ma non eseguirete l'azione specifica dello
            strumento.
          </para>
          <para lang="nl">
            Tijdens het maken van een selectie kan het vasthouden van de
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> toets twee verschillende uitwerkingen
            hebben, afhankelijk de manier waarop u het doet:
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 的同时创建一个选区最多能同时产生两个效果。第一个效果取决于您使用的是什么工具：请看单独的工具文档。第二个效果，所有选择工具都是一样的：它使选取呈减去模式，您所勾勒的区域就从原有的选区上<emphasis>减去</emphasis>。如果只想进行一个动作，可以在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 键。这样做就使选区呈减去模式，而不执行相关的工具动作。
          </para>


          <itemizedlist lang="en;es;fr;nl">
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                If you hold down the key <emphasis>before
                clicking</emphasis> to start the selection, this
                selection will be in <emphasis>Subtraction</emphasis>
                mode as long as you press the key.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                  Si mantiene presionada la tecla <emphasis>antes de
                  hacer clic</emphasis> para comenzar a seleccionar,
                  esta selección se realizará en el modo de
                  <emphasis>extracción</emphasis>.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Si vous maintenez l'appui sur la touche
                <emphasis>avant de cliquer</emphasis> pour tracer la
                sélection, cette sélection sera en mode
                <emphasis>Soustraction</emphasis> tant que la touche
                restera enfoncée.
              </para>
              <para lang="nl"><!--Find translation for Subtraction-->
                Houdt u de toets vast <emphasis>voordat</emphasis> u de
                <mousebutton>muisknop</mousebutton>
                indrukt om de selectie te beginnen, dan zal deze nieuwe
                selectie werken in de modus om de selectie
                <emphasis>toe te voegen</emphasis>, zolang als u de
                <mousebutton>muisknop</mousebutton> vast houdt.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                If you hold down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key 
                <emphasis>after clicking</emphasis> to start the selection,
                the effect will depend on the tool you are using.
              </para>
              <para lang="es">
                  Si mantiene presionada la tecla <emphasis>luego de
                  hacer clic</emphasis> para comenzar a seleccionar,
                  el efecto dependerá de la herramienta que esté en
                  uso.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Si vous appuyez sur la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
                <emphasis>après avoir cliqué</emphasis> pour démarrer la
                sélection, l'effet dépendra de l'outil utilisé tant que
                persistera l'appui sur la touche.
              </para>
              <para lang="nl">
                Drukt u de <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> toets pas in
                <emphasis>nadat</emphasis>
                u de selectie begonnen bent door middel van een muisklik,
                dan is het effect afhankelijk van het exacte gereedschap dat
                u op dit moment gebruikt.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Alt</keycap></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding <keycap>Alt</keycap> will allow movement of the
            current selection (only its frame, not its content). If the
            whole image is moved instead of the selection only, try
            <keycap>Shift+Alt</keycap>.  Note that the
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is sometimes intercepted by the
            windowing system (meaning that GIMP never knows that it was
            pressed), so this may not work for everybody.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Podržení klávesy <keycap>Alt</keycap> umožní posun stávajícího
            výběru (pouze hranice výběru, nikoliv obsahu). Pokud se pohne celý
            obrázek místo samotného výběru, zkuste <keycap>Shift+Alt</keycap>.
            Uvědomte si, že klávesa <keycap>Alt</keycap> je občas odchytávána
            okenním systémem (což znamená, že se GIMP o jejím stlačení
            nedozví), takže tato vlastnost nemusí být u každého funkční.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie während der Verwendung eines Auswahlwerkzeuges die Taste
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> gedrückt halten, können Sie die aktuelle
            Auswahl (nur den Rahmen, nicht den Inhalt) verschieben. Wird wider
            Erwarten das gesamte Bild verschoben, versuchen Sie es nocheinmal
            während Sie
            <keycombo><keycap>Schift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>
            gedrückt halten.
          </para>
          <note lang="de">
            <para>
              Leider wird die <keycap>Alt</keycap> Taste von
              einigen Fenstermanagern (einem Teil des Betriebssystems Ihres
              Computers) nicht korrekt weitergeleitet, so das
              <acronym>GIMP</acronym> niemals erfährt das die Taste überhaupt
              gedrückt wurde. Dies kann dazu führen, dass die Funktion bei Ihnen
              gar nicht funktioniert.
              Falls Sie einen Apple Computer mit OS X benutzen, könne Sie
              versuchen das Problem zu beheben, indem Sie in den
              <guilabel>Einstellungen</guilabel> des Programms
              <application>X 11</application> unter
              <guilabel>Eingabe</guilabel> die Funktion
              <guilabel>Drei Maustasten nachbilden</guilabel> ausschalten.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="es">
            Mantener presionada <keycap>Alt</keycap> permite mover el
            marco de la selección, sin su contenido.  Si se mueve toda
            la imagen en vez de moverse sólo la selección, intente
            <keycap>Shift+Alt</keycap>.  Note que la tecla
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> aveces es interceptada por el
            administrador de ventanas (lo que significa que el GIMP
            nunca se entera de que fue presionada), así que la tecla
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> sin <keycap>Shift</keycap> no
            funciona para todos los usuarios.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Maintenir la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap> enfoncée permettra
            de mobiliser le cadre de la sélection courante sans déplacer
            son contenu. Si c'est l'ensemble de l'image qui se déplace,
            utilisez <keycap>Maj+Alt</keycap>
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Houdt u de <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            ingedrukt dan kunt u de huidige selectie verplaatsen. Let wel,
            hiermee verplaatst u de selectie (dus het gebied dat geselecteerd
            is) maar niet de inhoud van de selectie.<!--todo: try this part to see its working irl-->
            Als de hele afbeelding verplaatst moet worden in plaats van alleen
            de selectie, probeert u dan
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            </keycombo>.
          </para>

          <note lang="nl">
    	    <para>
    	      Houdt u er rekening me dat sommige Window Managers de <keycap>Alt</keycap> 
    	      toets onderscheppen. Dat betekent dat de Window Manager niet doorgeeft aan
    	      de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> dat de <keycap>Alt</keycap> toets ingedrukt is.
    	      In dat geval zal het dus niet mogelijk zijn de selectie te verplaatsen
    	      met behulp van de <keycap>Alt</keycap> toets.
    	    </para>
    	  </note>
              
    	  <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 允许移动当前的选区(只是其框架而不是其内部的像素)。如果不是选区而是整个图像移动了，试下 <keycap>Shift+Alt</keycap>。注意 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 键有时被窗口系统截获(也就是说 GIMP 不知道按了)，因此它可能不是对每个人都有用。
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap> premuto vi permetterà di spostare
            la selezione corrente (solo il suo contorno, non il
            contenuto).Se invece della sola selezione dovesse spostarsi
            l'intera immagine provate a premere
            <keycap>Maiusc+Alt</keycap>. Notate che il tasto
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> alle volte viente intercettato dal sistema 
            di gestione delle finestre (ciò significa che GIMP non saprà
            mai che è stato premuto), quindi potrebbe non funzionare a tutti.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;nl"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="cs"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="es"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Maj</keycap></term>
        <term lang="zh_CN"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="it"><keycap>Maiusc</keycap></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"> <!--changed 060615-->
            When creating a selection, holding down the
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> key can have two different actions
            according to the way you use it:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you hold down the key <emphasis>before
                    clicking</emphasis> to start the selection, this
                  selection will be in <emphasis>Addition</emphasis>
                  mode as long as you press the key.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you hold down the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key
                  <emphasis>after clicking</emphasis> to start the selection,
                  the effect will depend on the tool you are using: for
                  example, the selection will be a square with the
                  Rectangle Select tool.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Stejně jako v případě klávesy <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, podržení
            klávesy <keycap>Shift</keycap> během tvoření výběru může mít dva
            různé důsledky. První závislý na konkrétním nástroji (obvykle je
            to nějaké omezení, například nástroj pro výběr obdélníků omezuje
            na čtverce), druhý je společný. Tímto společným efektem je
            přepnutí nástroje do režimu přičítání, takže vybraná oblast bude
            přičtena k výběru již existujícímu. Pokud chcete použít pouze tuto
            společnou vlastnost, uvolněte <keycap>Shift</keycap> dříve než
            tlačítko myši.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie während der Verwendung eines Auswahlwerkzeuges die
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> Taste gedrückt halten, wird dies, wie bei
            der <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste, zwei Auswirkungen haben, Die
            Erste ist wiederum vom konkreten Auswahlwerkzeug abhängig, hat
            aber immer damit zu tun, dass das Seitenverhältnis derAuswahl
            konstant gehalten wird. Beispielsweise führt das Drücken der
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> Taste bei der Rechteckigen Auswahl zu
            einem quadratischen Bereich. Die zweite Auswirkung besteht darin,
            dass der Auswahlmodus auf Hinzufügen geändert wird. Dies bedeutet,
            dass die neue Auswahl zu einer bereits vorhandenen Auswahl
            hinzugefügt wird. Sollten Sie nur eine der beiden Funktionen
            wünschen, so können Sie die <keycap>Shift</keycap> Taste vor der
            <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> loslassen. Dies führt dazu,
            dass die Auswahl im Modus Hinzufügen ausgeführt wird, allerdings
            ohne Auswirkungen auf das Seitenverhältnis der Auswahl zu haben.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
    	    Al crear una selección, mantener presionada la tecla
    	    <keycap>Shift</keycap> puede resultar en dos acciones
    	    diferentes, de acuerdo a como se la utilice:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
        		  Si mantiene presionada la tecla <emphasis>antes de
        		  hacer clic</emphasis> para empezar a seleccionar,
        		  esta selección se hará en el modo de
        		  <emphasis>adición</emphasis>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
        		  Si mantiene presionada la tecla <emphasis>después
        		  de hacer clic</emphasis> para empezar a seleccionar,
        		  el efecto dependerá de la herramienta activa: por
        		  ejemplo, la forma de la selección se torna cuadrada
        		  para la herramienta de selección rectangular.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Lors de la création d'une sélection, la touche
            <keycap>Maj</keycap> peut avoir deux actions différentes selon
            la façon dont vous l'utilisez:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Si vous maintenez l'appui sur la touche
                  <emphasis>avant de cliquer</emphasis> pour tracer la
                  sélection, cette sélection sera en mode
                  <emphasis>Addition</emphasis> tant que la touche
                  restera enfoncée.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Si vous appuyez sur la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap>
                  <emphasis>après avoir cliqué</emphasis> pour démarrer la
                  sélection, l'effet dépendra de l'outil utilisé tant que
                  persistera l'appui sur la touche: par exemple la sélection
                  sera carrée avec l'outil Sélection rectangulaire.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            Come per il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, premendo
            <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> mentre create una selezione potrete
            ottenere due effetti distinti.  Il primo varia a seconda di
            quale strumento viene usato, ma generalmente implica una
            qualche costrizione per lo strumento: ad esempio, costringe
            lo strumento di selezione rettangolare a selezionare un'area
            <emphasis>quadrata</emphasis>. Il secondo effetto è quello
            di cambiare la modalità di selezione in  "addizione",
            cosicché la zona tracciata viene aggiunta alla selezione
            precedente.  Se avete bisogno che abbia luogo solo una di
            queste due azioni,  potete rilasciare il tasto
            <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> prima di rilasciare il
            <mousebutton>pulsante del mouse</mousebutton>.  Così facendo
            lascerete la selezione in modalità addizione, ma senza
            costrizioni.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl"> 
             Tijdens het maken van een selectie kan het vasthouden van de
             <keycap>Shift</keycap> toets twee verschillende uitwerkingen
             hebben (net zoals de <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> toets), afhankelijk 
    	     de manier waarop u het doet:
             <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                 <para><!--Find translation for Addition-->
                   Houdt u de toets vast <emphasis>voordat</emphasis>
                   u de <mousebutton>muisknop</mousebutton>
                   indrukt om de selectie te beginnen, dan zal deze nieuwe
                   selectie werken in de modus om de nieuwe selectie van de
                   huidige selectie <emphasis>af te trekken</emphasis>,
                   zolang als u de <mousebutton>muisknop</mousebutton>
                   vast houdt.
                 </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                 <para>
                   Drukt u de <keycap>Shift</keycap> toets pas in
                   <emphasis>nadat</emphasis>
                   u de selectie begonnen bent door middel van een muisklik,
                   dan is het effect afhankelijk van het exacte gereedschap
                   dat u op dit moment gebruikt.
                 </para>
               </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
           </para>
	  
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            和 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 键一样，按下 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 同时创建一个选区能产生两个不同的效果。第一个根据所使用的工具而有所不同，不过一般都是对工具在某方面进行限制：比如，它限制矩形选择工具选区一个<emphasis>正方形</emphasis>区域。第二个效果就是改变选取模式为“合并”，这样勾勒的区域就添加到现有选区。如果只想进行一个动作，可以在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 键。这样做就使选区呈合并模式，而不没有任何限制。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;nl"><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo></term>
        <term lang="cs"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo></term>
        <term lang="es"><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Maj</keycap></term>
        <term lang="zh_CN"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="it"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Maiusc</keycap></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Using
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            together can do a variety of things, depending on which
            tool is used.  Common to all selection tools is that the
            selection mode will be switched to intersection, so that
            after the operation is finished, the selection will
            consist of the intersection of the region traced out with
            the pre-existing selection. It is an exercise for the
            reader to play with the various combinations available
            when performing selections while holding <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap> </keycombo>
            and releasing either both or either prior to releasing the
            <mousebutton>mouse button</mousebutton>.
          </para>

          <para lang="cs">
            Použití kláves
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            dohromady může mít různé efekty v závislosti na konkrétním
            nástroji. Společné všem je přepnutí do režimu průniku, takže
            výsledný výběr se bude rovnat průniku výběru nového a již
            existujícího. Za domácí úkol si vyzkoušejterůzné kombinace
            při tvorbě výběru s klávesami
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            uvolňovanými dříve nebo později než <mousebutton>tlačítko
            myši</mousebutton>.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Durch Benutzung von
            <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            ergeben sich, in Abhängigkeit vom verwendeten Auswahlwerkzeug,
            viele verschiedene Anwendungsmöglichkeiten. Für alle
            Auswahlwerkzeuge gilt, dass wenn beide Tasten gleichzeitig
            gedrückt werden, der Auswahlmodus auf den Schnittmodus
            umgeschaltet wird. Ausserdem wird die Auswahl um den Mittelpunkt
            erstellt, sowie das Seitenverhältnis der Auswahl konstant
            gehalten. Experimentieren Sie etwas mit den Tastenkombinationen,
            um ein Gefühl dafür zu bekommen.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            La combinación
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            puede hacer una variedad de cosas, dependiendo de la herramienta
            que esté en uso. Es común a todas las herramientas que el modo de
            selección cambia a intersección, y hace que cuando la selección
            finalice, la selección consista en la intersección de la región
            trazada con la selección preexistente. Se deja como ejercicio para
            el lector jugar con las varias combinaciones disponibles al
            realizar selecciones mientras se mantienen
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            y liberándolas tanto antes como después de soltar el
            <mousebutton>botón del mouse</mousebutton>.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            La combinaison de touches
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            permet de réaliser plusieurs choses. D'abord, le mode de
            sélection passera en intersection. Ensuite, l'action spécifique 
            de l'outil sera réalisée.  C'est un bon exercice que de tester
            les différentes combinaisons possibles en appuyant sur
            <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            </keycombo> et en relâchant l'une ou l'autre avant de
            relâcher le <mousebutton>bouton gauche</mousebutton> de la
            souris.
          </para>

          <para lang="nl">
            Het gebruik van de
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            toetsen samen kan verschillende uitwerkingen hebben, ook weer
            afhankelijk van het gebruikte gereedschap. Standaard is het zo dat
            het gereedschap zal werken in <emphasis>snij</emphasis>
            modus. Dit houdt in dat zodra de gebruiker de huidige selectie
            afmaakt, de nieuwe selectie zal bestaan uit de intersectie (het
            gezamenlijke deel) van de oude selectie en de zojuist door de
            gebruiker gemaakte selectie. Ook het loslaten van een van de twee
            toetsen <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> of <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            kan verschillende uitwerkingen hebben. Het is nu dan ook een goed
            moment voor u om hier wat mee te experimenteren, zodat u een goede
            intuitie krijgt voor het effect van de verschillende knoppen.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            同时使用
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            会根据使用的何工具来做许多事。对所用选择工具相同的就是，它使选取模式呈相交，这样当操作结束后，您勾勒区域和原有选区的相交区域将构成选区。读者可以自己实践在创建选区时，按住 <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap> </keycombo> 和在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前同时松开或松开其中一个的多种不同组合。
          </para>

          <para lang="it">
            I tasti 
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
            </keycombo>
             usati insieme possono fare una varietà di cose a seconda
             dello strumento utilizzato.  Effetto comune a tutti gli
             strumenti di selezione è che la modalità di selezione verrà
             variata in "intersezione", quindi ad operazione finita, la
             selezione consisterà nell'intersezione dell'area tracciata
             e della selezione preesistente.  Lasciamo al lettore
             l'esercizio di giocare con le varie combinazioni
             disponibili per eseguire selezioni tenendo premuti i tasti
             <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
             </keycombo> rilasciandoli sia prima che dopo aver
             rilasciato il <mousebutton>pulsante del
             mouse</mousebutton>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry lang="en;es;fr;nl"> <!--Added 060217-->
        <term lang="en">Space bar</term>
        <term lang="es">Barra espaciadora</term>
        <term lang="fr">Barre d'espacement</term>
    	<term lang="nl">Spatiebalk</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Pressing the <keycap>Space Bar</keycap> while using a selection 
            tool transforms this tool into Move tool as long as you press 
            the bar.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Presionar la <keycap>barra espaciadora</keycap> mientras
            se utiliza una herramienta de selección, cambia a la
            herramienta para mover, en tanto se mantenga presionada.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous appuyez sur la <keycap>Barre d'espace</keycap> pendant 
            l'utilisation d'un outil de sélection, l'outil se tranforme en 
            outil de Déplacement aussi longtemps que vous appuyez sur la 
            barre.
          </para>
    	  <para lang="nl">
    	    Houdt u de <keycap>Spatiebalk</keycap> ingedrukt tijdens het
    	    gebruik van een Selectie gereedschap dan verandert het
    	    gereedschap tijdelijk in een Verplaats gereedschap. Dit blijft
    	    het geval totdat u de <keycap>Spatiebalk</keycap> weer los
    	    laat.
    	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
	  <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Opties</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      Here we describe the tool options that apply to all selection tools:
      options that apply only to some tools, or that affect each tool
      differently, are described in the sections devoted to the individual
      tools. The current settings for these options can be seen in the Tool
      Options dialog, which you should always have visible when you are using
      tools. (Most users keep it docked directly below the Toolbox.) To make
      the interface consistent, the same options are presented for all
      selection tools, even though some of them don't have any effect for some
      of the tools.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Zde popisujeme volby společné všem nástrojům pro výběr, ty které jsou
      jedinečné pro jednotlivé nástroje nebo fungují u různých nástrojů různě,
      zde neuvádíme – jsou popsány v částech věnovaných daným nástrojům.
      Aktuální nastavení těchto voleb si můžete prohlédnout v dialogu Volby
      nástrojů, který byste měli mít při práci s nástroji vždy na očích.
      (Většina uživatelů ho má dokovaný přímo pod Panelem nástrojů.) Aby bylo
      rozhraní konzistentní, jsou stejné volby zobrazeny u všech nástrojů, i
      když některé nemají u některých nástrojů žádný efekt.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Nachfolgend werden diejenigen Werkzeugeinstellungen beschrieben, die für
      alle Auswahlwerkzeuge verfügbar sind. Werkzeugspezifische Einstellungen
      sind jeweils in dem Abschnitt dokumentiert, der speziell diesem Werkzeug
      gewidmet ist. Die aktuellen Einstellungen eines Werkzeuges können im
      Dialog Werkzeugeinstellungen eingesehen werden, welchen Sie bei Ihrer
      Arbeit mit <acronym>GIMP</acronym> immer eingeblendet haben sollten.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Aquí describiremos las opciones de herramientas que se aplican a
      todas las herramientas de selección: las opciones que se aplican
      sólo a algunas herramientas, o las que afectan a cada
      herramienta de manera diferente, se describen en las secciones
      dedicadas a cada una.  La configuración actual de estas opciones
      pueden verse en el diálogo de opciones de herramientas (que la
      mayoría de los usuarios tienen empotrado bajo la caja de
      herramientas).  Para hacer que la interfaz sea consistente, las
      mismas opciones están presentes para todas las herramientas,
      inclusive cuando algunas de ellas no tienen efecto en la
      herramienta.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Nous allons décrire ici les options communes à tous les outils: les 
      options spécifiques à chaque outil seront décrites avec l'outil. Vous 
      trouverez les réglages actuels de l'outil dans une boîte de dialogue 
      Options des Outils que vous devriez rendre visible chaque fois que 
      vous utilisez un outil (la plupart des utilisateurs l'arriment sous la 
      Boîte à outils). Par souci d'uniformité, les mêmes options 
      apparaissent pour tous les outils, même si elles elles ne sont pas 
      concernées.
    </para>

    <para lang="nl">
      Een aantal gereedschaps opties zijn hetzelfde voor alle Selectie
      gereedschappen; deze zullen we hier beschrijven. Opties die slechts
      voor enkele gereedschappen gelden, of die verschillend werken op alle
      Selectie gereedschappen, zullen beschreven worden in de secties voor
      die gereedschappen zelf. De huidige instellingen voor de opties kunnen
      ten alle tijden gezien worden in het Gereedschap Opties venster. Het is
      aan te raden dit venste altijd open te houden (de meeste gebruikers 
      behouden de standaard instellingen om dit venster gedocked te houden in 
      het Gereedschaps Venster). Om de interface consistent te houden worden
      alle opties getoond voor elk Selectie gereedschap, ook al heeft de optie
      geen enkele invloed op de werking van dat gereedschap.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这里我们描述下应用于所有选择工具的选项：而那些只对一些工具或对各个工具效果不同的选项则在各个工具单独的章节介绍。工具选项对话框能看到选项当前的设置，您使用工具时，也应该一直让它可见。(大部分用户保持让它直接停靠在工具箱下。)为了保持界面的一致性，所有选择工具都有相同的选项，即使一些选项对其中有些工具无效。
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Ora descriviamo le opzioni che si applicano a tutti gli strumenti
      di selezione: le opzioni che trovano applicazione solo per alcuni
      strumenti, o che influenzano ogni strumento in modo differente,
      vengono descritte nelle sezioni dedicate ai singoli strumenti.  Le
      impostazioni correnti per queste opzioni si possono vedere nella
      finestra Opzioni strumento, che dovreste tenere sempre visibile
      mentre usate questi strumenti (la maggior parte degli utenti la
      tiene agganciata subito sotto alla barra degli strumenti).  Per
      rendere l'interfaccia più coerente vengono presentate le stesse
      opzioni per tutti gli strumenti di selezione anche se alcune di
      esse non hanno effetto su alcuni strumenti.
    </para>

    <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Mode</term>
      <term lang="cs">Režim</term>
      <term lang="de">Auswahlmodus</term>
      <term lang="es">Modo</term>
      <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
      <term lang="nl">Modus</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">模式</term>
      <term lang="it">Modalità</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This determines the way that the selection you create
          is combined with any pre-existing selection.  Note
          that the functions performed by these buttons can be
          duplicated using modifier keys, as described above.  For
          the most part, advanced users use the modifier keys; novice
          users find the mode buttons easier.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Režim určuje způsob, jakým je nově vytvořený výběr zkombinován s
          výběrem již existujícím. Funkce těchto tlačítek lze dosáhnout také
          výše zmíněnými modifikačními klávesami. Zkušení uživatelé obvykle
          používají klávesy, pro začátečníky jsou jednodušší tlačítka.
        </para>
  
        <para lang="de">
          Diese Eigenschaft legt fest, in welcher Weise eine neu erstellte
          Auswahl mit einer bereits existierenden Auswahl verküpft wird. Bitte
          beachten Sie in diesem Zusammenhang auch die für die Auswahlmodi
          verfügbaren Tastenkürzel, welche im vorigen Abschnitt des Handbuches
          ausführlich erklärt wurden.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          Determina la forma en que la selección que se crea se
          combina con cualquier selección preexistente.  Note que las
          funciones realizadas por estos botones pueden duplicarse
          haciendo uso de teclas modificadoras, como se ha descrito
          arriba.  Por lo general, los usuarios avanzados usan las
          teclas modificadores, mientras que los usuarios novatos
          encuentran a los botones más fáciles de usar.
        </para>
  
        <para lang="fr">
          Le Mode détermine la façon dont la sélection que vous créez sera 
          combinée à une sélection existante. Ces fonctions peuvent aussi 
          être réalisée avec les touches de contrôle, comme nous l'avons vu 
          plus haut.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
    	  De Modus bepaald de manier waarop de selectie die u maakt gecombineerd
    	  wordt met de (huidige) bestaande selectie. Deze opties komen overeen
    	  met de al beschreven sneltoetsen. Zoals gezegd maken gevorderde 
    	  gebruikers meestal gebruik van de sneltoetsen, omdat deze sneller werken.
    	  Voor beginners is het echter gemakkelijker om de modus knoppen te gebruiken.
        </para>
	
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          它决定您创建的选区和原有选区间的关系。要注意的是，上面提到过的，这些按钮所提供的功能于使用控制键是重复的。通常是高级用户使用控制键；新手觉得模式按钮更容易。
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Questa determina il modo in cui la selezione che create si
          combina con la selezione preesistente.  Notate che le funzioni
          eseguite da questi pulsanti si possono riprodurre usando i
          tasti modificatori come descritto sopra. In genere gli utenti
          esperti usano i tasti modificatori; i novizi trovano più
          facile usare i pulsanti.
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Replace mode will cause any existing selection to be destroyed or
          replaced when the new selection is created.
        </para>

        <para lang="cs">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Režim nahrazení zruší jakýkoliv již existující výběr a zcela ho
          nahradí výběrem novým. Na starý výběr se nebere žádný ohled.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Der Modus Ersetzen, ersetzt die vorhandene Auswahl durch die neu
          erstellte Auswahl
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          El modo reemplazar hace que cualquier selección existente sea
          destruida o reemplazada cuando una selección nueva sea creada.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Le mode Remplace la sélection courante fait que la sélection
          existante sera détruite par la nouvelle.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          De vervang modus zorgt ervoor dat de huidige selectie verwijderd
          wordt, en vervangen door de nieuwe selectie wanneer deze nieuwe
          selectie gemaakt wordt.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          当创建新的选区时，替换模式将破坏任何已经存在的选区。
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          La modalità di sostituzione comporterà la distruzione o la
          sostituzione di ogni selezione esistente ogni qualvolta viene creata
          una nuova selezione.
        </para>


        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Add mode will cause the new selection to be added to any existing
          selection regions.
        </para>

        <para lang="cs">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Režim přidávání stávající a nový výběr sečte.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Der Modus Hinzufügen, fügt die neue Auswahl zur bereits bestehenden
          Auswahl hinzu.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          El modo añadir hace que la selección sea añadida a cualquier
          selección existente.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Le mode Ajouter à la sélection courante fait que la nouvelle
          sélection s'ajoute à l'existante.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          De modus om de selectie toe te voegen zorgt ervoor dat de nieuwe
          selectie toegevoegd wordt aan huidige selectie. De nieuwe selectie
          en de huidige selectie vormen dan samen een geselecteerd gebied.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          合并模式将添加新创建选区到任何已经存在的选择区域。
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          La modalità di addizione comporterà l'aggiunta della nuova selezione
          ad ogni zona selezionata esistente.
        </para>


        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Subtract mode will remove the new selection area from any existing
          selection regions.
        </para>

        <para lang="cs">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Režim ubírání odečte nový výběr od výběru stávajícího.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Im Modus Subtrahieren wird der sich überlappende Bereich zwischen
          einer neu erzeugten Auswahl und der vorhandenen Auswahl von der
          vorhandenen Auswahl abgezogen. Überlappen sich die neu erzeugte
          Auswahl und die bereits Bestehende nicht, bleibt die bestehende
          Auswahl vollständig erhalten.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          El modo de extracción borra el área de selección nuevo de cualquier
          selección existente.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Le mode Soustraire de la sélection courante soustrait de la
          sélection existante la partie commune aux deux sélections.
        </para>


        <para lang="nl">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          De modus om de selectie van de huidige selectie af te trekken doet
          precies dat: het resultaat is het gebied van de huidige selectie dat
          niet in de nieuwe selectie zit.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          减去模式将从任何已存在选区中去除新建选区。
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          La modalità di sottrazione rimuoverà l'area della nuova selezione da
          ogni zona selezionata esistente.
        </para>


        <para lang="cs">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Výsledkem použití režimu průnik je výběr pouze v oblastech, kde se
          starý a nový výběr překrývají.
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Intersection mode will make a new selection from the area where the
          existing selection region and the new selection region overlap.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Im Schnittmodus bildet der sich überlappende Bereich zwischen der
          erzeugten und der bestehenden Auswahl die neue Auswahl.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          El modo intersección hace una selección nueva del área en que la
          selección existente y la selección nueva se solapan.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Intersection avec la sélection courante crée une sélection
          résultante qui est la partie commune aux deux sélections.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          In de Snij modus bestaat het resultaat uit het overlappende gedeelte
          van de huidige selectie en de nieuwe selectie (ook wel de
          intersectie geheten).
        </para>


        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          相交模式将在已存在选区和新选择区域重合处产生一个新选区。
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref="../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png"
                format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          La modalità di intersezione creerà una nuova selezione nell'area
          dove la selezione esistente e la nuova selezione si sovrappongono.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Antialiasing</term>
      <term lang="cs">Vyhlazování</term>
      <term lang="de">Kantenglättung</term>
      <term lang="es">Alisado (antidentado)</term>
      <term lang="fr">Lissage</term>
      <term lang="nl">Anti-aliasing</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">边缘平滑</term>
      <term lang="it">Antialiasing</term>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This option only affects a few of the selection tools: it causes the
          boundary of the selection to be drawn more smoothly.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tato volba ovlivňuje jen některé nástroje pro výběr: výsledkem je
          hladší hranice výběru.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Diese Option hat nur auf einige der Auswahlwerkzeuge eine
          Auswirkung: Sie sorgt für eine Weichzeichnung der Auswahlkanten.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Esta opción sólo afecta a unas pocas herramientas de selección: hace
          que los contornos de la selección se dibujen más suavemente.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Cette option n'affecte que certains outils de sélection.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Quest'opzione influenza solo un paio degli strumenti di selezione:
          fa si che i bordi della selezione vengano tracciati in maniera più
          morbida.
        </para>
        <para lang="nl">
          Deze optie heeft maar op enkele van de Selectie gereedschappen
          effect: de rand van de selectie zal vloeiender gemaakt worden als
          deze optie aanstaat. Zonder anti-aliasing kan (met name een
          niet-rechte) rand erg hoekig worden, anti-aliasing maakt deze hoeken
          minder scherp, oftewel vloeiender.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">该选项只对一部分选择工具有效：它使选区边缘被画地更加平滑。</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Feather Edges</term>
      <term lang="cs">Feather Edges</term>
      <term lang="de">Kanten ausblenden</term>
      <term lang="es">Difuminar bordes</term>
      <term lang="fr">Adoucir les contours</term>
      <term lang="nl">Zachte Randen</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">边缘羽化</term>    
      <term lang="it">Margini sfumati</term>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This options allows the boundary of the selection to be
          blurred, so that points near the boundary are only partially
          selected.  For further information regarding feathering, see
          the glossary entry 
          <link linkend="glossary-feathering">Feathering</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="cs">
          Tato volba umožňuje vytvořit rozmazanou hranici výběru, takže body
          poblíž hranice jsou vybrány jen částečně. Více informací najdete v
          příslušném hesle ve slovníčku.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Der <guilabel>Radius</guilabel> Schieber legt die Länge des
          Übergangs der ausgeblendeten Kanten fest. Ein veränderter Wert
          wird für die nächste Auswahl wirksam. Der Radius kann einen
          Wert zwischen 0 (keine Überblendung der Kanten) und 100
          (starke Überblendung) annehmen. Eine ausführliche Beschreibung der
          Eigenschaft
          <link linkend="glossary-feathering">Kanten ausblenden</link>
          finden Sie im Glossar.
        </para>

        <para lang="es">
          Estas opciones permiten difuminar el contorno de la
          selección, de modo que los puntos cercanos al contorno se
          vean parcialmente seleccionados. Para mayor información
          sobre difuminado, diríjase a la entrada del <link
          linkend="glossary-feathering">glosario</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Le curseur <guilabel>Rayon</guilabel> règle la largeur en
          pixels de l'estompage des bords de la nouvelle sélection. Vous
          trouverez plus d'information dans le Glossaire à l'article
          <link linkend="glossary-feathering">Adoucir</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="nl">
          Met de zachte randen optie ingeschakeld wordt de rand van de 
          selectie vervaagt, door punten rondom deze rand slechts gedeeltelijk
          te selecteren. Meer informatie over 
          <!--<link linkend="glossary-feathering">-->Zachte randen<!--</link>--> vindt u in 
          het betreffende hoofdstuk.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该选项选区边缘被模糊，这样靠近边缘的点只是被部分选中。关于羽化的更多信息请看<link linkend="glossary-feathering">羽化</link>。
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Quest'opzione permette di sfumare i margini della selezione, in
          modo che i punti vicini ai bordi siano solo parzialmente
          selezionati. Per maggiori informazioni sulla sfumatura, vedi la
          voce di glossario
          <link linkend="glossary-feathering">Margini sfumati</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Additional information</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Další informace</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Ergänzende Informationen</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Información adicional</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Information supplémentaire</phrase>
      <phrase lang="nl">Aanvullende informatie</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">附加信息</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Informazioni aggiuntive</phrase>
    </title>

    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        When moving a selection beyond the boundaries of the image canvas, the
        selection will be cropped to the image area. Selections can exist on
        the visible canvas only. Selection movements and changes are, however,
        kept in the undo buffer should you need to repair an error.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Při přesunu výběru mimo hranice plátna bude výběr ořezán jen na část v
        obrázku. Výběry mohou existovat pouze na viditelném plátně. Přesuny a
        změny výběru však lze vrátit pomocí funkce Zpět, takže chybu lze
        napravit.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn die Auswahl über die Bildgrenze hinausgeht, wird diese an den
        Bildgrenzen beschnitten. Eine Auswahl kann nur auf der sichtbaren
        Ebene erstellt werden. Verschiebungen oder Veränderungen an der
        Auswahl lassen sich rückgängig machen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es"> 
      Al mover una selección mas allá de los contornos de la imagen,
      la selección será recortada al área de la imagen.  Las
      selecciones pueden existir solamente sobre el área visible.  Sin
      embargo, los movimientos de la selección y sus cambios se
      conservan en el historial de deshacer, en caso de que se
      necesite revertir un error.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quand vous déplacez une sélection au-delà des limites du canevas, elle
        est découpée aux limites de l'image. Les sélections ne peuvent exister
        que sur le canevas visible. Néanmoins, les mouvements et les
        changements de la sélection sont conservés dans le tampon Défaire au
        cas où vous auriez besoin de corriger une erreur.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Quando si sposta una selezione oltre ai limiti dei bordi della
        superfice dell'immagine, la selezione verrà tagliata all'area
        dell'immagine. Le selezioni possono esistere solo sulla superfice
        visibile. Gli spostamenti e le modifiche alle selezioni vengono
        comunque conservate nella memoria per gli annullamenti nel caso
        abbiate bisogno di rimediare ad un errore.
      </para>
      <para lang="nl">
        Wanneer u een selectie buiten de grenzen van het afbeeldings canvas
        maakt, wordt de selectie beperkt tot het gebied van de afbeelding.
        Selecties kunnen namelijk alleen op het zichtbare canvas bestaan.
        Bewegingen en veranderingen van de selecties worden desondanks
        opgeslagen in de bewerkingsgeschiedenis voor het geval u een en ander
        moet corrigeren.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当移动一个选区超过画布外时，其外的选区将被裁剪。选区只能在可见画布内。尽管如此，选区移动和更改都保存在撤消缓冲区内，您可以用其来修正错误。
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
