<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-painting' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Painting Tools (Pencil, Paintbrush, Airbrush)</title>
  <title lang="de">Bleistift, Pinsel, Airbrush</title>
  <title lang="fr">Outils de dessin (Crayon, Pinceau, Aérographe)</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">涂画工具(铅笔，画笔和喷枪)</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具箱</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Painting Tools</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">涂画工具</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/toolbox/painting-examples.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Three strokes painted with the same round fuzzy brush (outline
          shown in upper left), using the Pencil (left), Paintbrush
          (middle), and Airbrush (right).
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Drei Striche wurden mit der gleichen, weichen Pinselform
          gezeichnet. Von Links nach Rechts: Bleistift, Pinsel, Airbrush.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          三个使用相同圆的模糊画笔(显示在左上方)涂画的笔划，分别使用铅笔(左)，画笔(中)和喷枪(右)。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The tools in this group are GIMP's basic painting tools, and they
    have enough features in common to be worth discussing together in
    this section.  Features common to all brush tools are described in
    the <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Common Features</link>
    section.  Features specific to an individual tool are described in
    the section devoted to that tool.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    该组的工具是 GIMP 中基本的涂画工具，它们有很多相同的特性，所以有必要在这节将它们一起介绍。画笔工具的所以共同特性在<link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>基本特性</link>中有介绍，而每个工具单独的特性则在其自己的章节中介绍。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Pencil is the crudest of the tools in this group:  it makes
    hard, non-anti-aliased 
    brushstrokes.  The Paintbrush is intermediate: it is probably the
    most commonly used of the group.  The Airbrush is the most
    flexible and controllable:  it is the only one for which the
    amount of paint applied depends on the speed of brush movement.
    This flexibility also makes it a bit more difficult to use than
    the Paintbrush, however.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    铅笔是该组中最原始的工具：它产生硬质，没有平滑边缘的画笔笔划。画笔则高级一些：它可能是该组中最常用的。喷枪是最灵活和可控制的：它是唯一依靠画笔移动速度来决定其涂画量，不过该灵活性使它比画笔稍微难使用一些。
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    All of these tools share the same brushes, and the same options
    for choosing colors, either from the basic palette or from a
    gradient. All are capable of painting in a wide variety of modes. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    所以这些工具共享相同的画笔，和相同的选择颜色的选项--从渐变或基本色板中。它们都可以在多种模式中涂画。
  </para>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de modification</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="de">
          <keycap>Strg</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding down the Ctrl key changes each of these tools to a <link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Color Picker</link>:
              clicking on any pixel of any layer sets the foreground
              color (as displayed in the Toolbox Color Area) to the
              color of the pixel.
          </para>
          
          <para lang="de">
            Mit der <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste wird die <link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Pipette</link> aufgerufen.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> transforme le crayon en <link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Pipette à couleurs</link>.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 会使这些工具转为<link linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>颜色拾取</link>：点击任何图层中的像素，将使前景色(显示在工具箱颜色区域中)变为该像素的颜色。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Mode</term>
      <term lang="de">Modus</term>
      <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">模式</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>                         <!--changed 040908--> 
          The Mode dropdown list provides a selection of paint application
          modes. This setting appears in the Tool Options for all
          brush tools, but it is grayed out for all except the tools
          in this group, the Ink tool, and the Clone tool.  A list of
          possible modes can be found in the <link
          linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossary</link>.  For the most part
          these modes are the same as the layer combination modes
          available in the Layers dialog, and you can understand their
          effects by imagining that the paint is applied to a separate
          layer above the target layer, with the mode for the layer
          set as specified.  Three of the modes are special, though:
        </para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Color Erase</title>
          <para>
            This mode erases the foreground color, replacing it with
            partial transparency.  It acts like the <link
            linkend='plug-in-colortoalpha'>Color to Alpha</link>
            filter, applied to the area under the brushstroke.  Note
            that this only works on layers that possess an alpha
            channel; otherwise, this mode is identical to Normal.
           </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Behind</title>
          <para>
            This mode applies paint only to non-opaque areas of the
            layer:  the lower the opacity, the more paint is applied.
            Thus, painting opaque areas has no effect; painting
            transparent areas has the same effect as normal mode.  The
            result is always an increase in opacity.  Of course none of
            this is meaningful for layers that lack an alpha channel.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/dissolve-mode-example.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                Two brushstrokes made with the Airbrush, using the same
                fuzzy circular brush.  Left: Normal mode.  Right:
                Dissolve mode.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Dissolve</title>
          <para>
            In this very useful mode, for fuzzy brushes the gray level
            of the brush determines not the paint density, but rather
            the probability of applying paint.  This gives a nice way of
            creating rough-looking paintstrokes.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Die verfügbaren Modi verändern die Art und Weise, wie
          die Pixel auf die Ebene gezeichnet werden. Ähnlich den Modi
          der Ebenen, repräsentieren die Zeichenmodi eine
          Überblendung mit der ausgewählten Farbe
          (-muster) und der Zeichenebene. Mehr über die
          Modi, die <acronym>Gimp</acronym> zur Verfügung stellt,
          befindet sich im <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossar</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          La liste déroulante fournit une sélection des modes 
          d'application de la peinture. La liste de ces modes se trouve dans 
          le <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossaire</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>          
          模式下拉菜单提供一系列涂画应用模式。这些模式显示在所有的画笔工具的工具选项中，不过在除了该组的其它工具中是灰色的，不如墨水和克隆工具。可选模式的列表在<link linkend='glossary-modes'>术语表</link>中。这些模式大部分和图层对话框中可用的图层组合模式相同，要理解这些效果，可以将它们想象是在目标图层上的一个选定模式的单独图层上进行涂画。有三个模式比较特殊：
        </para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>颜色擦除</title>
          <para>
          该模式擦除前景色，并用部分透明代替，其效果和对画笔笔划使用<link linkend='plug-in-colortoalpha'>颜色到 Alpha</link>滤镜相同。需要注意的是它只能对有 Alpha 通道的图层上工作，否则就相当与“正常”模式
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>背后</title>
          <para>该模式只对应用在图层的有透明度区域：不透明度越低，应用的涂画越多，因此对不透明的图层没有效果;涂画透明区域则和正常模式相同。其结果常常是使不透明度增加。当然对于没有 Alpha 通道的图层该模式没有意义。
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/dissolve-mode-example.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                用相同圆形模糊画笔的喷枪产生的画笔笔划：左：普通模式。右：融化模式。
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <formalpara>
          <title>融化</title>
          <para>
          这是非常有用的模式，对于模糊画笔，其画笔的灰度等级不光决定涂画密度，还有应用画笔的机率。它提供了一种生成粗糙画笔的好办法。
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Gradient</term>       <!--changed 040908-->
      <term lang="de">Farbverlauf</term>
      <term lang="fr">Dégradé</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">渐变</term>


      <listitem>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject lang='en;de'>
              <imagedata
              fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-paint-gradient.png'
              format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang='fr'>
              <imagedata
              fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-paint-gradient.png'
              format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang='zh_CN'>
              <imagedata
              fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-paint-gradient.png'
              format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang='en'>
                Gradient options for painting tools.
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Farbverlaufsoptionen der Malwerkzeuge.
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Les options de dégradé des outils de dessin.
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                涂画工具的渐变选项。
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para lang='en'>   
          Instead of using the foreground color (as shown in the Color
          Area of the Toolbox), by checking the "Use color from
          gradient" option you can choose to paint with a gradient,
          giving colors that change gradually along the brush
          trajectory.  For basic information on gradients, see the
          <link linkend='gimp-concepts-gradients'>Gradients</link> section.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          You have several options to control what gradient is used
          and how it is laid out:
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Bei aktiviertem Kontrollkästchen, wird keine Vorder- oder
          Hintergrundfarbe zum Zeichnen verwendet, sondern der
          ausgewählte Farbverlauf. Diese Option steht in Verbindung
          mit der Auswahl des <guilabel>Farbverlaufs</guilabel>. Bei der
          Benutzung kann die <guilabel>Länge </guilabel> in Pixeln und
          die <guilabel>Wiederholungsart</guilabel> des Farbverlaufs
          eingestellt werden.
        </para>
        <formalpara lang='fr'>
          <title>Couleur à partir du Dégradé</title>
          <para>
            Avec cette option, ce n'est pas la couleur de premier-plan ou de 
            fond qui sera utilisée pour dessiner, mais le dégradé actif. Vous 
            pouvez choisir un dégradé en cliquant sur la boîte de sélection 
            située juste à droite de "Dégradé". En cochant la case 
            <guilabel>Inverser</guilabel> vous inversez le sens du dégradé.
          </para>
        </formalpara>

        <para lang="zh_CN">   
          除了使用前景色(在工具箱颜色区域显示)，通过“使用渐变中的颜色”选项，您可以用渐变中的颜色来涂画，其颜色会随画笔轨迹逐渐变化。关于渐变的基本信息，情看<link linkend='gimp-concepts-gradients'>渐变</link>这节。
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          您有很多控制使用什么渐变和如何排列的选项。
        </para>
 
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Gradient</title>
          <para>
            Here you see a display of the current gradient.
            Clicking on it brings up a Gradient Selector, which will
            allow you to choose a different gradient.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Reverse</title>
          <para>
            Normally a brushstroke starts with colors from the left
            side of the gradient, and progresses rightward.  If
            "Reverse" is checked, the stroke starts with colors from
            the right side, and progresses leftward.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='de'>
          Über den Farbverlaufsbrowser lassen sich zwischen eigens
          erstellten Farbverläufen auch die Standardfarbverläufe
          auswählen. Diese können mit
          <guilabel>Umkehren</guilabel> invertiert werden.
          Standardmässig wird ein linearer Farbverlauf zwischen
          Vorder- und Hintergrundfarbe generiert.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Vous permet de choisir le dégradé qui sera utilisé si vous cochez 
          l'option "Couleur à partir du dégradé". Ce dégradé peut être 
          inversé en cochant l'option <guilabel>Inverser</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>渐变</title>
          <para>
            这里显示当前渐变。点击它将唤出渐变选择器，其中可以选择不同的渐变。
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>反向</title>
          <para>
            画笔笔划其颜色一般是从渐变左边的颜色向右边进行，而勾选“反向”，笔划将从渐变右边的颜色向左边进行。
          </para>
        </formalpara>

        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Length</title>
          <para>
            This option sets the distance corresponding to one
            complete cycle through the gradient colors.  The default
            units are pixels, but you can choose a different unit
            from the adjoining Units menu.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Le dégradé est peint vers l'avant (sens gauche-droite de la 
          représentation du dégradé). Toute la séquence du dégradé sera 
          utilisée sur la <guilabel>Longueur</guilabel> fixée.
        </para>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>长度</title>
            <para>
              该选项设置遍历渐变颜色完整一圈的距离，其默认单位是像素，不过通过单位菜单可以更改为不同的单位。
            </para>
        </formalpara>

      <table frame='none'>
        <title lang='en'>
          Illustration of the effects of the three gradient-repeat
          options, for the "Abstract 2" gradient. 
        </title>
        <title lang='de'>
          Illustration der Effekte durch die Farbverlauf
          Wiederholungsoptionen.
        </title>
        <title lang="zh_CN">
          “Abstract 2”渐变的三种渐变重复模式。
        </title>
        <tgroup cols='3'>
        <colspec colwidth='1in' />
        <colspec colwidth='1in' />
        <colspec colwidth='1in' />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> 
                  <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-normal.png'
                    format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
            <entry />
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                Abstract2 Gradient
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Farbverlauf
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Dégradé
              </para>
              <para lang='zh_CN'>
                Abstract2 渐变
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry />
          </row>        
          <row>
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-none.png'
                  format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-sawtooth.png'
                  format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-triangular.png'
                  format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                None
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Keine
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Aucun
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                无
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                Sawtooth
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Sägezahn
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                En dents de scie
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                锯齿
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                Triangular
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Dreieckige
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Triangulaire
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                三角
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>


        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Repeat</title>
          <para>
            This option determines what happens if a brushstroke
            extends farther than the Length specified above.  There
            are three possibilities:  "None" means that the color
            from the end of the gradient will be used throughout the
            remainder of the stroke; "Sawtooth wave" means that the
            gradient will be restarted from the beginning, which
            will often produce a color discontinuity; "Triangular
            wave" means that the gradient will be traversed in
            reverse, afterwards bouncing back and forth until the
            end of the brushstroke.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='de'>
          Ist die Option <guilabel>Farbe aus Farbverlauf</guilabel> ohne
          <guilabel>Wiederholung</guilabel> aktiviert, wird bei
          längeren Strichen mit der Endfarbe des Gradienten
          weitergezeichnet.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          <guilabel>Sägezahn Welle</guilabel>: Der Farbverlauf
          wird hintereinander auf den Pinselstrich gezeichnet. In
          Abhängigkeit von der eingestellten
          <guilabel>Länge</guilabel> des Farbverlaufs, wird
          dieser wiederholend vom Beginn an, dargestellt.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          <guilabel>Dreieckswelle</guilabel>: Ebenso wie bei der
          Sägezahn Welle, wird der Farbverlauf hintereinander
          auf den Pinselstrich gezeichnet. Der Unterschied besteht
          hier, dass der Farbverlauf in Abhängigkeit von der
          eingestellten Länge, seine Richtung beim Zeichnen
          wechselt.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Onde en dents de scie</guilabel>: chaque fois que 
          le dégradé est terminé, il reprend depuis le début. 
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          <guilabel>Onde Triangulaire</guilabel>: Chaque fois que le 
          dégradé est terminé, il change de sens, et ce jusqu'à la fin 
          du trait de pinceau.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          <guilabel>Aucun</guilabel>: le dégradé ne sera appliqué 
          qu'une fois lors du coup de pinceau, sur la longueur fixée.
        </para>
        <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
          <title>重复</title>
          <para>
            该选项决定当画笔笔划超出上面设定的长度值时如何处理。有三种可能：“无”表示剩下的笔划将使用渐变尾部的颜色;“锯齿波”指反复渲染渐变，渐变从每个长度结束处重新从头开始渲染，它常常导致颜色不连贯。“三角波”也是重复渲染渐变，不过渐变在每个长度结束时都掉转方向继续渲染直到笔划结束。
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

   </variablelist>
 </simplesect>
 
</sect2>
