<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2008-03-01 j.h: rewrote Shrink Merged. Added "arrow keys"
  2008-01-18 ude: updated 'de'
  2008-01-11 j.h: updated to v2.4 'en;fr'
  2007-06-11 kost: added 'no'
  2007-04-18 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-05-13 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-02-06 en;fr revised by j.h
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-12-01 informalfigure replaced by figure by lexa
  0506609 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
  -->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-crop" lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-01-11</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-03-05</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-18</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-01-11</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-02-29</date>
        <authorinitials>kost</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <!--TODO es;it;pl; Name has changed v2.4-->
    <phrase lang="en">Crop</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Nástroj Ořez</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Zuschneiden</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Recortar y redimensionar</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Découpage</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Taglierino</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Beskjering</phrase>
    <phrase lang="pl">Каdrowanie i zmiana rozmiaru</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Кадрирование</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">剪裁工具</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Crop</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary><secondary>Crop</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Crop</secondary>
    <tertiary>Crop tool</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Panel nástrojů</primary>
    <secondary>Ořez</secondary>
    <tertiary>Skalpel</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Zuschneiden</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary><secondary>Zuschneiden</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Herramientas</primary>
    <secondary>Recortar</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Imagen</primary>
    <secondary>Recortar</secondary>
    <tertiary>Herramienta recortar</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Recortar</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Outils</primary>
    <secondary>Découpage</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Découpage</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Scalpel</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Découper</secondary>
    <tertiary>Outil Découpage</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary>
    <secondary>Taglio e ridimensionamento</secondary>
    <tertiary>Taglierino</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Verktøy</primary>
    <secondary>Beskjering</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Transformasjonsverktøy</primary>
    <secondary>Beskjering</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Beskjering</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="pl"><primary>Kadrowanie</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Narzędzia</primary><secondary>Kadrowanie</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Obraz</primary>
    <secondary>Kadrowanie</secondary>
    <tertiary>Kadrowanie</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Кадрирование</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Инструменты</primary><secondary>Кадрирование</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Изображение</primary>
    <secondary>Кадрирование</secondary>
    <tertiary>Инструмент кадрирования</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>工具箱</primary>
    <secondary>剪裁</secondary>
    <tertiary>修剪</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en;cs;zh_CN">Crop tool</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Das Werkzeug <quote>Zuschneiden</quote> im Werkzeugfenster
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Herramienta recortar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">L'outil Découpage dans la Boîte à outils</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Lo strumento taglierino</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Symbolet for <quote>beskjering</quote> i verktøykassa
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Kadrowanie na pasku narzędzi</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Инструмент кадрирования</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;es;pl;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-crop.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-crop.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-crop.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-crop.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-crop.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/toolbox-crop.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-crop.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Crop Tool is used to crop or clip an image. It works on all the
    layers of the image, visible and invisible. This tool is often used
    to remove borders, or to eliminate unwanted areas to provide you with a
    more focused working area. It is also useful if you need a specific image
    size that does not match the original dimensions of your image.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    <!--TODO es;it;pl v2.4-->
    Just like the selection tools, the new crop tool has been enhanced with
    the v2.4 release. The resize handles actually resize the crop rectangle
    instead of providing both resize and move functionality. The tool behaves
    more naturally and consistently with other GIMP tools.
    To move, simply drag the rectangle clicking within the area. Resizing is
    possible in one or two axes at the same time dragging the handle-bars on
    the sides and corners. The outside area can be darkened with a nice
    passepartout effect to better get the idea of how the final crop will
    look like. To validate cropping, click inside the crop rectangle or
    press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroj Ořez se používá k oříznutí okrajů obrázku nebo vrstvy. Často se
    používá k odstranění nechtěných okrajů obrázku nebo k vytvoření působivého
    výřezu fotografie. Je také užitečný v případech, kdy potřebujete změnit
    velikost obrázku.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroj se používá kliknutím do obrázku a tažením myši se stále stisknutým
    tlačítkem. Při kliknutí se otevře dialog zobrazující rozměry ořezové
    oblasti a umožňující provádět rozličné akce. Pokud je zapotřebí pozměnit
    ořezovou oblast, zle tak učinit buď kliknutím na zvýrazněné rohy oblasti a
    jejich tažením, nebo změnou hodnot v dialogu. Je-li ořezová oblast správně
    nastavena, lze operaci dokončit kliknutím do ořezové oblasti nebo
    stisknutím tlačítek Ořezat či Změnit velikost v dialogu. (Jejich význam je
    popsán níže).
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Zuschneiden</quote> können sie verwenden, um einen
    Rahmen oder sonstige nicht benötigte Bildbereiche zu entfernen. Auch um
    das Bild auf eine spezifische Bildgröße zu trimmen, kann das Werkzeug
    sehr hilfreich sein.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Zuschneiden</quote> wurde, wie auch die
    Auswahlwerkzeuge, mit der <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Version 2.4 verbessert.
    Die Griffbereiche ermöglichen nun eine Größenänderung des Rechtecks.
    Insgesamt ist das Werkzeug intuitiv bedienbar und verhält sich ähnlich wie
    die anderen <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Werkzeuge.  Zur Anwendung des
    Werkzeuges klicken Sie innerhalb des Bildes und ziehen Sie mit dem
    Mauszeiger einen rechteckigen Bereich auf. Danach lassen Sie die
    <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> los.  Wenn Sie Form und Größe des
    ausgewählten Bereiches ändern möchten, können Sie dies, indem Sie die
    Griffbereiche an den Seiten oder Ecken des Bereiches anklicken und
    verschieben. Alternativ können Sie auch direkt die Werte bei den
    Werkzeugeinstellungen ändern. Der Bereich außerhalb des Rechtecks ist
    abgedunkelt, so dass Sie das Endergebnis besser abschätzen können. Um das
    Zuschneiden abzuschließen, müssen Sie einmal innerhalb des Rechtecks
    klicken oder die <keycap>Eingabe</keycap>-Taste drücken.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    La herramienta recortar se usa para recortar o redimensionar una imagen
    o capa. A menudo, se usa para quitar bordes, o para eliminar areas no
    deseadas para proporcionar un area de trabajo más concentrada. También,
    es útil si necesitas un tamaño específico de imagen, distinto de las
    dimensiones del original.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Para usar esta herramienta, pulse sobre la imagen y arrastre la región
    rectángular antes de soltar el botón del ratón. Cuando se pulsa, aparece
    un diálogo mostrando las dimensiones de la región de recorte, y que
    permite relizar varias acciones. Si quiere alterar la región de recorte
    puede pulsar y arrastrar las esquinas o cambiando los valores en el
    diálogo. Cuando esté listo, puede completar la operación bien pulsando
    en el interior de la región de recorte o pulsando los botones recortar
    o redimensionar en el diálogo.
  </para>
  <tip lang="es">
    <para>
      Si encuentra que el diálogo se entromete en su camino más que ayudarle,
      puede evitar que aparezca manteniendo pulsada la tecla
      <keycap>Mayus</keycap> cuando pulsas por primera vez sobre la imagen.
      Trabajando de esta manera en la modificación de la región de recorte
      arrastrando las esquinas y pulsando en el interior de la misma.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cet outil sert à découper une image. Il agit sur tous les calques de
    l'image, visibles et invisibles. Il est surtout utilisé pour éliminer les
    bordures et pour supprimer des surfaces non désirées, de façon à vous
    fournir une surface de travail mieux ciblée. C'est l'outil de
    <emphasis>Recadrage</emphasis> par excellence.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le nom anglais de cet outil est <quote>Crop</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Comme les outils de sélection, le nouvel outil de Découpage a été
    amélioré avec la version 2.4. Les poignées de re-dimensionnement servent
    uniquement au redimensionnement au lieu de permettre aussi le
    déplacement. L'outil se comporte ainsi plus naturellement, en accord avec
    les autres outils. Pour déplacer la zone découpée, cliquez simplement à
    l'intérieur de la zone et faites-la glisser. Le redimensionnement est
    possible dans un ou deux axes en faisant glisser les poignées des bords
    et des coins. La zone qui sera éliminée peut être assombrie avec un joli
    effet de passe-partout, afin d'avoir une meilleur idée de ce à quoi le
    découpage final ressemblera. Pour valider le découpage, cliquez à
    l'intérieur du rectangle de découpage ou appuyez sur la touche
    <keycap>Entrée</keycap>.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Lo strumento taglierino viene usato per tagliare o ridimensionare
    un'immagine o un livello. Questo strumento viene spesso usato per
    rimuovere bordi o per eliminare aree indesiderate consentendo di
    concentrarsi maggiormente sull'area di interesse. È anche utile se serve
    specificare una dimensione immagine che non corrisponde con le dimensioni
    originali..
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Per usare lo strumento, fare clic dentro l'immagine e trascinare fuori una
    regione rettangolare prima di rilasciare il tasto del mouse. Quando si fa
    clic, si porta in primo piano una finestra che mostra le dimensioni della
    regione tagliata permettendo di effettuare varie azioni. Se si vuole, è
    possibile modificare la regione di taglio, sia facendo clic e trascinando
    gli angoli o cambiando i valori nella finestra di dialogo. Quando si è
    pronti, è possibile completare l'operazione facendo clic dentro la regione
    tagliata o premendo il pulsante del taglierino o del ridimensionamento
    sulla finestra di dialogo (vedere sotto...).
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Dette verktøyet blir først og fremst brukt for å beskjere biletet, dvs. å
    skjere vekk meir eller mindre av biletkantane for å framheva motivet
    eller gi betre balanse i biletet. Det kan også vere nyttig når du har
    behov for å ha biletet i eit bestemt format.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Tilliks med utvalsverktøya, blei også beskjeringsverktøyet forbetra
    i GIMP versjon 2.4. Handtaka i kvart hjørne av beskjeringsrektangelet
    blir nå bare brukt til å forandra storleiken på rektangelet, ikkje for
    å flytte det. Dette for å få verktøyet meir i samsvar med dei andre 
    verktøya i GIMP. For å flytte beskjeringa, klikkar du nå ein stad inne
    i rektangelet og drar det til ønskt stad. Ved å klikke og dra i eit av
    handtaka, kan du utvida rektanelet i ei eller to retningar. Det er 
    også tilsvarande handtak for kvar side i rektangelet. Det er råd å
    gjere alt som kjem utanfor beskjeringsrektangelet mørkare slik
    at det er lettare å sjå korleis utskjeringa blir. Når alt er slik du vil
    ha det, klikkar du på innsida av rektangelet, eller trykker 
    <keycap>Enter</keycap>-tastene, for å utføre klippinga.
  </para>

  <para lang="pl">
    Narzędzie służy do przycinania obrazu lub warstwy. Najczęściej jest ono
    używane w celu usunięcia brzegów lub niepotrzebnych części obrazu, aby
    łatwiej było się skupić na głównych obszarach obrazu. Narzędzie jest
    także przydatne do uzyskania obrazu o określonych wymiarach.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Aby skorzystać z narzędzia należy kliknąć wewnątrz obrazu i przy pomocy
    kursora zaznaczyć prostokątny obszar (przy wciąż wciśniętym LPM). Kliknięcie
    spowoduje pojawienie się okna dialogowego, wskazującego rozmiar kadrowanego
    obszaru i pozwalającego na przeprowadzenie różnych operacji. Aby zmienić
    rozmiar, wystarczy przeciągnąć rogi powstałego obszaru lub zmienić wartości
    w oknie. Skadrowanie nastąpi po kliknięciu we wnętrzu obrazu lub kliknięciu
    przycisków Каdruj lub Zmień rozmiar w oknie.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Инструмент кадрирования используется для отрезания частей изображения или
    слоя. Этот инструмент обычно используется для удаления краёв или ненужных
    областей для работы над главными частями изображения. Он также полезен,
    когда нужно получить изображение определённого размера.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Для использования инструмента нажмите внутри изображения и определите
    передвижением мышки прямоугольную область до отпускания кнопки. При нажатии
    появится диалог, который покажет размер кадрируемой области и позволит
    провести разные операции. Чтобы изменить размер, двиньте углы области или
    измените значения в диалоге. Кадрирование выполняется нажатием внутри
    изображения или нажатием кнопок Кадрировать или Изменить размер в диалоге.
    Внешняя область может быть затемнена, чтобы лучше увидеть, как будет
    выглядеть результат. Чтобы окончить кадрирование, нажмите внутри
    прямоугольника кадрирования или нажмите клавишу <keycap>Ввод</keycap>.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    剪裁工具被用做剪裁一个图像或图层。其最大用处就是可以移除边界，删除不想要的区域或提供更加集中的工作区域。在要得到特定图像大小(如桌面墙纸)时也非常有用。
  </para>

<!--Obsolete: no longer exists in v2.4
  <tip lang="en;cs;de;fr;it;no;pl;ru">
    <para lang="en">
      If you find that the dialog gets in your way more than it helps you, you
      can prevent it from appearing by holding down the <keycap>Shift</keycap>
      key when you first click on the image. Working this way means altering
      the crop region by dragging the corners, and executing the operation by
      clicking inside the image.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Pokud vám dialog překáží, lze jeho zobrazení zakázat podržením klávesy
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> při prvním kliknutí nástrojem do obrázku.
      Velikost a umístění ořezové oblasti je pak nutno měnit tažením jejích
      rohů; operaci je nutné dokončit kliknutím do ořezové oblasti.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie das Dialogfenster als eher störend denn hilfreich empfinden,
      können Sie es unterdrücken, indem Sie beim ersten Klick zur Erstellung
      des zu bearbeitenden Bereiches die <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste
      gedrückt halten. Wenn das Dialogfenster nicht angezeigt wird,
      können Sie den Bereich durch Verschieben der Eckpunkte korrigieren und
      mit einem Klick innerhalb des Bereiches die Aktion auslösen.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Si la fenêtre de dialogue vous gêne, vous pouvez l'empêcher
      d'apparaître en appuyant sur la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap>
      quand vous cliquez sur l'image au début de l'opération. En travaillant
      de cette façon, vous devrez tirer sur les coins pour modifier la
      région à découper, et exécuter l'opération en cliquant à l'intérieur
      de l'image.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Se trovate che la finestra di dialogo sia più d'impedimento che
      d'aiuto, è possibile evitarne l'apparizione mantenendo premuto il
      tasto <keycap>Maiusc</keycap> facendo il primo clic sull'immagine.
      Lavorando in questo modo è possibile modificare la regione di taglio
      trascinando gli angoli e successivamente eseguendo il comando facendo
      clic all'interno dell'immagine.
      image.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dersom dialogvindauget er meir i vegen enn til hjelp, kan du fjerne det
      ved å halde nede <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten når du klikka første
      gong på biletet. Du kan i tilfelle bare forandra på beskjeringsområdet
      med klikk-og-dra og bekrefta handlinga ved å klikke innføre biletet.
    </para>
    <para lang="pl">
      Jeśli okno dialogowe przeszkadza, zamiast pomagać, można go wyłączyć
      poprzez przytrzymanie <keycap>Shift</keycap> podczas pierwszego kliknięcia
      na obrazie. W tym wypadku wielkość kadrowanego obszaru można zmienić
      przeciągając jej rogi, а skadrowanie nastąpi po kliknięciu wewnątrz obrazu.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Если вам мешает диалог, его можно отключить, нажав клавишу
      <keycap>Shift</keycap> при первом нажатии на изображение. В этом случае
      область кадрирования определяется перемещением углов области, а операция
      выполняется нажатием внутри изображения.
    </para>
  </tip>-->

  <!--TODO es;it;no;pl;ru-->
  <para lang="en">
    When the mouse becomes the moving cross-hair, you can use the keyboard
    arrow keys to move the crop rectangle. Holding the
    <keycap>Shift</keycap> key down allows to move by steps of 25 pixels.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    You can use Guides to position the crop area. Make sure that the
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>View</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Snap to Guides</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    option is checked.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Wenn der Mauszeiger die Form eines Kreuzes annimmt als Zeichen zum
    Verschieben, können Sie auch die Pfeiltasten verwenden, um das
    Umrissrechteck zu verschieben. Halten Sie dabei die
    <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste gedrückt, erfolgt die Verschiebung jeweils
    in 25-Pixel-Schritten.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Sie können auch Hilfslinien benutzen, um den Auschneidebereich
    festzulegen. Vergewissern Sie sich aber, dass die Eigenschaft
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Ansicht</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Magnetische Hilflinien</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    aktiviert ist.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Quand le pointeur de la souris a la forme de la croix de déplacement,
    vous pouvez utiliser les touches fléchées du clavier pour déplacer le
    rectangle de découpage. En appuyant en même temps sur la touche
    <keycap>Maj (Shift)</keycap>, le déplacement se fait par pas de 25
    pixels.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Vous pouvez utiliser des Guides pour positionner le rectangle de
    découpage. Assurez-vous que l'option
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Affichage</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Aligner sur les guides</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    est cochée.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Activate the Tool</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar la herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione dello strumento</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Аktywacja narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Активация</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">启动工具</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist lang="cs">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Nástroj Ořez lze vyvolat z nabídky okna obrázku následujícím
          způsobem:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Nástroje</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Nástroje transformace</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Ořezání a rozměry</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Nástroj lze vyvolat i kliknutím na jeho ikonu v Panelu nástrojů:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="en">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this tool from the image-menu through:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Transform tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Crop</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Tool can also be called by clicking the tool icon:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <!--TODO it;es;pl-->
        <para>
          or by using the
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo> keys.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="de">
      Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten, das Werkzeug
      <quote>Zuschneiden</quote> zu aktivieren:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Menü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>T</accel>ransformationswerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>uschneiden</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          im Bildfenster,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          mit einem Mausklick auf das Symbol
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          im Werkzeugfenster sowie
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Tastenkürzel
          <keycombo><keycap>Umschalt</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="es">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          En el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Herramientas</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Herramientas de transformación</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Recortar y redimensionar</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          También se puede seleccionar pulsando sobre el icono de la
          herramienta:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="fr">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          L'outil Découper peut être appelé à partir de la barre de
          menus de l'image par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Outils</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Outils de transformation</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Découpage</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Il peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          dans la Boîte à outils,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          ou par le raccourci-clavier
          <keycombo><keycap>Maj</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="it">
      <listitem>
        <para>Lo strumento taglierino può essere invocato nel seguente
        ordine, dal menu immagine:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Strumenti</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Trasformazione</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Taglio e ridimensione</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Lo strumento può essere richiamato anche facendo clic sull'icona
          corrispondente:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan hente fram dette verktøyet på to måtar:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="no">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Frå biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Verktøy</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Transformasjonsverktøy</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Beskjering</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          ved å klikke på symbolet
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          i verktøykassa
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          eller ved å bruke tastekombinasjonen
          <keycap>Shift</keycap> + <keycap>C</keycap>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="pl">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Narzędzie można aktywować poprzez menu obrazu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Narzędzia</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Narzędzia przekształcania</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Kadruj</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Narzędzie może być również aktywowane poprzez kliknięcie ikony
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="ru">
      Инструмент кадрирования можно вызвать из меню изображения
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="ru">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Инструменты</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Инструменты преобразования</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Кадрирование</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          нажатием на пиктограмму инструмента
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          или при помощи клавиши
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem>
        <para>
           按如下步骤启动剪裁工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>变换工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>剪裁和改变大小</guimenuitem>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
           也可以点工具图标：
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <tip lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;pl;ru">
      <para lang="cs">
        Jinou, rychlejší možností, jak ořezat obrázek, je použití funkce
        Ořezat obrázek z nabídky Obrázek okna obrázku.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        A different and quicker way to crop selections is using the
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>rop Image</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        function in the Image menu.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Um ein Bild auf eine bestehende Auswahl zuzuschneiden, gibt es einen
        schnelleren Weg: wählen Sie im Bildfenster den Menüeintrag
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>B</accel>ild</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Bild <accel>z</accel>uschneiden</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Una manera rápida y diferente para recortar selecciones es el uso de
        la función
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>I</accel>magen</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>ecortar la imagen</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        en el menú de la imagen.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Une façon différente et plus rapide de découper une sélection
        est d'utiliser la fonction
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>I</accel>mage</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>écouper l'image</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        dans le menu de l'image.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Una maniera differente per ritagliare le selezioni è attraverso
        l'uso, nel menu immagine, della funzione Immagine / Ritaglia immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Ein annan, og raskare måte å beskjere utval er ved hjelp av
        funksjonen
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Bilete</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Beskjer til utvalet</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        i biletmenyen.
      </para>
      <para lang="pl">
        Szybszym sposobem aktywacji narzędzia jest wybranie
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Obraz</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Kadruj według zaznaczenia</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
  w menu obrazu.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Более быстрый способ кадрирования выделений находится в меню изображения
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Изображение</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Кадрировать изображение</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy (výchozí)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (predefinidas)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tasti modificatori (predefiniti)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Valtastane (førehandsvalde)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Кlawisze modyfikujące (Domyślne)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Клавишы-модификаторы (по умолчанию)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</phrase>
    </title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Zkratka</term>
        <term lang="en">Shortcut</term>
        <term lang="de">Tastenkürzel</term>
        <term lang="es">Atajos de teclado</term>
        <term lang="fr">Raccourcis clavier</term>
        <term lang="it">Scorciatoie</term>
        <term lang="no">Snarvegar</term>
  <term lang="pl">Skrót klawiszowy</term>
        <term lang="ru">Клавиша быстрого доступа</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">快捷键</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Zkratka
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
            přepne aktivní nástroj na Ořez.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>C</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            shortcut will change the active tool to the Crop Tool.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Tastenkombination
            <keycombo><keycap>Umschalt</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
            ruft das Werkzeug auf.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            El atajo
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Mayus</keycap>
              <keycap>C</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            cambiará la herramienta activa a la herramienta recortar
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le raccourci
            <keycombo><keycap>Maj</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
            activera l'outil Découper et Redimensionner.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La scorciatoia
            <keycombo><keycap>Maiusc</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
            cambierà lo strumento attivo nello strumento Taglio.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Tastekombinasjonen <keycap>Shift</keycap> +
             <keycap>C</keycap> vil endre det aktive verktøyet til
             beskjeringsverktøyet.
          </para>
    <para lang="pl">
            Skrót klawiszowy
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>U</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            aktywuje narzędzie.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Клавишы быстрого доступа
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>C</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            делают кадрирование активным инструментом.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
            将转到剪裁工具。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl v2.4-->
        <term lang="en">Key modifiers</term>
        <term lang="de">Tastenkombinationen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Touches de contrôle</term>
        <term lang="no">Valtastane</term>
        <term lang="ru">Клавиши-модификаторы</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When you maintain click on the crop rectangle, handles
            disapear and
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn Sie in den Zuschneidebereich klicken und die Maustaste
            gedrückt halten, verschwinden die Griffbereiche und
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Quand vous maintenez le clic sur le rectangle de découpage, les
            poignées disparaissent et
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Når du klikkar inne i beskjeringsrektangelet og held nede
            museknappen vil handtaka forsvinne.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Если продолжать нажимать на прямоугольник кадрирования, уголки
            исчезнуть и
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key toggles to the
                <guilabel>Extend from Center</guilabel> option,
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Drücken der <keycap>Strg</keycap>-Taste schaltet die
                Eigenschaft <guilabel>Aus der Mitte aufziehen</guilabel> um,
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                l'appui sur la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> bascule sur
                l'option <guilabel>Étendre depuis le centre</guilabel>,
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Trykk på <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten for å slå av og på
                <guilabel>Ekspander frå sentrum</guilabel>.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                нажатие клавиши <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> переключает параметр
                <guilabel>Расширить от центра</guilabel>,
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                holding down the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key toggles to the
                <guilabel>Fixed</guilabel> option, which makes some
                dimensions fixed.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                Drücken der <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>-Taste schaltet die
                Eigenschaft <guilabel>Fest</guilabel> um, die einige
                Größeneigenschaften fixiert.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                l'appui sur la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> bascule sur
                l'option <guilabel>Fixé</guilabel> qui permet de rendre fixes
                certaines dimensions.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                Trykker du nå ned på <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten vil du
                kunne slå av og på funksjonen <guilabel>Fast</guilabel>.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                нажатие клавиши <keycap>Shift</keycap> переключает параметр
                <guilabel>Фиксированные пропорции</guilabel>, что фиксирует
                некоторые измерения.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

<!--Obsolete v2.4
          <para lang="cs">
            Podržení klávesy <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            přepíná nástroj Ořez mezi režimy ořezu a změny velikosti.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            will switch the Crop Tool mode between Crop and Resize.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch gedrückt halten der Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap>
            wird zwischen den zwei Werkzeugmodi, <quote>Zuschneiden</quote>
            und <quote>Größe ändern</quote>, umgeschaltet.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Mantener <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> cambiará los modos de la
            herramienta entre recortar y redimensionar.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En maintenant <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            enfoncée, le mode basculera entre le mode Découper et le mode
            Redimensionner.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Mantenendo premuto il tasto <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            si passerà dallo strumento Taglio a Ridimensione.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Hald nede <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> for å bytte mellom
            <quote>beskjering</quote> og <quote>endre storleik</quote>.
          </para>
    <para lang="pl">
            Przytrzymywanie <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> pwowduje przełączanie
            pomiędzy kadrowaniem a zmianą rozmiaru.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Держание клавишы <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> переключает инструмент между
            кадрированием и изменением размера.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>，剪裁工具将在剪裁和改变大小模式间切换。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs;en;it;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="es">
          <keycap>Mayus</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="de">
          <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="es"><keycap>Mayus</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr">
          <keycap>Maj</keycap>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Podžení klávesy <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            přepíná funkci Pevný poměr stran.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            will toggle the of Fixed Aspect ratio.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch gedrückt halten der Taste <keycap>Umschalt</keycap>
            können Sie ein festes Seitenverhältnis einschalten.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Mantener <keycap>Mayus</keycap> conmutará mantener proporción.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En maintenant la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            enfoncée, on bascule la fonction Rapport L/H fixe.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Mantenendo premuto il tasto <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
            si abilita/disabilita il rapporto fisso delle proporzioni.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Hald nede <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten for å arbeida med
            uendra proporsjonar, dvs. forholdet mellom sidene.
          </para>
    <para lang="pl">
            Przytrzymanie <keycap>Shift</keycap> powoduje przełączenie
            ustawienia pola Stały: Proporcje.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Держание клавишы <keycap>Shift</keycap> переключает режим
            фиксированных пропорций.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">FIXME</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Podržení klávesy <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            přepíná funkci Povolit rozšíření.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            will toggle the use of Allow Enlarging.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch gedrückt halten der
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>-Taste wird die Eigenschaft
            <guilabel>Vergrößern zulassen</guilabel> aktiviert.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Mantener <keycap>Alt</keycap> conmutará permitir agrandar.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En maintenant la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            enfoncée, on bascule la fonction Permet d'élargir.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Mantenendo il tasto <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            si abiliterà l'uso di Permetti ingrandimento.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Hald nede <keycap>Alt</keycap>-tasten for å få lov til å
            forstørre.
          </para>
    <para lang="pl">
            Przytrzymanie <keycap>Alt</keycap> powoduje przełączanie
      stanu pola Allow growing.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Держание клавишы <keycap>Alt</keycap> переключает режим допуска
            увеличения.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Alt</keycap> 切换是否允许放大。
          </para>
        </listitem>-->

      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Verktøyinnstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Opcje narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;no;pl;ru">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Crop and Resize</quote> tool options
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften des Werkzeuges <quote>Zuschneiden</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Opciones de la herramienta <quote>Recortar y redimensionar</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Options de l'outil <quote>Découper et Redimensionner</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for verktøyet <quote>beskjering</quote>
        </phrase>
  <phrase lang="pl">
          Opcje <quote>Каdrowania i zmiany rozmiaru</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметра инструмента <quote>Кадрирование</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;es;pl;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-crop.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <!--TODO de: images/toolbox/de/tool-options-crop.png-->
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-crop.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/es/tool-options-crop.png"
                     format="PNG" lang="es" />
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-crop.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-options-crop.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Přehled</term>
        <term lang="en">Overview</term>
        <term lang="de">Übersicht</term>
        <term lang="es">Generalidades</term>
        <term lang="fr">Vue d'ensemble</term>
        <term lang="it">Panoramica</term>
        <term lang="no">Oversyn</term>
        <term lang="pl">Informacje ogólne</term>
        <term lang="ru">Общая информация</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">概述</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Volby dostupné pro nástroj Ořez lze zpřístupnit dvojitým kliknutím
            na ikonu nástroje Ořez v Panelu nástrojů:
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The available tool options for Crop can be accessed by double
            clicking the Crop tool icon.
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Werkzeugeinstellungen für das Werkzeug lassen sich durch ein
            Doppelklick auf das Symbol
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            anzeigen.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Se puede acceder a las opciones de herramientas disponibles para
            recortar pulsando dos veces en el icono de la herramienta.
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les options disponibles pour cet outil peuvent être obtenues par
            un double clic sur l'icône d'outil
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            .
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Le opzioni dello strumento disponibili per il Taglierino sono
            accessibili facendo doppio clic sull'icona dello strumento.
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Du kan få fram innstillingane for dette verktøyet ved å klikke,
            eventuelt dobbeltklikke, på symbolet
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            i verktøykassa.
          </para>
          <para lang="pl">
            Opcje narzędzia są wyświetlane po dwukrotnym kliknięciu ikony
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Параметры интсрумента доступны двойным нажатием на пиктограмму
            инструмента
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            双击剪裁工具图标可以得到可用的工具选项。
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-crop-22.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

<!--Obsolete v2.4
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Přepínač nástrojů</term>
        <term lang="en">Tool Toggle</term>
        <term lang="de">Werkzeug-Modus</term>
        <term lang="es">Conmutar herramienta</term>
        <term lang="fr">Moduler l'outil</term>
        <term lang="it">Commuta strumento</term>
        <term lang="no">Verktøymodus</term>
  <term lang="pl">Przełącznik</term>
        <term lang="ru">Переключатель инструмента</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">工具切换</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            The Tool Toggle for the Crop Tool alternates between
            <guilabel>Crop mode</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>Resize mode</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Crop Mode is the standard mode of operation for the Crop Tool.
            Cropping an image or layer will change a layer by eliminating
            everything outside the cropping area. The cropping area can be set
            by either dragging the tool to form a rectangle area or manually
            setting the origin, width, and height. Cropping areas can also be
            set based on an existing selection or by using the Auto Shrink
            button. These options are available within the Crop And Resize
            Information dialog which is shown when the Crop Tool is clicked on
            an image or layer.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            If you are cropping an image (not just a layer), then Resize Mode
            changes the shape of the image without altering the size or shape
            of the layers it contains. This may leave parts of some layers
            extending beyond the edges of the image, where you cannot see
            them, but if you move the layers, you will see that the contents
            still exist. If you are cropping a layer, Resize Mode does the
            same thing as crop mode.
          </para>
          <note lang="cs">
            <para>
              You can also switch to Resize mode in two other ways: first, by
              using the Resize button on the dialog instead of the Crop
              button; second, by holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              key while you click inside the crop region to complete the
              operation.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="en">
            The Tool Toggle for the Crop Tool alternates between
            <guilabel>Crop mode</guilabel>
            and <guilabel>Resize mode</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Crop Mode is the standard mode of operation for the Crop Tool.
            Cropping an image or layer will change a layer by eliminating
            everything outside the cropping area. The cropping area can be set
            by either dragging the tool to form a rectangle area or manually
            setting the origin, width, and height. Cropping areas can also be
            set based on an existing selection or by using the Auto Shrink
            button. These options are available within the Crop And Resize
            Information dialog which is shown when the Crop Tool is clicked on
            an image or layer.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            If you are cropping an image (not just a layer), then Resize Mode
            changes the shape of the image without altering the size or shape
            of the layers it contains. This may leave parts of some layers
            extending beyond the edges of the image, where you cannot see
            them, but if you move the layers, you will see that the contents
            still exist. If you are cropping a layer, Resize Mode does the
            same thing as crop mode.
          </para>
          <note lang="en">
            <para>
              You can also switch to Resize mode in two other ways: first, by
              using the Resize button on the dialog instead of the Crop
              button; second, by holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              key while you click inside the crop region to complete the
              operation.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="de">
            Der Werkzeug-Modus für das Zuschneiden-Werkzeug kann entweder auf
            <guilabel>Zuschneiden</guilabel> oder
            <guilabel>Größe ändern</guilabel> eingestellt werden.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Standardmäßig ist das Werkzeug auf den Modus
            <guilabel>Zuschneiden</guilabel>
            eingestellt. Der Bereich, auf den zugeschnitten werden soll, kann
            entweder durch Ziehen einer rechteckigen (Zuschneide-)Auswahl
            oder durch manuelles Eingeben der Höhen- und Breitenangaben
            erfolgen. Bei der Benutzung des Werkzeuges wird automatisch ein
            Dialogfenster eingeblendet. Dieses bietet Ihnen zusätzliche
            Einstellungsmöglichkeiten, die die Benutzung des Werkzeuges
            erleichtern.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Der Werkzeugmodus <guilabel>Größe ändern</guilabel>
            funktioniert ähnlich dem Modus <guilabel>Zuschneiden</guilabel>
            mit dem Unterschied, dass die Größe der betroffenen Ebenen nicht
            verändert wird. So bleibt die Größe der Ebene erhalten und nur
            die Pixel um den Zuschneidebereich werden entfernt.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Zuschneidebereiche können auch aus einer vorhandenen rechteckigen
            Auswahl erstellt werden. Ist der ausgewählte Bereich zu ungenau
            oder zu groß, können Sie die Funktion
            <guibutton>Automatisch schrumpfen</guibutton>
            benutzen, um den Zuschneidebereich automatisch verkleinern zu
            lassen. Dies funktioniert insbesondere dann sehr gut, wenn Sie
            einen einfarbigen Rahmen entfernen wollen.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            Conmutar herramienta, para recortar, alterna entre los modos
            <guilabel>Recortar</guilabel>
            y <guilabel>Redimensionar</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            El modo recortar es el modo estandar de operación de la
            herramienta recortar. El recorte de una imagen o capa cambiará
            la capa al eliminar todo lo exterior del area de recorte. Se
            puede seleccionar el area de recorte bien arrastrando la
            herramienta para formar un area rectángular o poniendo,
            manualmente, el origen, la anchura y la altura. Las areas de
            recorte, también se pueden basar en una selección existente o
            mediante el uso del botón autorecortar. Estas opciones están
            disponibles en el diálogo de informacion de recortar y
            redimensionar que se muestra cuando se pulsa sobre una imagen
            con la herramienta recortar.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Si está recortando una imagen ( no una capa), el modo
            redimensionar cambia la forma de la imagen sin alterar el tamaño
            o forma de las capas que contiene. Esto puede dejar parte de
            algunas capas extendidas más allá de los bordes de la imagen,
            donde no puede verlas, pero si las mueve, verá que el contenido
            todavia existe. Si está recortando una capa, el modo
            redimensionar hace lo mismo que el modo recortar.
          </para>
          <note lang="es">
            <para>
              También puede cambiar a modo redimensionar de dos maneras:
              la primera, mediante el uso del botón redimensionar en lugar
              de el botón recortar; lo segundo, manteniendo pulsada la tecla
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> mientras pulsa dentro de la región de
              recorte para completar la operación.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="fr">
            Moduler l'outil permet de passer du mode
            <guilabel>Découper les bords</guilabel>
            au mode <guilabel>Redimensionner</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le mode Découper est le mode opératoire standard pour cet outil.
            Le fait de découper une image ou un calque élimine tout ce qui est
            en dehors de l'aire découpée. L'aire découpée peut être définie
            soit en sélectionnant un rectangle avec la souris, soit en fixant
            manuellement l'origine, la largeur et la hauteur. Les aires de
            découpage peuvent aussi être basées sur une sélection ou en
            utilisant le bouton Réduction Automatique. Ces options sont
            disponibles dans la boîte d'information Découper et Redimensionner
            qui apparaît quand l'outil est cliqué sur une image ou un calque.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les deux modes, Découper et Dimensionner, peuvent donner
            l'impression que leur résultat est identique. En fait, si vous
            recadrez une image (et pas uniquement le calque actif), le mode
            Découper modifie la taille et la forme de l'image ainsi que la
            taille et la forme des calques qu'elle contient. Le mode
            Redimensionner modifie la taille et la forme de l'image sans
            modifier la taille ni la forme des calques qu'elle contient. Pour
            vous en rendre compte, utilisez l'outil Déplacement (en mode
            d'affectation Calque) et déplacez l'image : vous faites
            apparaître, dans le cadre de votre image, les parties des calques
            qui, en fait, n'ont pas été supprimées. Et cela, même si votre
            image n'a qu'un seul calque. Mais si vous recadrez seulement le
            calque actif, les deux modes Découper et Redimensionner ont le
            même effet.
          </para>
          <note lang="fr">
            <para>
              Vous pouvez aussi basculer vers le mode Rediemensionner de
              deux autres façons : en utilisant le bouton-radio <guibutton>
              Redimensionner</guibutton> dans la fenêtre des options de
              l'outil, ou en pressant la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> quand
              vous cliquez sur l'image pour réaliser l'opération.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="it">
            Commuta strumento alterna tra le modalità di
            <guilabel>Taglio</guilabel> e
            <guilabel>Ridimensione</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            La modalità Taglio è la modalità standard di operare per lo
            strumento. Tagliando un'immagine o un livello, si cambierà un
            livello eliminando ogni cosa al di fuori dell'area di taglio.
            L'area di taglio può essere impostata sia trascinando lo strumento
            per formare un'area rettangolare sia manualmente impostandone
            l'origine, la larghezza e l'altezza. Le aree di taglio possono
            essere impostate anche usando la selezione esistente, pulsante
            Dalla selezione, o tramite il pulsante di Riduzione automatica.
            Queste opzioni sono sono accessibili dalla finestra di
            informazioni di Taglio e ridimensione che viene mostrata quando si
            fa clic sullo strumento Taglierino su un'immagine o su un livello.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Se si sta tagliando un'immagine (non solo un livello) la modalità
            ridimensione cambierà la forma dell'immagine senza alterare la
            dimensione o la forma dei livelli che contiene. Ciò potrebbe
            lasciare parti di alcuni livelli che si estendono oltre i bordi
            dell'immagine, dove non è possibile vederli, ma se si spostano i
            livelli si vedrà che il contenuto esisterà ancora. Se si sta
            tagliando un livello la modalità ridimensione eseguirà la stessa
            operazione della modalità taglio.
          </para>
          <note lang="it">
            <para>
              È anche possibile passare alla modalità ridimensione in altri
              due modi: usando il tasto Ridimensione nella finestra di dialogo
              invece del tasto Taglio oppure tenendo premuto il tasto
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              mentre su fa clic all'interno della regione di taglio per
              completare l'operazione.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="no">
            Dette verktøyet har to modus: <guilabel>beskjer</guilabel> og
            <guilabel>endre storleik</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Til vanleg opererer dette verktøyet i beskjeringsmodus. Når eit
            bilete eller eit lag blir beskore, vil alt som ligg utanfor
            beskjeringsområdet bli fjerna. Sjølve beskjeringsområdet blir
            bestemt anten med klikk-og-dra eller ved å skrive nødvendige
            data i dialogvindauget. Det er også råd å bestemma dette
            området ut frå ei eksisterande markering ved å bruke knappen
            <guilabel>Autokrymp</guilabel>. Alle desse vala er tilgjengelege
            frå informasjonsvindauget som dukkar opp når du klikkar på
            biletet med dette verktøyet.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom du beskjerer eit bilete, ikkje bare eit lag, vil
            <guilabel>Endre storleik</guilabel> forandre forma på biletet
            utan å forandre laga som måtte vere der. Dette kan føre til at
            deler av biletlaga kjem utanfor biletet, og er difor usynlege til
            du flytter på laget. Ved beskjering av biletlag, gjer
            <guilabel>Endre storleik</guilabel> det same som
            <guilabel>Beskjer</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <note lang="no">
            <para>
              Du kan bytte til modus for å endre storleik på to måtar:
              ved å bruke knappen <guilabel>Endre storleik</guilabel> eller
              ved å halde nede <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten medan du
              klikkar innføre beskjeringsområdet.
            </para>
          </note>

    <para lang="pl">
            Pozwala on na przełączanie się pomiędzy
            <guilabel>trybem kadrowania</guilabel>
            i <guilabel>trybem zmiany rozmiaru</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="pl">
            Standardowym jest tryb kadrowania, pozwalający na przekształcanie warstwy
      poprzez usunięcie wszystkich elementów znajdujących się poza granicami
      kadrowanego obszaru. Obszar do kadrowania można zaznaczyć poprzez
      przeciąganie kursora lub ręcznie, wskazując jego początek i rozmiar.
            Obszar przeznaczony do kadrowania jest prostokątny. Można go także
            oznaczyć wzdłuż istniejącego zaznaczenia lub korzystając z przycisku
            Zmniejsz zaznaczenie. Funkcje te są dostępne w oknie dialogowym Kadrowania
            i zmiany rozmiaru, wyświetlanym po kliknięciu narzędziem na obrazie
            lub warstwie.
          </para>
          <para lang="pl">
            Podczas kadrowania obrazu (а nie tylko warstwy) wybranie trybu
            zmiany rozmiaru powoduje zmianę kształtu obrazu bez zmiany kształtu
      i rozmiaru warstw składowych. Może to spowodować pozostawienie części
      warstw za granicami obrazu, ale schowane części można zobaczyć
            przesuwając warstwę. Podczas kadrowania warstwy oba tryby działają
            tak samo.
          </para>
          <note lang="pl">
            <para>
              Na tryb zmiany rozmiaru można przejść na dwa sposoby:
              wybierając przycisk zmiany rozmiaru zamiast przycisku kadrowania
        w oknie dialogowym lub przytrzymując <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              przy jednoczesnym kliknięciu wewnątrz kadrowanego obszaru w celu
        zatwierdzenia operacji.
            </para>
          </note>

          <para lang="ru">
            Переключатель инструмента меняет режим между
            <guilabel>режимом кадрирования</guilabel>
            и <guilabel>режимом изменения размера</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Режим кадрирования есть стандартный режим для инструмента
            кадрирования. Кадрирование изображения изменит слой, удаляя всё за
            пределами кадрированной области. Область можно обозначить либо
            движением инструмента, либо вручную, указав начало и размер области.
            Область будет прямоугольной. Область также можно обозначить по
            существующему выделению, или используя кнопку автоскращения. Эти
            функции доступны в диалоге информации по кадрированию и изменению
            размера, который показывается при нажатии инструментом на
            изображение или слой.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При кадрировании изображения (а не только слоя) режим изменения
            размера изменяет форму изображения без изменения формы или размеры
            составляющих слоёв. Это может оставить часть слоёв за пределами
            изображения, но спрятанные части можно увидеть, передвинув слой.
            При кадрировании слоя, режимы изменения размера и кадрирования
            делают то же самое.
          </para>
          <note lang="ru">
            <para>
              Можно переключится в режим изменения размера двумя способами:
              используя кнопку изменения размера в диалоге вместо кнопки
              кадрирования; или держа клавишу <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> во время
              нажатия внутри региона кадрирования для завершения операции.
            </para>
          </note>


          <para lang="zh_CN">
            该选项在 <guilabel>剪裁模式</guilabel>
            和 <guilabel>改变大小模式</guilabel> 间切换。
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            剪裁模式是剪裁工具的标准模式。剪裁一个图像或图层将删除图层的剪裁区域外所有图像。剪裁区域可以通过托拽的矩形区域或直接输入原始，宽度和长度。剪裁区域也可以基于一个已存在的选区或使用自动收缩按钮。这些选项可以在用剪裁工具点击一个图案或图层时弹出的剪裁和改变大小信息对话框得到。
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            改变大小模式于剪裁模式工作方式相同，除了被剪裁的图层大小不改变。也就是说图层大小不变，不过剪裁区域外的像素信息被删除了。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>-->

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Pouze aktivní vrstva</term>
        <term lang="en">Current Layer Only</term>
        <term lang="de">Nur die aktive Ebene</term>
        <term lang="es">Solo la capa activa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Calque actuel seulement</term>
        <term lang="it">Solo livello corrente</term>
        <term lang="no">Bare dette laget</term>
        <term lang="pl">Тylko bieżąca warstwa</term>
        <term lang="ru">Только активный слой</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">仅对当前图层</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tato volba omezuje funkci nástroje pouze na aktivní vrstvu.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            This option will make crop affect only the active layer.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Das Zuschneiden findet nur auf der aktiven Ebene Anwendung. Andere
            Ebenen werden nicht durch das Werkzeug verändert.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Esta opción hará, que recortar o redimensionar, afecte, solo, a
            la capa activa.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Avec cette option, le découpage ne s'appliquera qu'au calque
            actif.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Quest'opzione farà in modo che il taglio o ridimensione riguardino
            solo il livello attivo.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Gjer at verktøyet verkar bare på det aktive laget.
          </para>
    <para lang="pl">
            Przy zaznaczonym polu narzędzie pracuje jedynie na warstwie aktywnej.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При выборе этого параметра, инструмент будет работать только над
            активным слоем.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">该选项使剪裁和改变大小只对当前图层有效。</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="cs">Povolit rozšíření</term>
        <term lang="en">Allow Growing</term>
        <term lang="de">Vergrößern zulassen</term>
        <term lang="es">Permitir agrandar</term>
        <term lang="fr">Autoriser l'agandissement</term>
        <term lang="it">Permetti ingrandimento</term>
        <term lang="no">Tillat forstørring</term>
        <term lang="pl">Allow growing</term>
        <term lang="ru">Позволять увеличение</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">允许放大</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tato volba umožňuje,a by ořezová oblast zasahovala mimo hranice
            obrázku či vrstvy.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            This option allows the crop or resize to take place outside the
            image or layer boundary.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese Eigenschaft erlaubt es, Größenänderungen außerhalb des
            Bildes oder der Ebenengrenzen durchzuführen.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Esta opción permite que el recorte o redimensionamiento ocupen
            parte exterior de los contornos de la imagen o capa
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette option permet au découpage de s'étendre au-delà des limites
            du calque ou de l'image.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Quest'opzione permette al taglio o alla ridimensione di
            coinvolgere anche le zone fuori dei bordi dell'immagine o del
            livello.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dette betyr at kantane av beskjeringsrektangelet kan gå 
            utanfor bilet- eller lagkanten. Biletet vil få same formatet
            som beskjeringsrektangelet.
          </para>
          <para lang="pl">
            Opcja pozwala narzędziu na wychodzenie poza granice obrazu
            lub warstwy.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Позволяет кадрированию и изменению размера выходить за пределы
            изображения или слоя.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">该选项允许剪裁和改变大小在图像或图层边缘外进行。
          </para>

          <figure lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
            <!--TODO es;it;pl;-->
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Example for <quote>Allow Growing</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Beispiel für <quote>Vergrößern zulassen</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">
                Exemple pour <quote>Autoriser l'agrandissement</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">
                Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Tillat forstørring</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="ru">
                Пример параметра <quote>Позволять увеличение</quote>
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/crop-grow-1.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  The option is checked: you can draw the crop rectangle
                  outside the image border.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Aktiviert: Sie können den Zuschneidebereich über den
                  Bildrand hinausziehen.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  L'option est cochée : vous pouvez tracer le rectangle de
                  découpage au-delà des limites de l'image.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Valet er aktivert og du kan teikne beskjeringsrektangelet
                  utanfor biletkanten.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  Выбор этого параметра: можно рисовать прямоугольник
                  кадрирования за пределами изображения.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/crop-grow-2.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  The resulting image has the same size as the crop
                  rectangle. The area outside the original image limit is
                  transparent.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Das resultierende Bild hat exakt dieselbe Größe wie das
                  Zuschneiderechteck. Der Bereich außerhalb des ursprünglichen
                  Bildes ist transparent.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  L'image résultante a la taille du rectangle de sélection.
                  La partie en dehors des limites de l'image d'origine est
                  transparente.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Resultatet blir eit bilete med same forma som 
                  beskjeringsrektangelet. Området utanfor originalbiletet
                  blir gjennomsiktig.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  У конечного изображения тот же размер, что и у прямоугольника
                  кадрирования. Область за пределами искомого изображения
                  прозрачна.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl v2.4-->
        <term lang="en">Expand from Center</term>
        <term lang="de">Aus der Mitte aufziehen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Étendre depuis le centre</term>
        <term lang="no">Ekspander frå sentrum</term>
        <term lang="ru">Расширить от центра</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When this option is checked, the crop rectangle expands from
            the first pixel you clicked taken for center. You can toggle
            this option with <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> while drawing the crop
            rectangle.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn diese Eigenschaft aktiviert ist, wird der angeklickte
            Bildpunkt der Mittelpunkt des Rechtecks. Sie können diese
            Eigenschaft umschalten, wenn Sie die <keycap>Strl</keycap>-Taste
            gedrückt halten, während Sie das Rechteck zeichnen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Quand cette option est cochée, le rectangle de découpage
            s'étendra à partir du premier pixel cliqué pris pour centre.
            Vous pouvez basculer cette option en cours de tracé en appuyant
            sur <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Denne funksjonen gjer at beskjeringsrektangelet vil utvida seg
            frå der du først klikka, med klikkpunktet som midtpunkt. Du kan
            slå denne funksjonen av og på med <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten
            medan du teiknar rektangelet.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При выборе этого параметра, прямоугольник кадрирования расширяется
            от первой нажатой точки, принимая её за центр расширения. Это
            поведение можно отключить нажатием клавиши <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> во
            время рисования прямоугольниа кадрирования.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <term lang="en">Fixed</term>
        <term lang="cs">Pevný poměr stran</term>
        <term lang="de">Fest</term>
        <term lang="es">Mantener proporción</term>
        <term lang="fr">Fixé</term>
        <term lang="it">Rapporto di dimensioni fisso</term>
        <term lang="no">Fast</term>
        <term lang="pl">Stały: Proporcje</term>
        <term lang="ru">Фиксированные пропорции</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">FIXME</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            You can also access this option by holding down the
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while drawing the crop rectangle.
            This option offers you several possibilities to make drawing
            the crop rectangle respect fixed dimensions, or their ratio:
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Je-li aktivní tato volba, bude zachováván pevný poměr mezi šířkou
            a výškou ořezové oblasti.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese Eigenschaft ermöglicht es Ihnen, verschiedene feste
            Seitenlängen oder ein festes Seitenverhältnisse zu verwenden.  Sie
            können die Eigenschaft durch Drücken der
            <keycap>Strg</keycap>-Taste, während Sie das Rechteck aufziehen,
            umschalten.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Con esta opción, el recorte mantendrá la proporción entre la
            anchura y la altura.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Vous pouvez aussi accéder à cette option en appuyant sur
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> lors du tracé du rectangle de découpage.
            Cette option vous offre plusieurs possibilities pour que
            certaines dimensions, ou leur rapport, restent fixes lors du
            tracé du rectangle de découpage :
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Con quest'opzione, il taglio rispetterà un rapporto di dimensioni
            fisso tra la larghezza e l'altezza.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Gjer at beskjeringa held seg til eit fast forhold mellom breidde
            og høgde. Du kan skrive inn dette forholdet i dialogvindauget.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            I dette valet kan du bestemma korleis beskjeringa skal bli i
            høve til originalbiletet. Du kan også slå dette valet av og på
            ved hjelp av <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten.
          </para>
          <para lang="pl">
            Opcja pozwala na zachowanie proporcji pomiędzy szerokością
            a wysokością.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот параметр активируется при нажатием клавиши
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> во время рисования прямоугольника
            кадрирования. Он позволяет сохранить ширину, высоту или пропорции
            между ними:
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">FIXME</para>

          <itemizedlist lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
            <!--TODO es;it;pl;  v2.4-->
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Aspect ratio</guilabel>: That's the default
                possibility. Width and Height keep the same ratio they have
                in the original image, when drawing the crop rectangle.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Seitenverhältnis</guilabel>: Die Voreinstellung.
                Breite und Höhe des Zuschneiderechtecks bleiben immer im
                selben Verhältnis wie beim Originalbild.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Rapport d'aspect</guilabel> : c'est la
                possibilité par défaut. La largeur et la hauteur conservent le
                rapport qu'elles ont dans l'image initiale, lors du tracé du
                rectangle de découpage.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guilabel>Sideforhold</guilabel>: Dette er det 
                førehandsinnstilde valet. Forholdet mellom breidde og høgde
                blir det same som i originalbiletet.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                <guilabel>Пропорция</guilabel>: выбран по умолчанию. Соотношение
                Ширины и высоты остаётся как и в искомом изображении.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Width / Height</guilabel>: only Width or Height
                will remain fixed. The value of this dimension can be set in
                the text box below; it defaults to 100 pixels.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Breite</guilabel>; <guilabel>Höhe</guilabel>: nur
                die ausgewählte Dimension wird fixiert. Die jeweilige Größe
                kann in dem Eingabefeld darunter festgelegt werden, ebenso wie
                die Einheit. Voreinstellung ist 100 Pixel.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Largeur / Hauteur</guilabel> : seule la largeur ou
                la hauteur restera fixe. La valeur de cette dimension peut
                être fixée dans la boîte de texte située en-dessous. Elle
                est de 100 pixels par défaut.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guilabel>Breidde / Høgde</guilabel>: Breidda eller høgda blir
                halde på den verdien som er sett i innskrivingsruta nedanfor.
                Førehandsvalet er sett til 100 pikslar.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                <guilabel>Ширина / Высота</guilabel>: только ширина или высота
                останется постоянной. Значение этого измерения можно указать в
                поле ввода ниже. По умолчанию оно - 100 точек.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Size</guilabel>: both Width and Height will be
                fixed. Their values can be set in the text box below, in the
                form <quote>150x100</quote> for example. The crop rectangle
                will adopt this values as soon as you click the image. On the
                right, two buttons let you choose a
                <guibutton>Landscape</guibutton> (widthwise) or
                <guibutton>Portrait</guibutton> (upright) format for the
                crop rectangle.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Größe</guilabel>: sowohl Breite als auch Höhe werden
                fixiert. Ihre Werte können in dem darunterliegenden
                Eingabefeld festgelegt werden, zum Beispiel
                <quote>150x100</quote>. Das Zuschneiderechteck nimmt diese
                Werte an, wenn Sie in das Bild klicken. Rechts neben dem
                Eingabefeld können Sie zwischen
                <guibutton>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <textobject><phrase>Hochformat</phrase></textobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guibutton>
                und
                <guibutton>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <textobject><phrase>Querformat</phrase></textobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                </guibutton>
                auswählen.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Taille</guilabel> : Hauteur et largeur seront
                fixes. Leur valeurs peuvent être définies dans la boîte de
                texte en-dessous, sous la forme <quote>150x50</quote> par
                exemple. Le rectangle de découpage adoptera ces valeurs dès
                que vous cliquerez sur l'image. Sur la droite, deux boutons
                vous permettent de choisir un format
                <guibutton>Paysage</guibutton> (en largeur) ou
                <guibutton>Portrait</guibutton> (en hauteur) pour le
                rectangle de découpage.
              </para>
              <para lang="no">
                <guilabel>Format</guilabel>: Breidda og høgda blir bestemt
                av tala i innskrivingsruta nedanfor. Formatet kan skrivast inn
                som to tal med ein bokstav mellom, eksempelvis som
                <quote>150x100</quote>. Beskjeringsrektangelet vil 
                bli sett til desse dimensjonane så snart du klikkar inne i 
                biletet. Heilt til høgre finn du to knappar. Den første knappen 
                gjer at formatet blir i ståande, dvs. i høgdeformat. Den andre 
                at det blir liggande, dvs. i breiddeformat.
              </para>
              <para lang="ru">
                <guilabel>Размер</guilabel>: ширина и высота останутся
                постоянными. Их значения можно ввести в поля ввода.
                Прямоугольник кадрирования примет этот размер при нажатии на
                изображение. Две кнопки справа позволяют выбрать формат
                прямоугольника:
                <guibutton>Ландшафт</guibutton> (по ширине) или
                <guibutton>Портрет</guibutton> (по высоте).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl; v2.4-->
        <term lang="en;de;fr">Position</term>
        <term lang="no">Posisjon</term>
        <term lang="ru">Положение</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            These two text boxes show the position (horizontal on the left,
            vertical on the right) of the upper left corner of the crop
            rectangle in real time and you can change it manually too. It is
            stated in pixels, but you can change the unit thanks to the
            drop-down list of the <guibutton>px</guibutton> button. The
            coordinate origin is the upper left corner of the canvas (not of
            the image).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese beiden Eingabefelder zeigen Ihnen die Position (links die
            horizontale, rechts die vertikale) der oberen linken Ecke des
            Zuschneiderechtecks. Die Position wird bei jeder Änderung
            aktualisiert. Außerdem können Sie auch über diese Felder die
            Position des Rechtecks verändern. Die Einheit ist standardmäßig
            Pixel (px), kann aber mit dem Klappmenü daneben geändert werden.
            Der Koordiantenursprung ist die linke obere Ecke der Zeichenfläche
            (nicht des Bildes).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ces deux boîtes de texte affichent en temps réel la position
            (horizontale à gauche et verticale à droite) du coin en haut à
            gauche du rectangle de découpage et vous pouvez aussi la
            modifier manuellement. Elle est exprimée en pixels, mais vous
            pouvez changer d'unité grâce à la liste déroulante du bouton
            <guibutton>px</guibutton>. L'origine des coordonnées est le coin
            en haut à gauche du canevas (et non pas de l'image).
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Desse to tekstrutene viser koordinata for det øvre, venstre
            hjørnet for beskjeringsrektangelet. Den venstre ruta viser
            horisontal og den høgre ruta vertikal posisjon. Du kan også skrive
            i boksane og såleis frandre posisjonen for rektangelet. 
            Måleeininga er til vanleg pikslar, men du kan få fram ei liste over
            andre måleeiningar ved å klikke på knappen
            <guibutton>px</guibutton>. Koordinata har nullpunktet i det
            øvre, venstre hjørnet av lerretet, ikkje biletet.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Эти поля ввода показывают позицию (слева - по горизонтали, справа -
            по вертикали) верхнего левого угла прямоугольника кадрирования в
            режиме реального времени. Позицию также можно изменить вручную.
            Единица измерения по умолчанию - точки, но её можно изменить из
            списка <guibutton>px</guibutton>. Начало координат находится в
            верхнем левом углу холста (не изображения).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl; v2.4-->
        <term lang="en">Size</term>
        <term lang="de">Größe</term>
        <term lang="fr">Taille</term>
        <term lang="no">Storleik</term>
        <term lang="ru">Размер</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            These two text boxes show the size (horizontal on the left,
            vertical on the right) of the croprectangle in real time and you
            can change it manually too. It is stated in pixels, but you can
            change the unit thanks to the drop-down list of the
            <guibutton>px</guibutton> button.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese beiden Eingabefelder geben die aktuelle Größe (links die
            horizontale, rechts die vertikale) des Rechtecks an. Auch hier
            haben Sie die Möglichkeit, die Größe durch eine Eingabe zu ändern.
            Wiederum ist die Einheit standardmäßig Pixel (px) und kann mit dem
            Klappmenü daneben geändert werden.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ces deux boîtes de texte affichent en temps réel la taille
            (horizontale à gauche et verticale à droite) du rectangle de
            découpage et vous pouvez aussi la modifier manuellement. Elle est
            exprimée en pixels, mais vous pouvez changer d'unité grâce à la
            liste déroulante du bouton <guibutton>px</guibutton>.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Den venstre ruta viser breidda og den høgre ruta høgda på
            beskjeringsrektangelet. Du kan også skrive i desse rutene.
            Måleeininga er til vanleg pikslar, men du kan få fram ei liste
            over andre måleeiningar ved å klikke på knappen
            <guibutton>px</guibutton>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Эти поля ввода показывают размер (слева - по горизонтали, справа -
            по вертикали) прямоугольника кадрирования в режиме реального
            времени. Размер также можно изменить вручную. Единица измерения по
            умолчанию - точки, но её можно изменить из списка
            <guibutton>px</guibutton>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl; v2.4-->
        <term lang="en">Highlight</term>
        <term lang="de">Hervorheben</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mise en évidence</term>
        <term lang="no">Utheving</term>
        <term lang="ru">Отблеск</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option toggles the dark outside area intended for
            highlighting the crop rectangle.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Hier können Sie umschalten, ob der Bereich außerhalb des Rechtecks
            verdunkelt werden soll, um den rechteckigen Bereich hervorzuheben.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette option bascule l'affichage de l'assombrissement
            périphérique destiné à mettre en évidence le rectangle de
            découpage.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dersom denne er aktivert, vil området utanfor 
            beskjeringsrektangelet bli gjort mørkare for å utheve rektangelet.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Этот параметр включает и выключает затемнение области за пределами
            прямоугольника кадрирования.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl; v2.4-->
        <term lang="en;fr">Guides</term>
        <term lang="de">Hilfslinien</term>
        <term lang="no">Hjelpelinjer</term>
        <term lang="ru">Направляющие</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            All kinds of guides are described in
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select" />
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die verschieden Arten von Hilfslinien, die Sie hier verwenden
            können, werden in <xref linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select" />
            beschrieben.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Toutes les sortes de guides sont décrites dans
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select" />
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Alle typar hjelpelinjer er omtalte i
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select" />
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Все виды направляющих описаны в разделе
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-rect-select" />
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl v2.4-->
        <term lang="en">Autoshrink</term>
        <term lang="de">Automatisch schrumpfen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Réduction automatique</term>
        <term lang="no">Autokrymp</term>
        <term lang="ru">Автосокращение</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The Auto Shrink button will attempt to locate a border, in the
            active layer, from which to draw dimensions from. This option
            only works well with isolated objects contrasting sharply with
            background.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Schaltfläche <guilabel>Automatisch schrumpfen</guilabel>
            versucht, den Zuschneidebereich an ein bestehendes Bildobjekt
            automatisch anzupassen. Dies funktioniert nur bei isolierten
            Objekten, die sich klar vom Hintergrund abheben,
            zufriedenstellend.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Une fois tracé le rectangle de découpage, le clic sur ce bouton
            adapte ce rectangle pour qu'il épouse au plus près l'objet à
            limite franche contenu dans le calque actif... s'il en trouve un.
            Ça ne marche bien qu'avec les objets isolés tranchant nettement
            sur le fond.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Denne knappen vil prøve å finne ein kant i det aktive laget 
            og legge beskjeringsrektangelet mest mogleg inntil denne 
            kanten. Denne funksjonen er nyttig bare dersom det finst 
            område som skil seg tydeleg ut frå bakgrunnen.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Кнопка автосокращения постарается найти границу а активном слое, от
            которой устанавливать размер. Этот параметр хорошо работает только
            с отдельными объектами, контрастирующими с фоном.
          </para>
          <figure lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
            <!--TODO es;it;pl;-->
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Example for <quote>Autoshrink</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Beispiel für <quote>Automatisch schrumpfen</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="fr">
                Exemple pour <quote>réduction automatique</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">
                Eksempel på bruk av <quote>Autokrymp</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="ru">
                Пример <quote>автосокращения</quote>
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/auto-shrink1.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  An image with a sharp limit in it and a crop rectangle.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Ein Bild mit einer scharfen Grenze und dem
                  Zuschneiderechteck.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Une image contenant une limite bien nette et un rectangle
                  de découpage.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Eit bilete med skarpe avgrensingar og eit
                  beskjeringsrektangel.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  Изображение с резкой границей и прямоугольником кадрирования.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/auto-shrink2.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  After clicking the Autoshrink button, the crop rectangle
                  has been shrunk to fit the sharp limits.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Nach einem Klick auf die Schaltfläche <guilabel>Automatisch
                  schrumpfen</guilabel> wird der Zuschneidebereich auf die
                  scharfen Grenzen verkleinert.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Après avoir cliqué sur le bouton Réduction automatique,
                  le rectangle de découpage a été réduit pour s'adapter aux
                  limites nettes.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Eit trykk på autokrymp-knappen resulterer i at 
                  beskjeringsrektangelet er tilpassa dei skarpe 
                  avgrensingane.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  После нажатия кнопки автосокращения, прямоугольник
                  кадрирования сократился до резких границ.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <!--TODO es;it;pl; v2.4-->
        <!--TODO ru Rewritten-->
        <term lang="en">Shrink Merged</term>
        <term lang="de">Vereinigung mitschrumpfen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Réduction fusionnée</term>
        <term lang="no">Krymp fletta</term>
        <term lang="ru">Сократить по образцу</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option works the same, with Auto Shrink or not. It uses the
            pixel information from all <emphasis>visible</emphasis> layers,
            rather than just from the active layer.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Falls die Eigenschaft
            <guilabel>Vereinigung mitschrumpfen</guilabel> aktiviert ist, wird
            beim Schrumpfen die Pixelinformationen aller
            <emphasis>sichtbaren</emphasis> Ebenen verwenden, nicht die der
            aktiven Ebene. Dies funktioniert unabhängig von der Eigenschaft
            <guilabel>Automatisch schrumpfen</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Cette option marche de la même façon, avec Réduction automatique
            ou non. Elle prend en compte tous les calques <emphasis>visibles
            </emphasis>, et pas seulement le calque actif.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Normalt vil autokrymp bruke data frå det aktive laget. Dersom
            <quote>krymp fletta</quote> er aktivert, vil det i staden bli 
            brukt data frå alle synlege lag.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            При выборе этого параметра автосокращение будет использовать точки
            со всего изображения, а не только из активного слоя.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

<!--Obsolete for v2.4
    <variablelist>
       <title>
        <phrase lang="cs">Informace o ořezu a rozměrech plátna</phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">Crop And Resize Information</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Zuschneideinformationen</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Información de recortar y redimensionar</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Informations Découper et Redimensionner</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Informazioni sul taglio e ridimensione</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Informasjon om beskjering og forandring av storleik
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="pl">Informacje o kadrowniu i zmianie rozmiaru</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Информация по кадрированию и изменению размера
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">剪裁和改变大小信息</phrase>
      </title>

        <para lang="de;no">
          <figure lang="de;no">
            <title>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Dialogfenster des Werkzeuges
                <quote>Zuschneiden / Größe ändern</quote>
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="no">
                Dialogvindauget for <quote>beskjering/forandre
                  storleik</quote>
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject lang="de">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-dialog-crop.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <imageobject lang="no">
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-dialog-crop.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="cs">Počátek (X a Y)</term>
          <term lang="en">Origin</term>
          <term lang="de">Ursprung X/Y</term>
          <term lang="es">Origen</term>
          <term lang="fr">Origine</term>
          <term lang="it">Origine</term>
          <term lang="no">Startpunkt</term>
          <term lang="pl">X i Y</term>
          <term lang="ru">Начало</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">原始</term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="cs">
              Tato pole umožňují ruční číselné nastavení polohy počátečního
              bodu (levého horního rohu) ořezové oblasti. Jednotky lze zvolit
              v sousedním rozbalovacím seznamu.
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              The Origin selectors allow the manual setting of the top left
              corner of the cropping region. The units may also be chosen.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Die Eingabefelder für den <guilabel>Ursprung</guilabel>
              dienen der manuellen Festlegung des Ursprungspunktes für den
              zuzuschneidenen Bereich. Der Ursprung ist immer die linke obere
              Ecke des Zuschneidebereiches. Zusätzlich können noch Einheiten
              für die Bereichsangaben ausgewählt werden.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Los selectores origen X/Y, arriba a la izquierda, permiten una
              selección manual. También se pueden escoger las unidades.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Les sélecteurs d'Origine permettent la définition manuelle du
              coin en haut à gauche de la zone à découper. On peut également
              choisir l'unité de mesure.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              L'inserimento dell'origine permette l'impostazione manuale
              dell'angolo in alto a sinistra della regione di taglio. L'unità
              di misura è selezionabile.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Startpunktet blir bestemt med koordinata skrivne inn i rutene
              <guilabel>Venstre</guilabel> og <guilabel>Topp</guilabel>.
              Utgangspunktet for verdiane er alltid det øvre, venstre
              hjørne som har koordinata (0,0).
            </para>
      <para lang="pl">
              Wartości X i Y pozwalają na wskazanie lewego górnego rogu
        kadrowania. Jednostkę miary można zmienić.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Позволяет вручную выбрать верхний левый угол области кадрирования.
              Также можно выбрать единицу измерения.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">即剪裁区域的左上起点。也可以选取其单位。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="cs">Šířka a Výška</term>
          <term lang="en">Width/Height</term>
          <term lang="de">Breite/Höhe</term>
          <term lang="es">Anchura y altura</term>
          <term lang="fr">Largeur/Hauteur</term>
          <term lang="it">Larghezza/Altezza</term>
          <term lang="no">Breidde/Høgde</term>
    <term lang="pl">Szerokość i Wysokość</term>
          <term lang="ru">Ширина и высота</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">宽度/高度</term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="cs">
              Pole Šířka a Výška umožňují manuální změnu velikosti ořezové
              oblasti přesným číselným nastavením. Rozbalovací seznam umožňuje
              zvolit používané jednotky.
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              The Width and Height selectors allow the manual setting of both
              the width and the height of the cropping area. The units may
              also be chosen.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Höhen- und Breitenangaben des Zuschneidebereiches können hier
              manuell eingegeben werden. Zusätzlich stehen noch verschiedene
              Einheiten für die Werte zu Auswahl.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Los selectores de anchura y altura permiten la configuración
              manual de ambos en el area de recorte. También se pueden
              escoger las unidades.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Les sélecteurs Largeur et Hauteur permettent de choisir
              manuellement la largeur et la hauteur de l'aire de découpage. On
              peut aussi choisir l'unité de mesure.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              L'inserimento della larghezza e dell'altezza permette la
              selezione manuale delle stesse. L'unità di misura è
              selezionabile.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Her bestemmer du breidda og høgda for beskjeringsområdet.
              Som for startpunktet, kan du også velje måleeining.
            </para>
      <para lang="pl">
              Pola pozwalają na wybranie pożądanej szerokości i wysokości
        kadrowanego obszaru. Jednostkę miary można zmienić.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Позволяют определить размер кадрируемой области. Также можно
              выбрать единицы измерения.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">允许您输入剪裁区域的宽度和高度。也可以选取其单位。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry lang="de;no">
          <term lang="de">Seitenverhältnis</term>
          <term lang="no">Breidde- og høgdeforhold</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="de">
              Hier können Sie ein festes Seitenverhältnis für den
              Zuschneidebereich eingeben.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Her kan du skrive inn eit fast tal for forholdet mellom sidene
              i beskjeringsområdet.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="cs">Z výběru</term>
          <term lang="en">From Selection</term>
          <term lang="de">Aus Auswahl</term>
          <term lang="es">Desde selecciones</term>
          <term lang="fr">D'après la Sélection</term>
          <term lang="it">Dalla selezione</term>
          <term lang="no">Frå markering</term>
    <term lang="pl">Z zaznaczenia</term>
          <term lang="ru">Из выделения</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">从选区得到</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="cs">
              Toto tlačítko změní velikost ořezové oblasti tak, aby zahrnovala
              všechny aktivní vybrané oblasti v obrázku, ne však zbytečně něco
              jiného.
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              This button will resize the cropping area to encompass all
              active selections contained within the image. If there is no
              selection, the cropping area is the whole image.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Diese Schaltfläche passt die Größe des Zuschneidebereiches an
              die Größe der bestehenden Auswahl an.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Este botón redimensiona el area de recorte para englobar todas
              las selecciones contenidas en la imagen. Si no hay selección ,
              el area de recorte es toda la imagen.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Ce bouton adapte le cadre de découpage pour qu'il englobe au
              plus près la sélection active dans l'image. S'il n'y a pas de
              sélection, la taille est étendue à toute l'image.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              Questo tasto ridimensionerà l'area di taglio per comprendere
              tutte le selezioni attive contenute nell'immagine.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Trykk på denne knappen for å la beskjeringsområdet omfatte
              alle markeringane i biletet. Dersom det ikkje er markeringar i
              biletet, vil veskjeringsområdet omfatte heile biletet.
            </para>
      <para lang="pl">
              Zmienia rozmiar kadrowanego obszaru tak, aby zawrzeć wszystkie
              zaznaczenia na obrazie. Jeśli zaznaczenia nie ma, kadrowany jest
              cały obraz.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Изменяет размер кадрируемой области так, чтобы включить все
              выделения в изображении. Если нет выделения, используется всё
              изображение.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">该按钮可以改变剪裁区域大小，并包含在图像中的所有活动选区。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="cs">Automaticky zmenšit</term>
          <term lang="en">Auto Shrink</term>
          <term lang="de">Automatisch schrumpfen</term>
          <term lang="es">Autorecorte</term>
          <term lang="fr">Réduction Automatique</term>
          <term lang="it">Riduzione automatica</term>
          <term lang="no">Autokrymp</term>
    <term lang="pl">Auto Shrink</term>
          <term lang="ru">Автосокращение</term>
          <term lang="zh_CN">自动收缩</term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="cs">
              Pokusí se automaticky nalézt okraj k odříznutí.<!FIXME: cs ->
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              The Auto Shrink button will attempt to locate a border from
              which to draw dimensions from. This option only works well with
              isolated objects contrasting sharply with background.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Die Schaltfläche
              <guibutton>Automatisch schrumpfen</guibutton> versucht,
              den Zuschneidebereich an ein bestehendes Bildobjekt automatisch
              anzupassen.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              El botón auto encoger intenta localizar un borde desde el cual
              diseñar las dimensiones. Esta selección solo trabaja bien con
              objetos, con contrastes definidos, diferenciados del fondo.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Une fois tracé le cadre de découpage, ce bouton adapte ce cadre
              pour qu'il épouse au plus près l'objet à limite franche qu'il
              contient... s'il en trouve un. Ça ne marche bien qu'avec les
              objets isolés tranchant nettement sur le fond.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              Il tasto di riduzione automatica tenterà di individuare un bordo
              dal quale disegnare delle dimensioni.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Denne funksjonen prøver å finne kantar i biletet som kan
              brukast som utgangspunkt for beskjeringa. Dette valet verkar
              best når objektet skil seg skarpt ut frå bakgrunnen.
            </para>
      <para lang="pl">
              Przycisk stara się znaleźć krawędź, od której zacznie rysowanie
              pomiarów. Opcja ta dobrze się sprawdza dla oddzielnych obiektów
              silnie kontrastujących z tłem.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Кнопка автосокращения старается найти край, от которого рисовать
              измерения. Это хотошо работает в условиях отдельных объектов с
              контрастным фоном.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">自动收缩按钮从所画的尺度中定位其边界线。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;pl;ru">
          <term lang="cs">Tlačítka Změnit velikost a Ořezat</term>
          <term lang="de">Größe ändern / zuschneiden</term>
          <term lang="en">Crop and Resize buttons</term>
          <term lang="es">Botones recortar y redimensionar</term>
          <term lang="fr">Les boutons Dimensionner et Découper</term>
          <term lang="it">Tasti di taglio e ridimensione</term>
          <term lang="no">Endre storleik/beskjer</term>
    <term lang="pl">Przyciski Kadruj i Zmień rozmiar</term>
          <term lang="ru">Кнопки Откадрировать и Изменить размер</term>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="cs">
              Tato dvě tlačítka provádí operaci dle svého názvu, bez ohledu na
              nastavení ve volbách nástroje.
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              These two buttons act according to their function, ignoring the
              mode setting in tool options.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Mit diesen zwei Schalflächen können Sie die gewünschte Funktion
              ausführen. Dies geschieht unabhängig vom eingestellten
              Werkzeugmodus.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Estos dos botones actuan de acuerdo a su función, ignorando la
              configuración de modo en opciones de herramientas.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Ces deux boutons accomplissent les actions concernées sans tenir
              compte du choix de mode des options de l'outil.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              Questi due pulsanti agiscono in accordo con le loro funzioni,
              ignorando la modalità dello strumento presente nelle opzioni.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Desse to knappane gjer det dei seier, uavhengig av modus sett
              i verktøyinnstillinga.
            </para>
      <para lang="pl">
              Oba przyciski działają zgodnie ze swoją funkcją, niezależnie
              оd trybu wybranego w opcjach narzędzia.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Эти две кнопки работают по своей функциональности, вне зависимости
              от режима в параметрах инструмента.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>-->
  </sect3>
</sect2>
