<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-18 kost: added norwegian
  2007-02-10 lexA: fixed bug #396404 for en and de
  2006-06-04 changed first para, added para in anti-erase, en;fr by j.h
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-12-01 informalfigure replaced by figure by lexa
  050521 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
  -->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-eraser" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="de;cs;en;es;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-04</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-10</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-08-06</date>
        <authorinitials>manuelq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-06-04</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Eraser</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Guma</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Radierer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">La goma de borrar</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Outil Gomme</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">La gomma</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Viskeleret</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Ластик</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">橡皮工具</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary><secondary>Eraser</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Eraser</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Transparency</primary>
    <secondary>Eraser tool</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Panel nástrojů</primary><secondary>Guma</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Guma</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary><secondary>Radieren</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Radieren</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Herramientas</primary><secondary>Goma</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Goma</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Outils</primary><secondary>Gomme</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Gomme</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Effacer</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Transparence</primary>
    <secondary>L'outil Gomme</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary><secondary>Gomma</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Gomma</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="no">Verktøy</primary>
    <secondary lang="no">Viskeleret</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Viskeleret</primary></indexterm>
  
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Инструменты</primary><secondary>Ластик</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Ластик</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Прозрачность</primary>
    <secondary>Ластик</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>工具箱</primary><secondary>橡皮</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Eraser tool icon in the Toolbox</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ikona nástroje Guma v Panelu nástrojů.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Der Radier im Werkzeugfenster</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">La goma de borrar en la caja de herramientas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">L'outil Gomme dans la Boîte à outils</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Icona della gomma nella barra degli strumenti.
      </phrase>

      <phrase lang="no">
        Symbolet for <quote>viskeleret</quote> i verktøyskrinet
      </phrase>

      <phrase lang="ru">
        Пиктограмма инструмента <quote>Ластик</quote> на панели инструментов
      </phrase>

      <phrase lang="zh_CN">工具箱中的橡皮工具图标</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;it;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/cs/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="es">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/es/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-eraser.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en"><!-- Changed 070210 -->
    The Eraser is used to remove areas of color from the current layer or from
    a selection of this layer. If the Eraser is used on something that does
    not support transparency (a selection mask channel, a layer mask, or the
    Background layer if it lacks an alpha channel), then erasing will show the
    background color, as displayed in the Color Area of the Toolbox (in case
    of a mask, the selection will be modified). Otherwise, erasing will
    produce either partial or full transparency, depending on the settings for
    the tool options. You can learn more on how to add an alpha channel to a
    layer in <xref linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add" />.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Guma se používá k odstranění barvy z aktivní vrstvy, výběru nebo obrázku.
    Pokud je Guma použita tam, kde není podporována průhlednost (v kanálu,
    masce vrstvy nebo na vrstvě pozadí bez alfa kanálu), je vygumovaná barva
    nahrazena barvou pozadí nastavenou v Panelu nástrojů. V ostatních
    případech mazání Gumou vytvoří částečně nebo zcela průhledné oblasti,
    v závislosti na nastavení nástroje.
  </para>

  <para lang="de"><!-- Changed 070210 -->
    Der Radierer wird benutzt, um Bereiche der aktuellen Ebene, einer Auswahl
    oder des Bildes zu löschen. Wird der Radierer auf einer Fläche benutzt,
    die keine Alphakanäle unterstützt (z.B. Kanäle oder Ebenenmasken), so
    erscheint als radierte Fläche die Hintergrundfarbe. Verfügt die Fläche
    über einen Alphakanal, dann erscheint die radierte Fläche als
    transparenter Bereich. Wie Sie einen Alphakanal zu einer Ebene hinzufügen
    können, erfahren Sie im <xref linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add" />.
    Umgekehrt können sie den Alphakanal einer Ebene natürlich auch wieder
    entfernen, um beim Radieren die Hintergrundfarbe zum Vorschein zu bringen.
    <!-- PENDING: de gimp 2.4 has a new command here -->
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    La goma de borrar se utiliza para borrar áreas de color de la capa actual
    o de una selección de la misma. Si la goma se utiliza en algo que no
    admita transparencia (un canal de máscara de selección, una máscara de
    capa, o la capa de fondo si no tiene canal alfa), entonces al borrar se
    mostrará el color de fondo del área de color de la caja de herramientas
    (en caso de ser una máscara, la selección será modificada). De otra forma,
    el borrar producirá la transparencia parcial o total, dependiendo de los
    ajustes en las opciones de herramientas.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Le nom anglais de cet outil est <quote>Eraser</quote>
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    La Gomme sert à effacer des plages de couleurs sur le calque actif ou une
    sélection.
    Si la Gomme est utilisée sur quelque chose qui ne possède pas la
    transparence (un canal masque de sélection, un masque de calque ou le
    calque de fond sans canal Alpha), elle peindra les zones effacées avec la
    couleur de fond telle qu'affichée dans la zone des couleurs de la Boîte à
    outils (s'il s'agit d'un masque, la sélection sera modifiée). Sinon, le
    fait d'effacer produira une transparence plus ou moins marquée selon les
    réglages des options de l'outil. Pour savoir comment ajouter un Canal
    Alpha, voyez
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add">Ajouter un canal Alpha</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    La gomma viene usata per rimuovere aree di colore da un livello, selezione
    o immagine. Se la gomma viene usata su elementi che non supportano la
    trasparenza (un canale, una maschera di livello o il livello di sfondo se
    questo non ha un canale alfa), allora cancellando si mostrerà il colore di
    sfondo, come mostrato nell'area colore della barra degli strumenti. In
    caso contrario la cancellazione produrrà trasparenze parziali o totali, in
    base alle impostazioni dello strumento.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Viskeleret blir brukt for å fjerne farge frå det aktive laget, markeringa
    eller bilete. Dersom viskeleret blir brukt på noe som ikkje er
    gjennomsiktig, slik som ein kanal, ei lagmaske eller eit bakgrunnslag
    utan alfakanal, vil viskeleret bruke bakgrunnsfargen som er vist i
    fargeområdet i verktøyvindauget. Elles vil viskeleret lage det området
    du viskar på heilt eller delvis transparent, avhengig av innstillingane
    for viskeleret. Korleis du kan legge inn alfakanal i ein kanal eller eit
    lag er omtalt i <xref linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add" />.
  </para>
  

  <para lang="ru">
    Ластик используется для удаления областей цвета из активного слоя или
    выделения в этом слое. Если ластик применяется к объекту, не поддерживающему
    прозрачность (маска выделения, маска слоя или слой фона без канала альфа),
    то удаление проявит цвет фона с панели инструментов. В случае с маской,
    выделение изменится. Удаление может быть полным или частичным, в зависимости
    от параметров инструмента. За тем, как добавить канал альфа к слою,
    обратитесь сюда <!--xref linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add" /-->.
  </para>


  <para lang="en">
    If you need to erase some group of pixels completely, leaving no trace
    behind of their previous contents, you should check the "Hard edge" box in
    the Tool Options. Otherwise, sub-pixel brush placement will cause partial
    erasure at the edges of the brush-stroke, even if you use a hard-edged
    brush.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Pokud chcete skupinu pixelů zcela a beze stopy vymazat, měli byste
    aktivovat volbu <guilabel>Ostré hrany</guilabel> v Volbách nástroje.
    Jinak totiž subpixelové umisťování štětce způsobí, že na okrajích
    mazané oblasti budou částečně smazané pixely, a to i v případě, že
    použijete stopu s ostrými hranami.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Wenn Sie eine Menge von Pixeln komplett löschen möchten, so dass alle
    Spuren des vorherigen Inhaltes wirklich gründlich entfernt sind, sollten
    Sie die Eigenschaft <guilabel>Harte Kante</guilabel> einschalten. Nur so
    ist sichergestellt, dass auch die Pixel an der Kante des Radierer
    vollständig gelöscht werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Si necesita borrar completamente un grupo de píxeles sin dejar rastros del
    contenido previo, debería activar la opción de
    <guilabel>Bordes duros</guilabel>
    en las opciones de herramientas. Si no lo hace, el alojamiento de subpíxel
    de la brocha causará un borrado parcial en los ejes del trazo, incluso
    para las brochas con bordes duros.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Si vous devez effacer complètement un groupe de pixels, sans en laisser
    aucune trace, vous devriez cocher l'option <quote>Bords nets</quote>
    (Contour dur) dans les options de l'outil. Sinon, les bords adoucis de la
    gomme donneront un effacement partiel.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Dersom du har behov for å fjerna ei gruppe biletpunkt fullstendig, 
    markerer du for <quote>Hard kant</quote> i avkryssingsboksen. Dersom
    denne ikkje er avkryssa, vil viskeleret lage gradvise overgangar, sjølv
    om du har teikna med hardkanta teikneverktøy. 
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Если необходимо полностью удалить группу точек, не оставляя следов от их
    предыдущего содержания, выберите параметр <quote>жёсткий край</quote>.
    Иначе подпиксельное положение кисти приведёт к частичному удалению по краям
    мазка, даже при примении кисти с жёстким краем.
  </para>


  <tip lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;no;ru">
    <para lang="en">
      If you use GIMP with a tablet, you may find it convenient to treat the
      reverse end of the stylus as an eraser. To make this work, all you need
      to do is click the reverse end on the Eraser tool in the Toolbox.
      Because each end of the stylus is treated as a separate input device,
      and each input device has its own separate tool assignment, the reverse
      end will then continue to function as an Eraser as long as you don't
      select a different tool with it.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Pokud při práci s Gimpem používáte grafický tablet, může být pohodlné
      používat opačný konec stylusu jako gumu. Aby to tak fungovalo, musíte
      kliknout tímto opačným koncem stylusu na nástroj Guma v Panelu nástrojů.
      Protože jsou oba konce stylusu považovány za dvě různá vstupní zařízení
      se samostatným přiřazováním nástrojů, bude opačný konec stylusu fungovat
      jako Guma do té doby, než s ním neaktivujete nějaký jiný nástroj.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sollten Sie <acronym>GIMP</acronym> mit einem Grafiktablett
      benutzen, bevorzugen Sie es sicher, das Radieren auf das hintere
      Ende des Stiftes zu legen. Aktivieren Sie hierzu das Werkzeug
      <quote>Radierer</quote> durch Klicken mit dem hinteren Ende des Stiftes
      im Werkzeugfenster. Jedes Ende des Stiftes wird im
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> als unterschiedliches Eingabegerät betrachtet
      und ermöglicht es Ihnen, jedes Ende mit einem anderen Werkzeug zu
      belegen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Si usa el GIMP con una tableta, puede resultarle conveniente tratar a la
      punta opuesta de la estilográfica como una goma de borrar. Para que esto
      funcione, lo único que debe hacer es clicar con la punta opuesta en la
      herramienta Goma de la caja de herramientas. Dado que cada punta de la
      estilográfica es tratada como un dispositivo de entrada aparte, y cada
      dispositivo de entrada tiene sus propia herramienta asignada, la punta
      opuesta continuará funcionando como Goma hasta que seleccione una
      herramienta diferente con la misma.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Si vous utilisez GIMP avec une tablette graphique, vous pouvez trouver
      pratique d'utiliser l'autre extrémité du stylet comme une gomme. Pour
      cela, il vous suffit de cliquer avec cette extrémité sur l'icône de la
      gomme dans la Boîte à outils. Comme cette autre extrémité est traitée
      comme un périphérique à part, et que chaque périphérique d'entrée a son
      propre outil affecté, cette autre extrémité continuera à être une gomme
      tant que vous n'aurez pas choisi un autre outil pour elle.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Dersom du bruker teiknebrett, kan det vere fornuftig å stille 
      inn den eine enden av teiknenåla som viskelêr. Dette får du til 
      ved å klikke enden av nåla inn i viskelêret i verktøyskrinet. 
      Fordi kvar ende av nåla blir oppfatta som ulike verktøy, og 
      såleis får tillagt eige teikneverktøy, vil denne innstillinga 
      vare heilt til du vel eit anna verktøy for den bakre enden av 
      nåla.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Если вы используете GIMP с графическим планшетом, удобно использовать
      обратный конец ручки как ластик. Для этого нужно нажать обратный конец
      на инструменте Ластик на панели инструментов. Поскольку каждый конец
      ручки расматривается как отдельный инструмент, у каждого своя связка с
      инструментом. Обратным концом можно пользоваться как ластиком до тех пор,
      пока не связать этот конец с каким-либо другим инструментом.
    </para>

  </tip>

  <para lang="de">
    Der Radierer im <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    funktioniert sehr ähnlich wie ein Radiergummi auf realen Papier. Neben dem
    Benutzen der verschiedenen Standardpinselformen bietet das Werkzeug
    zusätzliche Optionen, um das Radieren exakter und einfacher zu gestalten.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Se avete la necessità di cancellare completamente un gruppo di pixel
    senza lasciare nessuna traccia, abilitate l'opzione <guilabel>Margine
    netto</guilabel>. Senza questa opzione la cancellazione ai bordi del
    tratto sarà parziale, anche tramite l'utilizzo di un pennello a margine
    netto.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    橡皮用做从当前图层，选区或图像中擦除色块。当在背景图层上使用橡皮时，它将删除色彩区域并用当前背景色代替。而对于浮动图层，其颜色就会被透明代替。对非 Alpha 图像也是如此。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">How to Activate</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activación de la herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione dello strumento</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivere verktøyet</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Активация</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">启动工具</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">You can activate the Eraser tool in several ways :</para>
    <para lang="de">
      Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten, den Radierer zu aktivieren:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous pouvez accéder à la Gomme de différentes façons :
    </para>

    <para lang="no">Du kan hente fram dette verktøyet på fleire måtar:</para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Доступ к инструменту можно получить несколькими путями:
    </para>


    <itemizedlist lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          From the image menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Eraser</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>;
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          über das Menü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>alwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>adierer</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          im Bildfenster,
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Dans le menu d'image par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Ouils</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Outils de peinture</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Gomme</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          frå biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Verktøy</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Teikneverktøy</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Viskeler</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>

        <para lang="ru">
          Из меню изображения
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Инструменты</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Инструменты рисования</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Ластик</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>;
        </para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>;
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          mit einem Mausklick auf das Symbol
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          im Werkzeugfenster sowie
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          En cliquant sur l'icône
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          dans la Boîte à Outils.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          ved å klikke på symbolet
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          i verktøyskrinet
        </para>

        <para lang="ru">
          за панели инструментов нажатием на пиктограмму
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>;
        </para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or from the keyboard using the shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          über das Tastenkürzel
          <keycombo><keycap>Umschalt</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          En utilisant la combinaison de touches
          <keycombo><keycap>Maj</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          eller med tastesnarvegen <keycap>Shift</keycap> + <keycap>E</keycap>.
        </para>

        <para lang="ru">
          или с помощью клавиши быстрого доступа
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="cs">
      Gumu lze aktivovat z nabídky obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Nástroje</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Kreslící nástroje</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Guma</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      z Panelu nástrojů kliknutím na ikonu gumy
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      nebo z klávesnice pomocí zkratky <keycap>E</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      La goma puede ser activada siguiendo el menú de imagen en el
      siguiente orden:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Herramientas</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Herramientas de pintura</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Goma de borrar</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      y también puede activarse clicando en el ícono:
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o presionando la tecla de atajo <keycap>E</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      La gomma può essere richiamata tramite il menù dell'immagine:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>S<accel>t</accel>rumenti</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Strumenti di <accel>d</accel>isegno</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>G</accel>omma</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      dalla barra degli strumenti facendo clic sull'icona relativa
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o tramite la tastiera premendo il tasto <keycap>Maiusc+E</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      按如下步骤启动剪裁工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工
      具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>涂画工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>橡
      皮</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      也可以点工具图标：
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>e</keycap></keycombo>
      组合键将转到橡皮。
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Key modifiers</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (por omisión)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tasti modificatori</phrase>

      <phrase lang="no">Tastekombinasjonar (Normalinnstillinga)</phrase>

      <phrase lang="ru">Клавиши-модификаторы</phrase>

      <phrase lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      See the <xref linkend="gimp-tool-brush" /> for a description of key
      modifiers that have the same effect on all brush tools.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Popis modifikačních kláves platných pro všechny kreslící nástroje
      najdete v přehledu <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">kreslících
      nástrojů</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Bitte beachten Sie <xref linkend="gimp-tool-brush" />. Dort werden die
      Tastenkombinationen beschrieben, die für alle Malwerkzeuge, also auch
      den Radierer, gelten.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Vea la sección
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Herramientas de brocha</link>
      para una descripción de las teclas modificadoras que tienen el mismo
      efecto en todas las herramientas de brocha.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Voyez <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Fonctions communes des
      outils</link> pour une description des fonctions communes.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Guardare <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Generalità degli strumenti
      di disegno</link> per una descrizione dei tasti modificatori
      applicabili a molti strumenti di disegno.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Sjå oversynet over <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Teikneverktøya</link> 
      for omtale av dei modustastane som er felles for alle teikneverktøya. 
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Обратитесь к общей информации по инструментам кисти 
      <xref linkend="gimp-tool-brush" /> за описанием клавиш-модификаторов,
      общих для всех инструментов кисти.
    </para>


    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          For the Eraser, holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key puts it
          into <quote>color picker</quote> mode, so that it selects the color
          of any pixel it is clicked on. Unlike other brush tools, however,
          the Eraser sets the <emphasis>background</emphasis> color rather
          than the foreground color. This is more useful, because on
          drawables that don't support transparency, erasing replaces the
          erased areas with the current background color.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Stisknutí klávesy <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> přepne Gumu do režimu
          barevné pipety. Na rozdíl od podobného režimu u jiných nástrojů však
          Guma v režimu pipety nastaví podle obrázku <emphasis>barvu
          pozadí</emphasis>, nikoliv barvu popředí. To je užitečné z toho
          důvodu, že v prostředím nepodporujícím průhlednost nahrazuje Guma
          smazané pixely barvou pozadí.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          <keycap>Strg</keycap>:
          Wenn Sie die Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap> drücken, wird der Radierer
          in den Modus <quote>Pipette</quote> versetzt. Sie können dann mit
          einem Mausklick die Farbe des Pixels unter der Pipette aufnehmen.
          Allerdings wird, im Gegensatz zu den anderen Malwerkzeugen, die
          Farbe als <emphasis>Hintergrundfarbe</emphasis> und nicht als
          Vordergrundfarbe aufgenommen.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>: Al mantener presionada la tecla Ctrl
          la goma cambia al modo <quote>Recoge color</quote>, con el
          que puede seleccionar el color de cualquier píxel al clicar
          en el mismo.  Sin embargo, a diferencia de las otras
          herramientas de brocha, la goma modifica el <emphasis>color
          de fondo</emphasis> en vez del color de frente.  Esto es más
          útil, porque en las capas y otros objetos (drawables) que no
          admiten transparencia, la goma reemplaza el área con el
          color de fondo actual.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Pour la Gomme, la touche Ctrl la place dans le mode Pipette. En
          cliquant sur un pixel, sa couleur est sélectionnée comme couleur
          d'arrière-plan, à la différence des autres outils où il s'agit de la
          couleur de premier-plan. Ainsi, les zones effacées sont remplacées
          par la couleur d'arrière-plan courante pour les images qui ne gèrent
          pas la transparence.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Trasforma temporaneamente la gomma nello strumento di prelievo
          colore. Diversamente dagli altri strumenti però, per la gomma
          viene impostato il colore di <emphasis>sfondo</emphasis> invece
          di quello di primo piano. Questo accade perchè cancellando
          elementi che non supportano la trasparenza, le parti rimosse
          verranno rimpiazzate con il colore di sfondo.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Gjer viskeleret om til ein fargehentar. I motsetnad til dei 
          andre verktøya, hentar viskelêret bakgrunnsfarge i staden 
          for forgrunnsfarge. Når du viskar på område som ikkje er 
          gjennomsiktige, vil originalfargen bli erstatta med 
          bakgrunnsfargen. Dette er til vanleg det mest fornuftige. 
        </para>

        <para lang="ru">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>: Переключает Ластик в режим выборки цвета. В
          отличие от других инструментов кисти, Ластик устанавливает цвет
          <emphasis>фона</emphasis> на выбранный цвет, а не цвет переднего
          плана. Это полезно для объектов, не имеющих канала альфа. В таких
          случаях ластик зарисовывает объект цветом фона.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>：对于橡皮工具，按下 Ctrl 键使其呈“颜色拾取”模式，
          它拾取点击的任何像素的颜色。不像其它笔刷工具，
          橡皮是将拾取的颜色设为<emphasis>背景色</emphasis>，而不是前景色。这非常有用，
          因为对于不支持透明的可画，它就能用当前背景色覆盖被擦除区域。
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          For the Eraser, holding down the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key switches
          it into <quote>anti-erase</quote> mode, as described below in the
          Tool Options section. Note that on some systems, the
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is trapped by the Window Manager. If this
          happens to you, you may be able to use
          <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
          instead.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          Podržení klávesy <keycap>Alt</keycap> přepne Gumu do režimu
          „opak gumy“, popsaného níže v části věnované volbám nástroje.
          Na některých systémech však může být stisknutí klávesy
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> odchytáváno správcem oken, v takových
          případech může fungovat kombinace
          <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          Mit der Taste <keycap>Alt</keycap> wird der Radierer in den Modus
          <quote>Un-Radieren</quote> versetzt. Wie Sie diesen Modus anwenden
          können, wird im Abschnitt <quote>Eigenschaften</quote> beschrieben.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          Al mantener presionada la tecla Alt la goma cambia al modo
          <quote>anti-borrado</quote>, como se describe debajo en la
          sección de opciones de herramientas.  Note que en algunos
          sistemas la tecla Alt está capturada por el administrador de
          ventanas.  Si esto le sucede, debería poder usar Shift-Alt
          en su lugar.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          La touche Alt fait passer la Gomme en mode anti-effacement,
          comme décrit plus bas avec les options. Notez que sur certains
          systèmes, la touche Alt est déjà prise et vous devez utiliser
          Maj-Alt.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          Imposta lo strumento in modalità "anti gomma", come descritto
          nella sezione opzioni. Su alcuni sistemi, il tasto Alt potrebbe
          esseere usato dal Window Manager. In questo caso è possibile
          utilizzare la scorciatoia <keycap>Maiusc+Alt</keycap>.
        </para>

        <para lang="no">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>:
          Denne tasten set viskeleret i <quote>visk inn</quote>-modus.
          Dette finn du forklart nedanfor. Dersom Alt-tasten ikkje verkar på 
          maskinen din, prøv <keycap>Shift</keycap> + 
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> i staden. 
        </para>

        <para lang="ru">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>: переключает Ластик к режим антиластика,
          описанного ниже. На некоторых системах, эта клавиша перехватывается
          оконным управляющим. В таких случаях используйте комбинацию клавиш
          <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>：对于橡皮工具，按下 Alt 键使其呈“反擦除”模式，
          下面工具选项部分会具体介绍。需要注意的是，在某些系统中，Alt 键被窗口管理器所捕获。
          这时您可以使用 Shift-Alt 。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Tool Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones de herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>

      <phrase lang="no">Verktøyinnstillingar</phrase>

      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>

      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <note lang="cs;es;it;zh_CN">
      <para lang="cs">
        Volby platné pro všechny nebo většinu kreslících nástrojů jsou popsány
        v části <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Přehled kreslících
        nástrojů</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Diríjase a la descrición sobre las <link
        linkend="gimp-tool-brush">herramientas de brocha</link> para
        obtener información sobre las opciones que se aplican a varias
        o a todas estas herramientas.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Guardare <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Generalità degli strumenti
        di disegno</link> per una descrizione delle opzioni applicabili a
        tutti o a molti strumenti di disegno.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        关于许多或所有笔刷工具共有的工具选项的描述请看<link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">笔刷工具概述</link>。
      </para>
    </note>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="cs">Volby nástroje Guma.</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften des Radierers</phrase>
        <phrase lang="en">Tool Options for the Eraser tool</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Opciones de herramienta para la goma</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">Les options de l'outil Gomme.</phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">Opzioni per la gomma</phrase>

        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for verktøyet <quote>viskeler</quote>
        </phrase>

        <phrase lang="ru">Параметры инструмента <quote>Ластик</quote></phrase>

        <phrase lang="zh_CN">橡皮工具的工具选项</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/es/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-eraser.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry lang="en;de;cs;es;fr;it;no;ru;zh_CN">
        <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
        <term lang="cs">Krytí</term>
        <term lang="de">Deckkraft</term>
        <term lang="es">Opacidad</term>
        <term lang="fr">Opacité</term>
        <term lang="it">Opacità</term>
        <term lang="no">Dekkevne</term>
        <term lang="ru">Непрозрачность</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">不透明度</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> slider, in spite of its name,
            determines the <quote>strength</quote> of the tool. Thus, when
            you erase on a layer with an alpha channel, the higher the
            opacity you use, the more transparency you get!
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Posuvník <guilabel>Krytí</guilabel> ovládá <emphasis>sílu</emphasis>
            nástroje, takže, navzdory svému jménu, čím více krytí, tím více
            průhlednosti (ve vrstvách s alfa kanálem).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Der <guilabel>Deckkraft</guilabel>-Schieberegler bestimmt die
            Stärke, mit der ein Werkzeug
            angewendet wird. Konsequenterweise bewirkt die Eigenschaft also
            beim Radierer, wie stark gelöscht wird. Je höher also die
            Deckkraft ist, um so mehr Durchsichtigkeit erzeugt der Radierer.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            El deslizador <guilabel>Opacidad</guilabel>, a pesar de su
            nombre, determina la "intensidad" de la herramienta.  Por
            esto, cuando borra sobre una capa que tiene canal alfa,
            cuanta más "opacidad" uses, ¡obtendrá más transparencia!
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le curseur <guilabel>Opacité</guilabel> règle la force de l'outil.
            Ainsi, sur un calque avec canal Alpha, une opacité forte donne
            un rendu plus transparent et inversement.
          </para>
           <para lang="it">
             La barra orizzontale <guilabel>Opacità</guilabel> imposta il
             livello di trasparenza per lo strumento. Nel caso si cancelli un
             livello con un canale alfa, una maggiore opacità causerà una
             maggiore trasparenza.
           </para>

           <para lang="no">
            Dersom du for dette verktøyet erstattar ordet
            <quote>dekkevne</quote> med <quote>viskestyrken</quote>,
            vil denne innstillinga kanskje vere lettare å forstå. Dess større
            dekkevne, dess kraftigare viskar viskelêret. 
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Параметр <guilabel>Непрозрачность</guilabel> определяет силу
            инструмента. Чем больше значение параметра, чем прозрачней будет
            результат.
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            不透明度滑条设置该图像操作的透明程度。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;no;ru">
        <term lang="en">
          Brush; Pressure sensitivity; Fade out; Incremental; Hard edge
        </term>
        <term lang="de">
          Pinsel(-form); Druckempfindlichkeit; Verblassen; Steigernd; Harte
          Kanten
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">
          Brosse, Sensibilité à la pression, Estompage, Incrémentiel, Bord dur
        </term>
        <term lang="no">
          Pensel, trykkfølsemd, uttoning, auhande, hard kant
        </term>
        <term lang="ru">
          Непрозрачность; Кисть; Чуствительность к нажиму; Блекность; Жёсткие
          края
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <!-- A note about common features with link to description: -->
          <xi:include href="about-common-brush-options.xml" />
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Anti Erase</term>
        <term lang="cs">Opak Gumy</term>
        <term lang="de">Un-Radieren</term>
        <term lang="es">Anti-borrado</term>
        <term lang="fr">Anti-effacement</term>
        <term lang="it">Anti gomma</term>
        <term lang="no">Visk inn</term>
        <term lang="ru">Антиластик</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">反擦除</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The Anti Erase option of the Erase tool can un-erase areas of an
            image, even if they are completely transparent. This feature only
            works when used on layers with an alpha channel. In addition to
            the checkbutton in the Tool Options, it can also be activated
            on-the-fly by holding down the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key (or, if
            the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is trapped by the Window Manager, by
            holding down
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>).
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Volba Opak Gumy přepne Gumu do režimu, ve kterém umí jakoby
            zázrakem obnovit dříve smazané části obrázku. Tato vlastnost
            funguje pouze na vrstvách s alfa kanálem. Kromě zaškrtnutí
            přepínače lze tuto volbu aktivovat také modifikační klávesou
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> (nebo, pokud je
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> odchytáván správcem oken, kombinací
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>).
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Bei aktivierter Eigenschaft <guilabel>Un-Radieren</guilabel>
            könnnen Sie ausradierte Bildbereiche wieder herstellen. Sie können
            also mit dem Radierer den vorherigen Bildinhalt wieder hervorholen
            - <quote>Un-Radieren</quote> eben. Das funktioniert jedoch nur,
            wenn die Ebene über einen Alphakanal besitzt, Sie also beim
            Radieren die Bildbereiche transparent gemacht haben.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Alternativ zur Aktivierung dieser Eigenschaft über die
            Werkzeugeinstellungen, können Sie auch die
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> drücken, während Sie radieren.
          </para>

          <para lang="es">
            La opción de anti-borrado de la herramienta goma puede recuperar
            áreas de una imagen, incluso cuando estén completamente
            transparentes. Esta funcionalidad sólo existe para capas que
            tienen canal alfa. En adición al botón del diálogo de opciones de
            herramientas, también puede activarse al vuelo manteniendo
            apretada a tecla Alt (o, si la tecla Alt está capturada por el
            administrador de ventanas, manteniendo apretadas Shift y Alt al
            mismo tiempo).
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            L'option <guilabel>Anti-effacement</guilabel>
            défait l'effacement. Elle ne marche qu'avec les images possédant
            un canal alpha. On peut y accéder par la touche Alt (ou Maj-Alt
            sur certains systèmes où Alt active l'outil Déplacement).
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questa opzione viene utilizzata per ripristinare aree di immagine
            precendentemente cancellate, anche se queste sono completamente
            trasparenti. Questa funzionalità è disponibile unicamente quando
            si lavora su livelli che dispongono di un canale alfa. Oltre ad
            essere attivata tramite la casella di controllo, questa opzione
            può essere attivata al volo premendo il tasto
            <keycap>Alt</keycap>.
          </para>

          <para lang="no">
            Det motsette av å viske ut må vel vere å viske inn. Viskeleret
            vil <quote>av-viske</quote> eit område på biletet dersom dette
            valet er markert. Du kan sjå på <quote>visk inn</quote> som ein
            variant av å <quote>angre</quote> utviskinga. Funksjonen kan
            bare brukast på lag med alfakanal. Du kan også aktivera denne
            funksjonen ved å halde nede <keycap>Alt</keycap>-tasten, eller
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> + <keycap>Alt</keycap> på noen
            maskiner. 
          </para>

          <para lang="ru">
            Параметр антиластик инструмента позволяет отменить удаление в
            областях изображения, даже если они прозрачны. Этот параметр
            работает только над изображениями с каналом альфа. Его также можно
            активировать на лету, нажав клавишу <keycap>Alt</keycap> (или, если
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> перехватывается оконным управляющим, комбинацию
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>).
          </para>

          <para lang="zh_CN">
            <guilabel>反擦除</guilabel>
            选项能在一个图像上进行反擦除。该特性只有当图像有 Alpha 通道时才可用。
          </para>

          <note>
            <para lang="en">
              To understand how anti-erasing is possible, you should realize
              that erasing (or cutting, for that matter) only affects the
              alpha channel, not the RGB channels that contain the image data.
              Even if the result is completely transparent, the RGB data is
              still there, you simply can't see it. Anti-erasing increases the
              alpha value so that you can see the RGB data once again.
            </para>
            <para lang="en"><!--added 060604-->
              An annoying feature: on a layer you have created with a
              transparent background, using anti-erasing on non-painted areas
              paints with black!
            </para>

            <para lang="cs">
              Pokud vám není jasné, jak může Opak Gumy fungovat, musíte si
              uvědomit, že gumování (a nebo vyjímání například) mění pouze
              alfa kanál, nikoliv barevné kanály obsahující obrazová data. I
              když je výsledek zcela průhledný a tedy neviditelný, obrazová
              RGB data jsou stále přítomná a lze je snadno obnovit. Opak Gumy
              zvýší hodnotu alfy, takže se barevná data stanou opět viditelná.
            </para>

            <para lang="de">
              Um zu verstehen, was bei dem Un-Radieren passiert, müssen Sie
              sich vor Augen halten, dass das Radieren nur den Alphakanal
              betrifft, nicht jedoch die Farbkanäle selbst. Das Un-Radieren
              hebt einfach dei der Werte des Alphakanals an, um die Farbdaten
              wieder erscheinen zu lassen.
            </para>

            <para lang="es">
              Para comprender cómo es posible el anti-borrado, debería saber
              que el borrar (o cortar) sólo afecta al canal alfa, no a los
              canales RGB que contienen los datos de la imagen. Aún cuando el
              resultado sea completamente transparente, los datos RGB están
              todavía ahí, simplemente no los puede ver. El anti-borrado
              incrementa el valor del canal alfa para que vuelva a ver los
              datos RGB.
            </para>
            <para lang="es">
              Una propiedad enojosa: al utilizar el anti-borrado sobre las
              áreas no pintadas de una capa creada con un fondo transparente
              ¡se pinta con negro!
            </para>

            <para lang="fr">
              Pour comprendre comment l'anti-effacement est possible, vous
              devez réaliser que l'effacement n'affecte que le canal Alpha, et
              pas les canaux RVB qui contiennent les données de l'image. Même
              si le résultat est complètement transparent, les couleurs RVB
              sont toujours là, mais vous ne les voyez pas. L'anti-effacement
              augmente la valeur alpha de telle sorte que les couleurs
              réapparaissent.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Une particularité gênante : sur un calque que vous avez créé avec
              un fond transparent, l'utilisation de l'anti-effacement en
              dehors des parties peintes peint en noir !
            </para>

            <para lang="it">
              Per capire il funzionamente di questa opzione bisogna
              comprendere che la cancellazione agise unicamente sul canale
              alfa, non sul canale RGB che contiene i dati dell'immagine.
              Anche se l'immagine è completamente trasparente, le informazioni
              RGB ci sono ancora, semplicemente non è possibile vederle.
              Questa opzione aumenta il valore alfa cosicchè diventi possibile
              vedere nuovamente i dati RGB.
            </para>


            <para lang="no">
              For å forstå korleis <quote>innvisking</quote> er mogleg, bør
              du hugse på at utvisking bare påverkar alfakanalen, ikkje
              RGB-kanalen som inneheld biletdata. Så sjølv om resultatet av
              utviskinga er fullstendig gjennomsiktig, er RGB-dataane der, dei
              er bare usynlege. <quote>Visk inn</quote> aukar alfaverdien
              slik at dei underliggande data blir synlege igjen. 
            </para>
            <para>
              Eit irriterande fenomen: Dersom du visker inn på eit lag med
              gjennomsiktig bakgrunn, vil viskeleret teikne med svart på
              område som ikkje er teikna på frå før. 
            </para>
            

            <para lang="ru">
              Чтобы понять, как работает антиластик, нужно помнить что удаление
              изменяет только канал альфа, а не все каналы RGB изображения.
              Даже если результат полностью прозрачен, данные RGB сохранены, но
              невидимы. Антиластик просто увеличивает значение альфа и таким
              образом выявляет данные RGB.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Заметка: на новых слоях с прозрачным фоном антиластик рисует
              чёрным на незакрашенных областях!
            </para>


            <para lang="zh_CN"><!-- FIXME: zh_CN -->FIXME</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

</sect2>
