<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-select'>
  <title lang="en">Common Features</title>
  <title lang="de">Gemeinsam genutze Funktionen</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Selection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="de">Auswahl</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Sélection</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Selection tools are designed to select regions
    from images or layers so you can work on them without affecting
    the unselected areas.  Each tool has its own individual
    properties, but the selection tools also share a number of options
    and features in common.  These common features are described here;
    the variations are explained in the following sections for
    each tool specifically.  If you need help with what a "selection" is
    in Gimp, and how it works, see the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-image-selection'>Selections</link> in the chapter
    "Using Gimp".
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Die Auswahlwerkzeuge in <acronym>Gimp</acronym> werden benutzt, um
    Bereiche auf einer Ebene oder dem Bild, auszuwählen. Dies macht es
    möglich, nur ausgewählte Bereiche zu bearbeiten. Jedes
    Auswahlwerkzeug ist mit speziellen Eigenschaften ausgestattet,
    jedoch teilen sich alle Auswahlwerkzeuge Funktionen. Diese
    Funktionen Funktionen, die jedes Auswahlwerkzeug besitzt, sind im
    folgenden dokumentiert. 
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    There are six selection tools:
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Es gibt sechs Auswahlwerkzeuge:
  </para>  
  
  <itemizedlist lang="en">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Rectangle Select
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Ellipse Select
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Free Select (the Lasso)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Select Contiguous Regions (the Magic Wand)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Select by Color
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Select Shapes from Image (Intelligent Scissors)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist lang="de">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Rechteckige Auswahl
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Elliptische Auswahl
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Freie Auswahl 
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Zauberstab
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Auswahl nach Farbe
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Magnetische Auswahl
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang="en">
    In some ways the Path tool can also be thought of as a selection
    tool:  any closed path can be converted into a selection.  It also
    can do a great deal more, though, and does not share the same set
    of options with the other selection tools.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Auch das Pfadwerkzeug kann als ein Auswahlwerkzeug betrachtet
    werden. Jeder geschlossene Pfad kann in eine Auswahl konvertiert
    werden. Es ist um einiges reicher an Funktionen und kann
    dementsprechend mehr als nur Auswahlen zu erstellen. Dadurch benutzt
    es nicht die gemeinsam genutzen Funktionen der Auswahlwerkzeuge.
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen (Standardeinstellungen)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de modification (Par défaut)</title>

    <para lang="en">
      The behavior of selection tools is modified if you hold down the
      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>, and/or
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> keys while you use them.  
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Verhalten der Auswahlwerkzeuge wird durch das drücken von drei Tasten
      beeinflußt: <keycap>Strg</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap>,
      und/oder <keycap>Alt</keycap>.
    </para>

    <note lang='en'>
      Advanced users find the modifier keys very valuable, but novice
      users often find them confusing.  Fortunately, it is possible
      for most purposes to use the Mode buttons (described below)
      instead of modifier keys.  
    </note>
    <note lang='de'>
      Tastenkürzel werden häufig von fortgeschrittenen Benutzern
      gebraucht. Sie ermöglichen einen schnellen Zugriff auf
      verschiedene Eigenschaften der Auswahlwerkzeuge. Glücklicherweise
      können Sie die meisten Eigenschaften aus den Werkzeugeigenschaften
      per Mausklick verändern.
    </note>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Strg</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> while creating a selection can
            have as many as two effects simultaneously. The first effect
            is variable depending on which tool you are using: see the
            individual tool's documentation for this.  The second
            effect, is common to all selection tools: it puts the tool
            into subtraction mode, so that the region you trace out is
            <emphasis>subtracted</emphasis> from the pre-existing
            selection.  If you only want one of these actions to take
            place, you can release the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key prior
            to releasing the <mousebutton>mouse button</mousebutton>.
            Doing so will leave the selection in subtraction mode, but
            not perform the tool-specific action.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Die Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap> beeinflusst das Erstellen
            einer Auswahl auf zwei Arten. Bei der ersten Art, wird der
            Startpixel als Mittelpunkt benutzt. Um diesen Mittelpunkt
            wird die Auswahl erstellt. Bei der zweiten Art wird der
            Startpixel als rechte, untere Ecke benutzt, um die Auswahl
            zu erstellen. Zusätzlich befindet sich die Auswahl im
            Subtrahieren-Modus. Durch wechselseitiges Lösen von
            <keycap>Strg</keycap> und
            <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton>, kann man zwischen den
            zwei Arten, wie die Auswahl zu erstellen ist wechseln. Zudem
            lässt sich der Subtrahieren-Modus aktivieren oder
            deaktivieren.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Maintenir <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> pendant la création d'une
            sélection rectangulaire permet de réaliser deux choses. Tout
            d'abord, la sélection sera créée en prenant comme centre le
            pixel sur lequel vous avez démarré la sélection.
            Normalement, ce pixel détermine un coin. Ensuite,
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> placera la sélection en mode
            Soustraction (voir ci-dessus). Si vous n'avez besoin que
            d'une seule des actions, vous pouvez relâcher la touche
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> avant de relâcher le
            <mousebutton>Bouton gauche</mousebutton> de la souris. En
            agissant ainsi, la sélection restera en mode Soustraction,
            mais sans la contrainte du point central.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Alt</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding <keycap>Alt</keycap> will allow movement of the
            current selection (only its frame, not its content). If the
            whole image is moved instead of the selection only, try
            <keycap>Shift+Alt</keycap>.  Note that the
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is sometimes intercepted by the
            windowing system (meaning that Gimp never knows that it was
            pressed), so this may not work for everybody.
          </para>

          <para lang="de" status="fuzzy">
            Die <keycap>Alt</keycap> Taste erlaubt es, die aktuelle
            Auswahl zu verschieben.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Maintenir la touche <keycap>Alt</keycap> enfoncée permettra
            de mobiliser le cadre de la sélection courante sans déplacer
            son contenu. Si c'est l'ensemble de l'image qui se déplace,
            utilisez <keycap>Maj+Alt</keycap>
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Maj</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            As with the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key, holding down
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> while creating a selection can have
            two distinct effects.  The first varies according to which
            tool is used, but it generally involves constraining the
            tool in some way:  for example, it constrains the
            rectangle-select tool to select a
            <emphasis>square</emphasis> region.  The second effect is to
            change the selection mode to "addition", so that the region
            traced out is added to the pre-existing selection.If you
            require only one of these actions to take place, you can
            release the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key prior to releasing
            the <mousebutton>mouse button</mousebutton>. Doing so will
            leave the selection in addition mode, but without any
            constraints.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Die <keycap>Shift</keycap> Taste beeinflußt Höhe und Breite
            der Auswahl. Beide Größen werden konstant gehalten.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Maintenir la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> enfoncée pendant la
            création d'une sélection permet de réaliser deux choses.
            D'abord que la largeur et la hauteur de la sélection
            resteront égales (formant un carré). Ensuite, que le mode de
            sélection passe en Addition (voir ci-dessus).  Si vous
            n'avez besoin que d'une seule des actions, vous pouvez
            relâcher la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> avant de relâcher le
            <mousebutton>Bouton gauche</mousebutton> de la souris. En
            agissant ainsi, la sélection restera en mode Addition, mais
            sans la contrainte largeur / hauteur.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Strg</keycap>+<keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Maj</keycap></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Using
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
              together can do a variety of things, depending on which
              tool is used.  Common to all selection tools is thatthe
              selection mode will be switched to intersection, so that
              after the operation is finished, the selection will
              consist of the intersection of the region traced out with
              the pre-existing selection.It is an exercise for the
              reader to play with the various combinations available
              when performing selections while holding <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Shift</keycap> </keycombo>
              and releasing either both or either prior to releasing the
              <mousebutton>mouse button</mousebutton>.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Durch Benutzung von
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Strg</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
              ergeben sich verschiedene Anwendungsmöglichkeiten. Wenn
              beide Tasten gleichzeitig gedrückt werden, wird der
              Auswahlmodus auf Schnittmodus gestellt. Ausserdem wird die
              Auswahl um den Mittelpunkt erstellt, sowie die Höhen und
              Breiten der Auswahl konstant gehalten. Experimentieren Sie
              etwas mit den Tastenkombinationen, um ein Gefühl dafür zu
              bekommen.
            </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            La combinaison de touches
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            permet de réaliser plusieurs choses. D'abord, le mode de
            sélection passera en intersection. Ensuite, les deux
            contraintes de point central et de largeur/hauteur vues plus
            haut seront appliquées.  C'est un bon exercice que de tester
            les différentes combinaisons possibles en appuyant sur
            <keycombo> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            </keycombo> et en relâchant l'une ou l'autre avant de
            relâcher le <mousebutton>bouton gauche</mousebutton> de la
            souris.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
  <variablelist>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Overview</term>
      <term lang="de">Aufruf</term>
      <term lang="fr">Vue d'ensemble</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Here we describe the tool options that apply to all selection
          tools:  options that apply only to some tools, or that affect
          each tool differently, are described in the sections devoted
          to the individual tools.  The current settings for these
          options can be seen in the Tool Options dialog, which you
          should always have visible when you are using tools.  (Most
          users keep it docked directly below the Toolbox.)  To make the
          interface consistent, the same options are presented for all
          selection tools, even though some of them don't have any
          effect for some of the tools.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Die Werkzeugeinstellungen für die Auswahlwerkzeuge lassen sich
          durch ein Doppelklick auf das Icon <guiicon> <inlinegraphic
          fileref='../images/toolbox/rectsel.png'></inlinegraphic>
          </guiicon>anzeigen.
        </para>
      </listitem>

        <para lang="fr">
        Les options disponibles pour cet outil sont accessibles par un double 
        clic sur l'icône de l'outil.
          <guiicon> <inlinegraphic
              fileref='../images/toolbox/rectsel.png'></inlinegraphic>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Mode</term>
      <term lang="de">Auswahl Modi</term>
      <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This determines the way that the selection you create with
          the tool is combined with any pre-existing selection.  Note
          that the functions performed by these buttons can be
          duplicated by using modifier keys, as described above.  For
          the most part, advanced users use the modifier keys; novice
          users use the mode buttons.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Replace mode will cause any existing selection to be destroyed
          or replaced when the new selection is created.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
            Der Ersetzen-Modus ersetzt die vorhandene Auswahl mit einer
            neu erstellten Auswahl.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-replace.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Le mode Remplace la sélection courante fait que la sélection 
          existante sera détruite par la nouvelle.
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Add mode will cause the new selection to be added to any
          existing selection regions.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Der Hinzufüge-Modus, fügt eine neu erstellte Auswahl zu 
          einer bestehenden Auswahl hinzu.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-add.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Le mode Ajouter à la sélection courante fait que la 
          nouvelle sélection s'ajoute à l'existante.
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Subtract mode will remove the new selection area from any
          existing selection regions.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Im Substrahieren-Modus wird der sich überlappende Bereich, bei
          einer neu erzeugten Auswahl, von der vorhandenen Auswahl
          abgezogen. Überlappen sich die neu erzeugte Auswahl und die
          bereits Bestehende nicht, bleibt die bestehende Auswahl
          erhalten.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-subtract.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Le mode Soustraire de la sélection courante soustrait de la 
          sélection existante la partie commune aux deux sé lections.
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Intersection mode will make a new selection from the area
          where the existing selection region and the new selection region
          overlap. 
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Der Schnittmodus erzeugt eine neue Auswahl. Diese entsteht
          durch durch die Überlagerung eines vorhandenen ausgewählten
          Bereiches mit der angelegten neuen Auswahl.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/tool-options/rectsel-mode-intersect.png'
                format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          Intersection avec la sélection courante crée une sélection 
          résultante qui est la partie commune aux deux sélections.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Antialiasing</term>
      <term lang="de">Kantenglättung</term>
      <term lang="fr">Lissage</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This option only affects a few of the selection tools:  it
          causes the boundary of the selection to be drawn more
          smoothly. 
       </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Diese Option hat zur Zeit keine Funktion und wird nur aus
          Konsistenzgründen angezeigt.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Cette option ne sert à rien ici. Elle n'est présente que pour
          unifier l'interface utilisateur des différents types de
          sélection.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
    <term lang="en">Feather Edges</term>
    <term lang="de">Kanten ausblenden</term>
    <term lang="fr">Adoucir les contours</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This options allows the boundary of the selection to be
          blurred, so that points near the boundary are only partially
          selected.  For further information regarding feathering, see
          the glossary entry <link
          linkend='glossary-feathering'>Feathering</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
          Der <guilabel>Radius</guilabel> Schieber legt die Länge des
          Übergangs der ausgeblendeten Kanten fest. Ein veränderter Wert
          wird für die nächste Auswahl wirksam. Der Radius kann einen
          Wert zwischen 0 (keine Überblendung der Kanten) und 100
          (starke Überblendung) annehmen. Die Funktion der Option <link
          linkend='glossary-feathering'>Kanten ausblenden</link> wird
          nochmals näher im Glossar erklärt.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Le curseur <guilabel>Rayon</guilabel> règle la largeur en
          pixels de l'estompage des bords de la nouvelle sélection. Vous
          trouverez plus d'information dans le Glossaire à l'article
          <link linkend='glossary-feathering'>Adoucir</link>.
        </para>

      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</simplesect>

<simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Additional information</title>
    <title lang="de">Ergänzungen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Information en plus</title>
    <note lang="en">
      When moving a selection beyond the boundaries of the image canvas,
      the selection will be cropped to the image area. Selections can
      exist on the visible canvas only. Selection movements and changes
      are, however, kept in the undo buffer should you need to repair an
      error.
    </note>

    <note lang="de">
      Wenn die Auswahl über die Bildgrenze hinausgeht, wird diese an den
      Bildgrenzen reduziert. Auswahlen können nur auf sichtbare Ebenen
      erstellt werden. Verschiebungen oder Veränderungen an der Auswahl
      lassen sich rückgängig machen.
    </note>

    <note lang="fr">
      Quand vous déplacez une sélection au-delà des limites du canevas,
      elle est découpée aux limites de l'image. Les sélections ne
      peuvent exister que sur le canevas visible. Néanmoins, les
      mouvements et les changements de la sélection sont conservés dans
      le tampon Défaire au cas où vous auriez besoin de corriger une
      erreur.
    </note>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
