<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-12 PP rewieved en & fr and re-arranged according to tool-rect-select.xml page other lang. to verify
  2007-10-30 Dust: added 'ko' contents
  2007-10-05 lexa: reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
  2007-06-02 kost: added 'no'
  2006-03-30 lexa: added docbook compliance
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-12-01 informalfigure replaced by figure by lexa
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-ellipse-select" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">

  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;ko">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-22</date>
        <authorinitials>P.P</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="cs">2006-03-02</date>
        <authorinitials lang="cs">jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="de">2007-12-19</date>
        <authorinitials lang="de">ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="es">2006-10-13</date>
        <authorinitials lang="es">manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-22</date>
        <authorinitials>P.P</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date lang="ko">2007-10-30</date>
        <authorinitials lang="ko">Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>


  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Ellipse Selection</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Nástroj výběr eliptických oblastí</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Elliptische Auswahl</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Herramienta de selección elíptica</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Sélection Elliptique</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Strumento di selezione ellittica</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">타원형 선택 도구</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Ellipsemarkering</phrase>
    <phrase lang="pl">Zaznaczenie eliptyczne</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Эллиптическое выделение</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">椭圆选择工具</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary><secondary>Ellipse Selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selection</primary><secondary>Ellipse selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Ellipse Selection Tool</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Panel nástrojů</primary>
    <secondary>výběr</secondary>
    <tertiary>eliptický</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>výběr eliptický</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary><secondary>Elliptische Auswahl</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Auswahl</primary><secondary>Elliptisch</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Herramientas</primary><secondary>Elíptica, selección</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Elíptica, selección</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Outils</primary><secondary>Sélection Elliptique</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélection</primary><secondary>Sélection elliptique</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Ellipse : Outil de Sélection</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary><secondary>Selezione Ellittica</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Selezione Ellittica</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>도구</primary>
    <secondary>타원형 선택</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>선택</primary>
    <secondary>타원형 선택</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>타원형 선택 도구</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Verktøy</primary><secondary>Ellipsemarkering</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Markeringar</primary><secondary>Ellipsemarkering</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Narzędzia</primary><secondary>Zaznaczenie eliptyczne</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Zaznaczenie</primary><secondary>Zaznaczenie eliptyczne</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl"><primary>Zaznaczenie eliptyczne</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Инструменты</primary>
    <secondary>Эллиптическое выделение</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Выделение</primary><secondary>Эллиптическое выделение</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Ellipse Select icon in the Toolbox</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">
        Ikona nástroje Výběr eliptických oblastí v Panelu nástrojů
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Die elliptische Auswahl im Werkzeugfenster.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        El icono de la herramienta de selección elíptica en la caja.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        L'icône Sélection Elliptique dans la Boîte à outils.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        L'icona della selezione ellittica nella barra degli strumenti
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구상자의 타원형 선택 도구 아이콘</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Symbolet for ellipsemarkeringa i verktøyskrinet
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">
      <quote>Zaznaczenie eliptyczne</quote> na pasku narzędzi
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">
        Пиктограмма инструмента <quote>Эллиптическое выделение</quote> в
        панели инструментов
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">FIXME: zh_CN</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs;es;pl;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ko">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ko/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-ellipsel.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Ellipse Selection tool is designed to select circular and elliptical
    regions from an image, with high-quality anti-aliasing if you want it. For
    information on selections and how they are used in GIMP see
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Selections</link>;
    for information on features common to all selection tools see
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Selection Tools</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    This tool is also used for rendering a circle or ellipse on an image. To
    render a filled ellipse, create an elliptical selection, and then fill it
    using the <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket Fill tool</link>.
    To create an elliptical outline, the simplest and most flexible approach
    is to create an elliptical selection and then
    <link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">stroke</link>
    it. However, the quality of anti-aliasing with this approach is rather
    crude. A higher quality outline can be obtained by creating two elliptical
    selections with different sizes, subtracting the inner one from the outer
    one; however this is not always easy to get right. The command
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Selection</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Border...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    makes it easy.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroj Výběr elipsy lze použít k výběru eliptických nebo kruhových
    oblastí obrázku. Pokud chcete, může být výběr velmi kvalitně vyhlazen.
    Více se o výběrech a jejich použití v GIMPu dozvíte v části <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Výběry</link>; o vlastnostech společných
    všem nástrojům pro výběr se dozvíte v části <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro výběr</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Tento nástroj se také používá pro kreslení kruhů a elips. Chcete-li do
    obrázku nakreslit vyplněnou elipsu, vytvořte eliptický výběr a vyplňte ho
    pomocí <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Plechovky</link>. Chcete-li
    nakreslit pouze obrys elipsy, nejjednodušší je vytvořit eliptický výběr a
    ten <link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">vykreslit</link>. Vyhlazování
    však v tomto případě není příliš dobré. Kvalitnějšího výsledku lze
    dosáhnout vytvořením dvou elips o různých velikostech, odečtením vnitřní
    elipsy od vnější a vyplněním výsledného výběru. Není to však úplně snadné.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Elliptische Auswahl</quote> ermöglicht es Ihnen, eine
    Auswahl aus kreisförmigen und elliptischen Bereichen des Bildes oder der
    aktuellen Ebene zu erstellen. Diese Auswahl kann dann benutzt werden, um
    Bildmanipulationen nur auf den ausgewählten Bereich anzuwenden.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Dieses Werkzeug wird auch für das Zeichnen von kreisrunden oder
    elliptischen Flächen verwendet. Hierzu erstellen Sie zunächst eine
    entsprechende Auswahl und füllen diese dann mit Hilfe des
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Fülleimer</link>-Werkzeuges.
    Um einen runden oder elliptischen Rahmen zu erzeugen, ist die
    einfachste und flexibelste Vorgehensweise die Erstellung einer passenden
    Auswahl, welche dann <link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">umrandet</link>
    wird. Allerdings ist die Qualität bei diesem Ansatz eher bescheiden. Eine
    qualitativ hochwertigerer Rahmen kann erzeugt werden, indem Sie zwei
    Auswahlen verschiedener Größe erstellen und dann die innere Auswahl von
    der äußeren subtrahieren. Allerdings ist es nicht immer leicht, die
    passenden Auswahlen zu erstellen.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    La herramienta de selección elíptica está diseñada para seleccionar
    regiones circulares y elípticas de una imagen, y ofrece la posibilidad de
    hacerlo con una alta calidad, usando alisado.  El concepto de selección y
    su empleo en el GIMP se describe en la sección <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Selecciones</link>.  La información
    sobre las características que todas las herramientas de selección tienen
    en común se describe en la sección <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-select">Herramientas de selección</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    Esta herramienta puede ser utilizada para pintar un círculo o una elipsis
    en la imagen.  Para hacer una elipsis rellena cree una selección elíptica,
    y luego rellénela empleando el <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Relleno de cubeta</link>.  Para hacer sólo
    el contorno de la elipsis, la manera más simple y flexible es crear una
    selección elíptica y luego <link
    linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">trazarla</link>.  Sin embargo, la calidad
    del alisado (antialiasing) que proporciona este método es bastante pobre.
    Se puede obtener un contorno de mejor calidad haciendo dos selecciones de
    diferentes tamaños, sustrayendo la segunda elipsis a la primera, pero esto
    no siempre es fácil de lograr.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil de Sélection Elliptique sélectionne une région elliptique ou
    circulaire par déplacement du curseur de la souris sur le calque actif.
    La sélection devient active dès qu'on relâche le bouton de souris.
    On peut la supprimer en cliquant en dehors de la sélection.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Cet outil peut aussi être utilisé pour créer un objet de forme
    elliptique dans l'image, en le remplissant à l'aide de l'outil
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Remplissage</link>. Si vous ne
    voulez conserver que le contour elliptique, utilisez l'option
    <link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">Tracer la Sélection</link>
    du menu d'image. Vous pouvez aussi dessiner deux sélections
    concentriques  et soustraire la sélection intérieure, ne laissant ainsi
    qu'un anneau. La commande
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Sélection</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Bordure...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    rend cela facile.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le nom anglais de cet outil est <quote>Ellipse Selection</quote>
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Lo strumento di selezione ellittica è studiato per selezionare zone
    circolari ed ellittiche all'interno di un'immagine, volendo con un
    anti-aliasing di elevata qualità. Per informazioni sulle selezioni
    e su come vengono usate in GIMP vedi <!-- FIXME: it link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-selection" -->Selezioni<!-- /link-->;
    per informazioni sulle caratteristiche comuni a tutti questi strumenti
    vedi <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Strumenti di selezione</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Questo strumento viene usato anche per disegnare dei cerchi o delle
    ellissi in un'immagine. Per disegnare un'ellisse piena, creare una
    selezione ellittica e poi riempirla usando lo strumento <!-- FIXME: it link
    linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill"  -->riempimento colore<!--/link-->.
    Per creare il contorno di un'ellissi,
    l'approccio più semplice e flessibile è quello di creare una selezione
    ellittica e poi applicare su di essa la funzione <!--  FIXME: it link
    linkend="gimp-selection-stroke" -->delinea<!--/link-->.
    Con questo approccio però la qualità dell'anti-aliasing è piuttosto
    grezza. Una migliore qualità del contorno può essere ottenuta creando
    due selezioni ellittiche di diverse dimensioni, sottraendo quella interna
    da quella esterna; ciò però non è sempre facile da ottenere con precisione.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    타원형 선택 도구는 원형이나 타원형으로 선택을 합니다. 그리고 굉장히
    높은 수준의 안티 앨리어싱을 제공합니다. 선택에 대한 자세한 내용은
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">선택</link> 섹션을
    참고하시고, 선택도구의 일반적인 특징에 대한 정보는
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link> 섹션을 참고하세요.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    이 도구를 이용해 원이나 타원을 그릴 수도 있습니다. 속이 채워진 타형을
    그리려면 먼저 타원형의 선택을 만들고
    <!-- FIXME: ko <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket Fill tool</link> -->
    채우기 도구를 이용해 선택을 칠합니다. 그리고 타원형 테두리는 타원형
    선택을 만들고,
    <!-- FIXME:ko <link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">stroke</link>-->
    선택따라 그리기를 이용해 그립니다. 이때 고품질의 안티 앨리어싱을
    적용하면 오히려 안좋은 결과를 가져올 수도 있습니다. 깔끔한 타원형
    테두리를 만들려면 크기가 다른 두 개의 타원을 만들고 바깥원에서 안쪽원을
    빼주는 것이 좋습니다. 이 과정은
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>선택</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>테두리...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    메뉴를 이용하면 굉장히 쉽게 할 수 있습니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Verktøyet for elliptiske markering blir brukt til å velje ut og markere
    runde og elliptiske (ovale) område på eit bilete, eventuelt med
    kantutjamning om du ønskjer det. Sjå i <link
    linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">Markeringar</link> for nærare
    opplysningar om bruken av verktøyet. Sjå <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-select">felles uttrykk</link> for nærare opplysningar
    om dei innstillingane som er felles for markeringsverktøya.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Dette verktøyet blir også brukt for å teikne sirklar eller ellipsar på
    eit bilete. Lag ei markering og fyll denne ved hjelp av <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">fyllverktøyet</link>. Ønskjer du å bare
    teikne omrisset, kan du i staden <link
    linkend="gimp-selection-stroke">streke opp</link> markeringa med høveleg
    farge og strøk. Ein annan metode som er vanskelegare, men gir betre
    kvalitet, er å lage to elliptiske markeringar med litt ulik storleik og
    subtrahere den innarste frå den yttarste. Dette er ikkje alltid like
    lett å få til, så kanskje kommandoen
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Marker</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Ramme...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    er løysinga.
  </para>

  <para lang="pl">
    Narzędzie służy do zaznaczania obszarów eliptycznych na obrazie,
    z wygładzaniem lub bez. Więcej informacji na temat zaznaczania
    obszarów w programie GIMP znaleźć można na
    <!--link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection"-->Zaznaczanie<!--/link-->. Opcje
    wspólne dla wszystkich narzędzi zaznaczania zostały opisane na
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="pl">
    Narzędzie może być również wykorzystywane do rysowania okręgu lub
    elipsy na obrazie. Aby otrzymać wypełnioną elipsę, należy utworzyć
    zaznaczenie eliptyczne, a następnie wypełnić je przy pomocy
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Wypełnienia kubełkiem</link>.
    Najprostszym i jednocześnie najbardziej przystępnym sposobem uzyskania
    obwodu elipsy jest utworzenie zaznaczenia eliptycznego, a następnie
    <!--link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke"-->rysowanie<!--/link--> wzdłuż niego. W ostatnim
    przypadku zmiękczanie krawędzi nie będzie zbyt wysokiej jakości. Lepszą
    jakość można uzyskać tworząc dwa zaznaczenia eliptyczne różnego rozmiaru,
    a następnie wycinając zewnętrzne od wewnętrznego. Jednak tę operację trudno
    jest przeprowadzić prawidłowo. Polecenie
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Zaznaczenie</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Zaokrąglenie...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    znacznie ułatwia pracę.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Этот инструмент выделяет эллиптическую область в активном изображении, при
    желании, со сглаживанием. За справкой о том, выделения используются в GIMP
    обращайтесь к
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-selection">выделениям</link>; обращайтесь к
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">инструментам выделения</link> за
    информацией об общих их свойствах.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    С эллиптическим выделением можно делать всё, что и с обычным выделением,
    на пример залить его цветом с помощью
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">инструмента заливки</link> или
    обвести края в помощью
    <!--link linkend="gimp-selection-stroke"-->штриха<!--/link-->. Сглаживание
    краёв в последнем случае будет невысокого качества. Лучшего качества можно
    достичь, создав два выделения разного размера и вычтя внутреннее от
    внешнего, однако эту процедуру трудно проделать правильно. Команда
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Выделение</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Рамка...</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    облегчает работу.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    椭圆选择区域工具被用作在图像或图层上选取圆形或椭圆形区域，这样您就可以在这些特别区域上进行操作。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">How to Activate</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activación de la herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구 선택하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Аktywacja narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Активация инструмента</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">启动工具</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Ellipse Selection Tool can be activated from an image
      menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ellipse Select</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      or from the keyboard by using the <keycap>e</keycap> shortcut.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Nástroj Výběr elipsy lze aktivovat z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Nástroje</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Nástroje</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Výběr elipsy</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      nebo kliknutím na ikonu nástroje v panelu
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      či stisknutím klávesy <keycap>e</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten, das Werkzeug <quote>Elliptische
      Auswahl</quote> zu aktivieren:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Menü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uswahlwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>lliptische Auswahl</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          im Bildfenster,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          mit einem Mausklick auf das Symbol
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          im Werkzeugfenster sowie
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Tastenkürzel <keycap>E</keycap>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="es">
      La herramienta de selección elíptica se puede activar seleccionando
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Herramientas</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Herramientas de selección</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Selección elíptica</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      desde el menú de la imagen.  O desde la caja de herramientas haciendo
      clic sobre el icono
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o desde el teclado usando el atajo <keycap>e</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil Sélection Elliptique peut être appelé à partir de la
      barre de menus de l'image par
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Outils de <accel>s</accel>élection</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sélection <accel>E</accel>lliptique</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à outils,
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      ou par la touche de raccourci <keycap>E</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Lo strumento di selezione ellittica può essere attivato dal menu
      immagine come segue
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Strumenti</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selezione</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ellittica</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      ; dalla barra degli strumenti facendo clic sull'icona
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      ; o da tastiera usando il tasto <keycap>e</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      타원형 선택 도구는 이미지 메뉴에서
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>도구</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>선택 도구</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>타원 선택</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      을 이용하거나, 도구 상자의 도구 아이콘
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      을 클릭하거나, 키보드 단축키 <keycap>e</keycap>를 눌러 사용할 수
      있습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan hente fram markeringsverktøya på tre måtar:
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Frå biletmenyen via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Verktøy</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Markeringsverktøya</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Rektangelmarkering</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      ved å klikke på symbolet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      i verktøyskrinet
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      eller med tastesnarvegen <keycap>E</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="pl">
      Narzędzie można aktywować na kilka sposobów: poprzez menu obrazu:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Narzędzia</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Narzędzia zaznaczania</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Zaznaczenie eliptyczne</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      klikając ikonę
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> na pasku narzędzi
      lub przy pomocy skrótu klawiszowego <keycap>E</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Инструмент доступен несколькими способами: из меню изображения
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Инструменты</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Инструменты выделения</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Эллиптическое выделение</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      нажатием на пиктограмму инструмента
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> на панели инструментов
      или используя клавишу быстрого доступа <keycap>e</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      按如下步骤启动椭圆选择工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工
      具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>选择工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>椭圆
      选择</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      也可以点工具图标：
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <keycap>e</keycap> 键将转到椭圆选择。
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Key modifiers</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (por defecto)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Touches de contrôle</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tasti modificatori</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">동작 변경 키</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Tastekombinasjonar (Normalinnstillingae)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Klawisze modyfikujące</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">клавишы-модификаторы</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">相关按键</phrase>
    </title>

    <!-- A note about common modifier keys with link to description: -->
    <xi:include href="about-common-select-modifiers.xml" />

    <!--TODO es it ko no pl ru zh_CN: consider switching to the
        above include file (check/edit it before!)-->
    <note lang="cs;es;it;ko;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
      <!--para lang="en;de;fr">
        Moved to "src/toolbox/about-common-select-modifiers.xml"
      </para-->
      <para lang="cs">
        Část <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro výběr</link>
        popisuje modifikační klávesy společné všem těmto nástrojům. Zde jsou
        popsány pouze efekty specifické pro eliptický výběr.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        En la sección <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Herramientas de
        selección</link> se encuentran las teclas modificadoras que afectan a
        todas estas herramientas de la misma forma.  Sólo los efectos
        específicos a la herramienta de selección elíptica son explicados
        aquí.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per avere aiuto sui tasti modificatori che influenzano allo stesso
        modo tutti questi strumenti vedi
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Strumenti di selezione</link>.
        Qui vengono spiegati solo gli effetti specifici della selezione
        ellittica.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        모든 선택 도구에 해당되는 동작 변경키는
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link> 섹션에 설명되어
        있으므로, 여기서는 타원형 선택 도구에만 영향을 주는 특수한 키에
        대해 설명할 것입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Sjå <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">felles eigenskapar</link> for
        eit oversyn over tastekombinasjonar som er felles for fleire av
        markeringsverktøya. Bare kombinasjonar som er spesifikke for dette
        verktøyet blir omtalte i dette avsnittet.
      </para>
      <para lang="pl">
        Klawisze modyfikujące wspólne dla wszystkich narzędzi
      zaznaczania zostały opisane na
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
      Poniżej opisano jedynie klawisze charakterystyczne dla
      Zaznaczenia eliptycznego.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Обратитесь к <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Инструментам выделения
        </link> за справкой об клавишах-модификаторах, общих для всех
        инструментов выделения. Здесь описаны только клавишы, присущие
        инструменту Эллиптическое выделение.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        关于控制键用相同方式影响这些工具的帮助请看<link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>，下面只解释对椭圆选择工具特有的影响。
      </para>
    </note>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;es;fr;it;ko;nl;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Strg</keycap></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Pressing the key after starting your selection, and holding it
            down until you are finished, causes your starting point to be used
            as the center of the selected ellipse, instead of a corner of the
            rectangle that may contain it. Note that if you press the Ctrl key
            <emphasis>before</emphasis>
            starting to make the selection, the resulting selection will be
            subtracted from the existing selection.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Stisknutí klávesy Ctrl po zahájení výběru
            a její držení, dokud není výběr hotov, způsobí, že počáteční bod
            bude považován za střed elipsy, nikoliv za roh obdélníkové obálky
            elipsy. Pokud však klávesu Ctrl stisknete <emphasis>před</emphasis>
            zahájením tvorby výběru, bude se výsledný výběr odečítat od
            stávajícího výběru.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Das Drücken der Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap>
            <emphasis>nach</emphasis> dem Beginn der Erstellung einer Auswahl
            bewirkt, dass der Startpixel als Mittelpunkt der neuen Auswahl
            benutzt wird und nicht als Ecke eines gedachten, die Auswahl
            umgebenden Rechtecks. Bitte beachten Sie, dass, wenn Sie
            die Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap> drücken, <emphasis>bevor</emphasis>
            Sie beginnen, die Auswahl zu erstellen, der Auswahlmodus auf
            <quote>Subtrahieren</quote> gestellt wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            presionar la tecla Ctrl luego de haber
            comenzado la selección, y mantenerla presionada hasta que se haya
            terminado la selección, hace que el punto de inicio se use como
            centro de la elipsis, en vez de usarse como una esquina del
            rectángulo en que se haya inscripta.  Note que si presiona la tecla
            Ctrl <emphasis>antes</emphasis> de haber comenzado la selección,
            ésta se sustraerá a la selección existente.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous appuyez sur la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> pendant la
            création de la sélection elliptique, la sélection sera créée
            en utilisant le pixel sur lequel vous avez cliqué comme
            centre. Habituellement, la sélection est créée en utilisant ce
            pixel comme coin du rectangle encadrant l'ellipse.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous appuyez sur la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> avant ou
            après la création de la sélection, la nouvelle sélection passera
            en mode Soustraction.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            la pressione del tasto Ctrl dopo aver iniziato la selezione,
            tenendolo premuto fino a che essa non viene completata, fa si che il
            punto iniziale della selezione sia il centro dell'ellisse
            selezionata, anzichè un angolo del rettangolo che potrebbe
            contenerla. Notare che se il tasto Ctrl viene premuto
            <emphasis>prima</emphasis>
            di cominciare a selezionare, la selezione effettuata verrà sottratta
            dalla selezione esistente.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            선택을 만들기 시작한 후 Ctrl 키를 누르고 이를 선택이
                    완료될 때까지 누르고 있으면, 처음 시작한 점이 타원
                    선택의 중심이 됩니다. 하지만 선택을 만들기
                    <emphasis>전에</emphasis> Ctrl 키를 누르면, 기존의 선택에서
                    새로운 선택을 빼는 모드가 됩니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Trykker du ned <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten
            etter at du har byrja markeringa, og held han nede til du er
            ferdig med markeringa, vil startpunktet bli brukt som sentrum i
            markeringa i staden for å bli eit av hjørna i det tenkte
            rektanglet som omgir figuren. Trykker du ned
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-tasten før du startar markeringa, vil den
            nye markering bli subtrahert frå den eksisterande markeringa.
          </para>
        <para lang="pl">
            Przytrzymywanie klawisza po rozpoczęciu zaznaczania sprawia,
          że centrum zaznaczenia staje się punkt kliknięcia. W przeciwnym
            wypadku punkt kliknięcia zostanie wewnątrz prostokąta, zawierającego
          elipsę. Natomiast przytrzymanie Ctrl <emphasis>przed</emphasis>
            rozpoczęciem zaznaczania odejmie nowe zaznaczenie od już istniejącego.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Нажатие и держание клавиши после начала
            выделения фиксирует центр выделения на начальной точке. Иначе
            начальная точка остаётся в углу прямоугольника, содержащего эллипс.
            Заметьте, что нажатие клавиши <emphasis>до</emphasis> начала
            выделения вычитает новое выделение из уже существующего.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 同时创建一个椭圆选区会同时做两件事。第一，创建的选区将以您选取的起点作为圆心。一般情况下， 会以您选取的起点作为一角。第二，<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 会使选取呈减去模式。如果只想完成其中一个动作，可以在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 键，这样选取只变为减去模式，而不会以选取的起点作为圆心。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;es;ko;nl;no;pl;ru;zh_CN"><keycap>Shift</keycap></term>
        <term lang="de"><keycap>Umschalt</keycap></term>
        <term lang="fr"><keycap>Maj</keycap></term>
        <term lang="it"><keycap>Maiusc</keycap></term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Pressing the Shift key after starting your selection, and holding
            it down until you are finished, constrains the selection to be a
            circle. Note that if you press the Shift key
            <emphasis>before</emphasis>
            starting to make the selection, the resulting selection will be
            added to the existing selection.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Stisknutí klávesy Shift po zahájení výběru
            a její držení, dokud není výběr hotov, způsobí vytvoření kruhového
            výběru. Pokud však klávesu Shift stisknete <emphasis>před</emphasis>
            zahájením tvorby výběru, bude se výsledný výběr přičítat k
            stávajícímu výběru.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Das Drücken der Umschalttaste
            <emphasis>nach</emphasis> dem Beginn der
            Erstellung einer Auswahl bewirkt, dass die neue Auswahl kreisrund
            sein wird. Bitte beachten Sie, dass, wenn Sie die Taste
            <keycap>Umschalt</keycap> <emphasis>vor</emphasis> dem Beginn der
            Erstellung der neuen Auswahl drücken, der Auswahlmodus auf
            <quote>Hinzufügen</quote> gestellt wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            presionar la tecla Shift luego de haber comenzado la selección, y
            mantenerla presionada hasta finalizar la selección, restringe su
            forma para que sea un círculo. Note que si presiona la tecla Shift
            <emphasis>antes</emphasis>
            de comenzar la selección, ésta se añadirá a la selección
            existente.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous appuyez sur la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            <emphasis>pendant</emphasis> la création de la sélection, la
            sélection prendra la forme d'un cercle.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si vous appuyez sur la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            <emphasis>avant ou après</emphasis> la création de la sélection,
            la nouvelle sélection passera en mode Addition.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            la pressione del tasto Maiusc dopo aver iniziato la selezione,
            tenendolo premuto fino al che essa non viene completata, obbliga la
            selezione ad essere circolare. Notare che se si preme il tasto
            Maiusc <emphasis>prima</emphasis>
            di cominciare a selezionare, la selezione effettuata verrà aggiunta
            alla selezione esistente.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            선택을 만들기 시작한 후 Shift 키를 누르고 이를 선택이
            완료될때까지 누르고 있으면, 선택은 원형으로 고정됩니다.
            하지만 선택을 만들기 <emphasis>전에</emphasis> Shift
            키를 누르면, 기존의 선택에서 새로운 선택을 더하는 모드가 됩니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Trykker du ned
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten etter at du har byrja markeringa,
            og held han nede til du er ferdig med markeringa, vil markeringa
            bli avgrensa til ein sirkel. Trykker du ned
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>-tasten før du startar markeringa, vil den
            nye markeringa bli addert til den eksisterande markeringa.
          </para>
        <para lang="pl">
            Przytrzymywanie klawisza po rozpoczęciu zaznaczania sprawi,
            że zaznaczenie będzie okrągłe. Przytrzymanie Shift
            <emphasis>przed</emphasis> rozpoczęciem zaznaczania doda nowe
          zaznaczenie do już istniejącego.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Нажатие и держание клавиши после начала
            выделения делает выделение круглым. Заметьте, что нажатие клавиши
            <emphasis>до</emphasis> начала выделения добавляет новое выделение к
            уже существующему.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            按住 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 的同时创建一个选区将做两件不同的事。第一，它保持选区的长宽或长短轴相同。第二，该组合键使选取呈合并模式。如果只想完成其中一个动作，可以在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 键，这样选取只变为合并模式，而不会约束其长宽或长短轴相同。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;es;ko;nl;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
        </term>
        <term lang="de">
          <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Umschalt</keycap></keycombo>
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Maj</keycap></keycombo>
        </term>
        <term lang="it">
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Maiusc</keycap></keycombo>
        </term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Pressing both keys combines the two effects, giving you a circular
            selection centered on your starting point.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Stisknutí obou kláves kombinuje jejich efekty, vytváří
            se tedy kruhový výběr se středem v počátečním bodě.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Das Drücken von
            <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Umschalt</keycap></keycombo>
            führt zu einer kreisrunden Auswahl, wobei der Startpixel als
            Mittelpunkt der neuen Auswahl verwendet wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            presionar ambas teclas luego de haber comenzado la selección
            produce la combinación de los dos efectos, y la selección es un
            círculo centrado en el punto inicial. Note que presionando estas
            teclas antes de comenzar la selección da como resultado la
            intersección de la selección actual con la existente.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            la combinaison de touches
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Maj</keycap></keycombo>
            vous donne une sélection circulaire centrée sur le point de
            départ.
          </para>
              <para lang="it">
            Premendo entrambi i tasti si combinano i due effetti, realizzando
            una selezione circolare centrata rispetto al punto di partenza.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            선택을 만들기 시작한 후에 두 키를 누르면, 두 가지 효과가
            중복되어, 처음 시작점을 중심으로 하는 원형의 선택이
            만들어집니다. 하지만 선택을 만들기 전에 이 키들을 누르면,
            마우스 포인터의 모양이 바뀌면서 기존의 선택과 새로운 선택이
            겹치는 부분만 남게 됩니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Dette gir ein
            kombinert effekt: Ei sirkulær markering sentrert om
            startpunktet. Held du nede desse to tastane før du byrjar
            markeringa, vil den nye markeringa lage eit snitt med den
            eksisterande. Dette blir også vist med at musemarkøren viser
            snitt-symbolet <quote>∩</quote>.
          </para>
        <para lang="pl">
            Jednoczesne przytrzymanie obu klawiszy spowoduje nałożenie się ich
            efektów, tworząc okrąg, którego środkiem jest punkt kliknięcia.
            Przytrzymanie klawiszy przed rozpoczęciem zaznaczania spowoduje
            przecięcie nowego zaznaczenia z już istniejącym. Kursor odpowiednio
          się zmienia.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Нажатие обеих клавиш после начала выделения объединяет эти два
            эффекта, создавая круг с центром в начальной точке выделения.
            Заметьте, что нажатие клавиш до начала выделения даёт пересечение
            нового выделения со уже существующим. Курсор меняется соответсвенно.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            使用
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            可以干一系列事。各个键单独拿出来都可以干两件事。首先，选择模式将变为相交。其次，选区将以其起始点作为圆心(上面讨论过)且长宽或长短轴相同(上面也讨论过)。读者可以在使用椭圆选择同时按住<keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>时尝试在放开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开一个键或全部键。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="tool-ellipse-select-manip" lang="en;fr"><!-- section added by PP 19/12/2007  -
     TODO es;de;it;nl;no;pl;ru;zh_CN  -->
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Tool handling</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Manipulation de l'outil</phrase>
    </title>
    <para lang="en">
      When this tool is selected the mouse pointer comes with a circle icon
      as soon as it is over the image. A drag-and-drop allows you to
      get an ellipse (or a circle) within a rectangular box.
      When the mouse button is relaxed, a dotted line (<quote>marching
      ants</quote>) outlines the elliptic selection. It's not necessary to
      adjust the selection with care ; you can resize it easily later.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">Lorsque cet outil est sélectionné, le pointeur de la
    souris est accompagé d'une icône de cercle dès qu'il est sur l'image.
    Un cliquer-glisser permet de tracer une ellipse (ou un cercle) contenue
    dans une boîte rectangulaire. Lorsque le bouton de
    la souris est relâché, la sélection elliptique est délimitée par des
    pointillés qui se déplacent autour de celle-ci. Il n'est pas nécessaire
    d'ajuster rigoureusement la sélection, celle-ci peut facilement être
    redimensionnée et déplacée par la suite.
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      When the pointer is moving on the canvas, the pointer and selection
      aspects change. You can change the size of the selection by using
      handles. See
      <link linkend="tool-rect-select-manip">Tool handling</link> within
      the rectangular chapter.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">Selon la position du curseur, son aspect change ainsi
      que celui de la sélection. Les différents aspects du pointeur de la
      souris concernant la modification de la taille de la sélection sont
      les mêmes que pour l'outil de sélection rectangulaire et la
      manipulation de cet outil se fait exactement de la même façon. On
      pourra donc utilement se reporter à
      <link linkend="tool-rect-select-manip"> Manipulation de
      l'outil</link> relatif à la sélection rectangulaire.
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones de la herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">선택 사항</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Opcje narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Tool Options for the Ellipse Select tool</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Volby nástroje Výběr elipsy</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften des Werkzeuges <quote>Elliptische Auswahl</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Las opciones de la herramienta de selección elíptica.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Les options de l'outil de sélection elliptique.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Le opzioni strumento per la selezione ellittica
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">
          타원 선택 도구의 선택사항
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for verktøyet <quote>ellipsemarkering</quote>
        </phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">
          Opcje <quote>Zaznaczenia eliptycznego</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры инструмента <quote>Эллиптическое выделение</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">椭圆选择工具的工具选项</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;pl;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="cs">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="es">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="ko">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ko/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-ellipsel.png"
                    format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

 <!--  this part must be delete and re-arranged  to standardize vs tool-rect-select.xml presentation
      see later below  -  PP on 2007/12/02

      <note>
      <para lang="en">
        See <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Selection Tools</link>
        for help with options that are common to all these tools. Only options
        that are specific to the Ellipse Select tool are described here.
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        V části <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro výběr</link>
        jsou popsány volby společné všem těmto nástrojům. Zde jsou popsány
        pouze volby specifické pro nástroj Výběr elipsy.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        In diesem Abschnitt werden nur die speziellen Eigenschaften des
        Werkzeuges beschrieben. Schauen sie bitte unter
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Auswahlwerkzeuge</link>
        nach, falls Sie Hilfe zu den allgemeinen Einstellungen der
        Auswahlwerkzeuge benötigen.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Diríjase a la sección <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Herramientas de
        selección</link> para conocer las opciones que son comunes a todas las
        herramientas de este grupo.  Aquí sólo se explican las opciones
        específicas a la herramienta de selección elíptica.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Voyez <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Outils de sélection</link>
        pour avoir de l'aide sur les options communes à tous ces outils.
        Seules les options spécifiques à l'outil de sélection elliptique sont
        décrites ici.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per aiuto sulle opzioni comuni a tutti questi strumenti vedi
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Strumenti di selezione</link>.
        Qui vengono spiegate soltanto le opzioni specifiche dello strumento
        di selezione ellittica.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        모든 선택도구에 동일하게 적용되는 선택사항은
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link>를 참조하세요.
        여기서는 타원 선택 도구에만 적용되는 특수한 선택 사항에 대해 설명할
        것입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Sjå <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Markeringsverktøya</link> for
        eit oversyn over tastekombinasjonar som er felles for fleire av
        markeringsverktøya. Bare kombinasjonar som er spesifikke for
        ellipseverktøyet blir omtalte i dette avsnittet.
      </para>
      <para lang="pl">
        Оpcje wspólne dla wszystkich narzędzi zaznaczania zostały opisane
      na <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
      Poniżej opisano jedynie opcje, charakterystyczne dla Zaznaczenia
      eliptycznego.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Обратитесь к <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Инструментам выделения
        </link> за справкой об параметрах, общих для всех инструментов
        выделения. Здесь описаны только параметры, присущие инструменту
        Эллиптическое выделение.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        这些工具共有的选项请看
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>。下面只解释椭圆选择工具所特有的选项。
      </para>
    </note>   -->

    <para lang="en">
      You can access to the Ellipse Selection options by double-clicking on
      the
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      icon.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      volby nástroje elipsy se zpřístupní dvojitým kliknutím na ikonu nástroje
      v panelu nástrojů
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die aktuellen Einstellungen für die elliptische Auswahl lassen sich
      durch einen Doppelklick auf das Symbol
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      anzeigen.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Puede acceder a las opciones de esta herramienta efectuando doble clic
      sobre el icono
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      On accède aux options de l'outil Sélection Elliptique par un double clic
      sur l'icône de cet outil
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      타원 선택 선택사항은
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      아이콘을 더블 클릭하면 볼 수 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Du får tilgang til innstillingane for ellipseverktøyet ved å klikka
      på symbolet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      i verktøyskrinet.
    </para>
    <para lang="pl">
      Opcje <quote>Zaznaczenia eliptycznego</quote> wyświetlane są po dwukrotnym
      kliknięciu ikony
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Инструмент <quote>Эллиптическое выделение</quote> доступен нажатием на
      пиктограмму
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-ellipse-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <!-- FIXME: es it ko nl no ru zh_CN review needed -->
        <!--  I re-arranged accordling to what is presented in tool-rect-select.xml - PP 2007/12/02
                  I delete Rounded corners  in "term" for all languages -->

      <!-- A note about common options with link to description: -->
      <xi:include href="about-common-select-options.xml" />

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;es;it;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
          Modus; Antialias; Feather edges
        </term>
        <term lang="de">Modus; Kanten glätten; Kanten ausblenden</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mode ; Lissage ; Adoucir les bords</term>
        <term lang="ko">양식; 안티앨리어스</term>
        <term lang="pl">Tryb; Wygładzaj krawędzie</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Common select options.</para>
          <para lang="de">Allgemeine Auswahleigenschaften.</para>
          <para lang="fr">Options de sélection communes.</para>
          <!--TODO es it ko no pl ru zh_CN: consider switching to the
              above include file (check/edit it before!)-->
          <note lang="es;it;ko;nl;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
            <para lang="es">
              Diríjase a la sección
              <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">
                Herramientas de selección
              </link>
              para conocer las opciones que son comunes a todas las
              herramientas de este grupo. Aquí sólo se explican las opciones
              específicas a la herramienta de selección rectangular.
            </para>
            <para lang="it">
              Per aiuto sulle opzioni comuni a tutti questi strumenti vedi
              <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Strumenti di selezione</link>.
              Qui vengono spiegate soltanto le opzioni specifiche dello
              strumento di selezione rettangolare.
            </para>
            <para lang="ko">
              모든 선택도구에 동일하게 적용되는 선택사항은
              <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link>
              를 참조하세요. 여기서는 사각 선택 도구에만 적용되는 특수한 선택 사항에 대해 설명할 것입니다.
            </para>
            <para lang="nl">
              Zie
              <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Selectie Gereedschappen</link>
              voor meer informatie over eigenschappen die gelden voor alle
              selectie gereedschappen. Alleen opties specifiek voor het
              rechthoekselectie gereedschap worden hier besproken.
            </para>
            <para lang="no">
              Sjå
              <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">felles eigenskapar</link>
              for eit oversyn over tastekombinasjonar som er felles for fleire
              av markeringsverktøya. Bare kombinasjonar som er spesifikke for
              dette verktøyet blir omtalte i dette avsnittet.
            </para>
          <para lang="pl">
              Opcje wspólne dla wszystkich narzędzi zaznaczania zostały opisane
              na <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
              Poniżej opisano jedynie opcje, charakterystyczne dla Zaznaczenia
            eliptycznego.
            </para>
            <para lang="ru">
              Обратитесь к
              <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Инструментам выделения</link>
              за справкой об параметрах, общих для всех инструментов
              выделения. Здесь описаны только параметры, присущие инструменту
              Прямоугольное выделение.
            </para>
            <para lang="zh_CN">
              这些工具共用的选项请看 <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>
              。下面只解释矩形选择工具所特有的选项。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <!-- FIXME: es  it ko nl no ru zh_CN review needed -->
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en;es;it;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
          All other options
        </term>
        <term lang="de">
          Alle anderen Eigenschaften
          <!--Aus der Mitte aufziehen; Festes Seitenverhältnis; Hervorheben;
          X; Y; Breite; Höhe; Hilfslinien; Auswahl automatisch schrumpfen;
          Vereinigung mitschrumpfen-->
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">Toutes autres options</term>
        <term lang="ko">양식; 안티앨리어스; 둥근 모서리</term>
      <term lang="pl">Tryb; Wygładzaj; Zmiękczaj krawędzie</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en;es;it;nl;no;ru;zh_CN">
            All these options work exactly the same way, they were described
            for the rectangular selection already. See for
            <xref linkend="tool-rect-select-options" /> details.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            All diese Eigenschaften der elliptischen Auswahl entsprechen genau
            denen, welche im <xref linkend="tool-rect-select-options" />
            bereits für die rechteckige Auswahl beschrieben wurden.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Toutes les autres options fonctionnent de façon tout à fait
            semblable à ce qui a déjà été décrit pour la sélection
            rectangulaire ; vous pouvez donc, si nécessaire, vous reporter à
            <xref linkend="tool-rect-select-options" />.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            모든 옵션은 사각 선택 도구와 동이랗게 동작합니다. 더
            자세한 내용은 <xref linkend="tool-rect-select-options" />
            을 참고하세요.
          </para>
        <para lang="pl">
            Opcje te działają dokładnie w ten sam sposób, jak te
            opisane dla Zaznaczenia prostokątnego. Więcej informacji w
            <xref linkend="tool-rect-select-options" />.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
