<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-12-20  PP reviewed fr & en ; added section3 for tool manipulation
  2007-10-05 lexa: reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
  2007-08-11 added 'ko' contents by Mr.Dust
  2007-06-02 KoSt: added 'no'
  06-02-10 en;fr revised by j.h
  05/10/14 reviewed by axel.wernicke
  05/05/18 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-fuzzy-select" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr;ko">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-22</date>
        <authorinitials>P.P</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-01-09</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-03-27</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-22</date>
        <authorinitials>P.P</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-08-11</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Fuzzy selection (Magic wand)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Přibližný výběr (Kouzelná hůlka)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Zauberstab</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">
      Herramienta de selección borrosa (la varita mágica)
    </phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Sélection contiguë (Baguette magique)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">
      Selezione di regioni contigue (bacchetta magica - fuzzy)
    </phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">연속적인 선택(마법 지팡이)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Tryllestaven</phrase>
    <phrase lang="pl">Zaznaczenie rozmyte</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Выделение связанной области (Волшебная палочка)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">模糊选择工具</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary><secondary>Fuzzy Selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selection</primary><secondary>Fuzzy selection</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Fuzzy Selection</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Magic Wand</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Panel nástrojů</primary>
    <secondary>Výběr</secondary>
    <tertiary>Přibližný</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary><secondary>Zauberstab</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Auswahlwerkzeug</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Zauberstab</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Herramientas</primary>
    <secondary>Selección borrosa</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Selección</primary><secondary>Selección borrosa</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Varita mágica</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Outils</primary><secondary>Sélection contiguë</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Baguette magique</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélection</primary><secondary>Sélection contiguë</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary>
    <secondary>Selezione di regioni contigue</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Selezione di regioni contigue</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Bacchetta magica</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>도구</primary><secondary>연속적인 선택</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>선택</primary><secondary>연속적인 선택</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>연속적인 선택</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>마법 지팡이</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Verktøy</primary><secondary>Tryllestaven</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Markeringar</primary><secondary>Tryllestaven</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Narzędzia</primary><secondary>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Zaznaczenie</primary><secondary>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl"><primary>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl"><primary>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Инструменты</primary>
    <secondary>Выделение связанной области</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Выделение</primary>
    <secondary>Выделение связанной области</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Волшебная палочка</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>工具箱</primary><secondary>选择</secondary>
  </indexterm>


  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Magic Wand tool icon in the Toolbox</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Ikona kouzelné hůlky v Panelu nástrojů.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Der Zauberstab im Werkzeugfenster.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">La varita mágica en la caja de herramientas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        L'outil Baguette magique dans la Boîte à outils.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        L'icona della bacchetta magica nella barra degli strumenti.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구상자의 마법 지팡이 도구 아이콘</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Symbolet for tryllestaven i verktøyskrinet</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">
        <quote>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</quote> na pasku narzędzi
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">
        Пиктограмма инструмента <quote>Выделение связанной области</quote> в
        панели инструментов
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">工具箱中魔术棒工具图标</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;es;pl;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/cs/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ko">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ko/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-wand.png"
                   format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en"> <!--A part  is moved to section "Tool handling" for en & fr by PP   22/12/07 -->
  <!-- TODO cs es it ko no pl ru zh_CN: move parts to section "Tool handling" -->
    The Fuzzy Select (Magic Wand) tool is designed to select areas of the
    current layer or image based on color similarity.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    When using this tool, it is very important to pick the right starting
    point. If you select the wrong spot, you might get something very
    different from what you want, or even the opposite.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The Wand is a good tool for selecting objects with sharp edges. It is fun
    to use, so beginners often start out using it a lot. You will probably
    find, however, that the more you use it, the more frustrated you become
    with the difficulty of selecting exactly what you what, no more, no less.
    Perhaps the most frustrating aspect is that after you have released the
    mouse button, you can't make small adjustments to the threshold: you have
    to start over again from scratch. More experienced users find that the
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path</link> and
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Color Select</link>
    tools are often more efficient, and use the Wand less. Still, it is useful
    for selecting an area within a contour, or touching up imperfect
    selections. It often works very well for selecting a solid-colored (or
    nearly solid-colored) background area.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Note that as the selected area expands outward from the center, it does
    not only propagate to pixels that touch each other: it is capable of
    jumping over small gaps. The distance it can jump over is set in the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Tool Options</link>
    page of the Preferences dialog: the "Default threshold" for Finding
    Continguous Regions. By raising or lowering this value, you can make the
    Magic Wand either more or less aggressive. (Filling with the Bucket Fill
    and Blend tools will also be affected.)
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroj Přibližný výběr (Kouzelná hůlka) je určen k výběru oblastí aktivní
    vrstvy nebo obrázku na základě podobnosti barev. Výběr začne tam, kam v
    obrázku kouzelnou hůlkou kliknete, a rozšíří se dál podobně jako rozlitá
    voda po všech sousedních pixelech, jejichž barva je podobná pixelu
    počátečnímu. Práh podobnosti můžete měnit tažením myši dolů nebo doprava.
    Čím dále jí potáhnete, tím větší bude vybraná oblast.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Při používání kouzelné hůlky je velmi důležité dobře zvolit správný
    počáteční bod. Pokud zvolíte špatně, může být výsledek úplně jiný, než si
    představujete.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Kouzelná hůlka se dobře hodí k vybírání objektů s ostrými hranami. Dobře
    se s ní pracuje, takže si ji brzy oblíbí mnoho začátečníků. Čím déle s ní
    však budete pracovat, tím více poznáte, že vybrat hůlkou přesně to, co
    chcete, je dosti obtížné. Nejhorší je, že po uvolnění myši už nemůžete
    dělat drobné úpravy prahy podobnosti barev; musíte začít od začátku.
    Zkušenější uživatelé si proto brzy oblíbí nástroje Cesty FIXLINK a nástroj
    pro výběr podle barev. Ty jsou totiž v mnoha případech efektivnější než
    kouzelná hůlka. Kouzelná hůlka je však stále dobrá pro výběr dobře
    ohraničených oblastí nebo dolaďování nedokonalých výběrů. Často se dobře
    hodí k výběru pozadí, pokud je jednobarevné nebo téměř jednobarevné.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Povšimněte si, že jak se vybraná oblast rozšiřuje směrem od počátku,
    nešíří se jen po pixelech, které se skutečně dotýkají, ale je schopna
    překonávat malé mezery. Vzdálenost, kterou může výběr přeskočit, lze
    nastavit dialogu Předvolby v části
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Volby nástrojů</link>
    : Implicitní práh. Zvýšením hodnoty můžete hůlku učinit agresivnější.
    (Nastavení se projeví i u Plechovky.)
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Zauberstab</quote> ermöglicht es Ihnen, eine Auswahl
    auf der Basis von Bereichen eines Bildes oder der aktuellen Ebene mit
    ähnlichen Farbwerten zu erstellen.
  </para>
  <!--para lang="de">
    "When using this tool,..." is added as a note before the first sect3.
  </para-->
  <para lang="de">
    Der Zauberstab ist sehr gut geeignet, um eine Auswahl aus
    Bildteilen zu erstellen, welche durch starke Kanten von ihrer Umgebung
    abgegrenzt sind. Es macht Spaß, den Zauberstab zu benutzen, daher arbeiten
    gerade <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Einsteiger sehr viel mit ihm. Wenn Sie eine
    Weile den Zauberstab verwendet haben, kann es allerdings passieren, dass
    Sie es als eher schwierig empfinden, damit exakt den Bereich auszuwählen,
    den Sie wollen - weder mehr, noch weniger. Das möglicherweise
    Frustrierendste bei der Benutzung des Zauberstabes ist, dass, wenn Sie
    erst einmal die <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> losgelassen haben,
    Sie keine Möglichkeit mehr haben, kleine Änderungen an der Eigenschaft
    <guilabel>Schwelle</guilabel> vorzunehmen. Sie müssen zuerst die
    Einstellung anpassen und dann die Auswahl neu erstellen.
    Erfahrenere Anwender empfinden daher die Arbeit mit den Werkzeugen
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Pfad</link> oder
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Nach Farbe auswählen</link>
    als wesentlich effizienter und verwenden den Zauberstab deutlich seltener.
    Trotzdem, der Zauberstab ist sehr nützlich, wenn es darum geht, einen
    Bereich des Bildes auszuwählen, der von einer Kontur begrenzt wird. Er
    funktioniert auch sehr gut, um einen (nahezu) einfarbigen Hintergrund
    auszuwählen.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Bitte beachten Sie, dass der ausgewählte Bereich nicht nur Pixel umfasst,
    die direkt mit dem Startpunkt verbunden sind. Der Zauberstab ist auch in
    der Lage, kleine Lücken zu überspringen. Die Größe dieser Lücken lässt
    sich im Bereich
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Werkzeugeinstellungen</link>
    des Dialogs <quote>Einstellungen</quote>
    verändern. Hierzu passen Sie bitte die Eigenschaft
    <guilabel>Voreingestellter Schwellwert</guilabel>
    Ihren Bedürfnissen an. Durch ein Vergrößern oder Verkleinern dieser
    Einstellung machen Sie den Zauberstab mehr oder weniger aggressiv.
  </para>

  <para lang="es">
    La herramienta de selección borrosa, también llamada varita mágica,
    selecciona áreas continuas de color similar.  Puede emplear los colores de
    la capa actual o en toda la imagen.  Comienza seleccionando el lugar en
    donde se hace clic, y se expande como agua que desciende, seleccionando
    los píxeles contiguos cuyos colores sean similares al píxel inicial.
    Puede controlar el rango de similaridad arrastrando el ratón hacia abajo o
    hacia la derecha: mientras más lejos lo lleve, mayor será el área
    seleccionada.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Cuando emplee esta herramienta, es muy importante escoger el punto inicial
    más apropiado.  Si selecciona un mal punto, probablemente obtendrá una
    selección muy diferente a la esperada.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    La varita es una buena herramienta para seleccionar áreas que están bien
    delimitadas por bordes.  Es entretenido usarla, y los principiantes la
    usan frecuentemente.  Se dará cuenta, sin embargo, que es difícil
    seleccionar exactamente lo que desea con precisión.  Tal vez su mayor
    desventaja es que no se pueden hacer pequeños ajustes una vez soltado el
    botón, hay que volver a comenzar, elegiendo nuevamente el punto inicial.
    Los usuarios más experimentados a menudo hallan a las <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-path">rutas</link> y a la <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">selección por colores</link> más
    eficientes, y emplean menos a la varita.  Aún así, como hemos dicho, es
    útil para las áreas bien delineadas.  En general trabaja bien para
    seleccionar fondos con un color sólido.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Note que a medida que el área se expande, no sólo se propaga por píxeles
    consecutivos, sino que puede dar pequeños saltos.  La distancia que puede
    obviar se define en la página <link
    linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Opciones de herramienta</link> del
    diálogo Preferencias, es el "umbral predeterminado" para las regiones
    continuas.  Al cambiar este valor puede hacer a la varita más o menos
    agresiva.  El relleno con la cubeta y con la herramienta de mezcla también
    se verán afectados.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Le nom anglais de cet outil est <quote>Fuzzy Selection</quote>
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil Sélection contiguë (ou Baguette magique, ou encore
    Sélection floue) sert à sélectionner des régions du calque actif ou
    d'une image sur la base de la similarité des couleurs : les pixels
    voisins du pixel cliqué, de même Teinte ou de Teinte proche, sont
    inclus dans la sélection.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Quand vous utilisez cet outil, il est important de choisir le bon
    pixel de départ, sinon le résultat risque de ne pas être celui que
    vous attendiez.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    La Baguette magique est un bon outil pour sélectionner les objets
    qui ont un bord net. Il est amusant à utiliser, et les débutants
    ne s'en privent pas, mais vous serez vite déçu par la difficulté à
    obtenir exactement ce que vous voulez. Particulièrement frustrante
    est l'impossibilité de modifier le seuil de sélection une fois
    relâché le bouton de la souris. Les utilisateurs plus expérimentés
    préfèreront les outils  <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Chemin
    </link> et <link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Sélection par
    couleur</link>. Néanmoins, l'outil convient bien aux aires de
    couleur uniforme.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Notez que le processus de sélection ne s'étend pas seulement aux
    pixels immédiatement adjacents, mais est capable de sauter un peu
    au-delà, en fonction du réglage de la page
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Options des outils</link>
    du dialogue des Préférences, à la rubrique <quote>Recherche de régions
    contiguës</quote> (Cette valeur affecte aussi le remplissage avec les
    outils Pot de peinture et Dégradé).
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Lo strumento selezione regioni contigue (bacchetta magica - fuzzy)
    è progettato per selezionare delle zone dal livello attivo o
    dall'immagine in base alla somiglianza dei colori. Partendo da un clic
    su un punto dell'immagine, la selezione si espande esternamente ad
    esso come un'innondazione d'acqua che allaga delle zone pianeggianti,
    selezionando i pixel che confinano i cui colori sono simili a quelli del
    pixel di partenza.  E' possibile controllare la soglia di somiglianza
    trascinando il mouse verso il basso o verso destra:  più
    lontano viene trascinato, più larga sarà l'area selezionata.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Usando questo strumento è molto importante scegliere un punto iniziale
    appropriato. Selezionando un punto sbagliato si potrebbe ottenere
    qualcosa di molto differente rispetto alle aspettative, se non l'esatto
    contrario.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    La bacchetta è un buon strumento per la selezione di oggetti con margini
    definiti. E' divertente da usare e per questo i principianti spesso la
    usano molto. Probabilmente però più la si usa più si avverte un senso di
    frustrazione per la difficoltà a selezionare esattamente ciò che si
    desidera, niente di più, niente di meno. Forse l'aspetto più frustrante è
    che se si è già rilasciato il pulsante del mouse non è possibile
    effettuare piccoli aggiustamenti alla soglia: bisogna ricominciare da
    capo. Gli utenti più esperti trovano spesso più efficenti gli strumenti
    <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="gimp-tool-path" -->tracciati<!--/link-->
    e <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select" -->
    selezione per colore<!--/link-->
    , ed usano meno la bacchetta. Nonostante tutto essa è utile per
    selezionare un area all'interno di un contorno, o per ritoccare delle
    selezioni imperfette. Spesso funziona molto bene per selezionare delle
    zone con uno sfondo colorato in tinta unita (o quasi tinta unita).
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Da notare che quando l'area selezionata si espande dal centro, essa non
    si propaga solo ai pixel che si toccano l'un l'altro: ma può
    saltare oltre a dei piccoli spazi. La distanza oltre alla quale può
    saltare viene impostata nella scheda
    <!-- FIXME: it link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options" -->opzioni strumenti<!--/link--> della
    finestra delle preferenze:  la "soglia predefinita" per seleziona
    regioni contigue.  Incrementando o diminuendo questo valore, si può
    rendere la bacchetta magica più o meno aggressiva. (Ciò influeza anche
    gli strumenti di riempimento colore e riempimento con un gradiente.)
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    연속적인 선택(마법 지팡이) 도구는 현재 이미지나 레이어에서 비슷한
    색상이 연속적으로 이어진 영역을 선택하는 도구입니다. 이미지의 한 지점을
    선택하면, 마치 낮은 곳으로 물이 흐르듯, 해당 지점의 색상과 비슷한
    색상으로 이어진 픽셀들이 모두 선택되어 집니다. 마우스 버튼을 누른 채
    드래그해서 유사성의 임계값을 조절할 수 있습니다. 아래쪽이나 오른쪽으로
    드래그하면 더 많은 영역이 선택되어지고, 위쪽이나 왼쪽으로 드래그하면
    조금 더 적은 영역이 선택되어집니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    이 도구를 사용할 때 가장 중요한 것은 정확한 기준점을 찾는 것입니다.
    만약 엉뚱한 지점을 기준으로 잡으면, 원하는대로 선택을 하지 못할 수도
    있습니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    마법 지팡이 도구는 날카로운 경계를 가진 물체를 선택하기에 좋은
    도구입니다. 또한 사용하기에 재미있는 도구로 초보자들이 즐겨씁니다.
    하지만 써보면 써볼수록 정말 원하는 모양을 선택하기가 쉽지 않다라는 것을
    알게 될 것입니다. 그리고 마우스 버튼을 놓아 선택이 완성된 후에는
    임계값을 조절할 수 없으므로, 처음부터 다시 시작해야 합니다. 그런 까닭에
    고급 사용자들은 마법 지팡이 도구대신
    <!--FIXME : ko <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path</link> --> 경로 도구와
    <!-- FIXME: ko<link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Color Select</link>-->색상 선택
    도구를 이용해 조금더 효과적인 선택을 합니다. 하지만 단색으로 된 영역을
    선택하거나 대강의 선택을 만들 때에는 여전히 유용합니다. 특히 단색
    계열의 배경을 가진 경우에 많이 쓰입니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
    선택되는 영역은 연속된 픽셀뿐만 아니라 약간 떨어진 곳도 포함됩니다.
    이렇게 선택가능한 거리는 기본 설정 대화상자의
    <!-- FIXME : ko <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Tool Options</link> -->
    도구 선택사항 페이지에 있는 "기본 임계값" 에서 설정할 수 있습니다.
    이 값을 조절함으로써 마법 지팡이 도구의 영향 범위를 바꿀 수 있습니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    <emphasis>Tryllestaven</emphasis>, eller <quote>verktøyet for å
    markera samanhengande område</quote>, blir brukt for å velje ut
    område på det aktive laget eller biletet etter likskap i farge.
    Tryllestaven blir aktivisert ved at du klikkar på eit fargepunkt i
    biletet. Du vil då sjå korleis markeringa flyt utover som vatn over
    eit flatt lende etter kvart som punkta med liknande farge som
    startpunktet blir markerte. Du kan kontrollera kor like fargane må
    vera for å bli tatt med i markeringa ved å flytta musepeikaren nedover
    eller mot høgre. Dess lenger du flyttar peikaren, dess større område.
    Flytter du peikaren oppover eller mot venstre, blir området redusert.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Når du nyttar dette verktøyet, er det svært viktig å velja det
    rette startpunktet. Vel du feil, kan resultatet bli nokså langt
    frå det du hadde venta deg, eller til og med heilt omvendt.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Tryllestaven er eit godt verktøy for å velje ut område med skarpe,
    markerte kantar. I tillegg er det morosamt å bruka det, så
    nybegynnarane likar ofte dette verktøyet svært godt. Etterkvart vil
    kanskje gleda blir bytt ut med frustrasjon over at du ikkje greier
    å gjere nøyaktig den markeringa du ønskjer. Meir frustrerande er det
    kanskje likevel at etter at du har sleppt museknappen, kan du ikkje gjere
    endringar i markeringa. Er du misnøgd, må du gjere heile markeringa om
    igjen. Etter kvart vil du kanskje finne ut at verktøya for
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">bane</link> og <link
    linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Marker etter farge</link> er vel så
    nyttige. Du bør likevel ikkje avskriva tryllestaven. Han er fin til
    å velje ut eit område innføre eit omriss, og for å retta opp unøyaktige
    markeringar. Vidare er han ofte svært nyttig for å velje einsfarga
    eller nær einsfarga bakgrunnar eller større fargeflater.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Legg merke til at det valde området forplantar seg utover frå senter.
    Det spreier seg ikkje bare til nærliggande fargepunkt, men kan også
    gjere små hopp. Kor lange desse hoppa kan vere, bestemmer du i
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Verktøyalternativ</link> under
    <guimenuitem>Innstillingar</guimenuitem> i Hovudmenyen. Ved å auka
    eller minska verdien i <quote>Terskelverdien</quote> i avsnittet
    <quote>Vel samanhengande område</quote> kan du gjere tryllestaven meir
    eller mindre aggressiv. Ver bare klar over at dette også påverkar fylle
    og blande-verktøya.
  </para>

  <para lang="pl">
    Narzędzie służy do zaznaczania obszarów warstwy aktywnej lub obrazu,
    opierając się na podobieństwie kolorów. Zaznaczanie rozpoczyna się
    w wybranym punkcie, po czym rozciąga się we wszystkich kierunkach,
    obejmując piksele o kolorach zbliżonych do koloru wybranego punktu.
    Stopień podobieństwa kolorów może być kontrolowany poprzez przeciąganie
    kursora w dół lub w prawo dla zwiększenia zaznaczonego obszaru lub
    w górę lub w lewo dla jej zmniejszenia.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Bardzo ważne jest prawidłowe wybranie punktu początkowego. Jeśli zostanie
    on wybrany nieprawidłowo, rezultaty mogą różnić się od oczekiwanych,
    a nawet być przeciwnymi.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Zaznaczenie rozmyte dobrze sprawdza się podczas zaznaczania obiektów
    o ostrych krawędziach. Używanie narzędzia jest bardzo wciągające, dlatego
    też początkujący użykownicy używają go bardzo często. Jednak w miarę
    nabywania doświadczenia okazuje się, że narzędzie trudno jest ustawić
    tak, aby zaznaczało dokładnie wybrany obszar. Najbardziej zniechęcający
    jest fakt, że skala nie może być zmieniana po puszczeniu LPM. W takich
    wypadkach całą operację trzeba zaczynać od nowa. Bardziej doświadczeni
    użytkownicy zamiast Zaznaczenia rozmytego wolą używać
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Ścieżek</link> i
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">Zaznaczenia według koloru</link>.
    Zaznaczenie rozmyte jest pomocne podczas zaznaczania obszarów ścieżek lub
    przy wprowadzaniu niewielkich zmian zaznaczenia. Szczególnie dobrze
    narzędzie sprawdza się podczas zaznaczania jednolitego lub prawie
    jednolitego koloru tła.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Warto zauważyć, że w miarę powiększania się zaznaczenia, nie tylko
    obejmuje ono sąsiednie piksele, ale i może przskakiwać niewielkie
    odległości. Ich rozmiar określany jest w
    <!--link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options"-->Opcjach narzędzia<!--/link--> okna
    ustawień: domyślny próg do znajdowania obszarów rozmytych. Zmiana jego
    wartości powoduje zwiększenie lub zmniejszenie akcetowanej przez narzędzie
    różnicy kolorów. Opcja ta ma również wpływ na Wypełnienie kubełkiem i Gradient.
  </para>

  <para lang="ru">
    Инструмент выделение связанной области (Волшебная палочка) выделяет
    области активного слоя или изображения по признаку схожести цветов. Он
    начинает в одной выбранной точке и растекается от этой точки во все
    стороны, выделяя точки с приблизительно теми же цветами, что и у начальной
    точки. Степень схожести регулируется смещением мышки вправо или вниз (для
    увеличения выделенной области) или влево вверх (для уменьшения выделенной
    области).
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    При использовании этого инструмента очень важно правильно выбрать
    начальную точку. Если точка не выбрана правильно, то можно получить
    совершенно другие результаты, а то и противоположное от ожидаемого.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Волшебная палочка подходит для выделения объектов с резкими краями.
    Использывать её очень увлекательно, поэтому начинающие пользователи часто
    её применяют. Однако по мере приобретения опыта, вы обнаружите, что этот
    инструмент трудно настроить чтобы выбрать точно, что вы хотите. Особенно
    обескураживает то обстоятельство, что диапазон нельзя изменить после
    отпускания кнопки мышки. В таких случаях приходится начинать сначала. Более
    опытные пользователи используют более эффективные инструменты
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Контур</link> и
    <!--link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select"-->Выделение по цвету<!--/link-->.
    Всё равно, этот инструмент годится для выделения областей в контуре, или
    небольших изменений выделений. Особенно он хорош для выделения сплошного
    или почти сплошного цвета фона.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Заметьте, что по мере расширения выделенной области от центра, она не
    только захватывает соседние точки, но и может перепрыгивать через маленькие
    промежутки. Размер промежутков устанавливается на странице
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Параметры иструментов</link>
    диалога настроек: порог по умолчанию для нахождения связанных областей.
    Изменение этот параметра меняет агрессивность волшебной палочки. Этот
    параметр также влияет на инструмент простой и градиентной заливки.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    模糊选择工具，也叫魔术棒工具用作选取图层或图像中颜色相近区域，它将颜色相近的像素连接起来。点图像中的一点就开始选取了，该魔术棒从这点开始选取，并向外延伸直到它认为颜色太不同时就结束。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
     要控制魔术棒的灵敏度，可以在您定位光标后按下鼠标键，从左上方拖动光标(不要松开鼠标键)向右或正下方(都一样)，就可以逐渐从一个小选区变为一个非常大的。<emphasis>小心定位您的起始点，如果您选错了点，结果可能和您预计的相差甚远。</emphasis>换句话说，选错点可能使魔术棒选取除了您想要的所有部分。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    魔术棒工具很适合选取边缘分明的物体。它容易使用并且比较好玩，初学者经常使用它。更有经验的用户则觉得<link linkend="gimp-tool-path">路径</link>和<link linkend="gimp-tool-by-color-select">按颜色选择</link>对选取更有效，而很少使用魔术棒。即使这样，魔术棒在选取带轮廓线的区域和润色有问题选区时还是有用的，而在删除剪切-粘贴的选区的背景色时有很有效。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    模糊选择选项对话框中有个勾选框叫位样合并。在您的图像有多个图层，并且活动图层要么是半透明要么不是设置为“正常”的图层模式时，该选项就其作用了。在这种情况下，图层中本来的颜色和实际图像中的颜色是不同的。如果未勾选位样合并，当它创建一个选区时就只考虑活动图层上的颜色。如果勾选，它就将所有可见图层上混合的颜色一并考虑。
  </para>

  <tip lang="de">
    <para lang="de">
      Sie können die Schwelle, bis zu der sich die Auswahl ausbreitet,
      verändern, indem Sie den Mauszeiger nach unten oder nach rechts bewegen.
      Je weiter Sie den Mauszeiger vom Startpunkt entfernen, um so größer wird
      die Auswahl. Beim Verschieben nach oben oder nach links wird die Auswahl
      entsprechend verkleinert.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <note lang="de">
    <para lang="de">
      Wenn Sie den Zauberstab benutzen, ist es sehr wichtig, den richtigen
      Startpunkt zu wählen. Wenn Sie dies nicht sorgfältig tun, werden Sie
      sehr wahrscheinlich eine Auswahl erstellen, die nicht der entspricht,
      die Sie sich vorgestellt haben.
    </para>
  </note>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">How to Activate</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activación de la herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구 선택하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Аktywacja narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Активировать инструмент</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">启动工具</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Magic Wand Tool can be activated from an image
      menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fuzzy Select</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      <!--TODO es;it;ko;no;ru  "U" in v2.4-->
      or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>U</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Kouzelnou hůlku lze vyvolat z nabídky obrázku jako
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Nástroje</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Nástroje pro výběr</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Přibližný výběr</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      z Panelu nástrojů kliknutím na ikonu kouzelné hůlky
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      nebo z klávesnice zkratkou <keycap>z</keycap>.
      ("Z" je z německého "Zauber", tedy magie.)
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten, den Zauberstab zu aktivieren:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Menü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uswahlwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>auberstab</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          im Bildfenster,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          mit einem Mausklick auf das Symbol
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          im Werkzeugfenster sowie
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Tastenkürzel <keycap>U</keycap>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="es">
      La varita mágica se puede activar desde el menú de la imagen siguiendo
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Herramientas</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Herramientas de selección</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Selección borrosa</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      o desde la caja de herramientas haciendo clic sobre el icono
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o por medio del atajo de teclado <keycap>z</keycap>.  La "Z" es la
      inicial de "Zauber", término que en alemán significa magia.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil Sélection contiguë peut être appelé à partir de la
      barre de menus de l'image par
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>
      <guimenuitem>Outils de <accel>s</accel>élection</guimenuitem>
      <guimenuitem>Sélection <accel>c</accel>ontiguë</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à outils,
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      ou par la touche de raccourci-clavier<keycap>U</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      La bacchetta magica può essere attivata dal menu immagine con
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Strumenti</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selezione</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fuzzy</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      dalla barra degli strumenti facendo clic sull'icona
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o da tastiera usando il tasto <keycap>z</keycap>.
      ("Z" stà per "Zauber", il termine tedesco per "magica".)
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      마법 지팡이 도구는 이미지 메뉴에서
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>도구</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>선택 도구</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>연속적인 선택</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      메뉴를 선택하거나 도구상자의 도구 아이콘
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      을 클릭하거나, 키보드 단축키 <keycap>z</keycap> 키를 이용해 사용할 수
      있습니다("Z" 는 마법이라는 독일어 "Zauber" 를 의미합니다).
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan få fram dette verktøyet ved å gå inn i biletmenyen på
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Verktøy</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Markeringsverktøy</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tryllestaven</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      frå Verktøyskrinet ved å klikke på ikonet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      eller frå tastaturet med bokstaven
      <keycap>z</keycap>
      (frå tysk <quote>Zauber</quote> som betyr trolldom).
    </para>

    <para lang="pl">
      Narzędzie może być aktywowane poprzez menu obrazu
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Narzędzia</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Narzędzia zaznaczania</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      klikając ikonę
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      przy pomocy skrótu klawiszowego <keycap>U</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Инструмент активируется через пункт меню изображения
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Инструменты</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Инструменты выделения</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Выделение связанной области</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      или нажатием на пиктограмму
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      или с помощью клавиши быстрого доступа <keycap>z</keycap>.
      ("Z" означает "Zauber", волшебство по-немецки.)
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      按如下步骤启动模糊选择工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工
      具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>选择工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>模糊
      选择</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      也可以点工具图标：
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <keycap>z</keycap> 键将转到模糊选择。
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy (výchozí)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (por defecto)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tasti modificatori (predefiniti)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">동작 변경키(기본값)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Tastekombinasjonar (Standardinnstilling)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Кlawisze modyfikujące (Domyślne)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Клавиши-модификаторы (По умолчанию)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Fuzzy Select tool does not have any special key modifiers, only the
      ones that affect all selection tools in the same way. See
      <xref linkend="gimp-tool-select" /> for help with these.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Kouzelná hůlka nemá žádné zvláštní modifikační klávesy, pouze ty, které
      ovlivňují všechny nástroje pro výběr stejným způsobem. Více se o nich
      dozvíte v kapitole <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro
      výběr</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Der Zauberstab hat keine speziellen Tastenkombinationen. Die allgemeinen
      Tastenkombinationen für
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> stehen Ihnen
      aber zur Verfügung.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      La herramienta de selección borrosa no tiene ningún modificador
      especial, sólo los que afectan a todas las herramientas de selección.
      Vea la sección <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Herramientas de
      selección</link> para saber de éstos.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil Sélection Contiguë n'a pas de touches de contrôle
      particulières, seulement celles qui s'appliquent à tous les
      outils de sélection. Voyez
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Outils de sélection</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Lo strumento di selezione regioni contigue (fuzzy) non ha tasti
      modificatori specifici, oltre a quelli che influenzano tutti gli
      strumenti di selezione allo stesso modo. Per aiuto su questo
      argomento vedi
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">strumenti di selezione</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      연속적인 선택 도구에는 특별한 동작 변경 키가 없습니다. 다만 모든
      도구에 영향을 주는 동작 변경 키만 사용할 수 있습니다. 이에 대한
      자세한 내용은 <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link>
      섹션에 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dette verktøyet har ingen spesielle tastekombinasjonar utover dei
      som er omtalte som felles for alle <link
      linkend="gimp-tool-select">markeringsverktøya</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="pl">
      <quote>Zaznaczenie rozmyte</quote> nie posiada własnych
      klawiszy modyfikujących, a jedynie klawisze wspólne dla
      wszystkich narzędzi zaznaczania, opisanych na
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      У инструмента <quote>Выделение связанной области</quote> нет собственных
      клавиш-модификаторов, только общие клавиши для всех
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Инструментов выделения</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了那些所有选择工具共有的键(请看<link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>)，模糊选择工具没有其它任何特有的按键。
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 lang="en;de;fr"><!--  section added for en & fr by PP 20/12/2007-->
    <!--TODO de es it ko no pl ru zh_CN   -->
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Tool handling</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Benutzung des Zauberstabs</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Manipulation de l'outil</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      It starts selecting when you click at a spot in the image, and expands
      outwards like water flooding low-lying areas, selecting contiguous
      pixels whose colors are similar to the starting pixel. You can control
      the threshold of similarity by dragging the mouse downward or to the
      right: the farther you drag it, the larger you get the selected region.
      And you can reduce the selection by dragging upwards or to the left.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      To move the selection see
      <link linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving">Moving selections</link>
      (you can move the selection outline with the arrow keys, not with the
      mouse...).
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Der <quote>Zauberstab</quote> beginnt eine Auswahl zu erstellen, sobald
      Sie einen Bereich des Bildes anklicken. Die Auswahl vergrößert sich
      ausgehend von dem von Ihnen gewählten Punkt, als würden Sie Wasser
      ausschütten, welches über alle Bereich mit gleicher oder ähnlicher Farbe
      läuft.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Wie man die Auswahl verschiebt, wird <!-- PENDING de in <xref
      linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving"/--> im Kapitel
      <quote>Auswahl verschieben</quote>
      beschrieben (Sie können den Umriss der Auswahl auch mit den Pfeiltasten
      anstelle der Maus bewegen...).
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Cet outil commence à sélectionner dès que vous cliquez en un point de
      l'image. La sélection s'étend de façon centrifuge à partir de ce
      point, sélectionnant les pixels dont la Teinte est similaire à
      celle du pixel de départ. Vous pouvez contrôler le seuil de
      similarité par un  cliquer-glisser du pointeur de la souris vers
      le bas ou la droite : plus grand est le déplacement, et plus grande
      est l'aire sélectionnée. De même, vous pourrez réduire la sélection
      par un cliquer-glisser vers le haut ou vers la gauche.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Pour déplacer la sélection, voyez
      <link linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving">Déplacer les
        sélections</link>
      (Vous pouvez déplacer le contour de la sélection avec les touches
      fléchées, pas avec la souris...).
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="tool-fuzzy-select-options">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">선택 사항</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Verktøyinnstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Opcje narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Tool Options for the Magic Wand tool</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Volby nástrojů pro magickou hůlku</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften des Zauberstabes</phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Opciones de herramienta para la varita mágica
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Les options de l'outil de sélection contiguë
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Le opzioni strumento per la bacchetta magica
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">마법 지팡이 도구의 도구 선택사항</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Innstillingane for tryllestaven</phrase>
  <phrase lang="pl">
          Opcje <quote>Zaznaczenia rozmytego</quote></phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры инструмента
          <quote>Волшебная Палочка</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">魔术棒工具的工具选项</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;es;pl;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-wand.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-wand.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-wand.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/tool-options-wand.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="ko">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ko/tool-options-wand.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-options-wand.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-wand.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <!-- A note about common options with link to description: -->
    <xi:include href="about-common-select-options.xml" />

    <!--TODO cs es it ko no pl ru zh_CN: consider switching to the
        above include file (check/edit it before!)-->
    <note lang="cs;es;it;ko;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
      <!--para lang="en;de">
        Moved to "src/toolbox/about-common-select-options.xml"
      </para-->
      <para lang="cs">
        Obecné volby společné pro všechny nástroje tohoto typu naleznete v
        kapitole <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro výběr</link>.
        Zde jsou popsány pouze volby specifické pro kouzelnou hůlku.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Vea la sección <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Herramientas de
        selección</link> para las opciones que tienen en común este tipo de
        herramientas.  Sólo las opciones específicas a la varita mágica se
        explican aquí.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Per aiuto sulle opzioni comuni a tutti questi strumenti vedi
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">strumenti di selezione</link>.
        Qui vengono spiegate soltanto le opzioni specifiche
        dello strumento bacchetta magica.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        모든 선택 도구에 동일하게 적용되는 동작 변경 키에 대해서는
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link>를 보세요.
        여기서는 마법 지팡이 도구에만 적용되는 특수한 키에 대해 설명할
        것입니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Sjå <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">felles eigenskapar</link> for
        eit oversyn over tastekombinasjonar som er felles for fleire av
        markeringsverktøya. Bare kombinasjonar som er spesifikke for
        tryllestaven blir omtalte i dette avsnittet.
      </para>
      <para lang="pl">
        Оpcje wspólne dla wszystkich narzędzi zaznaczania zostały opisane
  na <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
        Poniżej opisano jedynie opcje, charakterystyczne dla
        <quote>Zaznaczenia rozmytego</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Обратитесь к
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Инструментам выделения</link> за
        справкой об общих параметрах. Здесь описаны параметры только для
        инструмента <quote>Волшебная палочка</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        这些工具共用的选项请看<link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>。下面只解释魔术棒工具所特有的选项。
      </para>
    </note>

    <para lang="de">
      Die aktuellen Einstellungen für den Zauberstab lassen sich durch einen
      Doppelklick auf das Symbol
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      anzeigen.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Les options disponibles pour l'outil Sélection Contiguë
      sont obtenues par un double clic gauche sur l'icône de l'outil.
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du får fram verktøyinnstillingane ved å klikka, eventuelt
      dobbeltklikka på verktøyikonet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-fuzzy-select-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      i verktøyskrinet.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Finding Similar Colors</term>
        <term lang="cs">Hledání podobných barev</term>
        <term lang="de">Ähnliche Farben finden</term>
        <term lang="es">Buscando colores similares</term>
        <term lang="fr">Recherche de couleurs similaires</term>
        <term lang="it">Trova colori simili</term>
        <term lang="ko">비슷한 색상 찾기</term>
        <term lang="no">Finn liknande fargar</term>
        <term lang="pl">Wyszukiwanie podobnych kolorów</term>
        <term lang="ru">Поиск похожих цветов</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">寻找相近的颜色</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            These options affect the way the Magic Wand expands the selection
            out from the initial point.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Tyto volby ovlivňují způsob, kterým kouzelná hůlka rozšiřuje výběr
            z počátečního bodu dál.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Diese Eigenschaften beeinflussen die Art und Weise, wie der
            Zauberstab ausgehend vom Startpunkt die Auswahl erzeugt.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Estas opciones afectan a la manera en que la varita mágica expande
            la selección desde el punto inicial.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Ces options (les quatre dernières) affectent la façon dont la
            Baguette Magique étend la sélection à partir du point initial.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Queste opzioni influenzano il modo in cui la bacchetta magica
            espande la selezione a partire dal punto iniziale.
          </para>
          <para lang="ko">
            이 옵션은 시작점으로부터 선택을 확장하는 방법에 대한 것입니다.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Desse innstillingane påverkar måten tryllestaven utvidar seg på ut
            frå det valde startpunktet.
          </para>
          <para lang="pl">
            Opcja ta określa, w jaki sposób zaznaczenie będzie się powiększać
            od punktu kliknięcia.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Эти параметры влияют на то, как волшебная палочка будет расширять
            выделение от искомой точки.
          </para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Select Transparent Areas</term>
              <term lang="cs">Zvolit průhledné oblasti</term>
              <term lang="de">Transparente Bereiche auswählen</term>
              <term lang="es">Seleccionar las áreas transparentes</term>
              <term lang="fr">Sélectionne des régions transparentes</term>
              <term lang="it">Seleziona aree trasparenti</term>
              <term lang="ko">투명한 영역 선택</term>
              <term lang="no">Vel gjennomsiktige område</term>
              <term lang="pl">Z obszarami przezroczystymi</term>
              <term lang="ru">Выделять прозрачные области</term>
              <term lang="zh_CN">选择透明区域</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This option gives the Magic Wand the ability to select areas
                  that are completely transparent. If this option is not
                  checked, transparent areas will never be included in the
                  selection.
                </para>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Tato volba umožňuje hůlce vybírat i zcela průhledné oblasti.
                  Pokud není zaškrtnuta, nebudou průhledné oblasti ve výběru
                  nikdy zahrnuty.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Wenn Sie diese Eigenschaft aktivieren, lassen sich mit dem
                  Zauberstab auch transparente Bereiche auswählen. Andernfalls
                  lassen sich transparente Bereiche mit dem Zauberstab nicht
                  auswählen.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Esta opción habilita a la varita mágica para que seleccione
                  áreas completamente transparentes. Si esta opción no está
                  activada, las áreas transparentes no van a ser incluidas en
                  la selección.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Cette option permet à l'outil Sélection Contiguë de
                  sélectionner les aires possédant une transparence. Sans
                  cette option, les aires possédant une transparence ne seront
                  pas sélectionnées.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Quest'opzione permette alla bacchetta magica di selezionare
                  aree che sono completamente trasparenti. Quando
                  quest'opzione non è attiva le aree trasparenti non vengono
                  mai incluse nella selezione.
                </para>
                <para lang="ko">
                  이 옵션을 이용하면 마법 지팡이를 이용해 완벽하게 투명한
                  영역을 선택할 수 있습니다. 이 옵션이 선택되어 있지
                  않으면, 투명한 영역은 선택에서 제외됩니다.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Dersom denne er avmerka, vil tryllestaven kunne markere
                  gjennomsiktige område. Er han ikkje avkryssa, vil desse
                  områda ikkje bli inkluderte i markeringa.
                </para>
                <para lang="pl">
                  Pole pozwala na zaznaczanie obszarów przezroczystych. Jeśli
                  pole nie zostanie zaznaczone, obszary przezroczyste nie będą
                  włączone do zaznaczenia.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  Этот параметр позволяет выделять прозрачные области. Если
                  этот параметр не выделен, прозрачные области никогда не
                  будут включены в выделение.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">让模糊选择工具选取透明区域。如果未勾选改选项，选取透明区域是不被允许的。</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Sample Merged</term>
              <term lang="cs">Ukázka sloučení</term>
              <term lang="de">Vereinigung überprüfen</term>
              <term lang="es">Muestra combinada</term>
              <term lang="fr">Échantillonner sur tous les calques</term>
              <term lang="it">Campiona a video</term>
              <term lang="ko">표본 합치기</term>
              <term lang="no">Markeringsfletting</term>
              <term lang="pl">Próbkuj wszystkie warstwy</term>
              <term lang="ru">Объединять по образцу</term>
              <term lang="zh_CN">位样合并</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This option becomes relevant when you have several layers in
                  your image, and the active layer is either semi-transparent
                  or is set to another Layer Mode than Normal. If this is the
                  case, the colors present in the layer will be different from
                  the colors in the composite image. If the
                  <quote>Sample Merged</quote>
                  option is unchecked, the wand will only react to the color
                  in the active layer when it creates a selection. If it is
                  checked it will react to the composite color of all visible
                  layers. For further information, see the glossary entry
                  <link linkend="glossary-samplemerge">Sample Merged</link>.
                </para>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Tato volba je relevantní, když je v obrázku více vrstev a
                  aktivní vrstva je buď poloprůhledná nebo je v jiném než
                  normálním režimu. Pokud tomu tak je, barvy ve složeném
                  obrázku budou jiné než ve vrstvě. Pokud je volba "Ukázka
                  sloučení" neaktivní, hůlka bere v úvahu pouze barvy z
                  aktivní vrstvy. Pokud je naopak aktivní, pracuje hůlka s
                  barvami z celého složeného obrázku. Více informací najdete
                  ve slovníčku pod heslem Ukázka sloučení.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Diese Eigenschaft wird wichtig, wenn das Bild mehrere Ebenen
                  hat und die aktiven Ebene entweder halb durchsichtig ist
                  oder einen anderen Modus hat als <quote>Normal</quote>.
                  In einem solchen Fall unterscheiden sich die Farben in der
                  aktiven Eben von denen des Gesamtbildes. Wenn die
                  Eigenschaft <guilabel>Vereinigung überprüfen</guilabel>
                  ausgeschaltet ist, reagiert der Zauberstab ausschließlich
                  auf die Farben in der aktiven Ebene. Wenn Sie eingeschaltet
                  ist, werden in die Erstellung der Auswahl die Farben aller
                  sichtbaren Ebenen einbezogen. Weitere Informationen finden
                  Sie unter <xref linkend="glossary-samplemerge" />.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Esta opción se torna relevante cuando la imagen tiene varias
                  capas, y la capa activa es semitransparente o está en un
                  modo que no es el Normal. En estos casos, los colores que se
                  presentan difieren de los colores de la capa. Si la opción
                  de <quote>muestra combinada</quote>
                  no se activa, la varita reaccionará sólo a los colores de la
                  capa activa. Si en cambio se activa la opción, la varita
                  reaccionará a la composición de colores de todas las capas
                  visibles. Para mayor información, vea la entrada del
                  glosario <xref linkend="glossary-samplemerge" />.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Avec cette option, la couleur choisie pour chaque pixel est
                  la couleur vue effectivement dans l'image, c.-à-d. qu'elle
                  est la combinaison des couleurs de ce pixel dans les
                  différents calques composant l'image, à condition bien sûr
                  qu'ils soient suffisamment transparents. Le seuil s'applique
                  alors aux différents calques.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Quest'opzione acquista rilevanza solo quando l'immagine ha
                  più livelli ed il livello attivo è semi trasparente oppure è
                  impostato ad una modalità diversa da normale. In questi casi
                  i colori presenti nel livello attivo saranno differenti da
                  quelli dell'immagine composta. Se l'opzione "campiona a
                  video" non è attiva, la bacchetta nel creare la selezione
                  agirà solo sui colori del livello attivo. Se invece
                  l'opzione è selezionata agirà sui colori composti da tutti i
                  livelli visibili. Per maggiori informazioni vedi alla voce
                  di glossario
                  <!--  FIXME: it link linkend="glossary-samplemerge" -->
                  campiona a video<!--/link-->.
                </para>
                <para lang="ko">
                  이 옵션은 여거 개의 레이어를 가지고 있고, 활성 레이어에
                  반투명한 부분이 있거나 레이어 모드가 "보통"이 아닌 다른
                  모드로 되어 있을 때 유용합니다. 이런 경우에는 현재
                  레이어의 색상이 겹쳐진 전체 이미지의 색상과 다를 수
                  있습니다. <quote>표본 합치기</quote> 옵션을 선택해제하면,
                  마법 지팡이는 현재 활동화된 레이어의 색상에 대해서만
                  동작을 하고, <quote>표본 합치기</quote> 옵션이 선택되어
                  있으면, 보이는 모든 레이어를 통해 합쳐진 색상에 대해
                  동작하게 됩니다. 표본 합치기에 대한 자세한 내용은
                  용어집의
                  <link linkend="glossary-samplemerge">표본 합치기</link>
                  를 참조하세요.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Dette valet kan vere relevant når du har mange lag i
                  biletet, og det aktive laget anten er litt gjennomsiktig
                  eller er sett til ein annan modus enn normal. Dersom dette
                  er tilfelle, vil fargane i laget vere annleis enn fargane i
                  det synlege biletet. Tryllestaven vil, dersom du har kryssa
                  av for dette valet, reagere på fargane slik dei ser ut for
                  oss. Dersom valet er umarkert, vil tryllestaven reagere bare
                  på fargane i det aktive laget. Sjå nærare i ordboka under
                  <xref linkend="glossary-samplemerge-no" />.
                 </para>
                 <para lang="pl">
                  Opcja jest przydatna, gdy obraz ma kilka warstw, а warstwa
                  аktywna jest półprzezroczysta lub w trybie innym niż Normalny.
                  W tym wypadku kolory warstwy będą się odróżniać od kolorów
                  całego obrazu. Jeśli pole
                  <quote>Próbkuj wszystkie warstwy</quote>
                  nie jest zaznaczone, narzędzie tworząc zaznaczenie będzie
                  zwracać uwagę tylko na kolor warstwy aktywnej. Jeśli zaś pole
                  będzie zaznaczone, narzędzie będzie brało pod uwagę kolory
                  wszystkich widocznych warstw. Więcej informacji można
                  znaleźć na <!--xref linkend="glossary-samplemerge" /-->.
                 </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  Этот параметр значит, когда в изображении несколько слоёв, а
                  активный слой либо полупрозрачный, либо в нежиме,
                  отличающегося от нормального. В этом случае цвета в слое
                  будут отличаться от цветов всего изображения. Если параметр
                  <quote>Объединять по образцу</quote>
                  не выделен, палочка при воздании выделения будет реагировать
                  только на цвет активного слоя. Если параметр выбран, она
                  будет реагировать на цвета всех видимых слоёв. За
                  дополнительной информацией обратитесь в глоссарий по
                  <xref linkend="glossary-samplemerge" />.
                 </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  将改变模糊选择工具决定选区起始点和结束点的方式。如果勾选
                  <guilabel>位样合并</guilabel>
                  ,在所有可见图层的颜色将被作为选取的基准，而不是仅仅是当前图层。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Threshold</term>
              <term lang="cs">Práh</term>
              <term lang="de">Schwelle</term>
              <term lang="es">Umbral</term>
              <term lang="fr">Seuil</term>
              <term lang="it">Soglia</term>
              <term lang="ko">임계값</term>
              <term lang="no">Terskel</term>
              <term lang="pl">Próg</term>
              <term lang="ru">Порог</term>
              <term lang="zh_CN">阈值</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This slider determines the range of colors that will be
                  selected at the moment you click the pointer on the initial
                  point, before dragging it: the higher the threshold, the
                  larger the resulting selection. After the first
                  button-press, dragging the pointer downward or to the right
                  will increase the size of the selection; dragging upward or
                  to the left will decrease it. Thus, you have the same set of
                  possibilities regardless of the Threshold setting: what
                  differs is the amount of dragging you have to do to get the
                  result you want.
                </para>
                <para lang="cs">
                  Tento posuvník určuje rozsah barev, které budou vybrány, v
                  momentě, kdy kliknete na počáteční bod a ještě netáhnete
                  myší. Čím vyšší práh, tím větší výběr. Po prvním stisknutí
                  tlačítka myši se tažením dolů nebo doprava dá velikost
                  výběru zvyšovat. Tažením doleva nebo nahoru pak zmenšovat.
                  Proto, bez ohledu na nastavení prahu, máte vždy stejné
                  možnosti – liší se pouze to, jak moc musíte táhnout myší a
                  na kterou stranu, abyste dosáhli požadovaného výsledku.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dem Schieberegler für die Eigenschaft
                  <guilabel>Schwelle</guilabel>
                  lässt sich die Empfindlichkeit des Zauberstabes steuern. Die
                  einstellbaren Werte reichen von 0 (minimale Farbdifferenz)
                  bis 255 (maximale Farbdifferenz). Es ist auch möglich, die
                  Eigenschaft bei der Erstellung einer neuen Auswahl zu
                  verändern. Halten Sie hierzu die
                  <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton>
                  nach dem Klick auf den Startpunkt gedrückt und verschieben
                  Sie den Mauszeiger nach oben oder unten. Der Schwellwert
                  wird sofort angepasst, so dass Sie das Ergebnis prüfen
                  können. Das Einstellen des Schwellwertes mit der Maus
                  erfordert allerdings etwas Übung.
                </para>
                <para lang="es">
                  Este deslizador determina el rango de colores que será
                  seleccionado cuando haga clic sobre el punto inicial, antes
                  de que empieze a arrastrar el ratón. Mientras mayor defina
                  el umbral, mayor será el área resultante. Como se dijo
                  arriba, puede variar el área si al hacer clic mantiene
                  presionado el botón y arrastra el ratón, por lo tanto tiene
                  las mismas posibilidades independientemente del umbral, que
                  define sólo el valor inicial.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Ce curseur fixe l'écart de Teinte à prendre en compte pour
                  le choix des pixels de la sélection. Autrement dit, les
                  pixels dont la différence de Teinte avec le pixel d'origine
                  excède le seuil seront refusés. Plus cet écart augmente, et
                  plus de pixels sont sélectionnés. Si vous maintenez enfoncé
                  le <mousebutton>bouton de la souris</mousebutton>
                  pendant la sélection, vous pourrez ajuster le
                  <guilabel>Seuil</guilabel>
                  en déplaçant la souris vers le haut ou le bas. La valeur par
                  défaut de ce seuil est fixée dans le menu Préférences, à la
                  section Options des outils, à la rubrique
                  <quote>Recherche de régions contiguës</quote>.
                </para>
                <para lang="it">
                  Questa barra di scorrimento determina l'arco di colori che
                  saranno selezionati al momento del clic del mouse sul punto
                  iniziale, prima di iniziare a trascinarlo: maggiore è la
                  soglia, più larga sarà la selezione risultante. Dopo la
                  pressione del pulsante, il trascinamento del puntatore in
                  basso o verso destra farà aumentare l'ampiezza della
                  selezione; il trascinamento in alto o verso sinistra la
                  faranno diminuire. Perciò le possibilità sono le stesse
                  indipendentemente dall'impostazione della soglia: ciò che
                  cambia è la quantità di trascinamento da effettuare per
                  ottenere il risultato desiderato.
                </para>
                <para lang="ko">
                  이 조절바는 처음 지점을 기준으로 선택할 색상의 범위를
                  결정하는 바입니다. 높은 값일수록 넓은 범위를 선택하게
                  되며, 마우스를 클릭한 뒤 드래그를 통해 값을 변경할 수
                  있습니다. 아래쪽이나 오른쪽으로 드래그하면 값이 증가하고
                  위쪽이나 왼쪽으로 드래그하면 값이 감소합니다. 따라서
                  원래의 임계값에 관계없이 드래그로 그때그때 원하는 만큼의
                  값을 설정해 사용할 수 있습니다.
                </para>
                <para lang="no">
                  Denne glidebrytaren bestemmer kor like fargane må vere
                  fargen i du startar med. Dess større verdi, dess større
                  område blir markert. Dersom du etter det første
                  knappetrykket drar peikaren nedover eller til høgre, vil
                  området bli større. Drar du peikaren oppover eller til
                  venstre, vil området bli redusert. Du har såleis eigentleg
                  ikkje bruk for denne brytaren til anna enn eventuelt å
                  minske avstanden du må flytta peikaren.
                </para>
                <para lang="pl">
                  Suwak określa skalę kolorów w momencie pierwszego kliknięcia,
                  jeszcze przed przeciągnięciem. Im wyższa wartość progu, tym
                  większe zaznaczenie. Po pierwszym kliknięciu, przeciągnięcie
                  kursora w prawo lub w dół zwiększy zaznaczenie, zaś jego
                  przeciągnięcie w górę lub w lewo - zmniejszy je. Możliwości
                  narzędzia nie są zależne od Progu. Ma on jedynie wpływ na
                  ilość ruchów, które należy wykonać, aby osiągnąć pożądany
                  efekt.
                </para>
                <para lang="ru">
                  Этот ползунок определяет диапазон цветов в момент нажатия на
                  начальную точку, до передвижения. Чем выше порог, тем больше
                  конечное выделение. После первого нажатия, перемещение вниз
                  и вправо увеличит выделение, перемещение вверх и влево
                  уменьшит его. Возможности выделения не зависят от порога, а
                  зависит лишь количество передвижения, чтобы достичь нужного
                  результата.
                </para>
                <para lang="zh_CN">
                  该滑条控制哪些颜色范围值认为是“临近”定位点的颜色。一个高值将选择一个更大的区域。如果在您进行选择操作时按住
                  <mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>，您可以通过上下移动鼠标来调整
                  <guilabel>阈值</guilabel>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <!-- TODO: cs es it no ru zh_CN content missing -->
            <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;ko">
              <term lang="en">Selection by</term>
              <term lang="de">Auswählen nach</term>
              <term lang="fr">Sélectionner par</term>
              <term lang="ko">선택 기준</term>
              <term lang="pl">Zaznaczenie</term>

              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  With this option you can choose which component of the image
                  GIMP shall use to calculate the similarity.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Mit dieser Eigenschaft legen Sie fest, welche Komponente des
                  Bildes von GIMP zur Berechnung der Ähnlichkeit verwendet
                  wird.
                </para>
                <para lang="fr">
                  Avec cette option vous pouvez choisir de quelle façon vous
                  voulez évaluer la similarité : soit sur la couleur
                  globalement, soit sur chacune des composantes RVB ou TSV,
                  prises individuellement.
                </para>
                <para lang="ko">
                  이 옵션을 통해 이미지의 일부 성분만 선택할 수 있습니다.
                </para>
                <para lang="pl">
                  Opcja określa, który element obrazu program GIMP będzie
                  używany do obliczenia podobieństwa.
                </para>

                <para lang="en">
                  The components you can choose from are
                  <guimenuitem>Red</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Green</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Blue</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Hue</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Saturation</guimenuitem> and
                  <guimenuitem>Value</guimenuitem>.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die Komponenten, welche hier zur Auswahl stehen, umfassen
                  <guimenuitem>Rot</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Grün</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Blau</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Farbton</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Sättigung</guimenuitem> und
                  <guimenuitem>Wert</guimenuitem>.
                </para>
                <para lang="ko">
                  선택 가능한 성분은
                  <guimenuitem>빨강</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>녹색</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>파랑</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>색상</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>채도</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>명도</guimenuitem> 입니다.
                </para>
                <para lang="pl">
                  Dostępne są następujące możliwości wyboru:
                  <guimenuitem>Czerwony</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Zielony</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Niebieski</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Odcień</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Nasycenie</guimenuitem> i
                  <guimenuitem>Wartość</guimenuitem>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
