<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<!-- 050517 de reviewed by axel.wernicke -->
<sect2 id='gimp-tool-ellipse-select' lang="de;en;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Ellipse Selection Tool</title>
  <title lang="de">Elliptische Auswahl</title>
  <title lang="fr">Outil de Sélection Elliptique</title>  <!--050506-->
  <title lang="it">Strumento di selezione ellittica</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">椭圆选择工具</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à outils</primary>
    <primary lang="it">Barra degli strumenti</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具箱</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Selection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="de">Auswahl</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Sélection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="it">Selezione</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">选择</secondary>
    <tertiary lang='en'>Ellipse</tertiary>
    <tertiary lang='de'>Elliptisch</tertiary>
    <tertiary lang='fr'>Elliptique</tertiary>
    <tertiary lang='it'>Ellittica</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-ellipsel.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-ellipsel.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-ellipsel.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='it'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-ellipsel.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-ellipsel.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Ellipse Select icon in the Toolbox
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Die Elliptische Auswahl im Werkzeugfenster.
        </para>
				<para lang='fr'>
				  L'icône Sélection Elliptique dans la Boîte à outils.
				</para>
        <para lang='it'>
          L'icona della selezione ellittica nella barra degli strumenti
        </para>
        <para lang='zh_CN'>
          工具箱中的椭圆选择图标
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  
  <para lang="en">
    The Ellipse Selection tool is designed to select circular and
    elliptical regions from an image, with high-quality anti-aliasing
    if you want it. For information on selections and how
    they are used in GIMP see <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-selection'>Selections</link>; for information on
    features common to all selection tools see <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="en"> 
    This tool is also used for rendering a circle or ellipse on an
    image.  To render a filled ellipse, create an elliptical
    selection, and then fill it using the <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-bucket-fill'>Bucket Fill tool</link>.  To
    create an elliptical outline, the simplest and most flexible
    approach is to create an elliptical selection and then <link
    linkend='gimp-concepts-stroke'>stroke</link> it.  However, the quality of
    anti-aliasing with this approach is rather crude.  A higher
    quality outline can be obtained by creating two elliptical
    selections with different sizes, subtracting the inner one from
    the outer one; however this is not always easy to get right.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug Elliptische Auswahl ermöglicht es Ihnen eine Auswahl aus
		kreisförmigen und elliptischen Bereichen des Bildes oder der aktuellen
		Ebene zu erstellen. Diese Auswahl kann dann benutzt werden, um
		Bildmanipulationen nur auf den ausgewählten Bereich anzuwenden.
  </para>
	<para lang="de">
		Dieses Werkzeug wird auch für das Zeichnen von kreisrunden oder
		elliptischen Flächen verwendet. Hierzu erstellen Sie zunächst eine 
		entsprechende Auswahl und füllen diese dann mit Hilfe des
		<link linkend='gimp-tool-bucket-fill'>Fülleimer</link> Werkzeuges. Um
		einen runden oder elliptischen Rahmen zu erzeugen, ist die einfachste und
		flexibelste Vorgehensweise die Erstellung einer passenden Auswahl, welche
		dann
		umrandet
		<!-- de PENDING: <link linkend='gimp-concepts-stroke'>umrandet</link> -->
		wird. Allerdings ist die Qualität bei diesem Ansatz eher bescheiden. Eine
		qualitativ hochwertigerer Rahmen kann erzeugt werden, indem Sie zwei
		Auswahlen verschiedener Größe erstellen und dann die innere Auswahl von
		der äußeren Subtrahieren. Allerdings ist es nicht immer leicht die
		passenden Auswahlen zu erstellen.
	</para>

  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil de Sélection Elliptique crée une sélection 
    elliptique ou circulaire par déplacement du curseur de la souris 
    sur une image ou un calque. La sélection devient active dès 
    qu'on relâche le bouton de souris. On peut la supprimer en 
    cliquant en dehors de la sélection. 
  </para>
	
  <para lang='fr'>
    Cet outil peut aussi être utilisé pour créer on objet de forme 
    elliptique dans l'image, en le remplissant à l'aide de l'outil Pôt 
    de peinture (Remplissage). Si vous ne voulez conserver que le 
    contour elliptique, utilisez l'option Édition/Tracer la sélection 
    du menu d'image, ou l'option Sélection/Bordure. Vous pouvez aussi 
    dessiner deux sélections concentriques et soustraire la sélection 
    intérieure, ne laissant ainsi qu'un anneau.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="it">
    Lo strumento di selezione ellittica è studiato per selezionare zone
    circolari ed ellittiche all'interno di un'immagine, volendo con un 
    anti-aliasing di elevata qualità. Per informazioni sulle selezioni 
    e su come vengono usate in GIMP vedi <!--link 
    linkend='gimp-concepts-selection' FIXME -->Selezioni<!-- /link-->; 
    per informazioni sulle caratteristiche comuni a tutti questi strumenti
    vedi <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Strumenti di selezione</link>.
  </para>

  <para lang="it"> 
    Questo strumento viene usato anche per disegnare dei cerchi o delle 
    ellissi in un'immagine. Per disegnare un'ellisse piena, creare una 
    selezione ellittica e poi riempirla usando lo strumento <!--link 
    linkend='gimp-tool-bucket-fill' FIXME -->riempimento colore<!--/link-->. 
    Per creare il contorno di un'ellissi, 
    l'approccio più semplice e flessibile è quello di creare una selezione 
    ellittica e poi applicare su di essa la funzione <!-- link 
    linkend='gimp-concepts-stroke' FIXME -->delinea<!--/link-->.  
    Con questo approccio però la qualità dell'anti-aliasing è piuttosto 
    grezza. Una migliore qualità del contorno può essere ottenuta creando 
    due selezioni ellittiche di diverse dimensioni, sottraendo quella interna 
    da quella esterna; ciò però non è sempre facile da ottenere con precisione.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    椭圆选择区域工具被用作在图像或图层上选取圆形或椭圆形区域，这样您就可以在这些特别区域上进行操作。
  </para>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">How to Activate</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</title>
    <title lang="it">Attivazione</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Ellipse Selection Tool can be activated from an image
      menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ellipse Select</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; 
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon 
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>e</keycap>.
    </para>

		<para lang="de">
			Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten das Werkzeug Elliptische
			Auswahl zu aktivieren:
		</para>
    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
				<para>
					Über das Menü
					<menuchoice>
						<guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
			      <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uswahlwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
				    <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>lliptische Auswahl</guimenuitem>
					</menuchoice>
					im Bildfenster,
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Mit einen Mausklick auf das Symbol
		      <guiicon>
						<inlinemediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png"></imagedata>
							</imageobject>
						</inlinemediaobject>
					</guiicon>
					im Werkzeugfenster, sowie
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Über das Tastenkürzel <keycap>E</keycap>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para lang='fr'>
      L'outil Sélection Elliptique peut être appelé à partir de la 
      barre de menus de l'image par 
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Outils de <accel>s</accel>élection</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Sélection <accel>E</accel>lliptique</guimenuitem>. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône 
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à outils.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La touche <keycap>e</keycap> transformera l'outil actif en 
      Sélection Elliptique.
    </para>

    <para lang='it'>
      Lo strumento di selezione ellittica può essere attivato dal menu immagine
      come segue
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Strumenti</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selezione</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ellittica</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; 
      dalla barra degli strumenti cliccando sull'icona 
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o da tastiera usando il tasto <keycap>e</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      按如下步骤启动椭圆选择工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>选择工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>椭圆选择</guimenuitem> 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      也可以点工具图标：
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <keycap>e</keycap> 键将转到椭圆选择。
    </para>
  </simplesect> 

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Standardeinstellungen)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de contrôle</title>
    <title lang="it">Tasti modificatori</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键</title>

    <note lang='en'>
      <para>
        See <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link> for
        help with modifier keys that affect all these tools in the same
        way.  Only effects that are specific to the Ellipse Select
        tool are explained here.
      </para>
    </note>

    <note lang='it'>
      <para>
        Per avere aiuto sui tasti modificatori che influenzano allo stesso 
        modo tutti questi strumenti vedi <link 
        linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Strumenti di selezione</link>. Qui 
        vengono spiegati solo gli effetti specifici della selezione 
        ellittica.
      </para>
    </note>

    <note lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        关于控制键用相同方式影响这些工具的帮助请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>选择工具</link>，下面只解释对椭圆选择工具特有的影响。
      </para>
    </note>

    <itemizedlist lang='en'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:  Pressing the Ctrl key after starting
          your selection, and holding it down until you are finished,
          causes your starting point to be used as the center of the
          selected ellipse, instead of a corner of the rectangle that 
          may contain it.  Note that if you press the Ctrl key 
          <emphasis>before</emphasis> starting to make the selection, 
          the resulting selection will be subtracted from the existing 
          selection.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>:  Pressing the Shift key after starting
          your selection, and holding it down until you are finished,
          constrains the selection to be a circle.  Note that if you
          press the Shift key <emphasis>before</emphasis> starting to
          make the selection, the resulting selection will be
          added to the existing selection.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          </keycombo>:  Pressing both keys combines the two effects,
            giving you a circular selection centered on your starting
            point. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang='de'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Strg</keycap>: Das Drücken der Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap>
					<emphasis>nach</emphasis> dem Beginn der Erstellung einer Auszahl
					bewirkt, dass der Startpixel als Mittelpunkt der neuen Auswahl
					benutzt wird und nicht als Ecke eines gedachten, die Auswahl
					umgebenden, Rechtecks. Bitte beachten Sie, dass wenn Sie
					die Taste <keycap>Strg</keycap> drücken <emphasis>bevor</emphasis>
					Sie beginnen die Auswahl zu erstellen, der Auswahlmodus auf
					Subtrahieren gestellt wird.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>:  Das Drücken der Taste
					<keycap>Shift</keycap> <emphasis>nach</emphasis> dem Beginn der
					Erstellung einer Auszahl bewirkt, dass die neue Auswahl kreisrund
					sein wird. Bitte beachten Sie, dass wenn Sie die Taste
					<keycap>Shift</keycap> <emphasis>vor</emphasis> dem Beginn der
					Erstellung der neuen Auswahl drücken, der Auswahlmodus auf
					Hinzufügen gestellt wird.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycombo><keycap>Strg</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>:
					Das Drücken von
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Strg</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
					führt zu einer kreisrunden Auswahl, wobei der Startpixel als
					Mittelpunkt der neuen Auswahl verwendet wird.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:  
            En maintenant la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> appuyée, 
            pendant la création de la sélection elliptique, 
            vous pouvez réaliser deux choses:
            Premièrement, la sélection sera créée 
            en utilisant le pixel sur lequel vous avez cliqué comme 
            centre. Habituellement, la sélection est créée en 
            utilisant ce pixel comme coin.
            Ensuite,  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> placera la sélection en 
            mode Soustraction (voir plus haut).
            Si vous ne voulez utiliser qu'une seule de ces deux 
            actions, relâchez la touche <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> avant 
            de relâcher le bouton gauche de la souris. En agissant 
            ainsi, la sélection restera en mode Soustraction, mais 
            sans la contrainte du point central.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Maj</keycap>:  
            En maintenant la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> enfoncée, 
            vous pourrez réaliser deux choses:
            Premèrement, vous obligerez la hauteur et la largeur 
            à rester égales (un cercle).
            Ensuite,le mode de sélection passera en mode Addition 
            (voir plus haut).
            Si vous ne voulez utiliser qu'une seule de ces deux 
            actions, relâchez la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> avant de 
            relâcher le bouton gauche de la souris. En agissant ainsi, 
            la sélection restera en mode addition, mais sans la 
            contrainte largeur / hauteur. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+<keycap>Maj</keycap>:  La combinaison de 
            touches
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Maj</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            permet de réaliser plusieurs choses:
            D'abord, le mode de sélection sera basculé sur 
            Intersection.
            Ensuite, la sélection disposera des contraintes "point 
            central" et "largeur/hauteur" exposées ci-dessus.
            C'est un bon exercice que de réaliser des sélections 
            elliptiques en appuyant sur les touches 
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>
            enfoncées et en les relâchant ensemble ou séparément 
            avant de relâcher le bouton gauche de la souris.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist lang='it'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:  la pressione del tasto Ctrl dopo aver 
          iniziato la selezione, tenendolo premuto fino a che essa non 
          viene completata, fa si che il punto iniziale della selezione 
          sia il centro dell'ellisse selezionata, anzichè un angolo del 
          rettangolo che potrebbe contenerla.
          Notare che se il tasto Ctrl viene premuto 
          <emphasis>prima</emphasis> di cominciare a selezionare, la 
          selezione effettuata verrà sottratta dalla selezione esistente.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>: la pressione del tasto Maiusc dopo aver
          iniziato la selezione, tenendolo premuto fino al che essa non
          viene completata, obbliga la selezione ad essere circolare.
          Notare che se si preme il tasto Maiusc <emphasis>prima</emphasis>
          di cominciare a selezionare, la selezione effettuata verrà
          aggiunta alla selezione esistente.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
          <keycap>Maiusc</keycap>
          </keycombo>: Premendo entrambi i tasti si combinano i due effetti, 
          realizzando una selezione circolare centrata rispetto al punto di partenza.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>	

    <itemizedlist lang="zh_CN">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>: 
            按住 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 同时创建一个椭圆选区会同时做两件事。第一，创建的选区将以您选取的起点作为圆心。一般情况下， 会以您选取的起点作为一角。第二，<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 会使选取呈减去模式。如果只想完成其中一个动作，可以在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 键，这样选取只变为减去模式，而不会以选取的起点作为圆心。
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>: 
            按住 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 的同时创建一个选区将做两件不同的事。第一，它保持选区的长宽或长短轴相同。第二，该组合键使选取呈合并模式。如果只想完成其中一个动作，可以在松开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开 <keycap>Shift</keycap> 键，这样选取只变为合并模式，而不会约束其长宽或长短轴相同。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          使用
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
          </keycombo>
            可以干一系列事。各个键单独拿出来都可以干两件事。首先，选择模式将变为相交。其次，选区将以其起始点作为圆心(上面讨论过)且长宽或长短轴相同(上面也讨论过)。读者可以在使用椭圆选择同时按住<keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            </keycombo>时尝试在放开<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>前松开一个键或全部键。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Eigenschaften</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="it">Opzioni</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-ellipsel.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-ellipsel.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-ellipsel.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/it/tool-options-ellipsel.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-ellipsel.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <caption lang="en">
          <para>
            Tool Options for the Ellipse Select tool
          </para>
        </caption>

        <caption lang="de">
          <para>
            Eigenschaften des Werkzeuges Elliptische Auswahl
          </para>
        </caption>

        <caption lang="fr">
          <para>
            Les options de l'outil de sélection elliptique
          </para>
        </caption>

        <caption lang="it">
          <para>
            Le opzioni strumento per la selezione ellittica
          </para>
        </caption>
		
        <caption lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            椭圆选择工具的工具选项
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <note>
      <para lang='en'>
        See <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link> for
        help with options that are common to all these tools.  Only
        options that are specific to the Ellipse Select 
        tool are described here.
      </para>

      <para>
        In diesem Abschnitt werden nur die speziellen Eigenschaften des
				Werkzeuges beschrieben. Schauen sie bitte unter
				<link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> nach, falls
				Sie Hilfe zu den Allgemeinen Einstellungen der Auswahlwerkzeuge
				benötigen.
      </para>

			<para lang='fr'> 
				Voyez <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Outils de sélection</link> 
				pour avoir de l'aide sur les options communes à tous ces 
				outils. Seules les options spécifiques à l'outil de sélection 
				elliptique sont décrits ici.  
      </para>
      <para lang='it'>
        Per aiuto sulle opzioni comuni a tutti questi strumenti vedi 
        <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Strumenti di selezione</link>.  
        Qui vengono spiegate soltanto le opzioni specifiche 
        dello strumento di selezione ellittica.
      </para> 
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        这些工具共有的选项请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>选择工具</link>。下面只解释椭圆选择工具所特有的选项。
      </para>
   </note>

    <para lang="de">
      Die aktuellen Einstellungen für die Elliptische Auswahl
      lassen sich durch einen Doppelklick auf das Symbol 
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      anzeigen.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      On accède aux options de l'outil Sélection Elliptique par un 
      double clic sur l'icône de cet outil.
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/ellipsel.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Antialiasing</term>
      <term lang="de">Kantenglättung</term>
      <term lang="fr">Lissage</term>
      <term lang="it">Antialiasing</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">边缘平滑</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Checking this option will make the edge of the selection
          appear smoother, by partially selecting pixels that the edge
          passes through.  The idea of antialiasing is discussed in
          more detail under the glossary entry <link
          linkend='glossary-antialiasing'>Antialiasing</link>.  You
          will probably find that you get more satisfactory results by
          using it, in most cases.  The main situation where you might
          want not to use it is in cutting and pasting, where partial
          selection can sometimes create strange color fringes.
        </para>
 
       <para lang="de">
          Diese Eigenschaft lässt die Kanten der Auswahl weicher erscheinen,
					indem auf die Pixel am Rand der Auswahl ein
					<link linkend='glossary-antialiasing'>Antialiasing</link>
					Algorithmus angewendet wird. Sie werden meist feststellen, dass
					Ihnen die Ergebnisse besser gefallen, wenn das Antialiasing
					eingeschaltet ist. Der Hauptgrund der gegen die Verwendung dieser
					Eigenschaft spricht ist, dass bei Ausschneide- und
					Einfügeoperationen Farbverschiebungen an den Rändern der Auswahl
					auftreten können.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Cette option fera disparaître l'aspect en escalier des bords 
          de la sélection. Le Lissage est expliqué plus 
          en détails dans le glossaire à l'entrée 
          <link linkend='glossary-antialiasing'>Lissage</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Abilitando quest'opzione il margine della selezione
          apparirà più liscio, cio avviene selezionando parzialmente i
          pixel attraversati dal bordo. Il concetto di antialiasing viene
          trattato più dettagliatamente alla voce del glossario <link
          linkend='glossary-antialiasing'>Antialiasing</link>.  
          Probabilmente, nella maggior parte dei casi, si ottengono 
          risultati più soddisfacenti usando quest'opzione. La situazione
          tipo dove può non essere preferibile non applicarla è quella
          del copia e incolla, dove le selezioni parziali alle volte
          provocano strane frange di colore.
        </para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  该选项用相邻的像素来消除选区边缘的锯齿使选区更加平滑。有关边缘平滑的详细讨论请看<link linkend='glossary-antialiasing'>边缘平滑</link>。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Auto Shrink Selection</term>
      <term lang="de">Automatisch verkleinern</term> 
      <term lang="fr">Réduction automatique de la sélection</term>
      <term lang="it">Auto riduzione della selezione</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">自动收缩选区</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The <guilabel>Auto Shrink Selection</guilabel> checkbox will
          make your next selection automatically shrink to the nearest
          elliptical shape available on the image layer.  The
          algorithm for finding the best ellipse to shrink to is
          "intelligent", which in this case means that it sometimes
          does surprisingly sophisticated things, and sometimes does
          surprisingly strange things.  In any case, if the region
          that you want to select has a solid-colored surround,
          auto-shrinking will always pick it out correctly.  Note that
          the resulting elliptical selection does not need to have the
          same shape as the one you sweep out.
        </para>
        
				<para lang="de">
					Wenn das Kontrollkästchen
					<guilabel>Automatisch verkleinern</guilabel> aktiviert ist, wird
					die nächste erstellte Auswahl automatisch auf die räumlich nächste
					in der Bildebene befindliche elliptische Form verkleinert. Der
					Algorithmus, welcher diese Form erkennt ist
					<quote>intelligent</quote>, was in diesem Fall bedeutet, dass
					gelegentlich erstaunlich raffinierte Ergebnisse erzeugt werden.
					Manchmal jedoch auch überraschend sonderbare. Sofern jedoch die
					rechteckige Form die Sie auswählen wollen von einer gleichmäßigen
					Farbe umgeben ist, wird das Ergebnis Ihren Erwartungen
					entsprechen. Zu beachten ist noch, dass die verkleinerte Auswahl
					in iherer Form nicht in allen Fällen exakt der von Ihnen
					vorgegebenen Form entsprechen wird.
				</para>
        
        <para lang="fr">
          Avec cette option, la sélection est automatiquement rétrécie 
          à la forme elliptique la plus proche dans le calque actif. 
          L'algorithme de détection de la forme elliptique est 
          suffisamment «intelligent» pour donner d'excellents 
          résultats, surtout si la sélection se trouve sur un fond 
          bien distinct et assez uniforme. La sélection rétrécie peut 
          avoir une forme différente de l'original. 
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          L'opzione Auto riduzione della selezione fa si che la prossima 
          selezione venga automaticamente ridotta alla forma ellittica 
          più vicina presente sul livello dell'immagine. 
          L'algoritmo per trovare l'ellissi migliore a cui ridurre la 
          selezione è "intelligente", il che significa che in alcuni casi 
          fa delle cose sorprendentemente sofisticate, ed altre volte fa 
          delle cose sorprendentemente strane. In ogni caso, se la zona 
          che si desidera selezionare ha un contorno colorato uniformemente,
          l'auto riduzione lo rileverà sempre correttamente. Da notare che 
          la selezione ellittica risultante non deve avere necessariamente 
          la stessa forma di quella sostituita.
        </para>

	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  <guilabel>自动收缩选区</guilabel>勾选框将使下次选取自动收缩到图像图层上最近的可以发现的椭圆形状上。
        </para>

        <para lang="en">
          If <guilabel>Sample Merged</guilabel> is also enabled, then
          the Auto Shrink will use the pixel information from all the
          layers of the image. For further information regarding Sample
          Merge, see the glossary entry <link
          linkend='glossary-samplemerge'>Sample Merged</link>.
        </para>

				<para lang="de">
					Wenn zusätzlich die Eigenschaft
					<guilabel>Vereinigung überprüfen</guilabel> eingeschaltet ist,
					wird die Funktion nicht auf Basis der Pixel in der aktiven Ebene
					berechnet, sondern vielmehr auf der Basis der aktuellen
					Darstellung des Bildes, also aller momentan sichbaren Ebenen.
					Für weiterführende Informationen lesen Sie den Glossareintrag
					<link linkend="glossary-samplemerge">Vereinigung überprüfen</link>.
				</para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Si <guilabel>Échantillonner sur tous les calques</guilabel> 
          est également activé, l'Auto-réduction utilisera  
          l'information de tous les calques de l'image. Plus 
          d'information sur Échantillonner sur tous les calques dans 
          le glossaire, à l'entrée 
          <link linkend='glossary-samplemerge-fr'>Échantillonner 
          sur tous les calques</link>.
        </para>

        <para lang="it">
          Se anche <guilabel>Campiona a video</guilabel> è abilitato, 
          l'auto riduzione userà le informazioni sui pixel di tutti i 
          livelli dell'immagine. Per maggiori informazioni a proposito 
          della campionatura a video, vedi alla voce di glossario <!-- 
          link linkend='glossary-samplemerge' FIXME -->campionatura a 
          video<!--/link-->.
        </para>        

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          如果<guilabel>位样合并</guilabel>也被勾选，那么自动收缩将使用图像所有图层上的像素信息。要得到关于位样合并更多的信息请看<link linkend='glossary-samplemerge'>位样合并</link>。
        </para>
        
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr;it;zh_CN">
      <term lang="en">Size Constraints</term>
			<term lang="de">Größenbeschränkung</term>
      <term lang="fr">Tailles contraintes</term>
      <term lang="it">Controllo delle misure</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">大小限制</term>

      <listitem>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject lang="en">
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-rectsel-size.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="de">
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-rectsel-size.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="fr">
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-rectsel-size.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="it">
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/it/tool-options-rectsel-size.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-rectsel-size.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang="en">
                Size Constraint Option Menu for the Ellipse Select tool
              </para>
							<para lang="de">
								Auswahlmenü für die Typen von Größenbeschränkungen
							</para>
              <para lang="fr">
                Menu des tailles de sélection contraintes
              </para>
              <para lang="it">
                Il menu delle opzioni di controllo delle misure per lo 
                strumento selezione ellittica
              </para>
              <para lang="zh_CN">
                椭圆选择工具的大小限制菜单
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para lang='en'>
          This menu allows you the option of constraining the shape of
          the ellipse in three different ways.
        </para>

				<para lang="de">
					Diese Menü erlaubt es Ihnen eine Größenbeschränkung der Auswahl
					auf drei verschiedene Arten vorzunehmen.
				</para>

        <para lang='fr'>
          Ce menu vous offre la possibilité de régler la forme de 
          l'ellipse de trois façons différentes:  
        </para>

         <para lang="it">
           Questo menu permette di controllare le misure dell'ellisse in tre diversi modi.
        </para>

        <para lang="zh_CN">
          该菜单中有限制椭圆形状的三种方式。
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara lang="en">
              <title>Free Select</title>
              <para>
                This option places no constraint on the ellipse.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

						<formalpara lang="de">
							<title>Freie Auswahl</title>
							<para>
								Diese Einstellung nimmt keine Beschränkung der Auswahl
								hinsichtlich der Größe oder des Seitenverhältnisses vor.
							</para>
						</formalpara>

						<formalpara lang="fr">
							<title>Sélection à main levée</title>
							<para>
								Avec cette option, vous pouvez tracer librement votre sélection.
							</para>
						</formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="it">
              <title>Selezione libera</title>
              <para>
                Quest'opzione non impone costrizioni all'ellisse.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
              <title>自由选择</title>
              <para>
                  该选项对矩形没有限制。
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
 
          <listitem>
            <formalpara lang="en">
              <title>Fixed Size</title> 

              <para>
                This will allow you to manually specify a size for the
                selection using the Width, Height, and Unit controls.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

						<formalpara lang="de">
							<title>Feste Größe</title>
							<para>
								Durch benutzen der Einstellung <guilabel>Feste
								Größe</guilabel>, lässt sich eine fixe Grösse für die
								Auswahl einstellen. Parameter wie
								<guilabel>Breite</guilabel> und <guilabel>Höhe</guilabel>
								beeinflussen die Auswahl.
							</para>
						</formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="fr">
              <title>Taille fixe</title>

              <para>
                Si l'option <guilabel>Taille fixe</guilabel> est
                activée, vous pourrez spécifier manuellement une taille
                pour les sélections en utilisant les contrôles
                <guilabel>Largeur</guilabel>,
                <guilabel>Hauteur</guilabel>, et
                <guilabel>Unité</guilabel>.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="it">
              <title>Ampiezza fissa</title> 

              <para>
                Quest'opzione permette di specificare manualmente le 
                dimensioni della selezione usando i controlli della 
                Larghezza, dell'Altezza e dell'Unità di misura.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
              <title>固定大小</title>

	      <para>
		选择<guilabel>固定大小</guilabel>让您手工输入选区的<guilabel>宽度</guilabel>，<guilabel>高度</guilabel>和<guilabel>单位</guilabel>。
	      </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara lang="en">
              <title>Fixed Aspect Ratio</title> 

              <para>
                This option allows you to resize the selection while
                keeping the aspect ratio fixed according to the two numbers
                entered in the Width and Height controls.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

						<formalpara lang="de">
							<title>Festes Seitenverhältnis</title>
							<para>
								Die Einstellung
								<guilabel>Festes Seitenverhältniss</guilabel> sorgt dafür,
								dass bei der Erstellung einer neuen Auswahl, das Verhältnis
								von Höhe und Breite konstant bleibt.
							</para>
						</formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="fr">
              <title>Rapport L/H fixe</title>
              <para>
                Avec l'option <guilabel>Rapport L/H Fixe</guilabel>,
                les sélections auront une taille variable, mais un 
                rapport largeur / hauteur fixe.  L'aire sélectionnée 
                peut aussi être spécifiée comme un pourcentage du 
                calque total.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="it">
              <title>Rapporto di dimensioni fisso</title> 

              <para>
                Quest'opzione permette di ridimensionare la selezione
                mantenendo fisso il rapporto delle dimensioni con 
                riferimento ai due numeri inseriti nei controlli della 
                Larghezza e dell'Altezza.
              </para>
            </formalpara>

            <formalpara lang="zh_CN">
              <title>固定宽高比</title>
	      <para>
		<guilabel>固定宽高比</guilabel>选项允许更容易控制的选择区域。通过设定尺寸到预想的值，设想的区域能被轻松选取。也可以选取和总的图层大小成比例的区域。
	      </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>    
 </simplesect>
</sect2>
