<?xml version='1.0'  encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-iscissors' lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Scissors Tool</title>
  <title lang="de">Magnetische Auswahl</title>
  <title lang="fr">Outil Ciseaux Intelligents</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">剪刀工具</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具箱</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Selection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="de">Auswahl</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Sélection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">选择</secondary>
    <tertiary lang='en'>Scissors</tertiary>
    <tertiary lang='de'>Magnetisch</tertiary>
    <tertiary lang="zh_CN">剪刀</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en;de'>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-scissor.png'
          format='PNG' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-scissor.png'
          format='PNG' />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata
          fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-scissor.png'
          format='PNG' />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
           Intelligent Scissors tool icon in the Toolbox.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Die magnetische Auswahl im Werkzeugfenster. 
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          工具箱中智能剪刀工具图标。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Intelligent Scissors tool is an interesting piece of
    equipment:  it has some features in common with the Lasso,
    some features in common with the Path tool, and some features all
    its own.  It is useful when you are trying to select a region
    defined by strong color-changes at the edges.  To use the
    Scissors, you click to create a set of "control nodes" 
    at the edges of the region you are trying to select.  The tool
    produces a continuous curve passing through these control nodes,
    following any high-contrast edges it can find.  If you are lucky,
    the path that the tool finds will correspond to the contour you
    are trying to select. 
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Each time you left-click with the mouse, you create a new control
    point, which is connected to the last control point by a curve
    that tries to follow edges in the image.  To finish, click on the
    first point (the cursor changes to indicate when you are in the
    right spot).  You can adjust the curve by dragging the control
    nodes, or by clicking to create new control nodes.  When you are
    satisfied, click anywhere inside the curve to convert it into a
    selection. 
  </para>
  <warning lang='en'>
    <para>
      Be sure not to click inside the curve until you are completely
      done adjusting it.  Once you have converted it into a selection,
      undoing takes you back to zero, and you will have to to start
      constructing the curve again from scratch if you need to change
      it. Also be sure not to switch to a different tool, or again all
      of your carefully created control nodes will be lost.
    </para>
  </warning>
  <para lang='en'>
    Unfortunately, there seem to be some problems with the
    edge-following logic for this tool, with the result that the
    selections it creates tend to be pretty crude in a lot of cases.  A
    good way to clean them up is to switch to <link
    linkend='gimp-qmask'>QuickMask</link> mode, and use paint tools to
    paint in the problematic parts.  On the whole, most people find
    the Path tool to be more useful than the Scissors, because, even
    though it does not have the intelligent edge-finding capability,
    the paths it produces persist until you delete them, and can be
    altered at any time. 
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit der magnetischen Auswahl ist es möglich, Auswahlen entlang von
    Konturen oder Farbbereichen zu erstellen. Das Werkzeug führt man
    entlang der Kontur und kann somit grössere Bereiche besser
    selektieren, die mit den anderen Auswahlwerkzeugen nur schwer
    möglich sind.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil semi-automatique Ciseaux est très pratique pour
    sélectionner des formes complexes. En cliquant, on dépose
    des points espacés sur le pourtour de la zone à
    sélectionner et l'outil cherche automatiquement à relier
    ces points entre eux en suivant la ligne de plus fort contraste. Un peu
    de pratique est nécessaire pour placer correctement les points
    afin d'éviter que les liaisons ne se fassent au cordeau.  Avec
    la souris, on peut déplacer chacun des points de contrôle
    (sauf le point de départ et le point d'arrivée). On ferme
    la courbe en plaçant le point d'arrivée sur le point de
    départ.  Quand elle est fermée, le curseur prend une
    forme différente selon qu'il se trouve en dedans, sur le bord ou
    en dehors de la sélection.  On valide la sélection en
    cliquant dessus.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    智能剪刀工具是一个非常有趣的工具。它能猜测您想要选取的边缘。自由选择工具很难控制好，除非您特别熟练灵巧。因此，就出现了智能剪刀。它允许您象自由选择工具一样(您可以稍稍粗略点)勾画出物体的外轮廓，不过当您勾画完后，它会自动搜寻您准备选取物体的边缘。
  </para>
  <para lang='zh_CN'>
    每当您点击鼠标左键时，就创建一个新的控制点，并和您已经勾画曲线上的最后一个控制点相接。点其起点就完成该选取(当点到起点时，光标会改变显示)。您可以通过拖动控制点或创建新的控制点来调整该曲线。修改完后，点曲线内任何地方就将它转变为一个选区。
  </para>
  <warning lang='zh_CN'>
    <para>
      请确认您完全调整好了再点击该曲线内部。一旦转变成了选区，撤消回去就什么都没有了，如果您还想修改的话，就不得不重新勾画曲线。
    </para>
  </warning>
  <para lang='zh_CN'>
    不幸的是，该工具在边缘判定逻辑上有些问题，在一些情况下，创建的选区比较丑陋。要将其清理掉，最好转到<link
    linkend='gimp-qmask'>快速蒙板</link>模式下，用涂画工具涂掉这些有问题的部分。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">How to Activate</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Intelligent Scissors can be activated from an image
      menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Intelligent Scissors</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; 
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon 
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/scissor.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang='de'>
      Die Magnetische Auswahl lässt sich über das
      Bildmenü aufrufen: <guimenuitem><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge
      </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>uswahlwerkzeuge
      </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>I</accel>ntelligente
      Schere</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Ebenfalls kann das Werkzeug über einen Mausklick auf das
      Werkzeugicon aufgerufen werden:
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/scissor.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die <keycap>z</keycap> Taste ruft die magnetische Auswahl auf.
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil Ciseaux Intelligents peut être appelé à partir de la barre 
      de menus de l'image par 
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Outils de <accel>s</accel>élection</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Ciseaux <accel>I</accel>ntelligents</guimenuitem>. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La touche <keycap>i</keycap> activera l'outil Ciseaux.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      剪刀工具在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>工具</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>选择工具</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>智能剪刀</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      也可以点击工具箱中的工具图标：
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/scissor.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      或用快捷键<keycap>i</keycap>。
    </para>
  </simplesect> 
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen (Standardeinstellungen)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Fuzzy Select tool does not have any special key modifiers,
      only the ones that affect all selection tools in the same way.
      See <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link> for
      help with these.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Die magnetische Auswahl hat keine speziellen Tastaturbindungen.
      Jedoch können Sie die gleichen Tastaturbindungen für Auswahlen,
      der <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link>
      entnehmen.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了那些所有选择工具共有的键(请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>选择工具</link>)，智能剪刀工具没有任何其它特有的按键。
    </para>      
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;de">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-scissor.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-scissor.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-scissor.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <caption>
          <para lang='en'>
            Tool Options for the Intelligent Scissors
          </para>
          <para lang='de'>
            Die Werkzeugoptionen der magnetischen Auswahl.
          </para>
          <para lang='fr'>
            Option des outils pour les ciseaux intelligents
          </para>
          <para lang='zh_CN'>
            智能剪刀的工具选项
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <note>
      <para lang='en'>
        See <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link> for
        help with options that are common to all these tools.  Only
        options that are specific to the Intelligent Scissors
        tool are explained here.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        Schauen sie bitte unter <link
        linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> nach, um
        Hilfe für Optionen zu finden, die diese Werkzeuge gemein haben.
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        这些工具共用的选项请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>选择工具</link>。下面只解释智能剪刀工具所特有的选项。
      </para>
    </note>

    <para lang="de">
      Die Werkzeugeinstellungen für die magentische Auswahl lassen sich
      durch ein Doppelklick auf das Icon<guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/scissor.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon> anzeigen.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Les options disponibles pour cet outil apparaissent 
      dès qu'on clique sur l'icône de l'outil
      <guiicon> 
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/scissor.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Show Interactive Boundary</term>
        <term lang="de">Interaktive Begrenzung anzeigen</term>
        <term lang="fr">Afficher les bord interactifs</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">显示互动边界</term>
      
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If this option is enabled, dragging a control node during
            placement will indicate the path that will be taken by the
            selection boundary.  If it is not enabled, the node will be
            shown connected to the previous node by a straight line
            while you are dragging it around, and you won't see the
            resulting path until you release the pointer button.  On
            slow systems, if your control nodes are far apart, this may
            give a bit of a speed-up.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Bei aktivierter Option wird der Auswahlpfad angezeigt,
            während der nächste Knoten mit der Maus entlang der
            Kontur geführt wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Si cette option est inactivée, la ligne de sélection entre le 
            point cliqué et le point précédent sera une ligne droite. Elle ne 
            s'adaptera au contour que lorsque vous relâcherez le bouton de la 
            souris. Quand elle est activée, cette ligne s'adapte d'emblée au 
            contour. 
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            如果开启该选项，在放置控制点时拖动其节点就会显示选区轮廓线将要经过的路径。当该选项关闭时，当您拖动节点时，它将显示为用直线连接前一个点，而在您释放鼠标键之前就看不到最终生成的路径。在一些比较慢的系统中，当控制点之间比较远时，关闭显示互动边界会带来一些速度上的提升。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
