<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-brightness-contrast' lang="cs;de;en;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Brightness-Contrast tool</title>
  <title lang="cs">Nástroj Jas-Kontrast</title>
  <title lang="de">Helligkeit-Kontrast Werkzeug</title>
  <title lang="fr">Outil Luminosité-Contraste</title>  <!--050505-->
  <title lang="it">Luminosità-Contrasto</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">亮度-对比度</title>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/tools-brightness.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/tools-brightness.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="de">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/de/tools-brightness.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tools-brightness.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="it">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/it/tools-brightness.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tools-brightness.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <!-- revised 05-31-05 Bill Skaggs -->  
  <para lang="en">
    The Brightness-Contrast tool adjusts the brightness and contrast 
    levels for the active layer or selection.  This tool is easy to
    use, but relatively unsophisticated.  The Levels and Curve tools 
    allow you to make the same types of adjustments, but also give you
    the ability to treat bright colors differently from darker colors.
    Generally speaking, the BC tool is great for doing a "quick and
    dirty" adjustment in a few seconds, but if the image is important
    and you want it to look as good as possible, you will use one of
    the other tools.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    In GIMP 2.4, a new way of operating this tool has been added:  by
    clicking the mouse inside the image, and dragging while keeping
    the left mouse button down.  Moving the mouse vertically changes
    the brightness; moving horizontally changes the contrast.  When
    you are satisfied with the result, you can either press the "OK"
    button on the dialog, or hit the Return key on your keyboard.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Nástroj Jas-Kontrast slouží k úpravě jasu a kontrastu aktivní vrstvy nebo
    výběru. Nástroje Úrovně a Křivky jsou však efektivnější.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit dem Helligkeit-Kontrast Werkzeug kann Helligkeit und Kontrast 
    der aktiven Ebene reguliert werden.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil Luminosité-Contraste permet de régler la luminosité (plus 
    ou moins clair) et le contraste de  la sélection ou du calque 
    actif. Les outils Niveaux et Courbe sont plus performants. 
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Lo strumento Luminosità-contrasto permette la regolazione dei livelli
    di luminosità e contrasto del livello o della selezione attivi.
    Attenzione: gli strumenti Livelli o Curve, a questo scopo, sono più
    complessi ma più potenti.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    亮度-对比度工具调整活动图层和选区的亮度和对比度。色阶和曲线工具更有效。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Activate Tool</title>
    <title lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</title>
    <title lang="it">Attivazione dello strumento</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>
    <para lang="en">   <!-- revised 05-31-05 Bill Skaggs --> 
      The Brightness-Contrast Tool can be called from an image menu:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Color Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Brightness-Contrast</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.  If you find yourself using this tool often, you
        can add it to the Toolbox using the <link
        linkend='gimp-tools-dialog'>Tools dialog</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Nástroj Jas-Kontrast lze vyvolat z nabídky obrázku volbou
      <guimenuitem>Nástroje</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Nástroje barev</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Jas-Kontrast</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Helligkeit-Kontrast Werkzeug lässt sich über das
      Bildmenü aufrufen: <guimenuitem><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge
        </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>F</accel>arben
        </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>H</accel>elligkeit-Kontrast
      </guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Depuis la fenêtre d'image il se trouve dans 
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Outils de <accel>c</accel>ouleurs</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Lo strumento di controllo del contrasto-luminosità del colore può
      essere invocato nel seguente ordine dal menu immagine:
      <guimenuitem>S<accel>t</accel>rumenti</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem><accel>C</accel>olore</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>Luminosità-Cont<accel>r</accel>asto.</guimenuitem> 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      要使用亮度-对比度工具可以通过图像菜单：<guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>颜色工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>亮度-对比度</guimenuitem>。
    </para>
  </simplesect> 

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="de">Eigenschaften</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="it">Opzioni</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Brightness</term>
      <term lang="cs">Jas</term>
      <term lang="de">Helligkeit</term>
      <term lang="fr">Luminosité</term>
      <term lang="it">Luminosità</term>
       <term lang="zh_CN">亮度</term>
       <listitem>
         <para lang="en">
           This slider sets a negative (to darken) or positive (to 
           brighten) value for the brightness,  decreasing or 
           increasing bright tones.
         </para>
         <para lang="cs">
           Tento posuvník nastavuje zápornou (pro ztmavení) nebo
           kladnou (pro zesvětlení) změnu jasu.
         </para>
         <para lang="de">
           Verschieben Sie den Schieberegler nach links um das Bild
           abzudunkeln oder nach rechts um das Bild aufzuhellen. Das
           Eingabefeld dient der Werteingabe, um wieviel verdunkelt
           oder aufgehellt werden soll. 
         </para>
         <para lang="fr">
           Ce curseur permet de donner une valeur négative (pour 
           assombrir) ou positive (pour éclaircir) à la luminosité, 
           en diminuant ou augmentant les tons clairs.
         </para> 
         <para lang="it">
           Questo cursore imposta un valore negativo (per scurire) o
           positivo (per chiarire) della luminosità, decrementando o
           rispettivamente incrementando la luminosità delle tonalità.
         </para>
	 <para lang="zh_CN">
	   该滑条设定亮度，负值(变暗)，正值(变亮)。
	 </para>
       </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Contrast</term>
      <term lang="cs">Kontrast</term>
      <term lang="de">Kontrast</term>
      <term lang="fr">Contraste</term>
      <term lang="it">Contrasto</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">对比度</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This slider sets a negative (to decrease) or positive (to
          increase) value for the contrast.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento posuvník nastavuje zápornou (pro snížení) nebo
          kladnou (pro zvýšení) změnu kontrastu.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Verschieben Sie den Schieberegler nach links um den 
          Kontrast des Bildes zu verringern oder nach rechts um ihn 
          zu erhöhen. Das Eingabefeld dient der Werteingabe, um 
          wieviel der Kontrast erhöht oder verringer werden soll.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Ce curseur permet de donner une valeur négative (pour 
          diminuer) ou positive (pour augmenter) le contraste, en 
          diminuant ou augmentant les tons clairs et les tons sombres.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Questo cursore imposta un valore negativo (per decrementare) o
          positivo (per incrementare) il valore del contrasto.
        </para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  该滑条设定对比度，负值(减少)，正值(增加)。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
       <term lang="en">Preview</term>
       <term lang="cs">Náhled</term>
       <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
       <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
       <term lang="it">Anteprima</term>
       <term lang="zh_CN">预览</term>
       <listitem>
         <para lang="en">
           The Preview checkbox makes all changes to the brightness 
           and contrast dynamically so that the new level settings 
           can be viewed immediately.
         </para>
         <para lang="cs">
           Je-li volba Náhled zaškrtnuta, všechny změny nastavení jasu a
           kontrastu se interaktivně promítají přímo do obrázku.
         </para>
         <para lang="de">
          Die Vorschau ermöglicht die Veränderung sichtbar zu machen,
          nachdem das Werkzeug auf das Bild angewendet wurde.
        </para>
         <para lang="fr">
           Quand cette option est cochée, les changements 
           apportés à la luminosité et au contraste apparaissent 
           aussitôt dans l'image. 
         </para>
         <para lang="it">
           L'opzione anteprima commuta l'aggiornamento dinamico
           dell'immagine. Se quest'opzione è abilitata, qualsiasi modifica
           fatta ai livelli di luminosità o contrasto viene immediatamente visualizzata.
         </para>
	 <para lang="zh_CN">
	   预览勾选框使任何对亮度和对比度的更改立即能看到。
	 </para>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
 </simplesect>
</sect2>
