<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2008-01-29 Dust : added 'ko'
     2008-01-09 PP : rewied fr & en for Gimp 2.4
     2007-10-05 lexa: reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
     2007-06-02 kost: added no
     2007-04-18 Added Spanish translation by manuq
     2006-06-06 warning modified en;fr by j.h
     2006-02-10 en;fr revised by j.h
     2005-12-06 replaced sect3 by sect3 by lexa
     2005-12-06 replaced informalfigure by figure by lexa
     050519 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
     -->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-iscissors" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr;ko">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-01-09</date>
        <authorinitials>P.P</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-12-19</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-18</date>
        <authorinitials>manuq</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-01-09</date>
        <authorinitials>P.P</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="ko">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2008-01-29</date>
        <authorinitials>Mr.Dust</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Scissors</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Nástroj Inteligentní nůžky</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Intelligente Schere (Magnetische Auswahl)</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Las tijeras inteligentes</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Ciseaux Intelligents</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Forbici intelligenti</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ko">가위 도구</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Intelligent saks</phrase>
    <phrase lang="pl">Inteligentne nożyce</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Умные Ножницы</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">剪刀工具</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary><secondary>Scissors</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Scissors Tool</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>Panel nástrojů</primary>
    <secondary>Výběr</secondary>
    <tertiary>Inteligentní nůžky</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Inteligentní nůžky</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary><secondary>Magnetische Auswahl</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Magnetische Auswahl</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Herramientas</primary><secondary>Tijeras</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Tijeras inteligentes</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Outils</primary><secondary>Ciseaux intelligents</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Ciseaux intelligents</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary><secondary>Forbici intelligenti</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Forbici intelligenti</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ko">
    <primary>도구</primary><secondary>가위</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>가위 도구</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Verktøy</primary><secondary>Intelligent saks</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Markeringar</primary><secondary>Intelligent saks</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="pl">
    <primary>Narzędzia</primary><secondary>Inteligentne nożyce</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="pl"><primary>Inteligentne nożyce</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Инструменты</primary><secondary>Ножницы</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Инструмент ножницы</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="zh_CN">
    <primary>工具箱</primary><secondary>选择</secondary><tertiary>剪刀</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>剪刀</primary></indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">
        Intelligent Scissors tool icon in the Toolbox.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">
        Ikona nástroje Inteligentní nůžky v Panelu nástrojů.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Die intelligente Schere im Werkzeugfenster.</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">
        El icono de las tijeras inteligentes en la caja de herramientas.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">
        L'icône des ciseaux magnétiques dans la Boîte à outils.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        L'icona delle forbici intelligenti nella barra degli strumenti.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">
        도구 상자의 지능적인 가위 도구 아이콘
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">
        Ikonet for verktøyet <quote>Den intelligente saksa</quote> i
        verktøyskrinet
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">
        <quote>Inteligentne nożyce</quote> na pasku narzędzi
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">
        Пиктограмма инструмента <quote>Умные ножницы</quote> в панели
        инструментов.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">工具箱中智能剪刀工具图标。</phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;es;pl;ru">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/cs/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="ko">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/toolbox-scissor.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="no">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-scissor.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <!--   for fr a part of this para has been moved to new sect3 "tool manipulation and rewrite  and completed for en in the new place    PP 08/01/2008
         TODO (??)  and adapt for other languages  -->
  <para lang="en">
    The Intelligent Scissors tool is an interesting piece of equipment: it has
    some features in common with the Lasso, some features in common with the
    Path tool, and some features all its own. It is useful when you are trying
    to select a region defined by strong color-changes at the edges. To use
    the Scissors, you click to create a set of "control nodes" at the edges of
    the region you are trying to select. The tool produces a continuous curve
    passing through these control nodes, following any high-contrast edges it
    can find. If you are lucky, the path that the tool finds will correspond
    to the contour you are trying to select.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Inteligentní nůžky jsou velmi zajímavým nástrojem – spojují některé
    vlastnosti lasa, cest a řadu svých jedinečných vlastností. Nůžky jsou
    užitečné, pokud chcete vybrat oblast ohraničenou ostrým přechodem
    barev. Nůžky se používají tak, že klikáním na hranice oblasti, kterou se
    snažíte vybrat, vytváříte řadu kontrolních bodů neboli uzlů. Nástroj tyto
    body spojuje hranicí, která sleduje kontrastní hranice barev nalezené v
    dané oblasti. Pokud máte trochu štěstí, odpovídá takto nalezení hranice
    hranicím oblasti, kterou se snažíte vybrat.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Das Werkzeug <quote>Intelligente Schere</quote> ist ein sehr interessantes
    Element der <acronym>GIMP</acronym>-Werkzeugkiste.
    Einige seiner Eigenschaften hat es mit dem
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-free-select">Lassowerkzeug</link>
    gemein, einige mit dem <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Pfadwerkzeug</link>,
    und die restlichen machen es einzigartig. Die intelligente Schere ist sehr
    nützlich, wenn Sie eine Auswahl aus einem Bildbereich erstellen wollen, der
    farblich deutlich abgegrenzt ist. Um die intelligente Schere zu verwenden,
    erzeugen Sie mit einzelnen Mausklicks Kontrollpunkte um die auszuwählende
    Region herum. Das Werkzeug erstellt aus diesen eine Kurve, welche die
    Kontrollpunkte verbindet und an der Farbkante entlangführt. Mit ein
    bisschen Glück stimmt diese Kurve mit der Kontur überein, die Sie
    auswählen wollten.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Esta herramienta es una pieza interesante: tiene algunas características
    en común con el lazo, otras con las rutas, y características propias.  Es
    útil cuando intenta seleccionar una región que está bien delimitada por
    cambios de color.  Para emplear las tijeras, Ud. hace clic sobre el borde
    de la región que intenta seleccionar, determinando un conjunto de "nodos
    de control".  La herramienta produce una curva continua que pasa por los
    nodos de control, siguiendo el borde de alto contraste que intenta hallar.
    Si Ud. tiene suerte, la ruta que halla la herramienta se corresponderá con
    el contorno del área que intenta seleccionar.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil semi-automatique Ciseaux est très pratique pour sélectionner des
    formes complexes. En cliquant, on dépose des points espacés sur le
    pourtour de la zone à sélectionner et l'outil cherche automatiquement à
    relier ces points entre eux en suivant la ligne de plus fort contraste. Un
    peu de pratique est nécessaire pour placer correctement les points afin
    d'éviter que les liaisons ne se fassent au cordeau.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Lo strumento Forbici intelligenti è una parte interessante
    dell'equipaggiamento: possiede alcune caratteristiche in comune con il
    lazo, altre con i tracciati ed alcune caratteristiche proprie. È utile
    quando si prova a selezionare una zona definita da forti variazioni di
    colore ai margini. Per usare le forbici si fa clic ai margini della zona
    che si sta tentando di selezionare per creare un insieme di "nodi di
    controllo". Lo strumento produce una curva continua che passa attraverso
    questi nodi di controllo, seguendo il margine ad alto contrasto che riesce
    a trovare. Con un po' di fortuna, il tracciato che lo strumento trova
    corrisponderà al contorno che si sta tentando di selezionare.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
   지능적인 가위 도구는 굉장히 독특한 도구입니다. 올가미 도구와 비슷한 면도
   있고, 경로 도구와 비슷한 기능을 가지고 있을 뿐만 아니라, 자신만의 독특한
   기능도 가지고 있습니다. 이 도구는 경계색이 분명한 영역을 선택할 때 유용합니다.
   가위 도구를 이용해 선택하려는 영역 주변에 "조절가능한 노드" 를 만듭니다.
   그러면 이 노드들 사이에 색상대비가 확연한 곳을 따라 연속된 경로가 생성됩니다.
   만약 운이 좋다면, 선택하려는 물체의 외각선과 일치하는 경로를 얻을 수도
   있습니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    <quote>Den intelligente saksa</quote> er eit interessant stykke verktøy.
    Det kan likna litt på <quote>Lassoen</quote>, men har også ein del av
    eigenskapane til baneverktøyet, i tillegg til noen som er spesielle
    for dette verktøyet. Saksa er særleg nyttig for å velje ut område som er
    avgrensa med sterke fargekontrastar. Når du bruker saksa, klikkar du
    av for eit sett med <quote>kontrollpunkt</quote> rundt kanten av det
    området du ønskjer å velje ut. Saksa vil setje opp ei kurve som går
    gjennom desse kontrollpunkta medan kurva følgjer mest mogleg dei
    fargekantane som måtte finnast mellom punkta. Dersom du er heldig, vil
    dette også vere konturen av det området du ønskjer å markera.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Narzędzie to będzie przydatne do zaznaczenia obszaru o dużej
    zmianie koloru na jego brzegach. Korzystając z narzędzia,
    tworzona jest seria punktów kontrolnych na brzegu obszaru, który
    chcemy zaznaczyć. Następnie narzędzie tworzy jednolitą krzywą,
    która towarzyszy znalezionym krawędziom o dużej kontrastowości.
    Przy odrobinie szczęścia, krzywa zaznaczy ten obszar, który
    zamiarzaliśmy zaznaczyć.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Этот инструмент годится, когда необходимо выделить область с большим
    изменением цвета по её краям. При пользовании инструментом, вы создаёте
    серию контрольных точек по краям области, которую вы хотите выделить.
    Инструмент затем создаёт сплошную кривую, которая следует любому
    контрастному краю, который найдёт. При некоторой удаче, эта кривая и
    выделит ту область, которую вы хотели выделить.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    智能剪刀工具是一个非常有趣的工具。它能猜测您想要选取的边缘。自由选择工具
    很难控制好，除非您特别熟练灵巧。因此，就出现了智能剪刀。它允许您象自由选
    择工具一样(您可以稍稍粗略点)勾画出物体的外轮廓，不过当您勾画完后，它会自
    动搜寻您准备选取物体的边缘。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    Each time you left-click with the mouse, you create a new control point,
    which is connected to the last control point by a curve that tries to
    follow edges in the image. To finish, click on the first point (the cursor
    changes to indicate when you are in the right spot). You can adjust the
    curve by dragging the control nodes, or by clicking to create new control
    nodes. When you are satisfied, click anywhere inside the curve to convert
    it into a selection.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Při každém kliknutí levým tlačítkem myši se vytvoří nový kontrolní bod
    spojený s předchozím křivkou, která se snaží sledovat hrany v obrázku.
    Chcete-li výběr ukončit, klikněte na první kontrolní bod (kurzor se změní,
    pokud jste na správném místě). Křivku můžete upravit tažením kontrolních
    bodů nebo vytvářením nových. Když jste s tvarem křivky spokojeni, klikněte
    kamkoliv dovnitř, křivka se tak změní na klasický výběr.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Jedesmal, wenn Sie mit der Maus klicken, erzeugt die intelligente Schere
    einen neuen Kontrollpunkt. Dieser wird automatisch mit dem vorherigen
    Kontrollpunkt verbunden. Um die Auswahl abzuschließen, klicken Sie auf
    den allerersten Kontrollpunkt. Beobachten Sie den Mauszeiger, er ändert
    seine Form, wenn er sich über dem entsprechenden Kontrollpunkt befindet.
    Sie können die Kurve korrigieren, indem Sie die Kontrollpunkte verschieben
    und neue Kontrollpunkte durch Mausklicks einfügen. Sobald Sie mit dem
    Ergebnis zufrieden sind, klicken Sie mit der Maus in die umrandete Region
    hinein, um die Kurve in eine Auswahl umzuwandeln.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Cada vez que se hace un clic izquierdo con el ratón, se crea un punto de
    control, que se conecta con el punto de control anteriormente colocado,
    por una curva que intenta seguir bordes de la imagen.  Para finalizar,
    haga clic sobre el primer punto de control (el cursor cambia para indicar
    cuándo se halla en el punto correcto).  Puede ajustar la curva arrastrando
    los puntos de control. Cuando esté satisfecho, haga clic en cualquier
    lugar dentro de la curva para convertirla en una selección.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Ogni volta che si fa clic con il tasto sinistro del mouse, si crea un
    nuovo punto di controllo, collegato al punto di controllo precedente da
    una curva che cerca di seguire i margini presenti nell'immagine. Per
    terminare, si fa clic sul primo punto (il cursore cambia per indicare
    quando si è sul punto giusto). Si può aggiustare la curva trascinando i
    nodi di controllo o fare clic per creare nuovi punti di controllo. Quando
    si è soddisfatti, facendo clic in un punto qualunque all'interno della
    curva la si converte in una selezione.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
   마우스로 클릭할때마다 새로운 노드가 생깁니다. 새 노드는 이전의 노드와
   잡아낼 수 있는 경계를 따라 곡선으로 연결됩니다. 선택을 마치려면 처음 노드를
   클릭합니다(처음 노드에 마우스를 갖다대면, 마우스 포인터가 바뀝니다).
   각 노드를 움직여 곡선을 조정하거나 새로운 노드를 추가할 수도 있습니다.
   정확히 원하는 모양이 만들어졌으면, 곡선 내부를 클릭해 선택으로 변환합니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kvar gong du venstreklikkar med museknappen, set du av eit
    kontrollpunkt. Dette blir bunde til det førre kontrollpunktet med ei
    kurve som prøver å følgje fargeskilnadane i biletet. For å avslutta,
    klikkar du på det første punktet. (Markøren endrar utsjånad for å
    vise at du har funne det første punktet). Du kan justera kurva ved
    å dra i kontrollpunkta, eller setja inn nye punkt. Når resultatet er
    slik du vil ha det, klikkar du ein eller annan stad innføre området
    for å lage utvalet om til ei markering.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Кażde kliknięcie LPM tworzy nowy punkt kontrolny, który jest połączony
    z poprzednią krzywą, która stara się iść wzdłuż granicy obrazu. Aby
    zakończyć operację, należy kliknąć pierwszy punk kontrolny (kursor
    odpowiednio się zmienia). Krzywą można poprawić poprzez przesuwanie
    punktów kontrolnych lub tworzenie nowych punktów. Kiedy operacja jest
    zakończona, należy kliknąć wewnątrz krzywej, aby przekształcić ją na
    zaznaczenie.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Каждое нажатие левой кнопки мышки создаёт новую контрольную точку,
    соединяемая с предыдущей кривой, которая старается следовать границе в
    изображении. Чтобы закончить, нажмите на первую контрольную точку (курсор
    меняется соответственно). Кривую можно исправить перемещением контрольных
    точек или созданием новых точек. Когда процесс окончен, нажмите внутри
    кривой, чтобы преобразовать её в выделение.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    每当您点击鼠标左键时，就创建一个新的控制点，并和您已经勾画曲线上的最后一
    个控制点相接。点其起点就完成该选取(当点到起点时，光标会改变显示)。您可以
    通过拖动控制点或创建新的控制点来调整该曲线。修改完后，点曲线内任何地方就
    将它转变为一个选区。
  </para>
  <!-- paras for en & fr has been moved to new sect3 "tool manipulation  by PP 08/01/2008
       TODO   (??) for other languages -->
  <warning lang="cs;de;es;it;ko;no;pl;ru;zh_CN">
    <para lang="cs">
      Dejte pozor, abyste neklikli dovnitř oblasti vymezené křivkou dříve, než
      jste s jejími úpravami zcela hotovi. Jakmile je totiž křivka převedena
      na výběr, není cesty zpět (funkce zpět vás vrátí před použití nůžek, na
      začátek) a budete muset křivku nůžkami vytvořit zcela znovu. Také si
      dávejte pozor, abyste se nepřepnuli do jiného nástroje, jinak ztratíte
      všechny pracně vytvořené kontrolní body.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Achten Sie darauf, nicht in die durch die Kurve umrandete Region
      hinein zu klicken, bevor Sie alle Kontrollpunkte erzeugt und korrigiert
      haben. Wenn die Kurve erst einmal in eine Auswahl umgewandelt ist, können
      Sie die Kurve nicht mehr korrigieren und müssten von vorn beginnen.
      Außerdem sollten Sie darauf achten, dass Sie während der Erstellung
      einer Kurve mit der intelligenten Schere nicht das Werkzeug wechseln,
      denn auch dabei wird die Kurve in eine Auswahl umgewandelt, und Sie
      verlieren alle Kontrollpunkte.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Asegúrese de no hacer clic dentro de la curva hasta que la haya ajustado
      completamente, porque una vez que la ha convertido, si deshace vuelve a
      empezar desde el principio, y va a tener que volver a construir la
      curva.  También asegúrese de no cambiar de herramienta, porque se
      pierden los nodos de control creados (si le sucede esto todavía puede
      transformar su selección en una ruta y trabajarla con la herramienta de
      rutas).
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      È necessario accertarsi di non fare clic all'interno della curva prima
      di aver completato gli aggiustamenti. Una volta convertita in una
      selezione, un'operazione di annullamento riporta la curva allo stato
      iniziale, e se vi è la necessita di modificare la curva bisognerà
      ricostruirla dall'inizio. Bisognerà anche assicurarsi di non passare ad
      un altro strumento, altrimenti, anche in questo caso, si perderanno
      tutti i punti di controllo meticolosamente creati.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
     주의해야 할 점은 노드 조정을 완료하기 전까지는 곡선 내부를 클릭해서는
     안된다라는 점입니다. 한번 선택으로 변환한 뒤에는, 되돌리기를 할 수 없습니다.
     되돌리기를 하면 가위 도구를 실행하기 전으로 돌아갑니다. 따라서 선택으로
     변환한 뒤에 이를 조절하려면, 처음부터 곡선을 다시 만들어야 합니다. 그리고
     다른 도구로 전환할 경우 모든 노드가 사라집니다. 하지만 선택을 경로로 만든
     다음 경로를 수정할 수는 있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Ikkje klikk innføre området før du er sikker på at markeringa er
      slik du vil ha ho. Angrehistorikken registrerer ikkje kvart enkelt
      klikk. Klikkar du på <quote>angre</quote>, blir du ført tilbake til
      biletet slik det var før du byrja å bruke saksa, og du må begynne heilt
      frå nytt igjen. Klikkar du deg over til eit anna verktøy, vil også alle
      punkta du har prikka inn forsvinne. Du kan likevel omforma markeringa
      til ein bane og arbeida vidare på denne med baneverktøyet.
    </para>
    <para lang="pl">
      Nie należy klikać wewnątrz krzywej przed zakończeniem jej poprawiania.
      Po przekształceniu jej w zaznaczenie, zmiana całkowicie ją usuwa i cały
      proces trzeba zaczynać od początku. Nie należy też wybierać innego narzędzia,
      gdyż spowoduje to usunięcie punktów kontrolnych. Zaznaczenie można potem
      zamienić na ścieżkę i w ten sposób modyfikować.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Не нажимайте внутри кривой до тех пор, пока полностью не перестали её
      исправлять. После того, как её преобразовать в выделение, отмена её
      полностью удаляет, и процесс нужно начинать заново. Также не
      переключайтесь на другой инструмент, иначе все контрольные точки будут
      потеряны. Выделение можно потом преобразовать в контур и изменять таким
      образом.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      请确认您完全调整好了再点击该曲线内部。一旦转变成了选区，撤消回去就什么
      都没有了，如果您还想修改的话，就不得不重新勾画曲线。
    </para>
  </warning>

  <para lang="en">
    Unfortunately, there seem to be some problems with the edge-following
    logic for this tool, with the result that the selections it creates tend
    to be pretty crude in a lot of cases. A good way to clean them up is to
    switch to <link linkend="gimp-qmask">QuickMask</link>
    mode, and use paint tools to paint in the problematic parts. On the whole,
    most people find the Path tool to be more useful than the Scissors,
    because, even though it does not have the intelligent edge-finding
    capability, the paths it produces persist until you delete them, and can
    be altered at any time.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Bohužel algoritmus používaný nůžkami má své chyby a proto je výsledek jeho
    použití často příliš hrubý a nepřesný. Lze to napravit přepnutím do
    režimu <link linkend="gimp-qmask">rychlé masky</link> a opravou
    problematických částí pomocí kreslících nástrojů. Většina lidí před
    nůžkami upřednostňuje nástroj Cesty, protože, i když nemá schopnost
    inteligentně vyhledávat hrany v obrázku, jím vytvořené cesty přetrvávají,
    dokud je nesmažete, a lze je kdykoliv upravovat.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Unglücklicherweise scheint es einige Problem mit der Logik zu geben, die
    benutzt wird, um die Farbkanten zu bestimmen, an denen die Kurve
    entlanggeführt wird. Das Ergebnis ist gelegentlich eine Auswahl, die sehr
    unsauber an der gewünschten Kante entlangführt. Ein guter Weg, dies dann
    zu korrigieren, ist, in den Modus
    <link linkend='gimp-qmask'>Schnellmaske</link>
    zu wechseln und mit Hilfe der Malwerkzeuge die problematischen Stellen
    auszubessern. Alles in allem sollte man bei Problemen mit der
    intelligenten Schere einen Blick auf das
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Pfadwerkzeug</link>
    werfen. Dieses ist zwar nicht in der Lage, die Kurve automatisch an
    Farbkanten entlangzuführen, dafür bleiben aber die Kontrollpunkte der
    Kurve erhalten und können beliebig lange korrigiert werden.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Desafortunadamente, a veces parecen haber algunos problemas con el
    algoritmo que determina el borde a seguir, y el resultado tiende a ser
    bastante crudo en muchos casos.  Una buena manera de corregirlo es pasar
    al modo de <link linkend="gimp-qmask">máscara rápida</link> y emplear
    herramientas de pintura para limpiar las partes problemáticas.  En
    general, la gente encuentra más útil a la herramienta de rutas que a las
    tijeras, porque aunque no posee la capacidad de seguir los bordes, su
    curva persiste hasta que Ud. decide borrarla, y puede cambiarla en
    cualquier momento.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Malheureusement, il semble y avoir quelques problèmes dans l'algorithme de
    cet outil concernant l'adaptation au contour. Vous aurez donc souvent à
    effectuer un détourage complémentaire en vous aidant du
    <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Masque rapide</link>.
    En général, les utilisateurs trouvent que l'outil Chemin est plus
    pratique, même s'il ne dispose pas de la capacité d'adaptation automatique
    au contour. Le chemin persiste jusqu'à ce que vous le supprimiez et vous
    pouvez le modifier n'importe quand.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Le nom anglais de cet outil est <quote>Scissors</quote>.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    Sfortunatamente, sembra esserci qualche problema con la logica
    utilizzata da questo strumento per seguire i margini, con il risultato
    che le selezioni da esso create tendono in molti casi ad essere
    grossolane. Un buon modo per affinarle è quello di attivare la
    modalità<link linkend="gimp-qmask"> maschera veloce</link> , ed
    usare gli strumenti di disegno sulle parti che presentano problemi.
    Nell'insieme, la maggior parte degli utenti trova che lo strumento
    tracciati sia più utile delle forbici, perchè, anche se questo non ha
    la capacità di trovare i margini in modo intelligente, i tracciati che
    produce persistono finchè non si decide di cancellarli e possono essere
    modificati in qualsiasi momento.
  </para>
  <para lang="ko">
   하지만 이 도구의 경계 선택에는 다소의 문제가 있어 대부분의 경우 깔끔한
   선택을 만들지 못합니다. 깨끗하게 선택하는 좋은 방법은
   <!-- FIXME ko: <link linkend="gimp-qmask">퀵마스크</link>-->
   퀵마스크 모드로 전환하여, 문제가 있는
   부분들을 수정하는 것입니다. 대부분의 사람들은 가위 도구보다 경로 도구를 더
   유용하게 사용하는데, 이는 비록 자동으로 경계를 찾아주는 기능이 없더라도,
   경로가 그대로 유지되며 나중에도 수정할 수 있기 때문입니다.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Diverre ser det ut til at kantføljingslogikken ikkje fungerer heilt slik
    han er tenkt. Markeringane kan bli nokså dårlege til sine tider. I slike
    tilfelle kan det vere lurt å slå over til <link
    linkend='gimp-qmask'>snarmaske</link> og bruke teikneverktøya på
    problemområda. I det heile er kanskje baneverktøyet meir brukbart
    enn saksa, sjølv om det ikkje har den <quote>intelligente</quote>
    kantfinningslogikken som saksa har. Banane står der til du fjernar
    dei, og kan bli endra når du har behov for det.
  </para>
  <para lang="pl">
    Niestety, w logice śledzenia krawędzi zdarzają się błędy, i rezultat nie jest
    zbyt dokładny. Aby usunąć błędy w zaznaczeniu, należy przejść na
    tryb <!--link linkend="gimp-qmask"-->szybkiej maski<!--/link--> i wykorzystać
    narzędzie rysownicze na części, którą chcemy poprawić. Reasumując,
    większość użytkowników za bardziej przydatne uważa
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Ścieżki</link>, gdyż mimo, że
    nie znajdują one krawędzi samodzielnie, ale istnieją dopóki nie
    zostaną usunięte i zawsze można je zmienić.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    К сожалению, в логике следования за краем есть ошибки, и результат
    получается неаккуратным. Чтобы очистить помехи в выделении, переключитесь
    в режим <link linkend="gimp-qmask">быстрой маски</link> и используйте
    инструменты рисования на проблематичных частях. В общем, пользователи
    находят, что инстумент <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Контур</link> более
    полезен, чем ножницы, потому что, хотя контур и не находит края
    самостоятельно, но контур сохраняется пока его не удалить, и его всегда
    можно изменить.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    不幸的是，该工具在边缘判定逻辑上有些问题，在一些情况下，创建的选区比较丑
    陋。要将其清理掉，最好转到<link linkend="gimp-qmask">快速蒙板</link>模式
    下，用涂画工具涂掉这些有问题的部分。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">How to Activate</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace nástroje</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activación de la herramienta</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구 선택하기</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Aktywacja narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">How to Activate</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">启动工具</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Intelligent Scissors can be activated from an image menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Intelligent Scissors</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>; or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Inteligentní nůžky lze vyvolat z nabídky obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Nástroje</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Nástroje pro výběr</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Inteligentní nůžky</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      z Panelu nástrojů kliknutím na ikonu nůžek
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      nebo klávesnicí zkratkou <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Sie haben verschiedene Möglichkeiten, das Werkzeug
      <quote>Intelligente Schere</quote>
      zu aktivieren:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist lang="de">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Menü
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>uswahlwerkzeuge</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem><accel>I</accel>ntelligente Schere</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          im Bildfenster,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          mit einem Mausklick auf das Symbol
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                          fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          im Werkzeugfenster sowie
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          über das Tastenkürzel <keycap>I</keycap>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="es">
      Las tijeras inteligentes se pueden activar desde el menú de la imagen
      siguiendo
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Herramientas</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Herramientas de selección</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tijeras inteligentes</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      desde la caja de herramientas clicando en el icono
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o desde el teclado mediante el atajo <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil Ciseaux Intelligents peut être appelé à partir de la
      barre de menus de l'image par
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Outils de <accel>s</accel>élection</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Ciseaux <accel>I</accel>ntelligents</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      ou en cliquant sur l'icône
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à Outils.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La touche <keycap>i</keycap> activera l'outil Ciseaux.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Le forbici intelligenti possono essere attivate dal menu immagine
      come segue
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Strumenti</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selezione</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Forbici intelligenti</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      dalla barra degli strumenti facendo clic sull'icona dello strumento
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      o da tastiera usando il tasto <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      지능적인 가위 도구는 이미지 메뉴에서
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>도구</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>선택 도구</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>색상으로 선택</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      을 선택하거나, 도구상자의 도구 아이콘
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      을 클릭하거나, 키보드 단축키 <keycap>i</keycap> 를 눌러 사용할 수
	  있습니다.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du kan aktivera saksa på tre måtar:
      Frå biletmenyen via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Verktøy</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Markeringsverktøy</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Intelligent saks</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      frå verktøyskrinet ved å klikke på ikonet
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      eller frå tastaturet med bokstaven
      <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="pl">
      <quote>Inteligentne nożyce</quote> można aktywować na kilka sposobów:
      poprzez menu obrazu
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Narzędzia</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Narzędzia zaznaczania</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Inteligentne nożyce</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      klikając ikonę
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      na pasku narzędzi lub przy pomocy sktótu klawiszowego
      <keycap>I</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Инструмент <quote>Умные ножницы</quote> доступен несколькими способами:
      из меню изображения
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Инструменты</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Инструменты выделения</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Умные ножницы</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>,
      нажатием на пиктограмму инструмента
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      на панели инструментов или используя клавишу быстрого доступа
      <keycap>i</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      剪刀工具在图像菜单的
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>工具</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>选择工具</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>智能剪刀</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>;
      也可以点击工具箱中的工具图标：
      <guiicon>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>; 或用快捷键
      <keycap>i</keycap>。
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Modifikační klávesy (výchozí)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Tastenkombinationen (Vorgabe-Einstellungen)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Teclas modificadoras (por defecto)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Tasti modificatori (predefiniti)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">동작 변경키 (기본값)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Tastekombinasjonar (Standardinnstilling)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Кlawisze modyfikujące (Domyślne)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Клавиши-модификаторы (По умолчанию)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      The Scissor tool does not have any special key modifiers, only the ones
      that affect all selection tools in the same way. See
      <xref linkend="gimp-tool-select" /> for help with these.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Nástroj Inteligentní nůžky nemá žádné zvláštní modifikační klávesy,
      pouze ty, které jsou společné všem nástrojům pro výběr. Jejich popis
      najdete v kapitole <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro
        výběr</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Werkzeug <quote>Intelligente Schere</quote> hat keine speziellen
      Tastenkombinationen. Die allgemeinen Tastenkombinationen für
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> stehen Ihnen
      jedoch zur Verfügung.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Las tijeras inteligentes no tienen teclas modificadoras especiales, sólo
      las que afectan a todas las herramientas de selección de la misma
      manera.  Éstas se explican en la sección sobre <link
      linkend="gimp-tool-select">herramientas de selección</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil Ciseaux Intelligents ne possède pas de touches de
      contrôle particulières mais seulement celles qui appartiennent
      à toutes les sélections. Voyez
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Fonctions communes</link> pour
      plus de renseignements.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Lo strumento di selezione per colore non ha tasti modificatori
      specifici, oltre a quelli che influenzano tutti gli strumenti
      di selezione allo stesso modo. Per un aiuto su questo argomento
      vedere <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Strumenti di selezione</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      색상으로 선택 도구에는 특별한 동작 변경 키가 없습니다. 다만 모든
	  도구에 영향을 주는 동작 변경 키만 사용할 수 있습니다. 이에 대한 자세한
      내용은 <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">선택 도구</link> 섹션에
      있습니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dette verktøyet har ingen spesielle tastekombinasjonar utover dei som
      er omtalte som felles for alle <link
      linkend="gimp-tool-select">markeringsverktøya</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="pl">
      <quote>Inteligentne nożyce</quote> nie posiadają własnych klawiszy
      modyfikujących. Klawisze modyfikujące, wspólne dla wszystkich narzędzi
      zaznaczania opisano na
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      У инструмента <quote>Умные ножницы</quote> нет клавиш-модификаторов,
      только общие клавиши, описанные в главе
      <xref linkend="gimp-tool-select" />.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了那些所有选择工具共有的键(请看<link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>)，智能剪刀工具没有任何其它特有的按键。
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3 lang="en;fr;ko;ru"><!--  section added for en & fr by PP 08/01/2008
                            TODO de es it ko no pl zh_CN   -->
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Tool handling</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Manipulation de l'outil</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">도구 사용</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Использование инструмента</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      As said above when you click with this tool you drop points. The selection
      boundary is drived by these points. During creation you can move each
      one by clicking and draging, except the first and the last one.
      The selection is closed when you are clicking the last point over the the
      first one. When the selection is closed the pointer shape change: inside it's
      a pointer with scissor, on the boudary it's a pointer with a "+" sign and
      outsiside it's a pointer with a panel of ban.
      You can adjust the selection creating new points by clicking on the boundary
      or by moving each driving points ( merged first and last point).
      The selection is valid when you clicked inside.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      To notice that you can get an only selection; if you create a second selection,
      the first one will be erased when you validate the second one.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Comme indiqué auparavant, en cliquant avec cet outil on dépose des points par
      lesquels va passer le contour de la sélection finale. Pendant la création on
      peut déplacer tous les points créés en cliquant dessus à l'exception du premier
      et du dernier. On ferme la courbe en plaçant le point d'arrivée sur le point de
      départ. Quand elle est fermée, le curseur prend une forme différente selon qu'il
      se trouve en dedans (pointeur avec ciseaux), sur le bord (pointeur avec un + pour
      ajouter un point) ou en dehors de la sélection (pointeur avec une vignette
      d'interdiction). Vous pouvez ajuster la sélection en créant de nouveaux points
      de contrôle ou en faisant glisser un des points existants, y compris alors le
      point de départ (alors confondu avec celui de fin).
      On valide la sélection en cliquant dessus.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      À noter qu'on ne peut avoir qu'une seule sélection ; si vous validez une seconde
      sélection, celle-ci remplacera la première qui sera sera effacée.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      앞서 설명한대로 클릭을 하면 점들이 찍히고 이 점들을 잇는 선이
	  선택의 경계가 됩니다. 그리고 선택을 완료하기 전까지는 첫번째 점과
	  마지막 점을 제외한 모든 점들을 클릭-끌기를 이용해 이동시킬 수
	  있습니다. 마지막 점을 첫번째 점과 일치시키면 선택이 완료되며,
	  마우스 커서의 모양이 바뀝니다. 선택한 영역 안쪽에 마우스 커서가
	  위치하면 가위 모양으로, 경계선에서는 "+", 영역 밖에서는 금지
	  모양으로 바뀝니다.
	  경계선에 클릭을 해서 새 이동점을 만들거나, 각 이동점을 이동시켜
	  선택 영역을 조절할 수 있습니다. 이후 선택 안쪽을 클릭하면 선택이
	  생성됩니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ko">
      주의해야 할 점은 하나의 선택만을 만들 수 있다라는 점입니다. 만약
	  두번째 선택을 만들면 첫번째 선택은 사라집니다.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Как сказано выше, нажатие этим инструментом создаёт точки. Граница
      выделения определяется этими точками. Во время создания можно двигать
      любые из этих точек, кроме первой и последней. Выделение закрывается при
      нажатии последней точки над первой. Когда выделение закрывается, курсор
      меняет форму: внутри он - указатель с ножницами, на границе - указатель
      со знаком <quote>+</quote>, над точкой - указатель с перекрестием (знак
      перемещения), а снаружи - указатель со знаком запрещения. Выделение можно
      изменить перещением границы или контрольных точек. Контур становится
      выделением после нажатия внутри контура.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Только одно выделение можно создать таким образом. При создании нового,
      старое удаляется.
    </para>


    <warning>  <!-- en & fr paras moved here    by PP 09/01/2008 -->
      <para lang="en"> <!--changed 060606-->
        Be sure not to click inside the curve until you are completely done
        adjusting it. Once you have converted it into a selection, undoing takes
        you back to zero, and you will have to to start constructing the curve
        again from scratch if you need to change it. Also be sure not to switch
        to a different tool, or again all of your carefully created control
        nodes will be lost. (But you still can transform your selection into a
        path and work it with the Path tool.)
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Faites bien attention à ne pas cliquer à l'intérieur de la courbe avant
        d'avoir fini de l'ajuster. Une fois qu'elle est transformée en
        sélection, la commande d'annulation efface tout et vous ramène à votre
        point de départ. Veillez aussi à ne pas sélectionner un autre outil,
        sous peine de perdre votre travail. Il vous reste néanmoins la
        possibilité de transformer votre courbe fermée en chemin et de la
        retravailler avec l'outil Chemins.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        따라서 영역 조정을 마무리하기 전까지는 곡선 안쪽을 클릭해서는
		안됩니다. 한번 선택으로 변환하면, 맨 처음 상태로밖에 되돌리기를
		할 수 없습니다. 따라서 처음부터 다시 영역을 만들기 시작해야
		합니다. 마찬가지로 중간에 다른 도구를 선택하면 그동안 만든
		조절점들이 모두 사라지므로 조심해야합니다. 하지만 선택의 경우,
		경로로 변환한 뒤, 경로 도구를 이용해 같은 작업을 계속할 수
		있습니다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Не нажимайте внутри кривой пока не кончили работать с ней. После
        создания выделения отмена удаляет и выделение, и кривую. Не
        переключайтесь на другой инструмент, иначе кривая удалится. Но
        выделение можно преобразовать в контур и работать с инструментом
        контура.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para lang="en">
      To move the selection, see
      <link linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving">Moving selections</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Pour déplacer la sélection, voir
      <link linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving">Déplacer les
        sélections</link>
    </para>

    <para lang="ko">
      선택의 이동에 대해서는
      <!--<link linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving">선택 이동하기</link>-->
	  선택 이동하기
	  를 참조하십시오.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      О том, как перемещать выделения, обратитесь к главе
      <link linkend="gimp-using-selections-moving">Перемещение выделений</link>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">선택 사항</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Verktøyinnstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="pl">Opcje narzędzia</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">选项</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Tool Options for the Intelligent Scissors</phrase>
        <phrase lang="cs">Volby nástrojů pro Inteligentní nůžky</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Die Werkzeugeinstellungen der intelligenten Schere.
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">Opciones de la herramienta</phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Option des outils pour les ciseaux intelligents
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Le opzioni dello strumento forbici intelligenti
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ko">지능적인 가위의 도구 옵션</phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Verktøyinnstillingane for <quote>Den intelligente saksa</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="pl">
          Opcje <quote>Inteligentnych nożyc</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры инструмента <quote>Умные ножницы</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="zh_CN">智能剪刀的工具选项</phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;cs;es;pl;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/tool-options-scissor.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-scissor.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-scissor.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="it">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/tool-options-scissor.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="ko">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/ko/tool-options-scissor.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/no/tool-options-scissor.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-scissor.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <!-- A note about common options with link to description: -->
    <xi:include href="about-common-select-options.xml" />

    <!--TODO es it ko nl no pl zh_CN: consider switching to the
             above include file (check/edit it before!)-->
    <note lang="cs;es;it;no;pl;zh_CN">
      <!--para lang="en;de">
      Moved to "src/toolbox/about-common-select-options.xml"
    </para-->
    <para lang="cs">
      Volby společné všem nástrojům pro výběr jsou popsané v kapitole
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Nástroje pro výběr</link>.
      Zde jsou popsány jen zvláštní volby Inteligentních nůžek.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Diríjase a la sección <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Herramientas de
        selección</link> para conocer las opciones que son comunes a todas las
      herramientas de este grupo.  Aquí sólo se explican las opciones
      específicas a las tijeras inteligentes.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Per aiuto sulle opzioni comuni a tutti questi strumenti vedere
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Strumenti di selezione</link>.
      Qui vengono spiegate soltanto le opzioni specifiche dello strumento
      forbici intelligenti.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Sjå <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">felles eigenskapar</link> for
      eit oversyn over tastekombinasjonar som er felles for fleire av
      markeringsverktøya. Bare kombinasjonar som er spesifikke for dette
      verktøyet blir omtalte i dette avsnittet.
    </para>
    <para lang="pl">
      Opis opcji, wspólnych dla wszystkich narzędzi zaznaczania, opisano
      na <link linkend="gimp-tool-select">Narzędzia zaznaczania</link>.
      Poniżej opisano jedynie opcje, charakterystyczne dla Inteligentnych
      nożyc.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这些工具共用的选项请看<link linkend="gimp-tool-select">选择工具</link>。下面只解释智能剪刀工具所特有的选项。
    </para>
  </note>
  <para lang="en">
    You can get the tool option display by double-clicking on the
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>
    icon within the Tool box.
  </para>


  <para lang="de">
    Die Werkzeugeinstellungen für die <quote>Intelligente Schere</quote>
    lassen sich durch einen Doppelklick auf das Symbol
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>
    anzeigen.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Les options disponibles pour cet outil apparaissent
    dès qu'on clique sur l'icône de l'outil
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>.
  </para>

  <para lang="ko">
    도구상자의
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>
    아이콘을 더블클릭하면 도구옵션이 호출됩니다.
  </para>

  <para lang="no">
    Du kan få fram innstillingane for dette verktøyet ved å klikke,
    eventuelt dobbeltklikke, på symbolet
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>
    i verktøyskrinet.
  </para>
  <para lang="ru">
    Диалог параметров инструмента можно вызвать даойным нажатием на
    пиктограмму
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/toolbox/stock-tool-iscissors-22.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon> на панели инструментов.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Interactive boundary</term>
      <term lang="cs">Zobrazit interaktivní hranici</term>
      <term lang="de">Interaktive Begrenzung anzeigen</term>
      <term lang="es">Mostrar los límites interactivamente</term>
      <term lang="fr">Contour interactif</term>
      <term lang="it">Mostra contorno interattivo</term>
      <term lang="ko">경계 바로보기</term>
      <term lang="no">Vis interaktiv grense</term>
      <term lang="pl">Wyświetlaj interaktywną granicę</term>
      <term lang="ru">Интерактивные границы</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">显示互动边界</term>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          If this option is enabled, dragging a control node during
          placement will indicate the path that will be taken by the
          selection boundary. If it is not enabled, the node will be shown
          connected to the previous node by a straight line while you are
          dragging it around, and you won't see the resulting path until you
          release the pointer button. On slow systems, if your control nodes
          are far apart, this may give a bit of a speed-up.
        </para>
        <para lang="cs">
          Pokud je tato volba povolena, zobrazuje se při umisťování nového
          kontrolního bodu křivka interaktivně. Pokud je zakázána, je
          kontrolní bod s předchozím bodem spojen úsečkou a výslednou křivku
          uvidíte až po uvolnění tlačítka myši. Na pomalých počítačích,
          pokud jsou body daleko od sebe, to může znamenat znatelné
          urychlení. (Tato volba nefunguje při přesouvání již existujících
          kontrolních bodů.)
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Wenn diese Eigenschaft aktiviert ist, wird bei der Erstellung
          eines Kontrollpunktes bereits die Kurve zum vorherigen
          Kontrollpunkt an der Farbkante entlanggeführt. Ist die Eigenschaft
          ausgeschaltet, wird hingegen die Verbindung zum vorherigen
          Kontrollpunkt durch eine gerade Linie symbolisiert. Wenn Ihr
          Computer nicht zu den leistungsstärksten gehört oder die
          Kontrollpunkte sehr weit auseinander liegen, kann dies die
          Arbeitsgeschwindigkeit erhöhen.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Si se activa esta opción, al arrastrar un punto de control
          mientras se lo ubica, se muestra el camino que tomará la curva. Si
          no está activada, el punto se muestra conectado al anterior por
          una línea recta mientras lo arrastra, y no verá el camino
          resultante hasta que libere el botón del ratón. En sistemas
          lentos, si los puntos están muy alejados, desactivar esta opción
          puede hacer que la herramienta trabaje más rápido.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Si cette option est activée, la ligne entre le point cliqué et
          le point précédent vous indiquera le contour de sélection avant de
          relâcher le bouton de la souris. Si l'option n'est pas activée,
          cette ligne sera droite et le contour de sélection ne s'inscrira
          qu'après avoir relâché le bouton de la souris, ce qui n'est
          intéressant qu'en cas d'ordinateur lent.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          Se quest'opzione è abilitata, quando si trascina un nodo di
          controllo verrà visualizzato il percorso che assumerà il margine
          della selezione. Se non è abilitata, mentre il nodo viene
          trascinato, questo viene visualizzato collegato a quello
          precedente da una linea diritta e non sarà visualizzato il
          percorso risultante fino a che non viene rilasciato il pulsante
          del mouse. Su dei sistemi lenti, se i punti di controllo sono
          distanti, questo comportamento può dare un po' più di velocità.
        </para>
        <para lang="ko">
          이 옵션을 활성화시키면, 조절점을 이동시키는 동안 선택의 경계가
		  될 경로가 표시됩니다. 비활성화시키면 조절점을 이동시키는 동안
		  해당 점이 이전 점과 직선으로 연결되며 마우스버튼을 놓은 후에
		  경로가 표시됩니다. 이는 느린 시스템에서 조절점간의 거리가 멀
		  경우 유용합니다.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Dersom du har merka av for dette valet, vil
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          vise ruta som grensemarkeringa vil ta frå det førre
          markeringspunktet og til det nye. Dersom dette valet ikkje er
          markert, vil <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          vise ei rett linje frå det førre markeringspunktet og til det nye.
          Først når du slepp museknappen vil den valde grensa bli markert.
          Dersom du har ein treg maskin og store avstandar mellom
          kontrollpunkta, kan det vere litt hjelp i å ikkje aktivisera dette
          valet.
        </para>
        <para lang="pl">
          Przy zaznaczonym polu przeciąganie kontrolnego węzła pokaże
          ścieżkę zaznaczenia. Jeśli pole nie zostało zaznaczone, to
          węzły są łączone linią prostą w trakcie przesuwania i końcowa
          krzywa pojawia się dopiero po puszczeniu LPM. Jest to pomocne
          przy pracy na wolnych komputerach.
        </para>
        <para lang="ru">
          При выборе этого параметра, перемещение контрольного узла во время
          помещения укажет контур выделения. Если параметр не выбран, то
          узлы соединяются прямой линией во время перемещения, и конечная
          кривая появится только после отпускания кнопки мышки. Это помогает
          на медленных компьютерах.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          如果开启该选项，在放置控制点时拖动其节点就会显示选区轮廓线将要经过的路径。当该选项关闭时，当您拖动节点时，它将显示为用直线连接前一个点，而在您释放鼠标键之前就看不到最终生成的路径。在一些比较慢的系统中，当控制点之间比较远时，关闭显示互动边界会带来一些速度上的提升。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
