<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-05-06 fixed the description for "direction"
  2006-04-30 added italian content by ciampix
  2005-12-06 replaced simplesect by sect3 by lexa
  2005-12-06 replaced informalfigure by figure by lexa
  0500606 de extracted general tool features by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-transform" lang="en;cs;de;fr;it">
  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Common Features</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Společné vlastnosti</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Allgemeine Eigenschaften</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Traits communs</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Funzioni comuni</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary><secondary>Transform Tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs">
    <primary>nástroje</primary><secondary>Transformační nástroje</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Werkzeug</primary><secondary>Transformationswerkzeug</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Outils</primary><secondary>Outils de transformation</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Strumenti</primary>
    <secondary>Strumenti di trasformazione</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">
        Eine Übersicht aller Transformationswerkzeuge von
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">
        Přehled transformačních nástrojů <acronym>GIMP</acronym>u.
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">An overview of the transform tools</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités sur les outils de transformation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Una panoramica sugli strumenti di trasformazione
      </phrase>
    </title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang="en;cs">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/transform-tools.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="de">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/de/transform-tools.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="fr">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/transform-tools.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="it">
        <imagedata fileref="../images/toolbox/it/transform-tools.png"
          format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    Inside the Transformation tool dialog, you will find seven tools to modify
    the presentation of the image or the presentation of an element of the
    image, selection, layer or path. Each transform tool has an Option dialog
    and an Information dialog to set parameters.
  </para>

  <para lang="cs">
    Mezi transformační nástroje patří sedm nástrojů sloužící ke změně tvaru,
    velikosti či polohy obrázku, výběru, vrstvy či cesty. Každý z
    transformačních nástrojů má dialog s volbami a informační dialog pro
    zadání parametrů.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Im mittleren Bereich des Werkzeugfensters finden Sie die sieben
    Transformationswerkzeuge, welche <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    Ihnen zur Verfügung stellt. Während die Malwerkzeuge die Eigenschaften von
    Pixeln verändern, werden durch die Transformationswerkzeuge die Pixel
    selbst verändert. Es werden also Pixel hinzugefügt, gelöscht oder
    verschoben, ohne dass dabei deren Eigenschaften wie Farbe oder Transparenz
    beeinflusst werden. Bei der Arbeit mit den Transformationswerkzeugen wird,
    sobald Sie das Bildelement auswählen, auf das die Transformation angewendet
    werden soll, ein Informationsdialog eingeblendet. In diesem Dialog können
    Sie alle Parameter exakt einstellen, bevor das Werkzeug angewendet wird.
  </para>

  <para lang="fr">
    Au sein de la fenêtre du Dialogue des outils, vous trouvez sept outils de
    transformation, que GIMP met à votre disposition. Ces outils vous
    permettront de modifier la présentation de l'image ou d'un des ses
    éléments, calque, sélection ou chemin. Chacun dispose d'une fenêtre
    d'options et d'une fenêtre d'information vous permettant d'ajuster les
    paramètres.
  </para>

  <para lang="it">
    All'interno della finestra degli strumenti di trasformazione si trovano
    sette strumenti per modificare l'aspetto dell'immagine o di un'elemento di
    essa, di una selezione, livello o tracciato. Ogni strumento di
    trasformazione possiede una finestra delle opzioni e una finestra di
    informazioni per impostare vari parametri.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gimp-tool-transform-options" lang="en;de;fr">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Tool Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby nástrojů</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options des outils de transformation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni dello strumento</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure>
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">Common options of transform tools</phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Allgemeine Werkzeugeigenschaften der Transformationswerkzeuge
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Options communes des outils de transformation
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/toolbox/transform-tools-common-options.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/toolbox/de/tool-options-transformcommon.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/toolbox/fr/transform-tools-common-options.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      Some options are shared by several transform tools. We will describe
      them here. More specific options will be described with their tool.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Viele Eigenschaften sind in mehreren Transformationswerkzeugen
      vorhanden. Diese werden hier beschrieben. Eigenschaften, die nur für ein
      spezielles Werkzeug verfügbar sind, werden in dem Kapitel beschrieben,
      in welchem das Werkzeug detailliert vorgestellt wird.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Certaines options sont communes à plusieurs outils de transformation.
      Elles seront décrites ici. Les options plus spécifiques seront décrites
      avec chaque outil.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Affect</term>
        <term lang="de">Wirkt auf</term>
        <term lang="fr">Affecte</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            offers you three buttons which let you select which image element
            the transform tool will work on.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            bietet drei Schaltflächen, um einstellen zu können, auf welches
            Bildelement die folgende Transformation angewendet wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            vous offre trois boutons vous permettant de choisir sur quel
            élément d'image l'outil de transformation va agir.
          </para>
          <warning lang="en;de;fr">
            <para lang="en">
              Remind that the Affect option persists when you quit the tool.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Denken Sie daran, dass die Eigenschaft auch nach dem Arbeiten
              mit diesem Werkzeug erhalten bleibt.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Gardez à l'esprit que l'option Affecte persiste quand vous
              quittez l'outil.
            </para>
          </warning>

          <para lang="en">
            When you ativate the first button
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-layer.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            The tool works on the active layer. If no selection exists in this
            layer, the whole layer will be transformed.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch Aktivieren der ersten Schaltfläche
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-layer.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            wird das Werkzeug auf die aktuelle Ebene angewendet. Sie sollten
            darauf achten, dass keine Auswahlen auf dem Bild existieren, da
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            die Auswahlen bevorzugt.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            En activant le premier bouton,
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-layer.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            , l'outil agira sur le calque actif. Si aucune sélection n'existe
            sur ce calque, l'outil agira sur l'ensemble du calque.
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            When you activate the second button
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-selection.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            the tool works on the selection only (the whole layer if no
            selection).
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Durch Aktivieren der zweiten Schaltfläche
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-selection.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            wird dafür gesorgt, dass das Werkzeug nur auf die Auswahl
            angewendet wird.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En activant le deuxième bouton,
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-selection.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            l'outil n'agira que sur la sélection existante (l'ensemble du
            calque en l'absence de sélection).
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            When you activate the third button,
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-path.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            The tool works on the path only.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit aktivierter dritter Schaltfläche
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-path.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            können nur Pfade transformiert werden.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En activant le troisième bouton
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref="../images/tool-options/rotate-affect-path.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>
            l'outil agira sur le chemin.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr">
        <term lang="en">Transform Direction</term>
        <term lang="de">Transformationsrichtung</term>
        <term lang="fr">Direction de transformation</term>

        <!-- FIXME: fr not a reference in here, just describe it properly -->
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The Transform Direction sets which way or direction a layer is
            transformed. The Traditional mode will transform the image or
            layer as one might expect. You just use the handles to do the
            transformation that want to see happen on the image or layer on
            the grid. When you then execute the transformation the image or
            layer is transformed to the shape and position you put the grid
            into.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Corrective Rotation is primarily used to repair digital images
            that have some geometric errors. To do so, you just have to align
            the grid to show the same error as the image or layer. If you then
            execute the transformation the grid and the image or layer wit it
            are transformed <quote>backwards</quote> until the grid is again
            in the rectangualar and straight shape it was when you started.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Mit dieser Eigenschaft können Sie einstellen, auf welche Art das
            Bild oder die Ebene transformiert wird. Hierzu bietet GIMP zwei
            Richtungen an: <guilabel>Vorwärts (Traditionell)</guilabel> und
            <guilabel>Rückwärts (Korrigierend)</guilabel>. Die traditionelle
            Transformationsrichtung arbeite so, wie Sie es intuitiv erwarten
            würden. Sie stellen die Form, die das Bild oder die Ebene nach der
            Transformation soll über mit Hilfe der Griffpunkte ein und sobald
            Sie die Transformation ausführen, wird das Bild beziehungsweise
            die Ebene entsprechend verformt, um dem eingestellten Gitter zu
            entsprechen.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die korrigierende Transformationsrichtung ist primär dazu gedacht,
            digitale Bilder wie Fotos oder Scans, welche nicht korrekt
            ausgerichtet sind, zu korrigieren. Hierzu stellen Sie mit Hilfe
            der Griffpunkte des Gitters Art und Stärke des Bildfehlers ein,
            dass heisst Sie richten das Gitter beispielsweise so aus, dass es
            die gleiche perspektivische Verzerrung aufweist wie das Bild.
            Wenn Sie dann die Transformation ausführen, wird das Gitter und
            mit diesem das Bild beziehungsweise die Ebene, derart
            <quote>rückwärts</quote> verformt, dass
            es sich wieder in der Ausgangsform und -position befindet.
          </para>  

          <para lang="fr">Voyez <xref linkend="gimp-tool-rotate"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr">
        <term>Interpolation</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel> drop-down list lets
            you choose the quality of the transformation. For more
            information about the different methods that can be employed,
            see the glossary entry <link
            linkend="glossary-interpolation">Interpolation</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Eigenschaft <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel>
            erlaubt es, die Qualität der Transformation auszuwählen. Hierzu
            können Sie in einem Menü die verschiedenen Methoden einstellen. Um
            mehr über die Algorithmen zur
            <link linkend="glossary-interpolation">Interpolation</link>
            zu erfahren, sei auf den Eintrag im Glossar verwiesen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            La liste déroulante <guilabel>Type d'Interpolation</guilabel>
            vous permet de choisir la qualité de la transformation. Vous
            trouverez plus de détails sur l'interpolation dans le
            Glossaire à l'article <link
            linkend='glossary-interpolation'>Interpolation</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr">
        <term lang="en">Supersampling</term>
        <term lang="de">Hochrechnung</term>
        <term lang="fr">Suréchantillonnage</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            See glossary for
            <link linkend="glossary-supersampling">Supersampling</link>
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Bei der Hochrechnung (engl.
            <foreignphrase>Supersampling</foreignphrase>) werden umliegende
            Pixel zur Berechnung eines Farbverlaufs mit einbezogen. Das
            Resultat wird dabei verbessert, jedoch wird für die Berechnung
            mehr Zeit benötigt.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Voyez le glossaire à la rubrique
            <link linkend="glossary-supersampling">Suréchantillonnage
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr">
        <term lang="en">Clip Result</term>
        <term lang="de">Ergebnis beschneiden</term>
        <term lang="fr">Rogner le résultat</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            After transformation, the image can be bigger. This option will
            clip the transformated image to the original image size.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Bei aktivierter Option wird die Größe des transformierten
            Elementes auf die Größe des Originals zugeschnitten.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Il se peut qu'après transformation, l'image résultante soit plus
            grande. Dans ce cas, cette option la découpe aux dimensions de
            l'image d'origine.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry lang="en;de;fr">
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> lets you select among four Preview
            possibilities :
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            bietet die Möglichkeit, zwischen vier verschiedenen Arten der
            Vorschau zu wählen:
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            L'Aperçu est ici superposé à l'image elle-même. La liste
            déroulante vous offre quatre possibilités :
          </para>

          <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Outline</guilabel>
                : Puts a frame to mark the image outline, with a handle on
                each corner. Movements will affect this frame only on the
                Preview, but the result of the transformation will concern
                either the content or the boundaries of the selection
                according to the selected Affect mode.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Umriss</guilabel>
                : Legt einen Rahmen um das Bild. Dieser Umriss hat an jeder
                Ecke einen aktiven Punkt, mit dem Sie die Transformation
                beeinflussen können. Diese wird zunächst nur am Rahmen
                sichtbar.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Contour</guilabel>
                 : entoure l'image d'un cadre fait d'une fine ligne, avec
                une poignée à chaque coin. Le mouvement ne concernera que le
                cadre sur l'Aperçu, mais le résultat de la transformation
                portera sur le contenu ou les limites de la sélection en
                fonction du mode Affecte choisi.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Grid</guilabel>
                : Puts a grid on the image, with four handles. Movements
                will affect this grid only on the Preview, but the result of
                the transformation will concern either the content or the
                boundaries of the selection according to the selected Affect
                mode.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Gitter</guilabel>
                : Legt ein Gitter auf das Bild. Dieses Gitter hat an jeder
                Ecke einen aktiven Punkt, mit dem Sie die Transformation
                beeinflussen können. Diese wird zunächst nur am Gitter
                sichtbar.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Grille</guilabel>
                 : plaque une grille sur l'image, avec quatre poignées. Le
                mouvement ne concernera que la grille sur l'Aperçu, mais le
                résultat de la transformation portera sur le contenu ou les
                limites de la sélection en fonction du mode Affecte choisi.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Image</guilabel>
                : Here, the preview is a copy of the image superimposed on
                the image, with an outline. Movements affect this copy and
                the underlying image appears.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Bild</guilabel>
                : In diesem Fall wird eine Kopie des Bildes mit einem Rahmen
                über das eigentliche Bild gelegt. Die Transformation wird
                für dieses Vorschaubild angezeigt, so dass Sie genau sehen,
                wie das Ergebnis aussehen würde.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Image</guilabel>
                 : l'aperçu est constitué ici d'une copie de l'image plaquée
                sur l'image et entourée d'un contour. Le mouvement concerne
                cette copie d'image, laissant apparaître l'image
                sous-jacente.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Grid+Image</guilabel>: Both turn at the
                same time.
              </para>
              <para lang="de">
                <guilabel>Bild + Gitter</guilabel>:
                Sowohl das Gitter als auch das Vorschaubild werden
                angezeigt.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Image+Grille</guilabel> : les deux tournent
                en même temps.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para lang="en">
            Preview is only for greater convenience. Whatever your
            choice, result will be the same when you clic on the
            <emphasis>Rotate</emphasis> button in the Rotate
            Informations dialog.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Options with grid activate a drop-list with two options:
            <guilabel>Number of Grid Lines</guilabel> will allow control
            over the total number of displayed grid lines. Use the
            slider to set the number of grid lines.
            <guilabel>Grid Line Spacing</guilabel> allows control over
            the distance between the grid lines. Use the slider to set
            the distance.
          </para>

          <para lang="de">
            Das Vorschaubild dient lediglich der besseren Bedienbarkeit. Es
            hat keinen Einfluss auf das endgültige Ergebnis, welches bei allen
            Arten der Vorschau identisch ist.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Wenn die gewählte Art der Vorschau ein Gitter verwendet, stehen
            Ihnen in einem Menü zwei weitere Eigenschaften zur Verfügung:
            <guilabel>Anzahl der Gitterlinien</guilabel>
            erlaubt es Ihnen einzustellen, wie viele Gitterlinien angezeigt
            werden. Verwenden Sie den Schieberegler, um die Anzahl
            festzulegen. <guilabel>Abstand der Gitterlinien</guilabel>
            erlaubt es Ihnen einzustellen, in welchem Abstand die Gitterlinien
            angezeigt werden. Verwenden Sie den Schieberegler, um den Abstand
            festzulegen.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            Le type d'Aperçu n'est qu'une commodité. Quel que soit
            l'Aperçu utilisé, le résultat sera le même quand vous
            cliquerez sur <emphasis>Pivoter</emphasis> dans la Fenêtre
            d'Information Rotation.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Les deux options avec grille activent la liste déroulante
            permettant de choisir le <guilabel>Nombre de lignes pour la
              grille </guilabel> et l'<guilabel>Espacement des lignes de
              la grille</guilabel>. Vous utiliserez pour cela le curseur,
            ou la boîte de saisie avec molette, sous-jacents.
          </para>

          <note>
            <para lang="en">
              When rotating a path, Preview options are not valid: only
              Outline is active.
            </para>
            <para lang="de">
              Wenn Sie einen Pfad transformieren, stehen Ihnen die
              Vorschaueinstellungen mit Vorschaubild nicht zur Verfügung. Nur
              der Umriss ist aktiv.
            </para>
            <para lang="fr">
              Quand vous faites pivoter un chemin, Les options de l'Aperçu ne
              sont pas valides : seule est active l'option Contour.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
