<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-painting' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Painting Tools (Pencil, Paintbrush, Airbrush)</title>
  <title lang="de">Bleistift, Pinsel, Airbrush</title>
  <title lang="fr">Crayon, Pinceau, Aérographe</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具栏</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Painting Tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/toolbox/painting-examples.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        Three strokes painted with the same round fuzzy brush (outline
        shown in upper left), using the Pencil (left), Paintbrush
        (middle), and Airbrush (right).
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The tools in this group are GIMP's basic painting tools, and they
    have enough features in common to be worth discussing together in
    this section.  Features common to all brush tools are described in
    the <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Common Features</link>
    section.  Features specific to an individual tool are described in
    the section devoted to that tool.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The Pencil is the crudest of the tools in this group:  it makes
    hard, non-anti-aliased 
    brushstrokes.  The Paintbrush is intermediate: it is probably the
    most commonly used of the group.  The Airbrush is the most
    flexible and controllable:  it is the only one for which the
    amount of paint applied depends on the speed of brush movement.
    This flexibility also makes it a bit more difficult to use than
    the Paintbrush, however.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    All of these tools share the same brushes, and the same options
    for choosing colors, either from the basic palette or from a
    gradient. All are capable of painting in a wide variety of modes. 
  </para>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de modification</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="de">
          <keycap>Strg</keycap>
        </term>
        <term lang="fr">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
	<term lang="zh_CN">
	  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
	</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding down the Ctrl key changes each of these tools to a <link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Color Picker</link>:
              clicking on any pixel of any layer sets the foreground
              color (as displayed in the Toolbox Color Area) to the
              color of the pixel.
          </para>
          
          <para lang="de">
            Mit der <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste wird die <link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Pipette</link> aufgerufen.
          </para>

          <para lang="fr">
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> transforme le crayon en <link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Pipette à couleurs</link>.
          </para>
	  <para lang="zh_CN">
	    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> 使铅笔工具转为<link
              linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>颜色拾取</link>。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Mode</term>
      <term lang="de">Modus</term>
      <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">模式</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>                         <!--changed 040908--> 
          The Mode dropdown list provides a selection of paint application
          modes. This setting appears in the Tool Options for all
          brush tools, but it is grayed out for all except the tools
          in this group, the Ink tool, and the Clone tool.  A list of
          possible modes can be found in the <link
          linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossary</link>.  For the most part
          these modes are the same as the layer combination modes
          available in the Layers dialog, and you can understand their
          effects by imagining that the paint is applied to a separate
          layer above the target layer, with the mode for the layer
          set as specified.  Three of the modes are special, though:
        </para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Color Erase</title>
          This mode erases the foreground color, replacing it with
          partial transparency.  It acts like the <link
          linkend='plug-in-colortoalpha'>Color to Alpha</link>
          filter, applied to the area under the brushstroke.  Note
          that this only works on layers that possess an alpha
          channel; otherwise, this mode is identical to Normal.
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Behind</title>
          This mode applies paint only to non-opaque areas of the
          layer:  the lower the opacity, the more paint is applied.
          Thus, painting opaque areas has no effect; painting
          transparent areas has the same effect as normal mode.  The
          result is always an increase in opacity.  Of course none of
          this is meaningful for layers that lack an alpha channel.
        </formalpara>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/toolbox/dissolve-mode-example.png'
                format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Two brushstrokes made with the Airbrush, using the same
              fuzzy circular brush.  Left: Normal mode.  Right:
              Dissolve mode.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </informalfigure>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Dissolve</title>
          In this very useful mode, for fuzzy brushes the gray level
          of the brush determines not the paint density, but rather
          the probability of applying paint.  This gives a nice way of
          creating rough-looking paintstrokes.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <para>
          Die verfügbaren Modi verändern die Art und Weise, wie
          die Pixel auf die Ebene gezeichnet werden. Ähnlich den Modi
          der Ebenen, repräsentieren die Zeichenmodi eine
          Überblendung mit der ausgewählten Farbe
          (-muster) und der Zeichenebene. Mehr über die
          Modi, die <acronym>Gimp</acronym> zur Verfügung stellt,
          befindet sich im <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossar</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          La liste déroulante fournit une sélection des modes 
          d'application de la peinture. La liste de ces modes se trouve dans 
          le <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossaire</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
	<para>
	  模式下拉列表提供一系列涂画应用模式。术语表中右这些模式的列表。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Gradient</term>       <!--changed 040908-->
      <term lang="de">Farbverlauf</term>
      <term lang="fr">Dégradé</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">渐变</term>


      <listitem>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
              fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-paint-gradient.png'
              format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang='en'>
              Gradient options for painting tools.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </informalfigure>

        <para lang='en'>   
          Instead of using the foreground color (as shown in the Color
          Area of the Toolbox), by checking the "Use color from
          gradient" option you can choose to paint with a gradient,
          giving colors that change gradually along the brush
          trajectory.  For basic information on gradients, see the
          <link linkend='gimp-gradients'>Gradients</link> section.
        </para>
        <para lang='en'>
          You have several options to control what gradient is used
          and how it is laid out:
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Bei aktiviertem Kontrollkästchen, wird keine Vorder- oder
          Hintergrundfarbe zum Zeichnen verwendet, sondern der
          ausgewählte Farbverlauf. Diese Option steht in Verbindung
          mit der Auswahl des <guilabel>Farbverlaufs</guilabel>. Bei der
          Benutzung kann die <guilabel>Länge </guilabel> in Pixeln und
          die <guilabel>Wiederholungsart</guilabel> des Farbverlaufs
          eingestellt werden.
        </para>
        <formalpara lang='fr'>
          <title>Couleur à partir du Dégradé</title>
          Avec cette option, ce n'est pas la couleur de premier-plan ou de 
          fond qui sera utilisée pour dessiner, mais le dégradé actif. Vous 
          pouvez choisir un dégradé en cliquant sur la boîte de sélection 
          située juste à droite de "Dégradé". En cochant la case 
          <guilabel>Inverser</guilabel> vous inversez le sens du dégradé.
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='zh_CN'>
          可以从下拉列表中选择不同的渐变图案。该工具生成一个从前景色逐渐转为背景色的淡出图案，其方向由用户在图像上画线的方向决定。<guilabel>反向</guilabel>勾选框交换渐变中的前景和背景色。
        </para>

        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Gradient</title>
          Here you see a display of the current gradient.
          Clicking on it brings up a Gradient Selector, which will
          allow you to choose a different gradient.
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Reverse</title>
          Normally a brushstroke starts with colors from the left
          side of the gradient, and progresses rightward.  If
          "Reverse" is checked, the stroke starts with colors from
          the right side, and progresses leftward.
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='de'>
          Über den Farbverlaufsbrowser lassen sich zwischen eigens
          erstellten Farbverläufen auch die Standardfarbverläufe
          auswählen. Diese können mit
          <guilabel>Reverse</guilabel> invertiert werden.
          Standardmässig wird ein linearer Farbverlauf zwischen
          Vorder- und Hintergrundfarbe generiert.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Vous permet de choisir le dégradé qui sera utilisé si vous cochez 
          l'option "Couleur à partir du dégradé". Ce dégradé peut être 
          inversé en cochant l'option <guilabel>Inverser</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          勾取勾选框时，将使用渐变中的颜色，而不是前景和背景色。
        </para> 

        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Length</title>
          This option sets the distance corresponding to one
          complete cycle through the gradient colors.  The default
          units are pixels, but you can choose a different unit
          from the adjoining Units menu.
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='fr'>
          Le dégradé est peint vers l'avant (sens gauche-droite de la 
          représentation du dégradé). Toute la séquence du dégradé sera 
          utilisée sur la <guilabel>Longueur</guilabel> fixée.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          渐变将被向前涂画。整个渐变的颜色顺序会在设定的长度内被渲染。
        </para>

      <informaltable frame='none'>
        <tgroup cols='3'>
        <colspec colwidth='1in' />
        <colspec colwidth='1in' />
        <colspec colwidth='1in' />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> 
                  <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-normal.png'
                    format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
            <entry />
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry />
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                Abstract2 Gradient
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Farbverlauf
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Dégradé
              </para>
              <para lang='zh_CN'>
                渐变
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry />
          </row>        
          <row>
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-none.png'
                  format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-sawtooth.png'
                  format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject> <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/tool-options/brush-gradient-triangular.png'
                  format='PNG' />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                None
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Keine
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Aucun
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                Sawtooth
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Sägezahn
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                En dents de scie
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para lang='en'>
                Triangular
              </para>
              <para lang='de'>
                Dreieckige
              </para>
              <para lang='fr'>
                Triangulaire
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
        </tgroup>
        <caption>
          <para lang='en'>
            Illustration of the effects of the three gradient-repeat
            options, for the "Abstract 2" gradient. 
          </para>
        </caption>
      </informaltable>


        <formalpara lang='en'>
          <title>Repeat</title>
          This option determines what happens if a brushstroke
          extends farther than the Length specified above.  There
          are three possibilities:  "None" means that the color
          from the end of the gradient will be used throughout the
          remainder of the stroke; "Sawtooth wave" means that the
          gradient will be restarted from the beginning, which
          will often produce a color discontinuity; "Triangular
          wave" means that the gradient will be traversed in
          reverse, afterwards bouncing back and forth until the
          end of the brushstroke.
        </formalpara>
        <para lang='de'>
          Ist die Option <guilabel>Farbe aus Farbverlauf</guilabel> ohne
          <guilabel>Wiederholung</guilabel> aktiviert, wird bei
          längeren Strichen mit der Endfarbe des Gradienten
          weitergezeichnet.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          <guilabel>Sägezahn Welle</guilabel>: Der Farbverlauf
          wird hintereinander auf den Pinselstrich gezeichnet. In
          Abhängigkeit von der eingestellten
          <guilabel>Länge</guilabel> des Farbverlaufs, wird
          dieser wiederholend vom Beginn an, dargestellt.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          <guilabel>Dreieckswelle</guilabel>: Ebenso wie bei der
          Sägezahn Welle, wird der Farbverlauf hintereinander
          auf den Pinselstrich gezeichnet. Der Unterschied besteht
          hier, dass der Farbverlauf in Abhängigkeit von der
          eingestellten Länge, seine Richtung beim Zeichnen
          wechselt.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang='fr'>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Onde en dents de scie</guilabel>: chaque fois que 
          le dégradé est terminé, il reprend depuis le début. 
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          <guilabel>Onde Triangulaire</guilabel>: Chaque fois que le 
          dégradé est terminé, il change de sens, et ce jusqu'à la fin 
          du trait de pinceau.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
          <guilabel>Aucun</guilabel>: le dégradé ne sera appliqué 
          qu'une fois lors du coup de pinceau, sur la longueur fixée.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <guilabel>锯齿波</guilabel>：反复渲染渐变。渐变从每个长度结束处重新开始渲染。	
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          <guilabel>三角波</guilabel>：重复渲染渐变。渐变在每个长度结束时都掉转方向继续渲染。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

   </variablelist>
 </simplesect>
 
</sect2>
