<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-brush'>
  <title lang="en">Overview</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Brush Tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata
        fileref='../images/toolbox/brush-tools.png'
        format="PNG"/> 
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <caption>
      <para lang='en'>
        The Brush tools
      </para>
    </caption>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang='en'>
    The GIMP Toolbox includes nine "brush tools", all grouped together
    at the bottom (in the default arrangement).  The feature they all
    have in common is that all of them are used by moving the pointer
    across the image display, creating brushstrokes.  Four of
    them---the Pencil, Paintbrush, Airbrush, and Ink tools---behave
    like the intuitive notion of "painting" with a brush.  The others
    use a brush to modify an image in some way rather than paint on it: the Eraser
    erases; the Clone tool copies from a pattern or image; the
    Convolve tool blurs or sharpens; the Dodge/Burn tool lightens or
    darkens; and the Smudge tool smears.
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    The advantages of using GIMP with a tablet instead of a mouse
    probably show up more clearly for brush tools than anywhere else:
    the gain is fine control is invaluable.  These tools also have
    special "Pressure sensitivity" options that are only usable with a
    tablet. 
  </para>

  <para lang='en'>
    In addition to the more common "hands-on" method, it is
    possible to apply brush tools in an automated way, by creating a
    selection or path and then "stroking" it.  You can choose to
    stroke with any of the brush tools, including nonstandard ones
    such as the Eraser, Smudge tool, etc., and any options you set for
    the tool will be applied.  See the section on <link
    linkend='gimp-stroke'>Stroking</link> for more information.
  </para>

  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen (Standardeinstellungen)</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de modification (Par défaut)</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          Holding down the Ctrl key has a special effect on every
          brush tool except the ink tool.  For the Pencil, Paintbrush,
          Airbrush, Eraser, and Smudge tools, it switches them
          into "color picker" mode, so that clicking on an image pixel
          causes GIMP's foreground to be set to the active layer's
          color at that point (or, for the Eraser, GIMP's background
          color).  For the Clone tool, the Ctrl key switches it into a
          mode where clicking sets the reference point for copying.
          For the Convolve tool, the Ctrl key switches between
          blur and sharpen modes; the the Dodge/Burn tool, it switches
          between dodging and burning.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
          Holding down the Shift key has the same effect on all brush
          tools:  it places the tool into <emphasis>straight
          line</emphasis> mode.  To create a straight line with any of
          the brush tools, first click on the starting point,
          <emphasis>then</emphasis> press the Shift key.  As long as
          you hold it down, you will see a thin line connecting the
          previously clicked point with the current pointer location.
          If you click again, while continuing to hold down the Shift
          key, a straight line will be rendered.  You can continue
          this process to create a series of connected line segments.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
          Diese  Taste schaltet das Werkzeug in den
          Linienzeichnenmodus. Durch gedrückt Halten
          der<keycap>Shift</keycap> Taste, wird das Werkzeug
          gezwungen, eine gerade Linie zu zeichnen.  Diese Linie
          entsteht zwischen dem letzten Punkt und einem Mausklick an
          der aktuellen Mauszeigerposition.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          <keycap>Maj</keycap> place l'outil en mode Ligne Droite: le 
          maintien de la touche <keycap>Maj</keycap> enfoncée tout 
          en cliquant génère un trait de pinceau en ligne 
          droite démarrant à la fin de la dernière 
          ligne. 
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang='en'>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>:
          </keycombo>:
          Holding down both keys puts the tool into
            <emphasis>constrained straight line</emphasis> mode.  This
            is similar to the effect of the Shift key alone, except
            that the orientation of the line is constrained to the
            nearest multiple of 15 degrees.  Use this if you want to
            create perfect horizontal, vertical, or diagonal lines.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Tool Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject lang="en">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
          fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-brushcommon.png'
          format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang='en'>
          Tool Options shared by all brush tools
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      Many tool options are shared by several brush tools:  these are
      described here.  Options that apply only to one specific tool,
      or to a small number of tools, are described in the sections
      devoted to those tools. 
    </para>
  
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
      <term lang="de">Deckkraft</term>
      <term lang="fr">Opacité</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">不透明度</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The Opacity slider sets the transparency level for the brush
          operation.  To understand how it works, imagine that instead
          of altering the active layer, the tool creates a transparent
          layer above the active layer and acts on that layer.
          Changing Opacity in the Tool Options has the same effect
          that changing opacity in the Layers dialog would have in the
          latter situation.  It controls the "strength" of all brush
          tools, not just those that paint on the active layer.  In
          the case of the Eraser, this can come across as a bit
          confusing:  it works out that the higher the "opacity" is,
          the more transparency you get.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Mit dem Schieber lässt sich die Deckkraft des Pinselsstrichs 
          regeln. So kann der Schieber zwischen standardmässig, voller
          (100) und keiner Deckkraft (0), eingestellt werden. 
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le curseur Opacité règle la transparence de la peinture. 
          Plus il est élevé, et plus l'opacité est forte et 
          inversement.
        </para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  不透明度滑条设置涂画的透明程度。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Mode</term>
      <term lang="de">Modus</term>
      <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">模式</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para lang='en'>
          The Mode dropdown list provides a selection of paint application
          modes; a list of modes can be found in the
          glossary. As with the opacity, the easiest way to understand
          what the Mode setting does is to imagine that the paint is
          actually applied to a layer above the layer you are working on, with the layer
          combination mode in the Layers dialog set to the selected
          mode.  You can obtain a great variety of special effects in
          this way.  The Mode option is only usable for tools that can
          be thought of as adding color to the image:  the Pencil,
          Paintbrush, Airbrush, Ink, and Clone tools.  For the other
          brush tools, the option appears for the sake of consistency
          but is always grayed out.
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Die verfügbaren Modi verändern die Art und Weise, wie
          die Pixel auf die Ebene gezeichnet werden. Ähnlich den Modi
          der Ebenen, repräsentieren die Zeichenmodi eine
          Überblendung mit der ausgewählten Farbe
          (-muster) und der Zeichenebene. Mehr über die
          Modi, die <acronym>Gimp</acronym> zur Verfügung stellt,
          befindet sich im <link linkend='glossary-modes'>Glossar</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang='fr'>
            La liste déroulante Mode fournit une sélection des modes 
            d'application de la peinture. Une liste de ces modes se trouve 
            dans le Glossaire.
        </para>
	<para lang='zh_CN'>
	  模式下拉列表提供一系列涂画应用模式。术语表中右这些模式的列表。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Brush</term>
      <term lang="de">Pinsel</term>
      <term lang="fr">Brosse</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">画笔</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The brush determines how much of the image is affected by
          the tool, and how it is affected, when you trace out a
          brushstroke with the pointer.  GIMP allows you to use
          several different types of brushes, which are described in
          the <link linkend='gimp-brushes'>Brushes</link> section.  The
          same brush choices are available for all brush tools except
          the Ink tool, which uses a unique type of procedurally
          generated brush.  The colors of a brush only come into play
          for tools where they are meaningful:  the Pencil,
          Paintbrush, and Airbrush tools.  For the other brush tools,
          only the intensity distribution of a brush is relevant.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Die eingestellte Form des zu benutzenden Pinsels. Für die
          Auswahl anderer Pinselformen erscheint bei einem Mausklick auf
          die Pinselform der Pinselformenbrowser. <!-- XXX -->
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Forme sélectionnée du pinceau. Pour sélectionner 
          une autre forme de pinceau, cliquez sur l'icône de Sélection 
          de la brosse.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
	  显示当前的画笔。点击画笔图标打开画笔选择对话框。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Pressure Sensitivity</term>
      <term lang="de">Druckempfindlichkeit</term>
      <term lang="fr">Sensibilité à la Pression</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">压力灵敏度</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The Pressure Sensitivity section is only meaningful if you
          are using a tablet:  it allows you to decide which aspects
          of the tool's action should be affected by how hard you
          press the stylus against the tablet.  The possibilities are
          "opacity", "hardness", "rate", "size", and "color".  They
          work together:  you can enable as many of them as you like.
          For each tool, only the ones that are meaningful are listed.
          Here is what they do:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist lang='en'>
         <listitem> 
           <formalpara>
              <title>Opacity</title>
              The effect of this option is described above.
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem> 
            <formalpara>
              <title>Hardness</title>
              This option applies to brushes with fuzzy edges.  If it
              is enabled, the harder you press, the darker the fuzzy
              parts of the brush will appear.
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem> 
            <formalpara>
              <title>Rate</title>
              This option applies to the Airbrush, Convolve tool, and
              Smudge tool, all of which have time-based effects.
              Pressing harder makes these tools act more rapidly.
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem> 
            <formalpara>
              <title>Size</title>
              This option applies to all of the pressure sensitive
              brush tools, but only if you are using a parametric
              brush, that is, a brush created using the Brush Editor.
              If the option is checked, and the brush is parametric,
              then pressing harder will increase the size of the area
              affected by the brush.
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem> 
            <formalpara>
              <title>Color</title>
              This option only applies to the painting tools:  the
              Pencil, Paintbrush, and Airbrush; and only if you are
              using colors from a gradient.  If these conditions are
              met, then pressing harder causes colors to be taken from
              higher in the gradient.
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para lang="de">
          Über den Einstellungen zur
          <guilabel>Druckempfindlichkeit</guilabel> lässt sich das
          Verhalten des Pinsels bei Eingabegeräte wie Grafiktablets,
          einstellen.<guilabel>Deckkraft</guilabel>,
          <guilabel>Härte</guilabel>, <guilabel>Grösse</guilabel>
          und <guilabel>Farbe</guilabel>können in den Optionen
          aktiviert werden. 
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Règle les niveaux de sensibilité (Opacité, 
          Dureté, Taille, Couleur) pour les périphériques 
          qui disposent de cette option (table graphique). 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Fade Out</term>
      <term lang="de">Verblassen</term>
      <term lang="fr">Estompage</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">淡出</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This option causes each stroke to fade out over the specified
          distance. It is easiest to visual for painting tools, but
          applies to all of the brush tools. It is equivalent to
          gradually reducing the opacity along the trajectory of the
          stroke.  Note that, if you are using a tablet, this option
          does not change the effects of brush pressure.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Die Option <guilabel>Verblassen</guilabel> bietet die
          Möglichkeit, den Pinselstrich nach der vorgegebenen
          <guilabel>Länge</guilabel> ausblenden zu lassen.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Cette option règle le trait de pinceau pour qu'il s'estompe 
          progressivement après avoir parcouru une certaine distance, 
          comme s'il manquait de peinture.
        </para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  该选项使笔划在设定的距离淡出。该笔划在完成设置距离后就变成透明。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Incremental</term>
      <term lang="de">Steigernd</term>
      <term lang="fr">Incrémentiel</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">增值</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The Incremental checkbox activates incremental mode for the
          tool.  If it is deactivated, the maximum efffect of a single
          stroke is determined by the opacity, and moving the brush
          repeatedly over the same spot will not increase the effect
          beyond this limit.  If Incremental is active, each
          additional pass with the brush will increase the effect.
          This option is available for all brush tools except those
          that have a "rate" control, which automatically implies an
          incremental effect.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Durch aktivieren des <guilabel>Steigernd</guilabel>
          Kontrollkästchens, wird jeder Pinsel einzeln auf das Bild
          gerendert. Mehr über diese Option findet man im Glossar
          unter <link linkend="glossary-incremental">Schrittweiser
          Zeichenmodus</link>
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Quand le mode Incrémentiel est sélectionné, l'opacité de la 
          couleur augmente à chaque fois que le pinceau est repassé 
          au même endroit mais ne peut pas dépasser l'opacité de la couleur 
          d'origine. 
        </para>
	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  增值勾选框激活该工具的增值涂画模式。有关增值涂画模式更多信息请看<link linkend="glossary-incremental">术语表</link>。 
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Hard Edge</term>
      <term lang="de">Harte Kanten</term>
      <term lang="fr">Bords nets</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">硬质边界</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Activating this option causes fuzzy brushes to be treated as
          though they were black-and-white.  The consequence is that
          all pixels affected by the tool are affected to the same
          degree.  "Hard edge" is available for all brush tools except
          the painting tools (Pencil, Paintbrush, and Airbrush),
          where it would be redundant, because giving a hard edge to
          the Paintbrush or Airbrush would simply make them behave
          like the Pencil tool.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Durch aktivieren des <guilabel>Harte Kanten</guilabel> Modus,
          werden die Kanten des Pinsels nicht mehr geglättet
          (antialiased). Man
          zeichnet mit einem Schwarz/Weiss Pinsel. Dies hat zur Folge, dass
          der Pinselstrich "rauh" an den Kanten wirkt, anstatt geglättet.
         </para>
         <para lang="fr">
          Par défaut, les bords d'un trait de pinceau sont en dégradé,
          un peu flous.
          La bascule <guilabel>Contour net</guilabel> change cela: les bords du 
          trait de pinceau seront nets.
         </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          克隆工具默认是柔化克隆区域的边界。<guilabel>硬质边界</guilabel>则改变这种情况。任何勾选该选项的克隆其画笔的边缘都没有柔化。 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

   </variablelist>
 </simplesect>
 
</sect2>
