<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-clone' lang="de;en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Clone Tool</title>
  <title lang="de">Klonwerkzeug</title>
  <title lang="fr">Outil Cloner</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">克隆工具</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具箱</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Clone</secondary>
    <secondary lang="de">Klonen</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Cloner</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">克隆</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <informalfigure>  
    <mediaobject lang="en">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-clone.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para lang='en'>
	  Clone tool icon in the Toolbox
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="de">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/de/toolbox-clone.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
	<para>
	  Das Klonwerkzeug Symbol im Werkzeugfenster.
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="fr">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-clone.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-clone.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  
  <para lang="en">
    The Clone tool uses the current brush to copy from an image or
    pattern.  It has many uses:  one of the most important is to
    repair problem areas in digital photos, by "painting over" them
    with pixel data from other areas.  This technique takes a while to
    learn, but in the hands of a skilled user it is very
    powerful. Another important use is to draw patterned lines or
    curves:  see <link linkend='gimp-patterns'>Patterns</link> for
    examples. 
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    If you want to clone from an image, instead of a pattern, you must
    tell GIMP which image you want to copy from.  You do this by
    holding down the Ctrl key and clicking in the desired source
    image.  Until you have set the source in this way, you will not be
    able to paint with the Clone tool:  the tool cursor tells you this
    by showing a "forbidden" symbol.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    If you clone from a pattern, the pattern is
    <emphasis>tiled</emphasis>; that is, when the point you are
    copying from moves past one of the edges, it jumps to the opposite
    edge and continues, as though the pattern were repeated
    side-by-side, indefinitely.  When you clone from an image this
    does not happen:  if you go beyond the edges of the source, the
    Clone tool stops producing any changes.
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    You can clone from any drawable (that is, any layer, layer mask,
    or channel) to any other drawable.  You can even clone to or from
    the selection mask, by switching to QuickMask mode.  If this means
    copying colors that the target does not support (for example,
    cloning from an RGB layer to an Indexed layer or a layer mask),
    then the colors will be converted to the closest possible
    approximations.
  </para>

  <para lang="de">
    Mit dem Konwerkzeug lassen sich Bildbereiche auswählen um diese
    dann als Pinselmuster verwenden zu können. Dabei werden die
    Bildbereiche von dem Quellpunkt kopiert.
  </para>
  
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil Cloner utilise le pinceau courant pour copier une partie d'image 
    ou un motif dans une autre partie d'image ou une autre image.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    克隆工具用当前画笔从源点拷贝。源点可以在图像或图案中。
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">How to Activate</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Clone tool can be activated from an image menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Clone</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; 
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon 
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic
          fileref='../images/toolbox/clone.png'></inlinegraphic>
      </guiicon>;
      or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>c</keycap>.
    </para>

    <para lang='de'>
      Das Klonwerkzeug lässt sich über das
      Bildmenü aufrufen: <guimenuitem><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge
        </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>M</accel>alwerkzeuge
        </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>K</accel>lonen
      </guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Ebenfalls kann das Klonwerkzeug über einen Mausklick auf das
      Werkzeugicon aufgerufen werden:
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic
          fileref='../images/toolbox/clone.png'></inlinegraphic>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die Taste
        <keycap>c</keycap>
        wechselt zum Klonwerkzeug.
    </para>

    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil Cloner peut être appelé à partir de la barre de menus de 
      l'image par 
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Outils de d<accel>e</accel>ssin</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Clo<accel>n</accel>er</guimenuitem>. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil peut aussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône 
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic
          fileref='../images/toolbox/clone.png'></inlinegraphic>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à outils.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La touche <keycap>c</keycap> activera l'outil Cloner.
    </para>

    <para lang='zh_CN'>
      可以通过如下顺序使用克隆工具，在图像菜单：<guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>涂画工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>克隆</guimenuitem> 
    </para>
    <para lang='zh_CN'>
      也可以双击该工具图标：
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic
          fileref='../images/toolbox/clone.png'></inlinegraphic>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <keycap>c</keycap>键将转到克隆工具。
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Touches de contrôle</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      See the <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Brush Tools
      Overview</link> for a description of key modifiers that have the
      same effect on all brush tools.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist lang='en'>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>:
          The Ctrl key is used to select the source, if you are
          cloning from an image:  it has no effect if you are
          cloning from a pattern.  You can clone from any layer of any
          image, by clicking on the image display, with the Ctrl key
          held down, while the layer is active (as shown in the Layers
          dialog).  If the Alignment is set to "Non-aligned" or
          "Aligned" in the Tool Options, then the point you click on
          becomes the origin for cloning:  the image data at that
          point will be used when you first begin painting with the
          Clone tool.  In source-selection mode, the cursor changes to
          a crosshair-symbol.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 

  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Tool Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-clone.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <caption lang='en'>
        <para>
          Tool Options for the Clone tool
        </para>
      </caption>
    </informalfigure>

    <para lang='en'>
      See the <link linkend='gimp-tool-brush'>Brush Tools
      Overview</link> for a description of tool options that apply to
      many or all brush tools.
    </para>

    <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Pattern</term>
      <term lang="de">Muster</term>
      <term lang="fr">Motif</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">图案</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Clicking on the pattern symbol brings up the Patterns
          dialog, which you can use to select the pattern to paint
          with.  This option is only relevant if you are cloning from
          a Pattern source.
        </para>
        
        <para lang="de">
          Das ausgewählte Muster welches für den nächsten
          Strich benutzt wird. Um das ausgewählte Muster benutzen zu
          können, muss bei der Quelleneinstellung ebenfalls
          <guilabel>Muster</guilabel> ausgewählt sein.
        </para>

        <para lang="fr">
          Vous indique le motif en cours. Si vous cliquez sur la boîte 
          de présentation, vous déroulez la liste des motifs et 
          vous pouvez en choisir un.
        </para>

	<para lang="zh_CN">
	  选择下次填充的图案。点击图案图标打开图案选择对话框。
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Source</term>
      <term lang="de">Quelle</term>
      <term lang="fr">Source</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">源</term>
      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          The choice you make here determines whether data will be
          copied from the pattern shown above, or from one of the
          images you have open.  If you choose "Image source", you
          must tell GIMP which layer to use as the source, by
          Ctrl-clicking on it, before you can paint with the tool.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="de">
        <tip>
	  <para>
	    Um Bildquellen zu klonen, benutzen sie die
	    <keycap>Strg</keycap> Taste um einen Startpunkt des zu
	    klonenden Bildbestandteils zu wählen.
	  </para>
        </tip>
        <para>
          Die ausgewählte Quelle gibt an, welcher Bereich des
          Bildobjekts
          geklont werden soll. Standardmässig ist
          <guilabel>Bildquelle</guilabel> ausgewählt, welches
          Bildbestandteile klont. Ebenso ist es möglich mit einem
          ausgewählten Muster das Werkzeug zum zeichnen zu benutzen.
        </para>

      </listitem> 
      <listitem lang="fr">
        <para>
          Avec l'option Image comme source, vous pointez dans la zone que 
          vous désirez répliquer avec un clic gauche tout en 
          appuyant sur Ctrl ce qui définira votre source. Puis vous 
          allez cliquer à l'endroit où vous voulez reproduire 
          la source, votre destination. Vous remarquez qu'un curseur en 
          forme de croix est apparu au niveau de la source, qui reproduit les 
          mouvements que vous imprimez au curseur de la souris au niveau de 
          la destination. Si vous avez choisi une brosse assez large, vous 
          verrez le curseur souris reproduire l'image balayée par le 
          curseur source. Source et destination peuvent se trouver dans des 
          fenêtres d'images différentes. 
        </para>
        <para>
          Avec l'option Motif, le curseur de la souris peint directement le 
          motif choisi.
        </para> 
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Alignment</term>
      <term lang="de">Ausrichtung</term>
      <term lang="fr">Alignement</term>
      <term lang="zh_CN">对齐</term>

      <listitem lang="en">
        <para>
          The Alignment mode sets how the source
          position is offset from each brush stroke.
        </para>

        <informaltable frame='none'>
          <tgroup cols='3'>
            <colspec colwidth='1.25in' />
            <colspec colwidth='1.25in' />
            <colspec colwidth='1.25in' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata
                        fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-non-align.png' 
                        format='PNG' />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-align.png'
                        format='PNG' />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-registered.png'
                        format='PNG' />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Non-aligned</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Aligned</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Registered</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
          <caption>
            <para>
              Schematic illustration of the three possible alignment
              modes.  The mouse cursor is shown as a red rectangle,
              and the source point as a black crosshair.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </informaltable>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Non-aligned</title>

	      <para>
		In this mode, each brushstroke is treated separately.  For
		each stroke, the point where you first click is copied from
		the source origin; there is no relationship between one
		brush stroke and another.  In non-aligned mode, different
		brush strokes will usually clash if they intersect each
		other.
	      </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Aligned</title>

	      <para>
		In this mode, the first click you make when painting sets
		the offset between the source origin and the cloned result,
		and all subsequent brushstrokes use the same offset.  Thus,
		you can use as many brushstrokes as you like, and they will
		all mesh smoothly with one another.
	      </para>
            </formalpara>

            <para>
              If you want to change the offset, you can do this by
              switching to non-aligned mode, painting one stroke, then
              switching back to aligned mode.  Subsequent strokes will
              use the same offset as the first stroke.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Registered</title> 

	      <para>
		This mode copies each pixel in the source to the pixel with
		the same offset in the target.  It is most commonly useful
		when you want to clone from one layer to another layer
		within the same image.  It is also useful when cloning from
		a pattern, if you want the left or upper edges of the
		pattern to line up precisely with the corresponding edges
		of the target layer.
	      </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="de">
	<para>
	  Die <guilabel>Ausrichtung</guilabel>  bestimmt, wie die
	  Position der Quelle für jeden Strich neu ausgerichtet
	  wird. Nachfolgend zur Verdeutlichung die Mauszeigerposition,
	  welche mit einem roten Quadrat und der Quellpunkt mit
	  einem schwarzen Fadenkreuz, gekennzeichnet sind.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-non-align.png'
			format='PNG' />
		    </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	    </para>         
	    <para>
	      Ein <guilabel>Nicht ausgerichtet</guilabel>er Modus,
	      hält den Abstand zwischen Quell- und Zielpunkt
	      konstant. Zielpunkt ist hierbei das Benutzen des Werkzeugs
	      mit gedrückter Maustaste. Der neue Quellpunkt ist hierbei
	      immer der vom Benutzer definierte Anfangsquellpunkt.
	    </para> 
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-align.png'
			format='PNG' />
		    </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	    </para> 
	    <para>
	      Im <guilabel>Ausgerichtet</guilabel> Modus wird der Abstand
	      ebenso konstant gehalten. Der Unterschied zum
	      <guilabel>Nicht ausgerichtet</guilabel> Modus liegt hier
	      jedoch bei der Festsetzung des Quellpunktes. Dieser bleibt
	      immer konstant.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-registered.png'
			format='PNG' />
		    </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para> 
	    <para>
	      In dem <guilabel>Registriert</guilabel> Modus ist der
	      Quellpunkt gleich dem Zielpunkt. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="fr">
      <para>
	Le mode <guilabel>alignement</guilabel> détermine comment la 
	position de la source est décalée à chaque nouveau coup de 
	pinceau. Les captures d'écran montrent le curseur de souris comme 
	un rectangle rouge et le point source comme un pointeur-croix.
       </para>
       <para>
	<itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-non-align.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		En mode <guilabel>Non Aligné</guilabel> le point 
		source ne bouge pas au cours des différents coups de 
		pinceau que vous donnerez à travers l'image.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <inlinemediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-align.png'
			format='PNG' />
		    </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		En mode <guilabel>Aligné</guilabel>, le point source 
		se décalera de la même façon que le point 
		destination au cours des différents coups de pinceau.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		    <imageobject>
		      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-registered.png'
			format='PNG' />
		    </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		Le mode <guilabel>Enregistré</guilabel> ne s'utilise que si 
		le clonage se fait entre deux images différentes. Il oblige 
		l'outil à utiliser les mêmes coordonnées 
		pour l'image source et l'image destination. Si l'image 
		source a une taille différente de celle de l'image de destination, 
		les deux seront alignées sur le coin en haut à gauche.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="zh_CN">
        <para>
          <guilabel>对齐</guilabel>模式设定源位置和每一笔划间的位移关系。截图将鼠标光标显示为一个红色矩形，而源点显示为一个黑色十字。
         </para>
         <para>
          <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-non-align.png'
                        format='PNG' />
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                  <guilabel>不对齐</guilabel>模式用源点和每个新笔划的起点作为位移量。
                </para>
              </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-align.png'
                          format='PNG' />
                      </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                  <guilabel>对齐</guilabel>模式用源点和第一笔划的起点作为位移量，并在后续的笔划中使用该位移。
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <inlinemediaobject>
                      <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref='../images/tool-options/clone-registered.png'
                          format='PNG' />
                      </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject>
                  <guilabel>记录</guilabel>模式没有位移量。如果原图像和目标图像大小不同，它们将在左上角对齐。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Further Information</title>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>Transparency</term>

        <listitem>    
          <para lang='en'>
            The effects of the Clone tool on transparency are a bit
            complicated.  You cannot clone transparency:  if you try to
            clone from a transparent source, nothing happens to the target.
            If you clone from a partially transparent source, the effect is
            weighted by the opacity of the source.  So, assuming 100%
            opacity and a hard brush:
          </para>
     
          <itemizedlist lang='en'>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent black onto white produces gray.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent black onto black produces black.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent white onto white produces white.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent white onto black produces gray.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang='en'>
            Cloning can never increase transparency, but, unless "keep
            transparency" is turned on for the layer, it can reduce it.
            Cloning an opaque area onto a translucent area produces an
            opaque result; cloning a translucent area onto another
            translucent area causes an increase in opacity.  
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>"Filter" brushes</term>

        <listitem>    
          <para lang='en'>
            There are a few non-obvious ways to use the Clone tool to
            obtain powerful effects.  One thing you can do is to create
            "Filter brushes", that is, create the effect of applying a
            filter with a brush.  To do this, duplicate the layer you
            want to work on, and apply the filter to the copy.  Then
            activate the Clone tool, setting Source to "Image source"
            and Alignment to "Registered".  Ctrl-click on the filtered
            layer to set it as the source, and paint on the original
            layer:  you will then in effect be painting the filtered
            image data onto the original layer. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang='en'>History brush</term>

        <listitem>    
          <para lang='en'>
            You can use a similar approach to imitate Photoshop's
            "History brush", which allows you to selectively undo or
            redo changes using a brush.  To do this, start by
            duplicating the image; then, in the original, go back to
            the desired state in the image's history, either by
            undoing or by using the Undo History dialog.  (This must
            be done in the original, not the copy, because duplicating
            an image does not duplicate the Undo history.)  Now
            activate the Clone tool, setting Source to "Image source" 
            and Alignment to "Registered".  Ctrl-click on a layer from
            one image, and paint on the corresponding layer from the
            other image.  Depending on how you do it, this gives you
            either an "undo brush" or a "redo brush".
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
