<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect2 id='gimp-tool-fuzzy-select' lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Fuzzy Selection Tool (Magic Wand)</title>
  <title lang="de">Zauberstab</title>
  <title lang="fr">Sélection contiguë</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">模糊选择工具</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Toolbox</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Werkzeugfenster</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Boîte à Outils</primary>
    <primary lang="zh_CN">工具箱</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Selection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="de">Auswahl</secondary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Sélection</secondary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">选择</secondary>
    <tertiary lang='en'>Fuzzy</tertiary>
    <tertiary lang='de'>Zauberstab</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject lang='en;de'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/toolbox-wand.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang='fr'>
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/toolbox-wand.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
        <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/toolbox-wand.png' format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>

      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Magic Wand tool icon in the Toolbox
        </para>
        <para lang='de'>
          Der Zauberstab im Werkzeugfenster.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          工具箱中魔术棒工具图标
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Fuzzy Select (Magic Wand) tool is designed to select areas of
    the current layer or image based on color similarity.  It starts
    selecting when you click at a 
    spot in the image, and expands outward like water flooding
    low-lying areas, selecting contiguous pixels whose colors are
    similar to the starting pixel.  You can control the threshold of
    similarity by dragging the mouse downward or to the right:  the
    farther you drag it, the larger the selected region.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    When using this tool, it is very important to pick the right
    starting point.  If you select the wrong spot, you might get
    something very different from what you want, or even the
    opposite. 
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The Wand is a good tool for selecting objects with sharp
    edges. It is fun to use, so beginners often start out using it a
    lot.  You will probably find, however, that the more you use it,
    the more frustrated you become with the difficulty of selecting
    exactly what you what, no more, no less.  Perhaps the most
    frustrating aspect is that after you have released the mouse button,
    you can't make small adjustments to the threshold:  you have to
    start over again from scratch. More experienced users find
    that the <link linkend='gimp-tool-path'>Path</link> and  <link
    linkend='gimp-tool-by-color-select'>Color Select</link> tools
    are often more efficient, and use the Wand less. Still, it is
    useful for selecting an area within a contour, or touching up
    imperfect selections. It often works very well for selecting a
    solid-colored (or nearly solid-colored) background area. 
  </para>
  <para lang='en'>
    Note that as the selected area expands outward from the center, it
    does not only propagate to pixels that touch each other:  it is
    capable of jumping over small gaps.  The distance it can jump
    over is set in the <link linkend='gimp-prefs-tool-options'>Tool 
    Options</link> page of the Preferences dialog:  the "Default
    threshold" for Finding Continguous Regions.  By raising or
    lowering this value, you can make the Magic Wand either more or less
    aggressive.  (Filling with the Bucket Fill and Blend tools will
    also be affected.)
  </para>
 
  <para lang="de">
    Der Zauberstab erlaubt es ähnliche Farbbereiche auf der aktuellen Ebene
    zu selektieren. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    L'outil Sélection contiguë sert à sélectionner 
    des régions d'un calque ou d'une image sur la base de la similarité 
    des couleurs: les pixels voisins du pixel cliqué, de même couleur 
    ou de couleur proche, sont inclus dans la sélection.
  </para>

  <para lang="zh_CN">
    模糊选择工具，也叫魔术棒工具用作选取图层或图像中颜色相近区域，它将颜色相近的像素连接起来。点图像中的一点就开始选取了，该魔术棒从这点开始选取，并向外延伸直到它认为颜色太不同时就结束。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
     要控制魔术棒的灵敏度，可以在您定位光标后按下鼠标键，从左上方拖动光标(不要松开鼠标键)向右或正下方(都一样)，就可以逐渐从一个小选区变为一个非常大的。<emphasis>小心定位您的起始点，如果您选错了点，结果可能和您预计的相差甚远。</emphasis>换句话说，选错点可能使魔术棒选取除了您想要的所有部分。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    魔术棒工具很适合选取边缘分明的物体。它容易使用并且比较好玩，初学者经常使用它。更有经验的用户则觉得<link linkend='gimp-tool-path'>路径</link>和<link linkend='gimp-tool-by-color-select'>按颜色选择</link>对选取更有效，而很少使用魔术棒。即使这样，魔术棒在选取带轮廓线的区域和润色有问题选区时还是有用的，而在删除剪切-粘贴的选区的背景色时有很有效。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    模糊选择选项对话框中有个勾选框叫位样合并。在您的图像有多个图层，并且活动图层要么是半透明要么不是设置为“正常”的图层模式时，该选项就其作用了。在这种情况下，图层中本来的颜色和实际图像中的颜色是不同的。如果未勾选位样合并，当它创建一个选区时就只考虑活动图层上的颜色。如果勾选，它就将所有可见图层上混合的颜色一并考虑。
  </para>   

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">How to Activate</title>
    <title lang="fr">Activation de l'outil</title>
    <title lang="de">Werkzeugaufruf</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">启动工具</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Magic Wand Tool can be activated from an image
      menu as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Selection Tools</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fuzzy Select</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>; 
      from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon 
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/wand.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>;
      or from the keyboard using the shortcut <keycap>z</keycap>.
          ("Z" stands for "Zauber", the German word for Magic.)
    </para>

    <para lang='de'>
      Der Zauberstab lässt sich über das
      Bildmenü aufrufen: <guimenuitem><accel>W</accel>erkzeuge
      </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>A</accel>uswahlwerkzeuge
      </guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem><accel>Z</accel>auberstab
      </guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Ebenfalls kann der Zauberstab über einen Mausklick auf das
      Werkzeugicon aufgerufen werden:
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/wand.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Die <keycap>z</keycap> Taste ruft den Zauberstab auf.
    </para>
    
    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil Sélection contiguë peut être appelé à partir de la 
      barre de menus de l'image par 
      <guimenuitem><accel>O</accel>utils</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Outils de <accel>s</accel>élection</guimenuitem>/
      <guimenuitem>Sélection <accel>c</accel>ontiguë</guimenuitem>. 
    </para>
    <para lang='fr'>
      L'outil peut ussi être appelé en cliquant sur l'icône 
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/wand.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      dans la Boîte à outils.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La touche <keycap>z</keycap> sélectionnera 
      l'outil Sélection Contiguë.
    </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      按如下步骤启动模糊选择工具,在图像菜单中：<guimenuitem>工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>选择工具</guimenuitem>/<guimenuitem>模糊选择</guimenuitem> 
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      也可以点工具图标：
      <guiicon>
	<inlinemediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/wand.png' />
	  </imageobject>
	</inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      <keycap>z</keycap> 键将转到模糊选择。
    </para>
  </simplesect> 
  

  <simplesect>
      <title lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</title>
      <title lang="de">Tastaturbindungen (Standardeinstellungen)</title>
      <title lang="fr">Touches de contrôle (Par défaut)</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">相关按键(默认值)</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The Fuzzy Select tool does not have any special key modifiers,
      only the ones that affect all selection tools in the same way.
      See <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link> for
      help with these.
    </para>
    <para lang='de'>
      Der Zauberstab hat keine besonderen Tastaturbindungen. Sie können
      aber Tastaturbindungen der <link
      linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> benutzen.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      除了那些所有选择工具共有的键(请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>选择工具</link>)，模糊选择工具没有其它任何特有的按键。
    </para>      
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="de">Optionen</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;de">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/tool-options-wand.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/fr/tool-options-wand.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject lang="zh_CN">
          <imagedata
            fileref='../images/toolbox/zh_CN/tool-options-wand.png'
            format="PNG"/> 
        </imageobject>

        <caption lang='en'>
          <para>
            Tool Options for the Magic Wand tool
          </para>
        </caption>

        <caption lang='de'>
          <para>
            Einstellungen für den Zauberstab
          </para>
        </caption>

        <caption lang='fr'>
          <para>
            Les options de l'outil de sélection contiguë
          </para>
        </caption>

        <caption lang="zh_CN">
          <para>
            魔术棒工具的工具选项
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <note>
      <para lang='en'>
        See <link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Selection Tools</link> for
        help with options that are common to all these tools.  Only
        options that are specific to the Magic Wand
        tool are explained here.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        Schauen sie bitte unter <link
        linkend='gimp-tool-select'>Auswahlwerkzeuge</link> nach, um
        Hilfe für Optionen zu finden, die diese Werkzeuge gemein haben.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        这些工具共用的选项请看<link linkend='gimp-tool-select'>选择工具</link>。下面只解释魔术棒工具所特有的选项。
      </para>
    </note>

    <para lang="de">
      Die Werkzeugeinstellungen für den Zauberstab lassen sich durch
      ein Doppelklick auf das Icon 
      <guiicon> 
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/wand.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
      anzeigen.
    </para>
    
    <para lang="fr">
      Les options disponibles pour l'outil Sélection Contiguë 
      sont obtenues par un double clic gauche sur l'icône de l'outil.
      <guiicon> 
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/toolbox/wand.png' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </guiicon>
    </para>
    
    <variablelist>    
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Finding Similar Colors</term>
        <term lang="de">ähnliche Farben finden</term>
        <term lang="fr">Recherche de couleurs similaires</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">寻找相近的颜色</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>
            These options affect the way the Magic Wand expands the
            selection out from the initial point.
          </para>

          <itemizedlist lang='en'>
            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Select Transparent Areas</title>

                <para>
                  This option gives the Magic Wand the ability to select
                  areas that are completely transparent. If this option is
                  not checked, transparent areas will never be included in
                  the selection.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Sample Merged</title>

                <para>
                  This option becomes relevant when you have several layers
                  in your image, and the active layer is either
                  semi-transparent or is set to another Layer Mode than
                  Normal. If this is the case, the colors present in the
                  layer will be different from the colors in the composite
                  image. If the "Sample Merged" option is unchecked, the
                  wand will only react to the color in the active layer
                  when it creates a selection. If it is checked it will
                  react to the composite color of all visible layers. For
                  further information, see the glossary entry <link
                  linkend='glossary-samplemerge'>Sample Merged</link>.  
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Threshold</title>

                <para>
                  This slider determines the range of colors that will be
                  selected at the moment you click the pointer on the
                  initial point, before dragging it:  the higher the
                  threshold, the larger the resulting selection.  After
                  the first button-press, dragging the pointer downward
                  or to the right will increase the size of the
                  selection; dragging upward or to the left will decrease
                  it.  Thus, you have the same set of possibilities
                  regardless of the Threshold setting:  what differs is
                  the amount of dragging you have to do to get the result
                  you want.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist lang='de'>
            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Transparente Bereiche auswählen</title>

                <para>
                  Mit diese Option lassen sich mit dem Zauberstab auch
                  transparente Bereiche auswählen. Ist diese Option nicht
                  aktiviert, lassen sich transparente Bereiche mit dem
                  Zauberstab nicht selektieren.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Vereinigung abtasten</title>

                <para>
                  Durch diese Option  ist es möglich den Auswahlbereich zu
                  beeinflussen, den der Zauberstab selektiert. Wenn diese
                  Option aktiviert ist, wird die Auswahl von allen
                  sichtbaren Ebenen beeinflusst. Mehr über Informationen
                  zu <link linkend='glossary-samplemerge'>Vereinigung
                  abtasten</link> bietet das Glossar.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Schwellwert</title>

                <para>
                  Mit dem lässt sich leicht die Empfindlichkeit des
                  Zauberstabs reguilieren. So kann der Schwellwert einen
                  Wert zwischen 0 (minimale Farbdifferenz) und 255
                  (maximale Farbdifferenz) annehmen. Es ist auch möglich
                  die <mousebutton>Maustaste</mousebutton> während der
                  Selektierung gedrückt zu halten und durch verschieben
                  der Maus nach oben oder unten, den Schwellwert zu
                  verändern. Das regeln des Schwellwertes mit der Maus
                  erfordert allerdings etwas Übung.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist lang='fr'>
            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Sélectionner les Aires Transparentes</title>

                <para>
                  Cette option permet à l'outil Sélection Contiguë de
                  sélectionner les aires possédant une transparence.
                  Sans cette option, les aires possédant une transparence
                  ne seront pas sélectionnées.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Echantillonner sur tous les calques</title>

                <para>
                  Avec cette option, la couleur choisie pour chaque pixel
                  est la couleur vue effectivement dans l'image, c-à-d
                  qu'elle  est la combinaison des couleurs de ce pixel dans
                  les différents calques composant l'image, à condition
                  bien sûr qu'ils soient suffisamment transparents.  Le
                  seuil s'applique alors aux différents calques. 
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Seuil</title>

                <para>
                  Cette curseur fixe l'écart de couleur à prendre en
                  compte pour le choix des pixels de la sélection.
                  Autrement dit, les pixels dont la différence de couleur
                  avec le pixel d'origine excède le seuil seront refusés.
                  Plus le seuil augmente, et plus de pixels sont
                  sélectionnés.  Si vous maintenez enfoncé le
                  <mousebutton>bouton de la souris</mousebutton> pendant la
                  sélection, vous pourrez ajuster le
                  <guilabel>Seuil</guilabel> en déplaçant la souris vers
                  le haut ou le bas.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist lang='zh_CN'>
            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>选择透明区域</title>

		<para>
		  让模糊选择工具选取透明区域。如果未勾选改选项，选取透明区域是不被允许的。
		</para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>位样合并</title>

		<para>
		  将改变模糊选择工具决定选区起始点和结束点的方式。如果勾选<guilabel>位样合并</guilabel>,在所有可见图层的颜色将被作为选取的基准，而不是仅仅是当前图层。
		</para>
	      </formalpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>阈值</title>

		<para>
		  该滑条控制哪些颜色范围值认为是“临近”定位点的颜色。一个高值将选择一个更大的区域。如果在您进行选择操作时按住<mousebutton>左键</mousebutton>，您可以通过上下移动鼠标来调整<guilabel>阈值</guilabel>
		</para>
              </formalpara>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
