<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-10-14 KoSt: updatet no to v2.4
  2007-09-06 AntI: added 'es'
  2007-08-19 alex falappa: new sections for 2.4 and torough review
  2007-08-07 alex falappa: ude's fix to 'it', polar mode
  2007-07-23 ude: new section and image for displacement details
  2007-07-04 kost: ude's fix to 'no'
  2007-07-04 ude: added polar mode for GIMP 2.4 (disabled)
  2007-07-02 ude: fixed description of displacement calculation
  2007-05-06 KoSt: added 'no'
  2006-12-12 lexa: added german translation
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-10-14 ceated by julien hardelin
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-displace">
  <title>Displace</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Map</secondary>
    <tertiary>Displace</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Displace</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Displacement examples</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace7a.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace7b.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The displacement map has four grey stripes with values of 210,
            160, 110, and 60, respectively.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace7c.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            X displacement coefficient is 30. Vacated pixels are black. The
            image areas corresponding to light gray (128) were displaced
            19 and 8 pixels to the left. The image areas corresponding to dark
            gray (127) were displaced 4 and 15 pixels to the right.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      This filter uses a <quote>displace-map</quote>
      to displace corresponding pixels of the image. This filter displaces
      the content of the specified drawable (active layer or selection) by
      the amounts specified in X and Y Displacement multiplied by the
      intensity of the corresponding pixel in the 'displace map' drawables.
      <emphasis>
        Both X and Y displace maps should be gray-scale images and have the
        same size as the drawable
      </emphasis>. This filter allows interesting distortion effects.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the filter</title>
    <para>
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Map</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Displace</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="plug-in-displace-general-options">
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Displace filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/options-map-displace.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Preview</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Uncheck this option if your processor is slow.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Displacement Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can choose working in
            <link linkend="plug-in-displace-cartesian">cartesian</link>
            coordinates, where pixels are displaced in X or Y direction, or
            working in
            <link linkend="plug-in-displace-polar">polar</link> coordinates,
            where the image is pinched and whirled by displacing pixels in
            radial or tangent direction.
          </para>
          <para>
            Please see the next sections for details about these options.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Edge Behavior</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These options allows you to set displacement behaviour on active
            layer or selection edges:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Wrap</guilabel>:
                With this option, what disappears on one edge reappears on
                the opposite edge.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Smear</guilabel>:
                With this option, pixels vacated by displacement are
                replaced with pixels stretched from the adjacent part of the
                image.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Black</guilabel>:
                With this option, pixels vacated by displacement are replaced
                with black.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <sect4 id="plug-in-displace-cartesian">
      <title>Cartesian Displacement Mode</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Displace filter options (Cartesian)</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/filters/options-map-displace-cartesian.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Displacement Mode: Cartesian</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        In both modes, direction and amount of displacement depend on the
        intensity of the corresponding pixel in the displacement map.
      </para>
      <para>
        The map, that should be a grayscale image, has 256 gray levels
        (0-255), the (theoretical) average value is 127.5. The filter
        displaces image pixels corresponding to pixels with values less than
        127.5 (0 to 127) in map to one direction, corresponding to pixels with
        values from 128 to 255 to the opposite direction.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>X/Y Displacements</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If the respective option is activated, image pixels
              corresponding to pixels from 0 to 127 will be displaced to the
              right for X, downwards for Y, image pixels corresponding to
              pixels from 128 to 255 will be displaced to the left for X,
              upwards for Y.
            </para>
            <para>
              What you enter in input boxes, directly or by using arrow-head
              buttons, is not the actual displacement. It's a coefficient used
              in a
              <inlineequation>
                <alt role="latex">
                  $displacement = (intensity x coefficient)$
                </alt>
                <graphic fileref="images/math/displace0.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </inlineequation>
              formula, which gives the pixel actual displacement according to
              the scaled intensity
              <footnote><para>
                  Scaled intensity = (intensity - 127.5) / 127.5;
                  see <xref linkend="plug-in-displace-calculation"/>.
                </para></footnote>
              of the corresponding pixel in map, modulated by the coefficient
              you enter. Introducing intensity into formula is important: this
              allows progressive displacement by using a gradient map.
            </para>
            <para>
              This value may be positive or negative. A negative displacement
              is reverse of a positive one. The value varies in limits equal
              to the double of image dimensions.
            </para>
            <para>
              When you click on the drop-down list button, a list appears
              where you can select a displacement map. To be present in this
              list, an image must respect two conditions. First, this image
              must be present on your screen when you call filter. Then, this
              image must have the same dimensions as the original image. Most
              often, it will be a duplicate original image, which is
              transformed to grey scale and modified appropriately, with a
              gradient. It may be possible to use RGB images, but color
              luminosity is used making result prevision difficult. Map may be
              different in horizontal and vertical directions.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="plug-in-displace-polar">
      <title>Polar Displacement Mode</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Displace filter options (Polar)</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/filters/options-map-displace-polar.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Displacement Mode: Polar</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Pinch</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If this option is activated, the radial coordinates (i.e. the
              distance to the image's midpoint, the <quote>pole</quote>)
              of the pixels will be changed. Image pixels corresponding to
              map pixels from 0 to 127 will be displaced outwards, image
              pixels corresponding to pixels from 128 to 255 will be displaced
              towards center.
            </para>
            <para>
              For the values and the displacement map see above
              (<quote>X/Y Displacements</quote>).
            </para>
            <para>
              The displacement is independent from the polar distance, all
              pixels are displaced by the same amount. So the image will not
              only be stretched or compressed, but also distorted:
            </para>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace-pinch.png"
                  format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>Image distortion by Pinch option</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>
              A 160x120 pixel image, plain white displacement map, and
              displacement coefficient 20.0: this results in a 20 pixels
              displacement towards center. This is a horizontal reduction in
              size by 25%, vertical by 33%, and diagonal by 20%, so the image
              will be distorted.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Whirl</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If this option is activated, the angular coordinates of the
              image pixels will be <quote>displaced</quote> by a map pixel
              dependent amount. For a plain displacement map, the image will
              be rotated, otherwise it will be whirled.
            </para>
            <para>
              Image pixels corresponding to pixels from 0 to 127 in the map
              will be displaced counterclockwise, image pixels corresponding
              to pixels from 128 to 255 will be displaced clockwise.
            </para>
            <para>
              For the values and the displacement map see above.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <note>
        <para>
          For a plain, non neutral map, if displace mode <quote>Polar</quote>
          is enabled, this filter works like
          <link linkend="plug-in-whirl-pinch">Whirl and Pinch</link>.
        </para>
      </note>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Using gradient to bend a text</title>
    <para>Follow following steps:</para>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>Start with opening your image.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Duplicate this image. Activate this duplicate and make it
          gray-scaled
          (<menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>GrayScale</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>).
          Fill it with the wanted gradient. This image will be your
          <emphasis>Displacement map</emphasis>, with the dimensions of
          original image.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/2zinnias-c.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Activate original image. Create a <emphasis>Text Layer</emphasis>
          with your text. Set layer to image size: right-click on the layer
          in layer dialog and, in the pop-menu, click on <quote>Layer to
          image size</quote>. Note that letters in text layer lie on a
          transparent background; now this filter doesn't displace
          transparent pixels. Only letters will be displaced.
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/2zinnias-i.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Activate the text layer. Open the Displace filter window. Set
          parameters, particularly the displacement coefficient, according to
          the result in Preview. Click <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace5.png"
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>This method also applies to standard layers:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace6.png"
          format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>
        To get the wanted gradient, first draw a black to white gradient.
        Then use the <link linkend="gimp-tool-curves">Curves</link> tool to
        modify the gradient curve.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="plug-in-displace-calculation">
    <title>Displacement Calculation</title>
    <para>
      The following section will show you how to calculate the amount of
      displacement, if you are interested in these details. If you don't want
      to know it, you can safely omit this section.
    </para>
    <para>
      The overview example showed the X displacement using a coefficient of
      30.0: 19, 8, 4, or 15 pixels, depending on the grey level of the
      displacement map's color.
    </para>
    <para>Why just these amounts? That's easy:</para>
    <para>
      <informalequation>
        <alt role="latex">$30.0 * \frac{I - 127.5}{127.5} = D$</alt>
        <graphic fileref="images/math/displace1.png" format="PNG"/>
      </informalequation>
    </para>
    <para>
      <informalequation>
        <alt role="latex">$30.0 * \frac{210 - 127.5}{127.5} = 19$</alt>
        <graphic fileref="images/math/displace2.png" format="PNG"/>
      </informalequation>
    </para>
    <para>
      <informalequation>
        <alt role="latex">$30.0 * \frac{(160 - 127.5)}{127.5} = 8$</alt>
        <graphic fileref="images/math/displace3.png" format="PNG"/>
      </informalequation>
    </para>
    <para>
      <informalequation>
        <alt role="latex">$30.0 * \frac{(110 - 127.5)}{127.5} = -4$</alt>
        <graphic fileref="images/math/displace4.png" format="PNG"/>
      </informalequation>
    </para>
    <para>
      <informalequation>
        <alt role="latex">$30.0 * \frac{(60 - 127.5)}{127.5} = -15$</alt>
        <graphic fileref="images/math/displace5.png" format="PNG"/>
      </informalequation>
    </para>
    <para>
      If you check these equations, you will notice that the values they give
      are not exactly the results we retained in the example
      (using non-integers, that's not surprising). So, were the results
      rounded to the nearest integer and then the pixels were
      displaced by a whole-numbered amount? No. Every pixel is displaced
      exactly by the calculated amount; a <quote>displacement by a fractional
      amount</quote> is realized by interpolation. A closer look at the
      example image will show it:
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>A closer look at the displacement example</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/map-displace8.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>A small area zoomed in by 800 percent.</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The displacement causes small (one pixel wide) areas of intermediate
      colors at the edges of plain color areas. E.g., the black area (zoomed
      in image) is caused by a displacement of -4.12, so the intermediate
      color is 12% black and 88% gold.
    </para>
    <para>
      So if you select a displacement coefficient of 30.01 instead of 30.00,
      you will indeed get a different image, although you won't see the
      difference, of course.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
