<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-10-10 j.h: no change for v2.4
  2007-05-14 Added Spanish translation by AntI
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-edit-paste-into" lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;lt;no;zh_CN">
  <sect2info lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;no" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-27</date>
        <authorinitials>sally</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="cs">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-02-08</date>
        <authorinitials>jfriedl</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-10-15</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-05-14</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-07-03</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="no">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-02-09</date>
        <authorinitials>KoSt</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="cs">Vložit do</phrase>
    <phrase lang="en">Paste Into</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">In Auswahl einfügen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Pegar en</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Coller dans</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Incolla dentro</phrase>
    <phrase lang="lt">Įdėti į vidų</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Lim inn i</phrase>
    <phrase lang="zh_CN">粘贴进入</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer</primary>
    <secondary>Paste</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Selection</primary>
    <secondary>Paste</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Paste Into</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Vložit do</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Zwischenablage</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Capa</primary>
    <secondary>Pegar</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Selección</primary>
    <secondary>Pegar</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Pegar en</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Calque</primary>
    <secondary>Coller</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Sélection</primary>
    <secondary>Coller</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Coller dans</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Incolla dentro</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Sluoksnis</primary>
    <secondary>Įdėti</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt">
    <primary>Pažymėjimas</primary>
    <secondary>Įdėti</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="lt"><primary>Įdėti į vidų</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Lim inn i</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>粘贴进入</primary></indexterm>

  <para lang="cs">
    Příkaz vložit do se velmi podobá příkazu vložit. Rozdíl je patrný tehdy,
    pokud v obrázku existuje výběr. Zatímco příkaz Vložit podle výběru pouze
    vycentruje vkládaná data a starý výběr odstraní, příkaz Vložit do vkládaná
    data ořízne podle existujícího výběru. Vložený plovoucí výběr je normálně
    pohyblivý, ale vždy se ořízne podle původního výběru.
  </para>
  <para lang="cs">
    Pokud žádný výběr neexistuje, jsou vložená data umístěna do středu plátna,
    stejně jako v případě příkazu Vložit.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The <guimenuitem>Paste Into</guimenuitem> command acts in a similar way
    to the <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem> command. The primary difference
    becomes apparent if there is a selection within the canvas. Unlike the
    <quote>Paste</quote> command, which simply centers the pasted image
    data over the selection and replaces the selection with its own,
    <quote>Paste Into</quote> clips the pasted image data by the existing
    selection. The new selection can be moved as usual, but it is always
    clipped by the original selection area.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    If no selection exists, the <quote>Paste Into</quote> command places
    the data from the Clipboard into the center of the canvas, as the
    <quote>Paste</quote> command does.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Dieses Kommando wirkt ähnlich wie das Kommando <link
    linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Einfügen</link>. Der  Hauptunterschied
    kommt zum Vorschein, wenn eine Auswahl im Bild existiert. Bei Verwendung
    des Kommandos <quote>Einfügen</quote> würde das eingefügte Objekt
    in der Auswahl zentriert und die alte Auswahl mit einer dem
    eingefügten Objekt angepassten Auswahl ersetzt werden. Anders jedoch
    das Kommando <quote>In Auswahl einfügen</quote>. Dieses beschneidet das
    eingefügte Objekt auf die Maße der erstellten Auswahl. Die neue Auswahl
    kann ganz normal verschoben werden, der sichtbare Bereich wird aber immer
    auf den Bereich der ursprünglichen Auswahl beschnitten.
  </para>
  <para lang="de">
    Sollte keine Auswahl existieren, verhält sich das Kommando
    genau wie <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Einfügen</link>.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    El comando <guimenuitem>Pegar en</guimenuitem> actua de manera similar a
    el comando <guimenuitem>Pegar</guimenuitem>. La principal diferencia se
    hace visible si hay una selección en el lienzo. A diferencia del comando
    <quote>Pegar</quote>, que, simplemente, centra los datos de la imagen
    pegada sobre la selección y reemplaza el contenido,
    <quote>Pegar en</quote>, recorta los datos de la imagen pegada en la
    selección. La nueva selección se puede mover, pero, siempre, recortada
    por el área de la selección original.
  </para>
  <para lang="es">
    Si no hay selección, el comando <quote>Pegar en</quote> situa los datos
    del portapeles en el centro del lienzo, como hace el comando
    <quote>Pegar</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    La commande <quote>Coller dans</quote> fonctionne de la même façon que
    la commande Coller. Son originalité apparaît quand il existe une
    sélection sur le canevas. À la différence de Coller qui simplement
    centre le collage sur la sélection et vient l'écraser, <quote>Coller
    dans</quote> découpera le collage selon les limites de la sélection.
    La nouvelle sélection peut être déplacée normalement.
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Si aucune sélection n'existe, la commande placera les données du
    presse-papier au centre du canevas comme avec la commande Coller.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Il comando <guimenuitem>Incolla dentro</guimenuitem> agisce in maniera
    simile al comando <guimenuitem>Incolla</guimenuitem>. La principale
    differenza risulta visibile se c'è una selezione nelle aree
    disegnabili. A differenza del comando <quote>Incolla</quote>, che
    semplicemente centra i dati immagine incollati sulla selezione e ne
    rimpiazza i contenuti, <quote>Incolla dentro</quote> ritaglia i dati
    immagine nella selezione corrente. La nuova selezione può essere
    spostata come al solito, ma sempre con dentro ritagliata l'area di
    selezione originale.
  </para>
  <para lang="it">
    Se non esiste selezione, il comando <quote>Incolla dentro</quote>
    piazza i dati degli appunti al centro dell'area disegnabile, in maniera
    analoga al funzionamento del comando <quote>Incolla</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Komanda <guimenuitem>Įdėti į vidų</guimenuitem> veikia panašiai kaip ir
    komanda <guimenuitem>Įdėti</guimenuitem>. Pagrindinis skirtumas
    pasirodo, jeigu piešimo erdvėje yra pažymėjimas. Skirtingai nei komanda
    <quote>Įdėti</quote>, kuri paprasčiausiai įdeda paveikslėlio duomenis
    pažymėjimo centre ir pakeičia pažymėjimą šiais duomenimis, komanda
    <quote>Įdėti į</quote> prisega įdėtus paveikslėlio domenis prie esamo
    pažymėjimo. Naująjį pažymėjimą galima perkelti kaip paprastai, tačiau
    jis bus visada prisegtas prie originalios pažymėjimo srities.
  </para>
  <para lang="lt">
    Jeigu nėra pažymėjimo, komanda <quote>Įdėti į vidų</quote> padeda duomenis
    iš iškarpinės piešimo erdvės centre, kaip ir komanda <quote>Įdėti</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Kommandoen <guimenuitem>Lim inn i</guimenuitem> liknar nokså mykje
    på <guimenuitem>Lim inn</guimenuitem>. Den viktigaste skilnaden er at
    dersom det finst eit utval i biletet, vil <guimenuitem>Lim
    inn</guimenuitem> bruke dette for å sentrera det innlimte området,
    medan <guimenuitem>Lim inn i</guimenuitem> bruker det gjeldande
    utvalet som yttergrenser for det innlimte partiet. Du kan flytte rundt
    på det innlimte laget som vanleg, men bare den delen som er innføre det
    gjeldande utvalet er synleg.
  </para>
  <para lang="no">
    Dersom det ikkje finst noe utvald område i biletet, vil <quote>Lim inn
    i</quote> plassere utklippet sentrert i biletet på same måten som
    kommandoen <quote>Lim inn</quote> gjer det.
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    粘贴进入和粘贴很相似。如果底图上有一个选择区，两者将区别的很明显。粘贴是
    用粘贴数据的选择区代替旧的选择区，然后将数据贴在里面。粘贴进入则不同，它
    是将粘贴数据贴在已有的选择区。新选区可以正常移动，但是将始终保持原来的选
    择区域。
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    如果没有选择区存在，这个命令将按照粘贴命令的做法，将剪贴板数据粘贴在底图的中心。
  </para>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Activating the Command</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Aktivace dialogu</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Aufruf des Kommandos</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Activar el comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Appel de la commande</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Attivazione del comando</phrase>
      <phrase lang="lt">Komandos aktyvavimas</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Aktivering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">开启对话框</phrase>
    </title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="cs">
          Tento příkaz lze vyvolat z nabídky obrázku volbou
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Upravit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Vložit do</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          You can access this command from the image menubar through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Paste <accel>I</accel>nto</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
          Der Menüeintrag kann aus dem Bildfenster
          erreicht werden:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Bearbeite<accel>n</accel></guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>In Aus<accel>w</accel>ahl einfügen</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="es">
          Puede acceder a este comando desde el menú de la imagen:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>ditar</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Pegar <accel>e</accel>n</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          On accède à cette commande à partir de la barre de menu de l'image
          par
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>É</accel>diter</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Coller <accel>d</accel>ans...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="fr">
          Le nom anglais de cette commande est <quote>Paste into</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="it">
          È possibile accedere a questo comando attraverso la barra del
          menu immagine tramite
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>M</accel>odifica</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Incolla <accel>d</accel>entro</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="lt">
          Šią komandą galite aktyvuoti paveikslėlio meniu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>K</accel>eisti</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Įdėt<accel>i</accel> į vidų</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="no">
          Du får tilgang til denne undermenyen på biletmenyen via
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Rediger</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Lim inn i</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="zh_CN">
          这个命令可以在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;编辑/粘贴进入</guimenuitem>找到.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
