<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-11-23 ciampix: added Italian translation
  2007-10-26 ude: added German translation
  2007-10-15 j.h : created (inspired from the GIMP Developers site)
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-edit-fade">
  <title>Fade</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Fade</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    This command is usually grayed out. It becomes active if you use the Fill
    function or the Blend tool, or if you apply some filters.
  </para>
  <para>
    It allows you to modify the paint mode and opacity of the
    <emphasis>last</emphasis> drawable operation (Fill, Blend, Filter) by
    creating a blend between the current state of the layer and the previous
    state. It performs the following operations: copy the active drawable,
    undo the last action, paste the copy as a new layer, set its
    <quote>Opacity</quote>, and merge both new layer and previously active
    drawable.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activate the command</title>
    <para>
      You can get to this command from the image Menu bar through:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fade...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <para>
      This command brings up a dialog window:
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Fade</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/edit/fade-options.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This drop-down list allows you to choose a
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Layer merge mode</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Opacity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This slider value is initially set to the opacity of the color
            you used with the Fill or Blend tool, which corresponds to
            the current state. Lowering the opacity to 0 changes the drawable
            to its previous state. Intermediate values produce a mixture of
            the two according to the mode you have chosen. The effect of
            this setting is visible in real time in the image, but you have
            to click on the <guibutton>Fade</guibutton> button to validate
            it.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
