<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- Section history:
  2007-10-14 j.h: rearranged according to v2.4
  2007-05-14 Added Spanish translation by AntI
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-path-stroke">
  <title>Stroke Paths</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Paths</primary>
    <secondary>Stroke</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Stroke path</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Stroke Paths…</guimenuitem> command strokes a path in
    the image. There are two ways you can stroke the path, either by using
    a paint tool, or without using one. There are various options which you
    can use to specify how this stroke should look.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      This command is active only if there is a path in your image.
    </para>
  </note>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this command from the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Stroke Paths…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can also access it by clicking on the button with the same name
          in the <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths Dialog</link>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Description of the Dialog Window</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Choose Stroke Style</quote> dialog window</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/edit/stroke-path.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Choose Stroke Style</guilabel> dialog box allows you to
      choose between stroking the path with the <guibutton>Line</guibutton>
      options you specify or stroking it with a
      <guibutton>Paint tool</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Line</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Foreground color</term>
        <term>Background color</term>
        <term>Pattern</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Choose whether the line is drawn with the current
            <guilabel>Foreground color</guilabel> or
            <guilabel>Background color</guilabel> or
            <guilabel>Pattern</guilabel>, set in the Toolbox.
            This is distinct from the <guilabel>Dash pattern</guilabel>.
            If you select one of the two color options with no dash pattern,
            an unbroken line is drawn in the color set in the Toolbox.
            If you select Pattern with no dash pattern, an unbroken line
            is drawn with the pattern set in the Toolbox. If you select a
            line with a dash pattern, the color or pattern is still
            determined by the color or pattern set in the Toolbox. That is,
            if you have a marbled pattern set in the Toolbox, and select
            <guilabel>Pattern</guilabel> and dashed lines as
            <guilabel>Dash pattern</guilabel>, the dashes are drawn in the
            marbled pattern.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Antialiasing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Curved strokes or strokes drawn at an angle may look jagged
            or stair-stepped. The anti-aliasing option smooths them out.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Line width</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can set the width of the stroke using the text box.
            The default unit is pixels, but you can choose another
            unit with the drop-down list button.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id="gimp-path-stroke-styles">
        <term>Cap style</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Choose the shape of the ends of an unclosed path, which can
            be <guilabel>Butt</guilabel>, <guilabel>Round</guilabel>
            or <guilabel>Square</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Join style</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can choose the shape of the path corners by
            clicking on <guilabel>Miter</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Round</guilabel> or <guilabel>Bevel</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Miter limit</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When two segments of a path come together, the mitering of
            the corner is determined by the Miter Limit. If the strokes
            were wide, and no mitering were done, there would be pointed
            ends sticking out at the corner. The Miter Limit setting
            determines how the gap, formed when the outer edges of the
            two lines are extended, will be filled. You can set it to a
            value between 0.0 and 100.0, by using the slider or the
            associated text box and its arrows.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Example of miter limit</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/menus/edit/stroke-path-miter.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>Left image: Limit=0. Right image: Limit=5.</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dash pattern</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            On the pixel level, a dashed line is drawn as a series of
            tiny boxes. You can modify the pattern of these boxes. The
            black area with thin vertical lines represents the pixels of
            the dash. If you click on a black pixel, you remove it from
            the dash. If you click on a white pixel, you add it to the
            dash. The gray areas indicate how the pattern will be
            repeated when a dashed line is drawn.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dash preset</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Instead of making your own dash pattern, you can choose
            one from the drop-down box. This pattern will
            then be displayed in the <guilabel>Dash pattern</guilabel>
            area, so you can get an idea of how it will look.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Paint Tool</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Paint tool</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Select a paint tool to use from the drop-down box to draw the
            stroke. The current options of the paint tool options are used
            to draw the stroke.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Emulate brush dynamics</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            See <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush-dynamics">Brush
            Dynamics</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
