<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-08-19 AntI: added 'es'
  2007-04-12 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050930 de replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
  050830 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-deinterlace" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;ru">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-24</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-04-21</date>
        <authorinitials>ude</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-08-19</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-24</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Deinterlace</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Odstranit prokládání</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Entflackern</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Desentrelazado</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Désentrelacer</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Deinterlacciamento</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Fjern annakvar linje</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Убрать черезстрочность</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Enhance</secondary>
    <tertiary>Deinterlace</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Deinterlace</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Odstranit prokládání</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary><secondary>Verbessern</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Entflackern</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Interlace</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Deinterlace</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Filtros</primary>
    <secondary>Realzar</secondary>
    <tertiary>Desentrelazado</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Desentrelazado</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Amélioration</secondary>
    <tertiary>Désentrelacer</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Désentrelacer</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary><secondary>Miglioramento</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Deinterlacciamento</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Forbetre</secondary>
    <tertiary>Fjern annakvar linje</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fjern annakvar linje</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Deinterlace</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Фильтр</primary><secondary>Усилить</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Убрать черезстрочность</primary></indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="it;ru">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/options-enhance-deinterlace.png"
        format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata
        fileref="../images/filters/cs/filters-enhance-deinterlace.png"
        format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Přehled</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Wirkungsweise</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Generalidades</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Oversyn</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="de;it;ru">
      <!-- FIXME all: This example has no interest: we need an interlaced
            original image -->
      <title>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Anwendungsbeispiel für das Filter <quote>Entflackern</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di applicazione del filtro Deinterlacciamento
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Изображение до и после применения фильтра <quote>Убрать
            черезстрочность</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="en;de">
          <para lang="en">
            Original image (although without interlace effects)
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Originalbild (allerdings ohne Interlace-Effekt)
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/examples/enhance-taj-deinterlace.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="en;de">
          <para lang="en">Filter <quote>Deinterlace</quote> applied</para>
          <para lang="de">Filter <quote>Entflackern</quote> angewandt</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Enhance</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Deinterlace</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Images captured by videocards, especially when fast movement is
      recorded, may look blurred and stripped, with splitted objects. This is
      due to how cameras work. They don't record 25 images per second, but 50,
      with half vertical resolution. There are two interlaced images in one
      frame. First line of first image is followed by first line of second
      image followed by second line of first image... etc. So, if there have
      been an important move between the two images, objects will appear
      splitted, shifted, stripped.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Deinterlace filter keeps only one of both images and replaces
      missing lines by a gradient between previous and following lines. The
      resulting image, or selection, will be somewhat blurred, but can be
      improved by enhance filters
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can find interlaced images at
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr naleznete v nabídce
      <guimenuitem>Obrázek&gt;Filtry/Vylepšení/Odstranit prokládání</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Obrázky zachycené videokartami, zvláště při záznamu rychlého pohybu,
      mohou vypadat rozmazaně a pruhované. Je to zapříčiněno principem funkce
      kamery. Ty nenahrávají 25 obrázků za sekundu, ale 50, s polovičním
      vertikálním rozlišením. V každém filmovém políčku jsou tedy dva obrázky.
      První řádek prvního obrázku je následovaný prvním řádkem druhého
      obrázku, za kterým následuje druhý řádek prvního obrázku… atd. Proto,
      pokud se mezi zachycením obou obrázků odehrál významný pohyb, vypadají
      objekty jako rozložené do proužků.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr Odstranění prokládání zachová pouze jeden z obou obrázků a
      chybějící řádky doplní postupným přechodem mezi sousedními řádky.
      Výsledný obrázek bude lehce rozmazaný, lze jej však dále vylepšit pomocí
      dalších filtrů.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Testovací obrázek najdete na stránce
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para lang="de">
      Bilder, die aus Videomaterial gewonnen werden, enthalten, besonders wenn
      sie aus einer Szene mit schnellen Bewegungen stammen, oftmals horizontale
      Streifen und unscharfe Objektkanten. Dies resultiert aus der Art, wie
      viele Kameras arbeiten. Diese erfassen oftmals nicht 25 Vollbilder pro
      Sekunde, sondern 50 Bilder im sogenannten Halbbildverfahren. Dabei
      wird zunächst ein Bild mit der halben vertikalen Auflösung erfasst und
      gleich darauf ein zweites Bild ebenfalls mit halber vertikaler
      Auflösung. Diese beiden Halbbilder werden dann zu einem Vollbild
      zusammengesetzt. Wenn es aber in der Zeit zwischen den beiden
      aufgenommenen Halbbildern Bewegungen im Bild gab, so werden diese
      Stellen unscharf und fehlerhaft dargestellt. Normalerweise ist das
      menschliche Auge zu träge, um in einem Video diese Fehler wahrzunehmen.
      Wird aber ein einzelnes Bild extrahiert, ist der Effekt deutlich zu
      erkennen.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Filter extrahiert eines der beiden Halbbilder wieder aus dem
      zusammengesetzten Vollbild und ersetzt die fehlende vertikale Auflösung
      durch eine Zeilenverdopplung. Dabei werden die fehlenden Bildstellen
      interpoliert. Dies führt zu einer etwas unscharfen Darstellung, die
      aber durch weitere Filter verbessert werden kann.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      In der
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>
      finden Sie ein Testbild.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Puede encontrar este filtro en
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtros</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Realzar</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Desentrelazado</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Las imágenes capturadas con targetas de video, especialmente, cuando se
      graba un movimiento rápido, puede parecer desenfocado y estriado, con
      objetos partidos. Esto se debe a como funcionan las cámaras. No graban
      25 imágenes por segundo, pero si 50, con una media resolución vertical.
      Hay dos imágenes entrelazadas en un cuadro. La primera línea de la
      primera imagen es seguida por la primera línea de la segunda imagen
      seguida por la segunda línea de la primera imagen... etc. Así, si hay
      un importante movimiento entre las dos imágenes, los objetos aparecerán
      partidos, escalados, estriados.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El filtro desentrelazado solo mantiene una de las imágenes y se
      reemplazan las líneas perdidas por un degradado entre las líneas previa
      y siguiente. La imagen resultante, o selección, será desenfocada en
      algún lugar, pero puede ser mejorada con los filtros realzar.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      Puede encontrar imágenes entrelazadas en 
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      On accède à ce filtre par
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Amélioration</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Désentrelacer</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les images capturées par carte vidéo, surtout quand un mouvement rapide
      est enregistré, peuvent paraître floues, striées de fines bandes
      horizontales, avec des objets dédoublés. Cela est dû au mode de
      fonctionnement des caméras qui n'enregistrent pas 25 images par seconde,
      mais 50 images par seconde en demi-résolution verticale, ces deux images
      étant entrelacées en une seule. La première ligne de la première image
      est suivie de la première ligne de la seconde image suivie de la
      deuxième ligne de la première image...etc. Ainsi, s'il y a eu un
      déplacement important entre les deux images, les objets apparaîtront
      dédoublés, décalés, striés.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Désentrelacer conserve une seule des deux images et remplace
      les lignes manquantes par un dégradé entre la précédente et la suivante.
      L'image, ou la sélection, résultante apparaît un peu floue, mais peut
      être améliorée par les filtres de netteté.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Vous trouverez une image d'entrelacement sur
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
      (Le Wikipedia français n'offre pas d'image d'entrelacement).
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro si trova nel menu Immagine sotto
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filt<accel>r</accel>i</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>iglioramento</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>D</accel>einterlacciamento</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Le immagini dalle schede di acquisizione video, specialmente quando si
      registrano movimenti veloci, possono sembrare confuse, a strisce e con
      oggetti tagliuzzati. Ciò è dovuto al funzionamento delle videocamere.
      Esse non registrano 25 fotogrammi al secondo ma 50 a risoluzione
      verticale dimezzata. Ci sono due immagini interlacciate nel primo
      fotogramma. La prima linea della prima immagine è seguita dalla prima
      linea della seconda immagine e così via. Quindi se c'è stato un
      movimento evidente tra le due immagini gli oggetti in movimento
      appariranno tagliuzzati, spostati a strisce.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il filtro di deinterlacciamento preserva solo una delle due immagini e
      rimpiazza le linee mancanti con un passaggio graduale tra la linea
      precedente e quella seguente. L'immagine risultante o la selezione
      risulterà in qualche modo sfumata ma a ciò si può rimediare con i filtri
      di miglioramento.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Una immagine di test si può trovare su
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du har tilgang til filteret frå biletmenyen via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Forbetre</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fjern annakvar linje</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Stillbilete som er laga på grunnlag av eit videobilete vil ofte sjå litt
      forstyrra ut, med både uklare område og uventa striper. Dette er
      særleg synleg ved raske rørsler. Årsaka ligg i måten videobileta er
      sett saman på. For å unngå flimring, blir bileta på skjermen teikna
      på nytt 25 gonger i sekundet. På eit biletrøyr blir teikninga utført ved
      å føre ein tynn elektronstråle vassrett over skjermen og såleis teikne
      linje for linje nedover. Andre skjermar arbeider annleis, men alle
      teikner linjer på ein eller annan måte. Videokameraet tar 50 bilete per
      sekund og viser to bilete samstundes. Linje 1 frå bilete nr. 1, linje 2 frå
      bilete nr. 2, linje 3 frå bilete 1 osv. annakvar gong. Medan bilete nr. 1 blir
      teikna, står bilete nr. 2 fast, og omvendt. Dersom det nå har skjedd
      større forandringar i mellomtida, kan dette føre til synlege hakk eller
      striper i biletet.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Filteret fjerner annankvar linje i biletet, altså det eine av desse to
      bileta. Tomrommet blir utfylt med fargeovergangar mellom to
      nærliggande linjer. Resultatet blir litt uklart, men som oftast betre
      enn originalen. Dessutan kan det nye biletet ofte forbetrast ved hjelp
      av eigna filter. (Prosessen med å flette saman to bilete blir ofte kalla
      <quote>interlace</quote> og den funksjonen filteret utfører blir
      difor ofte kalla <quote>deinterlace</quote>).
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Du kan finne eit testbilete for å prøve ut filteret på adressa
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр находится в меню
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Фильтры</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Усилить</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Убрать черезстрочность</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Изображения, взятые видеокартами, выглядят нечётко, особенно при быстром
      движении на экране. Это обусловленно тем, как работает камера. Камеры
      записывают сигнал 50 раз в секунду и с худшим вертикальным разрешением.
      При показе, два кадра совмещаются в один чередованием линий растра.
      Первая линия берётся из первого изображения, вторая - из второго, третья
      - опять из первого, и т.д. Если было быстрое движение между двумя
      кадрами, то движущийся объект будет разрезан по линиям.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Фильтр <quote>Убрать черезстрочность</quote> сохраняет только одно из
      изображений, заполняя пробелы градиентом между предыдущей и
      следующей строкой. Полученное изображение будет слегка нечётким, но это
      можно улучшить другими фильтрами усиления.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Изображение для испытания находится здесь:
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deinterlace">Wikipedia</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3 lang="de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Filteraufruf</phrase>
    </title>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter lässt sich über das Menü
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>V</accel>erbessern</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>E</accel>ntflackern</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      im Bildfenster aufrufen.
    </para>
  </sect3>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;no">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Deinterlace filter options
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften für das Filter <quote>Entflackern</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Opciones del filtro desentrelazado
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Options du filtre Désentrelacer
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for filteret <quote>Fjern annakvar linje</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;es">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/options-enhance-deinterlace.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/de/options-enhance-deinterlace.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/fr/options-enhance-deinterlace.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/no/options-enhance-deinterlace.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="cs">Náhled</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="es">Vista previa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <term lang="it">Anteprima</term>
        <term lang="no">Førehandsvising</term>
        <term lang="ru">Просмотр</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When <guilabel>Do preview</guilabel> is checked, parameter
            setting results are interactively displayed in preview.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Pokud je zaškrtnuta volba <guilabel>Náhled</guilabel>,
            zobrazuje se výsledek nastavení filtru interaktivně v náhledu.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In der Vorschau wird ein Ausschnitt des Bildes so dargestellt,
            als wäre das Filter mit den aktuellen Einstellungen auf das Bild
            angewandt worden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Cuando <guilabel>vista previa</guilabel> está marcada, los
            parámetros seleccionados se muestran interactivamente en la vista
            previa.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Quand l'option <guilabel>Effectuer l'aperçu</guilabel> est
            cochée, le résultat du réglage des paramètres est affiché en
            temps réel dans l'aperçu.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Quando la casella <guilabel>Anteprima</guilabel> è selezionata,
            l'effetto delle opzioni è mostrato interattivamente nell'anteprima.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Førehandsvisinga syner forandringane før du legg dei inn i biletet.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Когда выбран <guilabel>Просмотр</guilabel>, просмотр
            обновляется по мере изменения параметров.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mode</term>
        <term lang="cs">Režim</term>
        <term lang="de">Erhalte gerade / ungerade Zeilen</term>
        <term lang="es">Modo</term>
        <term lang="fr">Mode</term>
        <term lang="it">Modalità</term>
        <term lang="no">Behald ... felt</term>
        <term lang="ru">Режим</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Keep odd lines</guilabel> and <guilabel>Keep even
              lines</guilabel>: One of them may render a better result.
            You must try both.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Zachovat lichá pole</guilabel> a <guilabel>Zachovat sudá
              pole</guilabel>: Jedna z voleb může poskytovat lepší výsledky.
            Vyzkoušejte proto obě.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Hier können Sie auswählen welches der beiden Halbbilder erhalten
            bleiben soll. Probieren Sie beide aus.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <guilabel>Mantener los campos impares</guilabel> y 
            <guilabel>Mantener los campos pares</guilabel>: Uno de ellos
            puede producir mejores resultados. Debe intentar ambos.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Garder les lignes impaires</guilabel> et
            <guilabel>Garder les lignes paires</guilabel>: L'une ou
            l'autre de ces options peut être meilleure. Vous devez
            essayer les deux.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <guilabel>Mantieni linee dispari</guilabel> e <guilabel>Mantieni
              linee pari</guilabel>: Una di queste opzioni può portare ad un
            risultato migliore. Si dovrebbero provare entrambi.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            <guilabel>Behald odde linjer</guilabel> og <guilabel>Behald like
            linjer</guilabel>: Odde linjer er linje nr. 1, 3, 5 osv, like linjer er
            linje nr. 2, 4, 6 osv. Det er uråd å seie kva for eit val som gir best
            resultat. Du må prøve deg fram.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            <guilabel>Сохранить нечётные поля</guilabel> и
            <guilabel>Сохранить чётные поля</guilabel>: Один из них
            может произвести результат лучше другого. Необходимо
            испытать оба режима.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 lang="en;de;es;fr;no">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Example</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Beispiel</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Ejemplo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Exemple</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Esempio</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Eksempel</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;no">
      <!--interlace.xcf exists in images/filters/examples if you want to
          perform other tests-->
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Simple applying example for the Deinterlace filter
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          <!-- "Anwendungsbeispiel" und "Wirkungsweise" sind schon vergeben -->
          Dem Filter <quote>Entflackern</quote> bei der Arbeit zugeschaut
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Ejemplo de aplicación del filtro desentrelazado
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Exemple simple d'application du filtre Désentrelacer
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Eit lite eksempel på verknadane av filteret
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/interlaced.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            Top : even lines pixels are shifted by one pixel to the right.
            Bottom : one line is missing. These images are zoomed to show
            pixels.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Die Pixel in einigen geraden Zeilen sind um ein Pixel nach rechts
            verschoben. Unten fehlt eine Zeile.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Arriba : los píxeles de las líneas pares se han movido un píxel a
            la derecha. Abajo : una línea se ha perdido. Se han aumentado
            estas imágenes para mostrar los píxeles.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            En haut, décalage des pixels des lignes paires d'un pixel vers la
            droite. En bas, une ligne manquante. Ces images sont zoomées pour
            montrer les pixels.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Topp : Pikslane i like linjer er skifta med ein piksel mot høgre.
            Botn : Ei linje manglar. (Bileta er forstørra for å vise pikslane).
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/deinterlaced-1.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <quote>Keep even fields checked</quote>.
            Top : odd lines have been shifted to the right, to align
            themselves with the even lines. Bottom: the empty line has been
            filled with red.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <guilabel>Erhalte gerade Zeilen</guilabel> aktiviert: Die
            betreffenden ungeraden Zeilen wurden an den geraden Zeilen
            ausgerichtet und nach rechts verschoben. Die unten fehlende Zeile
            wurde mit Rot aufgefüllt.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <quote>Mantener los campos pares</quote>.
            Arriba : las líneas impares se han movido a la derecha, para
            alinearlas con las pares. Abajo: la línea vacia se ha alineado
            rellenada con rojo.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <quote>Garder les lignes paires</quote> cochée.
            En haut, décalage des pixels des lignes impaires d'un pixel
            vers la droite pour s'aligner sur les lignes paires. En bas, la
            ligne manquante a été comblée par du rouge.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Avkryssa for <guilabel>Behald like linjer</guilabel>.
            Topp : Odde linjer er skift mot høgre for at dei skal bli på linje
            med dei like linjene.
            Botn: Den tomme linja er fylt med raudt.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/deinterlaced-2.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <quote>Keep odd fields</quote> checked.
            Top : even lines have been shifted to the left, to align
            themselves with the odd lines. Bottom: the empty line persists,
            but joins up and down through a gradient.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            <guilabel>Erhalte ungerade Zeilen</guilabel> aktiviert: Die
            betreffenden geraden Zeilen wurden an den ungeraden Zeilen
            ausgerichtet und nach links verschoben. Die fehlende Zeile unten
            bleibt erhalten, wird aber durch einen Farbverlauf mit der Zeile
            darüber bzw. darunter verbunden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <quote>Mantener los campos pares </quote> marcados.
            Arriba : las líneas pares se mueven a la izquierda, para
            alinearse con las impares. Abajo: las líneas vacias persisten,
            pero se unen arriba y abajo con un grandiente.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <quote>Garder les lignes paires</quote> cochée.
            En haut, décalage des pixels des lignes paires d'un pixel
            vers la gauche, pour s'aligner sur les lignes impaires. En bas,
            la ligne manquante persiste, raccordée au reste par un dégradé.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Avkryssa for <guilabel>Behald odde linjer</guilabel>.
            Topp : Like linjer er skift mot venstre for at dei skal bli på linje
            med dei odde linjene.
            Botn: Den tomme linja er der framleis, men er nå glatta ut.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
