<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-08-19 AntI: added 'es'
  2007-04-15 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050930 de replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
  050831 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-sharpen" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;no;ru">
  <sect2info lang="en;de;es;fr" role="cvs">
    <revhistory>
      <revision lang="en">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-26</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="de">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-04</date>
        <authorinitials>lexa</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="es">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2007-08-19</date>
        <authorinitials>AntI</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision lang="fr">
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>2006-11-26</date>
        <authorinitials>j.h</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </sect2info>

  <title>
    <phrase lang="en">Sharpen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="cs">Doostřit</phrase>
    <phrase lang="de">Schärfen</phrase>
    <phrase lang="es">Enfocar</phrase>
    <phrase lang="fr">Augmenter les contrastes</phrase>
    <phrase lang="it">Aumenta contrasto</phrase>
    <phrase lang="no">Gjer skarpare</phrase>
    <phrase lang="ru">Повышение резкости</phrase>
  </title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Enhance</secondary>
    <tertiary>Sharpen</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Sharpen</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Doostřit</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="de">
    <primary>Filter</primary><secondary>Verbessern</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Schärfen</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="es">
    <primary>Filtros</primary>
    <secondary>Realzar</secondary>
    <tertiary>Enfocar</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Enfocar</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="fr">
    <primary>Filtres</primary>
    <secondary>Amélioration</secondary>
    <tertiary>Augmenter les contrastes</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Augmenter les contrastes</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="it">
    <primary>Filtri</primary><secondary>Miglioramento</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Aumenta contrasto</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="no">
    <primary>Filter</primary>
    <secondary>Forbetre</secondary>
    <tertiary>Gjer skarpare</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Gjer skarpare (filter)</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm lang="ru">
    <primary>Фильтр</primary><secondary>Усилить</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ru"><primary>Повышение резкости</primary></indexterm>


  <mediaobject lang="it;ru">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/filters-enhance-sharpen.png"
        format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/cs/filters-enhance-sharpen.png"
        format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>


  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Overview</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Přehled</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Wirkungsweise</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Generalidades</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Généralités</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Panoramica</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Oversyn</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Общая информация</phrase>
    </title>

    <para lang="en">
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Enhance</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sharpen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Most of digitized images need correction of sharpness. This is due to
      digitizing process that must chop a color continuum up in points with
      slightly different colors: elements thinner than sampling frequency
      will be averaged into an uniform color. So sharp borders are rendered
      a little blurred. The same phenomenon appears when printing color dots
      on paper.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Sharpen filter accentuates edges but also any noise or blemish and
      it may create noise in graduated color areas like the sky or a water
      surface. It competes with the Unsharp Mask filter, which is more
      sophisticated and renders more natural results.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr naleznete v nabídce
      <guimenuitem>Obrázek&gt;Filtry/Vylepšení/Doostřit</guimenuitem>
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Většina digitalizovaných obrázků vyžaduje upravení ostrosti. Vzhledem
      k procesu digitalizace, během kterého dochází ke vzorkování plynulého
      obrazu do jednotlivých pixelů, jsou objekty v obrázku menší než vzorkovací
      frekvence zprůměrovány do jednolité barvy. Ostré hrany jsou proto
      vykresleny poněkud rozmazaně. Ke stejnému jevu dochází při tisku
      barevných teček na papír.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr Doostřit zvýrazňuje hrany, ale také případný šum či jiné vady.
      Může též vytvořit šum v oblastech přecházejících barev, například na
      obloze nebo vodní hladině. Ke stejné funkci slouží filtr Rozostřit
      masku, který je složitější, ale poskytuje přirozenější výsledky.
    </para>

    <para lang="es">
      Puede encontrar este filtro en
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtros</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Realzar</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Enfocar</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      La mayoria de las imágenes digitalizadas necesitan corregir el
      contraste. Esto se debe a que en el proceso de digitalización  se debe
      recortar la continua subida de color en puntos con colores ligeramente
      diferentes: los elementos más tenues que la frecuencia de muestreo se
      calcularán en un color uniforme promedio. Los bordes se representan un
      poco borrosos. El mismo fenómeno aparece cuando se imprimen puntos de
      colores sobre papel.
    </para>
    <para lang="es">
      El filtro enfocar acentua los bordes pero también cualquier ruido o
      mancha podría crear ruido en áreas graduales de color como el cielo o
      una superficie de agua. Compite con el filtro máscara de desenfoque,
      que es más sofisticado y produce resultados más naturales.
    </para>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no;ru">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          Applying example for the Sharpen filter
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Anwendungsbeispiel für das Filter <quote>Schärfen</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Ejemplo de aplicación del filtro enfocar
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="it">
          Esempio di applicazione del filtro Aumenta contrasto
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Exemple d'application du filtre Renforcer les contrastes
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">Eksempel på bruk av filteret</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Изображение до и после применения фильтра <quote>Повышение
          резкости</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="de;no">
          <para lang="de">Originalbild</para>
          <para lang="no">Originalbilete</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../images/filters/examples/enhance-taj-sharpen.jpg"
            format="JPG" />
        </imageobject>
        <caption lang="de;no">
          <para lang="de">Filter angewandt</para>
          <para lang="no">
            Etter bruk av filteret <quote>Gjer skarpare</quote>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="de">
      Die meisten digitalisierten Bilder benötigen eine Korrektur der Schärfe.
      Dies resultiert aus den technischen Gegebenheiten dieses Vorganges, bei
      dem ein kontinuierliches Farbspektrum auf ein diskretes abgebildet
      werden muss. Elemente, welche kleiner als die Abtastfrequenz sind,
      werden mit Durchschnittsfarbe gefüllt. Dabei werden scharfe Kanten
      zwangsläufig weichgezeichnet. Der gleiche Effekt tritt auf, wenn farbig
      gedruckt wird.
    </para>
    <para lang="de">
      Das Filter verstärkt die Kanten, aber auch ein möglicherweise im Bild
      vorhandenes Rauschen. Dies kann sogar dazu führen, dass nach der
      Anwendung des Filters ein Rauschen sichtbar wird, welches zuvor
      scheinbar nicht vorhanden war. Alternativ können Sie auch das
      Filter <link linkend="plug-in-unsharp-mask">Unscharf Maskieren</link>
      in Betracht ziehen. Dieses ist exakter steuerbar und liefert damit
      oftmals bessere Ergebnisse.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      On accède à ce filtre par
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Amélioration</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Augmenter les contrastes</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La plupart des images numérisées nécessitent une correction de la
      netteté. Cela tient au processus de numérisation qui doit découper un
      continuum de teintes en points de teintes légèrement différentes: des
      éléments plus fins que la fréquence d'échantillonnage seront moyennés
      dans un pixel uniforme. Ainsi les limites nettes deviennent un peu
      floues. Le même phénomène se reproduit lors de l'impression sur papier
      des points colorés.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Augmenter les contrastes, accentue les bords mais aussi les
      imperfections, et il risque même de créer du bruit dans les aires de
      couleurs graduées comme le ciel ou des effets de rides sur l'eau. Il
      est en compétition avec le filtre Renforcer la netteté, qui, plus
      perfectionné, donne des résultats plus naturels.
    </para>

    <para lang="it">
      Questo filtro si trova nel menu Immagine sotto
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filt<accel>r</accel>i</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>M</accel>iglioramento</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>A<accel>u</accel>menta contrasto</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      La maggior parte delle immagini digitalizzate necessitano di una correzione
      del contrasto. Ciò è dovuto al processo di digitalizzazione che deve
      spezzettare una gamma continua di colori in intervalli di colori lievemente
      differenti: intervalli più piccoli della frequenza di campionamento saranno
      mediati in un colore uniforme. Quindi bordi netti sono resi leggermente
      sfocati. Lo stesso fenomeno si verifica quando si stampano punti di colore
      su carta.
    </para>
    <para lang="it">
      Il filtro Aumenta contrasto accentua i bordi ma anche ogni tipo di rumore
      o imperfezione e può creare del disturbo in aree con sfumature graduali
      come il cielo o uno specchio d'acqua. E' paragonabile al filtro Maschera di
      contrasto che però è più sofisticato e produce risultati più naturali.
    </para>

    <para lang="no">
      Du har tilgang til filteret frå biletmenyen via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Forbetre</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Gjer skarpare</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dei aller fleste digitale bileta treng å skjerpast. Dette fordi
      digitalteknikken deler alt opp i punkt. Fargane blir delte opp i
      fargepunkt i staden for kontinuerlege fargeovergangar slik det ofte
      er i naturen. Dersom fargeskilnadane i eit område er mindre enn den
      såkalla <quote>samplingsfrekvensen</quote>, vil alle fargepunkta i
      området bli eit gjennomsnitt av alle fargane der. Skarpe kantar blir
      litt uskarpe. Det same kan du sjå når fargane blir skrivne ut på papir.
    </para>
    <para lang="no">
      Dette filteret gjer kantane skarpare, men forsterkar også eventuell
      støy som måtte finnast i biletet. Filteret kan også generere støy i
      flater med små fargevariasjonar som t.d. ein himmel eller ei
      vassflate. I mange tilfelle vil du få eit betre og meir naturleg resultat
      med filteret <link
      linkend="plug-in-unsharp-mask">Uskarpmaske</link>.
    </para>

    <para lang="ru">
      Этот фильтр находится в меню
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Фильтры</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Усилить</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Повышение резкости</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Большинство оцифрованных изображений нуждаются в правке резкости. Это
      происходит из-за того, что процесс оцифровки преобразует аналоговую
      цветную шкалу в точки с слегка отличающимися цветами: элементы меньше
      чем частота выборки усредняются в однотонный цвет. Так, чёткие края
      становятся размытыми. То же происходит при распечатке цветных пятен на
      бумаге.
    </para>
    <para lang="ru">
      Фильтр <quote>Повышение резкости</quote> делает края более
      подчёркнутыми, но также любой шум и дефект в таких более или менее
      однотонных областях как небо и поверхность воды. Этот фильтр
      противостоит фильтру <quote>Нерезкая маска</quote>, который производит
      более натуральные результаты.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 lang="de">
    <title>
      <phrase lang="de">Filteraufruf</phrase>
    </title>
    <para lang="de">
      Dieses Filter lässt sich über das Menü
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ilter</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu><accel>V</accel>erbessern</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>chärfen</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      im Bildfenster aufrufen.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      <phrase lang="en">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="cs">Volby</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Eigenschaften</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Opciones</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Options</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Opzioni</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Innstillingar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ru">Параметры</phrase>
    </title>

    <figure lang="en;de;es;fr;no;ru">
      <title>
        <phrase lang="en">
          <quote>Sharpen</quote> filter options
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="de">
          Eigenschaften für das Filter <quote>Schärfen</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="es">
          Opciones del filtro <quote>Enfocar</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="fr">
          Options du filtre <quote>Augmenter les contrastes</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="no">
          Innstillingane for filteret <quote>Gjer skarpare</quote>
        </phrase>
        <phrase lang="ru">
          Параметры фильтра <quote>Повышение резкости</quote>
        </phrase>
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject lang="en;es;ru">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/options-enhance-sharpen.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="de">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/de/options-enhance-sharpen.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="fr">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/fr/options-enhance-sharpen.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject lang="no">
          <imagedata fileref="../images/filters/no/options-enhance-sharpen.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="cs">Náhled</term>
        <term lang="de">Vorschau</term>
        <term lang="es">Vista previa</term>
        <term lang="fr">Aperçu</term>
        <term lang="it">Anteprima</term>
        <term lang="no">Førehandsvising</term>
        <term lang="ru">Просмотр</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Parameter setting results are interactively displayed in preview.
            Scroll bars allow you to move around the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Nastavení parametrů filtru se interaktivně zobrazují v náhledu.
            Pomocí posuvníků můžete přesouvat náhled do jiných částí obrázku.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            In der Vorschau wird ein Ausschnitt des Bildes so dargestellt,
            als wäre das Filter mit den aktuellen Einstellungen auf das Bild
            angewandt worden.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            Los resultados de la selección de parámetros se muestran
            interactivamentes en la vista previa. Las barras de
            desplazamiento permiten moverse por la imagen.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le résultat du réglage des paramètres est affiché en temps réel
            dans l'aperçu. Les glissières de déplacement permettent de
            naviguer dans l'image.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            Questa anteprima mostra interattivamente i cambiamenti provocati
            dalla regolazione dei parametri prima che essi vengano applicati
            all'immagine. Le barre di scorrimento consentono di muoversi
            sull'immagine.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Førehandsvisinga syner endringane i biletet før dei blir lagt til
            i biletet ved å trykke på knappen <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            Окно просмотра обновляется по мере изменения параметров. Полосы
            прокрутки позволяют двигаться по всему изображению.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Parameter setting</term>
        <term lang="cs">Nastavení parametrů</term>
        <term lang="de">Schärfe</term>
        <term lang="es">Configuración</term>
        <term lang="fr">Réglage des paramètres</term>
        <term lang="it">Regolazione dei parametri</term>
        <term lang="no">Grad</term>
        <term lang="ru">Параметры</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Increase sharpness</guilabel>: slider and input boxes
            allow you to set sharpness (1-99) and you can judge result in
            preview. By increasing sharpness, you may increase image
            blemishes and also create noise in graduated color areas.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            <guilabel>Ostrost</guilabel>: posuvník a vstupní pole umožňující
            nastavit zvýšení ostrosti v rozsahu 1 až 99. Výsledek si pečlivě
            prohlížejte v náhledu, neboť zvýšením ostrosti můžete zvýraznit
            vady v obrázku nebo vytvořit šum v oblastech s přecházejícími
            barvami.
          </para>
          <para lang="de">
            Mit diesem Schieberegler können Sie die Stärke der Filterwirkung
            im Bereich von 1 bis 99 einstellen. Durch eine Erhöhung der
            Schärfe kann der oben beschriebene Effekt auftreten, dass in
            einigen Bereichen ein Rauschen auftritt.
          </para>
          <para lang="es">
            <guilabel>Agudeza</guilabel>: el deslizador y la caja de entrada
            permiten seleccionar el contraste (1-99) y se puede valorar el
            resultado en la vista previa. Al incrementar el contraste, se
            puede incrementar las imperfecciones de la imagen y también el
            ruido en las áreas graduales de color.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Augmentation du contraste</guilabel>: Le curseur et
            les boîtes de saisie permettent de régler la netteté (1-99), ce
            que vous appréciez dans l'Aperçu. En augmentant le contraste,
            vous risquez d'augmenter les imperfections de l'image et aussi
            des bruits parasites dans les zones faiblement nuancées.
          </para>
          <para lang="it">
            <guilabel>Aumenta contrasto</guilabel>: il cursore e la casella di
            testo consentono di impostare l'aumento del contrasto (1-99), si può
            valutare il risultato nell'anteprima. Aumentando il contrasto si
            potrebbero evidenziare le imperfezioni dell'immagine e creare
            disturbo nelle aree con sfumature grauali di colore.
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            Denne glidebrytaren blir brukt for å setje styrken på skjerpinga på
            ein skala frå 1 til 99. Dess høgare verdi dess skarpare bilete, men
            derme også kanskje meir tilført støy.
          </para>
          <para lang="ru">
            <guilabel>Повысить резкость</guilabel>: Ползунок и поля ввода
            позволяют определить резкость (1-99). Чем выше резкость, тем
            больше проявится  дефектов в изображении и шума в
            плавно-изменяющихся цветных районах.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
