<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2018-12-01 j.h: rename to Sharpen (Unsharp mask). Fix issue #88
  2006-12-17 Added a sect3 to explain Unsharp Mask by j.h
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-filter-unsharp-mask">
  <title>Sharpen (Unsharp Mask)</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Enhance</secondary>
    <tertiary>Sharpen (Unsharp Mask)</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Sharpen (Unsharp mask)</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Applying example for the Sharpen filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/enhance-taj-unsharp-mask.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>Sharpen</quote> applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Out-of-focus photographs and most digitized images often need a
      sharpness correction. This is due to the digitizing process that has
      to divide a color continuum in points with slightly different colors.
      Elements smaller than the sampling frequency will be averaged into a
      uniform color. So sharp borders will be rendered a little blurred. The
      same phenomenon appears when printing color dots on paper.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Sharpen filter (previously called Unsharp Mask) sharpens edges of the
      elements without increasing noise or blemish.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para>
        Some imaging devices like digital cameras or scanners offer to sharpen
        the created images for you. We strongly recommend you disable this
        means of sharpening and use <acronym>GIMP</acronym> filters instead.
        This way you regain the full control over the sharpening of your images.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
      To prevent color distortion while sharpening, you can
      <link linkend="plug-in-decompose">Decompose</link> your image to
      <guilabel>HSV</guilabel> and work only on <guilabel>Value</guilabel>.
      Go to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Components</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Decompose…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Make sure the <guilabel>Decompose to Layers</guilabel>
      box is checked. Choose HSV and click OK. You will get a new gray-level
      image with three layers, one for Hue, one for Saturation, and one for
      Value. (Close the original image so you won't get confused). Select
      the Value layer and apply your sharpening to it. When you are done,
      with that same layer selected, reverse the process by using
      <link linkend="plug-in-compose">Compose</link>.
      Go to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Components</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Compose…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Again choose HSV and click OK. You will get back your original image
      except that it will have been sharpened in the Value component.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Filter</title>
    <para>
      This filter is found in the main menu under
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Enhance</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Sharpen (Unsharp Mask)…</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title><quote>Sharpen</quote> filter options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/enhance/sharpen-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Presets</term>
        <term><quote>Input Type</quote></term>
        <term>Clipping</term>
        <term>Blending Options</term>
        <term>Preview</term>
        <term>Merge filter</term>
        <term>Split view</term>
        <listitem>
          <xi:include href="../about-common-features.xml"/>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Radius</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The slider and input boxes (0.0-1500.0) allow you to set how many
            pixels on either side of an edge will be affected by sharpening.
            It is better to always sharpen an image at its final resolution.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Amount</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This slider and input boxes (0.0-300.0) allow you to set the
            strength of sharpening.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Threshold</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This slider and input boxes (0.0-1.0) allow you to set the minimum
            difference in pixel values that indicates an edge where sharpen
            must be applied. So you can protect areas of smooth tonal
            transition from sharpening, and avoid creation of blemishes in
            face, sky or water surface.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>How does an unsharp mask work?</title>
    <para>
      Using an unsharp mask to sharpen an image can seem rather weird. Here is
      the explanation:
    </para>
    <para>
      Think of an image with a contrast in some place. The intensity curve of
      the pixels on a line going through this contrast will show an abrupt
      increase of intensity: like a stair if contrast is perfectly sharp (blue),
      like an S if there is some blur (yellow).
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/unsharp-mask-1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Now, we have an original image with some blur (black curve) we want to
      sharpen. We apply some more blur: the intensity variation will be
      more gradual (green curve).
    </para>
    <para>
      Let us subtract the difference between blurredness intensity (green
      curve) and the intensity of the original image (black curve) to the
      intensity of the original image (black curve). We get the red
      curve, which is more abrupt: contrast and sharpness are increased. QED.
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/unsharp-mask-2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
      Unsharp mask was first used in silver photography. The photographer
      first creates a copy of the original negative by contact, on a film,
      placing a thin glass plate between both; that will produce a blurred
      copy because of light diffusion. Then both films are placed in a photo
      enlarger, to reproduce them on paper. The dark areas of the positive
      blurred film, opposed to the clear areas of the original negative will
      prevent light to go through and so will be subtracted from the light
      going through the original film.
    </para>

    <procedure>
      <para>
        In digital photography, with GIMP, you will go through the following
        steps:
      </para>
      <step>
        <para>
          Open your image and duplicate it
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Duplicate</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          In the copy, duplicate the layer
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Duplicate layers</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>, then from the Filters menu apply
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Blur</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Gaussian Blur</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          to the duplicated layer with the default IIR option and radius 5.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          In the Layers dialog of the duplicated image, change Mode to
          <quote>Subtract</quote>, and in the right-click menu, select
          <quote>Merge down</quote>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click and drag the only layer you got into the original image, where
          it appears as a new layer.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Change the Mode in this Layers dialog to <quote>Addition</quote>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <para>
      Voilà. The <quote>Unsharp Mask</quote> plug-in does the same for you.
    </para>
    <para>
      At the beginning of the curve, you can see a dip. If blurring is
      important, this dip is very deep; the result of the subtraction can be
      negative, and a complementary color stripe will appear along the
      contrast, or a black halo around a star on the light background of a
      nebula (black eye effect).
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Black eye effect</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/unsharp-mask-3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
