<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-31 j.h: minor changes
  2008-12-29 j.h: link to File-references to be fixed
  2007-10-17 j.h: updated to v2.4 (comment)
  2006-09-19 lexa: minor change (link enabled)
  2006-07-03 changed the note by j.h
  2006-06-17 added a para for default image size by j.h
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-file-new">
  <title>New…</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>New</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>New</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>New Image</primary>
  </indexterm>


  <para>
    Using the <quote>Create a New Image</quote> dialog, you can
    create a new empty image and set its
    properties. The image is shown in a new image window.
    You may have more than one image on your screen at the same time.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access this command from the main menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>New…</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          or by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The <quote>Create a New Image</quote> dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/file/new/advanced-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Template</primary>
        <secondary>Menu</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Image</primary>
        <secondary>Image size</secondary>
        <tertiary>When creating</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Image size</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Template</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rather than entering all the values by hand, you can select some
            predefined values for your image from a menu of templates, which
            represent image types that are somewhat commonly useful. The
            templates set values for the size, resolution, comments, etc. If
            there is a particular image shape that you use often and it
            does not appear on the list, you can create a new template, using
            the <link linkend="gimp-template-dialog">Templates</link> dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Here you set the <guilabel>Width</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>Height</guilabel> of the new image.  The
            default units are pixels, but you can choose a different
            unit if you prefer, using the adjoining menu. If you do,
            note that the resulting pixel size is determined by
            the X and Y resolution (which you can change in the
            <guilabel>Advanced Options</guilabel>), and by setting
            <quote>Dot for Dot</quote> in the
            <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu.
          </para>
          <para>
            If no image is open, the <quote>New</quote> image is opened in
            the empty image window, with the default size you have determined.
            If you open the <quote>New</quote>image when another is open (or
            has been), then it is opened in another window, with the same
            size as the first image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Portrait/Landscape buttons</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Portrait/Landscape mode</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            These buttons toggle between Portrait and Landscape mode.
            Their effect is to exchange the values for <guilabel>Width</guilabel>
            and <guilabel>Height</guilabel>. If the X and Y resolutions are
            different (in Advanced Options), then these values are also
            exchanged. On the right, image size, image resolution and
            color space are displayed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <sect4>
      <title>Advanced Options</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Precision</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>8-bit, 16-bit, 32-bit</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Advanced Options</guilabel>
        are mostly of interest to more advanced <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        users. You can display these options by clicking on the small triangle
        on the lower edge of the dialog window. Note that you will need to scroll
        down to see all the available options.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Image</primary>
          <secondary>Resolution</secondary>
          <tertiary>Setting when creating</tertiary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Resolution</primary>
          <secondary>Setting when creating</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>X and Y resolution</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The values in the <guilabel>X resolution</guilabel> and
              <guilabel>Y resolution</guilabel>
              fields relate mainly to printing: they do not affect the size of
              the image in pixels, but they may determine its physical size when
              it is printed. The X and Y resolution values can determine how
              pixels are translated into other measurement units, such as
              millimeters or inches.
            </para>
            <tip>
              <para>
                If you want to display the image on the screen at the
                correct dimensions, select
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>View</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Dot for Dot</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
                Set the zoom factor to 100% to see the image at its true
                screen size. The calibration of the screen size is normally
                done when <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is installed,
                but if the image does not display at the correct size,
                you may have to adjust the screen parameters in
                <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You can do this in
                the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-display">Preferences</link>
                dialog.
              </para>
            </tip>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Color space</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can create the new image in different
              <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">color modes</link>, as either an
              <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link> image or a grayscale image.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>RGB color</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The image is created in the Red, Green, Blue color system,
                    which is the one used by your monitor or your television
                    screen.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Grayscale</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    The image is created in black and white, with various shades
                    of gray. Aside from your artistic interests, this type of
                    image may be necessary for some plug-ins. Nevertheless,
                    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows you to
                    <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-grayscale">change an RGB
                    image into grayscale</link>, if you would like.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>
              You cannot create an indexed image directly with this menu, but of
              course you can always convert the image to indexed mode after it
              has been created. To do that, use the
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Mode</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Indexed</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> command.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Precision</term>
          <!--From www.gimpusers.com/tutorials/whats-new-in gimp-2-10-->
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This setting lets you define the encoding used to store pixel
              information. For more details, please see the
              <link linkend="gimp-image-choosing-precision-encoding">
              Image Encoding</link> section.
            </para>
            <para>
              Five options are available:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    8-bit integer
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    16-bit integer
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    32-bit integer
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    16-bit floating point
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    32-bit floating point
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
              If you wonder what the difference is between integer and floating
              point (in the graphics area): If you have an image with 16-bit
              integer precision per channel, then you have 65,536 shades of
              different red, green and blue color tones – all of them equally
              stepped to each other (equal color distance). If you have it in
              floating point, then there are no equal-wide steps – so you can
              distribute the possible color values over selected ranges. For
              example: if you know that you have a very dark image with many
              shades of dark red color tones then you would benefit from floating
              point because you can decrease the importance of the brighter color
              tones and get most color detail out of only the darker reds.
            </para>
            <figure>
              <title>Precision example</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/menus/file/new/precision.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    Left image is 8-bit, right is 32-bit. You can see that there
                    are much more available colors between color transitions on
                    the right image.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Gamma</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Here you can choose the
              <link linkend="glossary-channel-encoding">channel encoding</link>
              for your image. Choices are <guilabel>Non-linear</guilabel> and
              <guilabel>Linear light</guilabel>.
              For 8-bit integer precision the default is Non-linear, and for
              32-bit floating point precision it is Linear light. For more
              information see
              <link linkend="gimp-image-choosing-precision-encoding">which
              precision options should you choose</link>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Color profile</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Here you can choose a color profile to be used for your image.
              The default is GIMP's standard color profile based on
              <guilabel>Color space</guilabel>, <guilabel>Precision</guilabel>,
              and <guilabel>Gamma</guilabel>.
              If you prefer to use a different color profile you can select an
              ICC color profile file from a location on your computer by
              choosing <guilabel>Select color profile from disk…</guilabel>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Soft-proofing color profile</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can attach a CMYK color profile to the image with this option.
              This profile will be used to create a soft-proofed display of the
              image when the <guilabel>Proof Colors</guilabel> option is enabled
              in the <guilabel>View</guilabel> menu.
              As with the <guilabel>Color Profile</guilabel>, if you prefer to use
              a different color profile you can select an ICC color profile file
              from a location on your computer by choosing
              <guilabel>Select color profile from disk…</guilabel>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Soft-proofing rendering intent</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This option lets you select the rendering intent that will be used
              to convert the colors from the soft-proofed image to your display
              device when
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>View</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Color Management</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Proof Colors</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>
              is enabled. The four intents are <quote>Perceptual</quote>,
              <quote>Relative colorimetric</quote>, <quote>Saturation</quote>
              and <quote>Absolute colorimetric</quote>.
              See <xref linkend="gimp-prefs-color-management"/> and
              <xref linkend="gimp-image-color-management"/> for more information.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Use Black Point Compensation</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              When enabled, the BPC algorithm attempts to adjust the display of
              darker areas in the image when the <guilabel>Proof Colors</guilabel>
              option is enabled in the <guilabel>View</guilabel> menu.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Fill with</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Here, you specify the background color that is used for your new
              image. It is certainly possible to change the background of an
              image later, too. You can find more information about doing that
              in the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <para>There are several choices:</para>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fill the image with the current <guilabel>Foreground
                  color</guilabel>, shown in the Toolbox.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Note that you can change the foreground color while the
                  <quote>New Image</quote> dialog window is open.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fill the image with the current <guilabel>Background
                  color</guilabel>, shown in the Toolbox. (You can change the
                  background color too, while the dialog window is open.)
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fill the image with <guilabel>Middle Gray (CIELAB)</guilabel>.
                  This will create a layer with a gray color that is 50% of perceptual
                  lightness in the selected <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">color mode</link>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fill the image with <guilabel>White</guilabel>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fill the image with <guilabel>Transparency</guilabel>. If you
                  choose this option, the image is created with an <link
                  linkend="glossary-alpha-channel">alpha&nbsp;channel</link> and
                  the background is transparent. The transparent parts of the
                  image are then displayed with a checkered pattern, to indicate
                  the transparency.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Fill the image with a <guilabel>Pattern</guilabel>. If you
                  choose this option, the image is filled with the currently
                  active pattern (which you can change while this dialog is open).
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Comment</term>
          <listitem>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Image</primary>
              <secondary>Comment</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Comment</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>
              You can write a descriptive comment here. The text is
              attached to the image as a
              <link linkend="glossary-parasite">parasite</link>, and is saved
              with the image by some file formats (PNG, JPEG, GIF).
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                You can view and edit this comment in the
                <link linkend="gimp-image-properties">Image Properties</link>
                dialog.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
