<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2088-12-22 j.h: updated to v2.6
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-02-07 Added 'no' by KoSt
  2006-02-26 j.h:  Added Right click -> Open location-Changed left pannel en;fr
  2005/10/18 zh_CN removed by romanofski - missing translation
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-file-open">
  <title>Open</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Open</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Open</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> command activates a dialog that lets
    you load an existing image from your hard-drive or an external medium.
    For alternative, and sometimes more convenient, ways of opening files, see
    the following commands (<xref linkend="gimp-file-open-as-layer"/> etc.).
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activate Dialog</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can access the <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> dialog
          from an image window through:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can also open the Dialog by using the keyboard shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>File browsing</title>

    <figure>
      <!--OLD: file-open-dialog.xcf.gz in src/images/menus-->
      <!--2.6: file-open.xcf.gz in src/images/menus-->
      <title>Open Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/menus/file/open.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      This browser looks like other browsers and it is mostly
      self-explanatory. It has some particuliar features nevertheless.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><!--1-->
        <para>
          The button <guibutton>Type a file name</guibutton> toggles between
          add and remove the <guilabel>Location</guilabel> text box.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>
          key combination has the same action as this button.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--2-->
        <para>
          In the <guilabel>Location</guilabel> text box you can type a path to
          an image file. If you don't type any path, the name of the selected
          file will be displayed. You can also type the first letters of the
          name: it will be auto-completed and a list of file names beginning
          with these letters will be displayed.
        </para>
        <para>
          When you search for a file or directory using the
          <guilabel>Search</guilabel> feature (see below, item 4), the label
          changes to <guilabel>Search</guilabel> and you can enter the name in
          this text box.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <!--
      <listitem><!-OLD 3->
        <para>
          <guibutton>Create a folder</guibutton> button: this button lets
          you add a new folder in the current folder. For some strange
          reason, this button is not always present and you can't remove
          this new folder.
        </para>
        XXX: Probably "Create folder" is only visible if you *save* a file
        - using the "Save Image" dialog.
      </listitem>
      -->

      <listitem><!--3-->
        <para>
          The path to the current folder is displayed. You can navigate along
          this path by clicking on an element.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--4-->
        <para>
          With <guilabel>Search</guilabel> you can look for a file (or
          directory), even if you don't know the exact name of that file.
          Click on <guilabel>Search</guilabel>, type a file name or just a
          part of a file name in the text box above, and press
          <keycap>Enter</keycap>. Then the central frame (7) will list all
          files and directories of your home directory with names containing
          the text you typed in. Unfortunately you can't restrict the results
          to files of a specified type (10). 
        </para>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Recently used</guilabel> is self-explanatory.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--5-->
        <para>
          Here, you can access to your main folders and to your store devices.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--6-->
        <para>
          Here, you can add bookmarks to folders, by using the
          <guibutton>Add</guibutton> or the <guilabel>Add to
          Bookmarks</guilabel> option you get by right-clicking a folder in
          the central panel, and also remove them.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--7-->
        <para>
          The contents of the selected folder is displayed here. Change your
          current folder by double left clicking on a folder in this
          panel. Select a file with a single left click. You can then open
          the file you have selected by  clicking on the
          <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button.
          A double left click opens the file directly. Please note that you
          can open image files only.
        </para>
        <para>
          Right-clicking a folder name opens a context menu:
        </para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/menus/file/open/folder-context-menu.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>The folder context menu</caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--8-->
        <para>
          The selected image is displayed in the <guilabel>Preview</guilabel>
          window. If it is an image created by <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, file
          size, resolution and image composition are displayed below the
          preview window.
        </para>

        <tip>
          <para>
            If your image has been modified by another program, click on the
            Preview window to update it.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--9-->
        <para>
          By clicking the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button, you add the
          selected folder to bookmarks.
        </para>
        <para>
          By clicking the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>, you remove the
          selected bookmark from the list.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--10-->
        <para>
          You will generally prefer to display the names of
          <guilabel>All images</guilabel>. You can also select
          <guilabel>All files</guilabel>. You can also limit yourself to
          a particular type of image (GIF, JPG, PNG ...).
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><!--11-->
        <para>
          <guilabel>Select File Type</guilabel>: In most cases you
          don't need to pay any attention to this, because
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can determine the file type
          automatically. In a few rare situations, neither the file
          extension nor internal information in the file are enough to tell
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> the file type. If this happens,
          you can set it by selecting it from the list.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
