<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-introduction-history'>
  <title lang="en">Gimp History</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">History</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang = "en">
    According to Peter Mattis and Spencer
    Kimball, the original creators of Gimp, in their announcement of
    Gimp 0.54: 
  </para>

  <para>
    The Gimp arose from the ashes of a hideously crafted cs164
    (compilers) class project. The setting: early morning. We were
    both weary from lack of sleep and the terrible strain of
    programming a compiler in LISP. The limits of our patience had
    long been exceeded, and yet still the dam held. 
  </para>

  <para>
    And then it happened. Common LISP messily dumped core when it
    could not allocate the 17 MB it needed to generate a parser for a
    simple grammar using yacc. An unbelieving moment passed, there was
    one shared look of disgust, and then our project was vapor. We had
    to write something...ANYTHING...useful. Something in C. Something
    that did not rely on nested lists to represent a bitmap. Thus, the
    Gimp was born. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Like the phoenix, glorious, new life sprung out of the burnt
    remnants of LISP and yacc. Ideas went flying, decisions were made,
    the Gimp began to take form. 
  </para>

  <para>
    An image manipulation program was the consensus. A program that
    would at the very least lessen the necessity of using commercial
    software under `Windoze' or on the `Macintoy.' A program that
    would provide the features missing from the other X painting and
    imaging tools. A program that would help maintain the long
    tradition of excellent and free UNIX applications. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Six months later, we've reached an early beta stage. We want to
    release now to start working on compatibility issues and
    cross-platform stability. Also, we feel now that the program is
    actually usable and would like to see other interested programmers
    developing plug-ins and various file format support. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Version 0.54 was released in February 1996, and had a major impact
    as the first truly professional free image manipulation
    program. This was the first free program that could compete with
    the big commercial image manipulation programs. 
  </para>


  <para>
    Version 0.54 was a beta release, but it was so stable that you
    could use it for daily work. However, one of the major drawbacks
    of 0.54 was that the toolkit (the slidebars, menus, dialog boxes,
    etc.)  was built on Motif, a commercial toolkit. This was a big
    drawback for systems like Linux, because you had to buy Motif if
    you wanted to use the faster, dynamically linked Gimp. Many
    developers were also students running Linux, who could not afford
    to buy Motif.  
  </para>

  <para>
    When 0.60 was released in July 1996, it had been under S and P
    (Spencer  and  Peter) development for four months. Main programming
    advantages were the new toolkits, GTK (Gimp Toolkit) and gdk (Gimp
    Drawing Kit), which eliminated the reliance on Motif. For the
    graphic artist, 0.60 was full of new features like: basic layers;
    improved painting tools (sub-pixel sampling, brush spacing); a
    better airbrush; paint modes; etc.
  </para>


  <para>
    Version 0.60 was only a developer's release, and was not intended
    for widespread use. It served as a workbench for 0.99 and the
    final 1.0 version, so functions and enhancement could be tested
    and dropped or changed. You can look at 0.60 as the alpha version
    of 0.99.
  </para>

  <para>
    In February 1997, 0.99 came on the scene. Together with other
    developers, S and P had made several changes to Gimp and added even
    more features. The main difference was the new API and the PDB,
    which made it possible to write scripts; Script-Fus (or macros)
    could now automate things that you would normally do by
    hand. GTK/gdk had also changed and was now called GTK+. In
    addition, 0.99 used a new form of tile-based memory handling that
    made it possible to load huge images into Gimp (loading a 100 MB
    image into Gimp is no problem). Version 0.99 also introduced a new
    native Gimp file format called XCF. 
  </para>

  <para>
    The new API made it really easy to write extensions and plug-ins
    for Gimp. Several new plug-ins and extensions emerged to make Gimp
    even more useful (such as SANE, which enables scanning directly
    into Gimp). 
  </para>

  <para>
    In the summer of 1997, Gimp had reached version 0.99.10, and S and P
    had to drop most of their support since they had graduated and
    begun jobs. However, the other developers of Gimp continued under
    the orchestration of Federico Mena to make Gimp ready for
    primetime. 
  </para>

  <para>
    GTK+ was separated from Gimp in September 1997. GTK+ had been
    recognized as an excellent toolkit, and other developers began
    using it to build their own applications. 
  </para>

  <para>
    Gimp went into feature freeze in October 1997. This meant that no
    new features would be added to the Gimp core libraries and
    program. GUM version 0.5 was also released early in October
    1997. The developing work continued to make Gimp stable and ready
    for version 1.0.
  </para>

  <para>
    Gimp version 1.0 was released on June 5, 1998. Finally, Gimp was
    considered stable enough to warrant a worldwide announcement and
    professional use.
  </para>

</sect1> 
 
