<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="gimp-introduction-whats-new">
  <title>What's New in GIMP 2.8? </title>
  
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.8 is an another important release from a
    development point of view, even more that it was for 2.6. It
    features a big change to the user interface addressing one of the
    most often received complain: the missing of a single windowing
    mode. Morover the integration effort of GEGL library had taken a
    big step forward, reaching more the 90% of the
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core, a new powerful transformation tool,
    layer groups, new common options, new brushes, improved text tool,
    and more.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>User Interface</title>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>New single window mode</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          With this new feature it will be possible to work with all
          the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> dialogs inside one big window,
          usually with the image(s) centered inside.  No more floating
          panels or toolbox but the dialogs could be arranged inside
          this single window.  This mode could be enabled or disabled
          all the time, even while working, and the option will be
          remembered through the sessions.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>The new look of the single window mode</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="images/using/single-window-mode.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry>
      <term>New file save workflow</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Now Save and Save as works only with xcf formats. If you
	  want to export an image in another format, say jpg or png,
	  you have to explicitly Export it. This enhance the workflow
	  and let you simple overwrite the original file or export to
	  various other formats.
         </para>
        <figure>
          <title>The new image workflow</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/save-image-overwrite.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>New image bar</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          With the new single window mode comes a new useful image bar
          that lets you switch easily between open images through the
          means of a tab bar with the miniature of the images. 
         </para>
        <figure>
          <title>The new image bar</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/multiple-image-tabs.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>New arrangement options</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will make high resolution monitor
	  owners happy: now it is possible to arrange the dialogs one
	  over the other, in tabs and in colums too.
         </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Multi column docks</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/multi-column-docks.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>New resources tags</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Brushes, Gradients, Pattern and
	  Palettes can be filtered and searched via tags. Tags are
	  text labels that the user can assign to resources. With Tags
	  the user can easily find the resources by means of a input
	  text box. Tags can be manually assigned by the user with the
	  same input box used for search tags, or they can be
	  automatically tagged using the directory name of the
	  imported items.
         </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Resource tags</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/painting-resources-tags.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Simple math in size entries</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Enhancements have also been made to the size entry widget,
	  which is used for inputting most of the x, y, width, height
	  parameters. For example, in the scale dialog it is now
	  possible to write <quote>50%</quote> in the Width field to
	  scale the image to 50% of the width. Expressions such as
	  <quote>30in + 40px</quote> and <quote>4 * 5.4in</quote>
	  work, too.
         </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Math size entries</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/math-size-entries.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Minor changes</term>
      <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The new <quote>Lock Pixels</quote> option in the layers
	    dialog can avoid undesired painting on a layer when
	    switching between them.
	  </para>
	  <figure>
	    <title>The new Lock Pixels option</title>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata format="PNG"
			   fileref="images/using/image-lock-pixels.png"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Now is possible to move between images in single and multi
            windows mode using the shortcuts
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>
            or
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Number</keycap></keycombo>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Add support for F2 to rename items in lists.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    You can now
	    <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Click</keycap></keycombo>
	    on layers in the Layers dialog to create a selection from
	    it. Add, subtract and intersect modifiers
	    <keycap>Click</keycap>, <keycap>Shift</keycap> and
	    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
	    keys work too. This makes it easy to compose contents of a
	    layer based on the contents of other layers, without
	    detours.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Since the keyboard shortcuts
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
            and
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
            have been repurposed for the image export mechanisms, new
            keyboard shortcuts have been setup for <quote>Shrink
            Wrap</quote> and <quote>Fit in Window</quote>, namely
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>J</keycap></keycombo>
            and
            <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>J</keycap></keycombo>
            respectively.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Added
            <menuchoice><guimenu>Windows</guimenu><guimenuitem>Hide
            docks</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item that does what
            <quote>Tab</quote> does and also displays its state, which
            is now persistent across sessions, too.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    The layer modes have been rearranged into more logical and
	    useful groups based on the effect they have on compositing
	    of a layer. Layer modes that make the composite lighter
	    are in one group, layer modes that make the composite
	    darker in another group, and so forth.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Allow closing the toolbox without closing the whole
	    application.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Removed Toolbox from list of Recently Closed Docks, handle
	    that directly in the Windows menu.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    New docks are created at the pointer position. 
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Allow binding arbitrary actions to extra mouse buttons.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Now it is possible to change the application language
	    directly from the preference menu.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Tools, Filters and Plug-ins</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>A new tool: Cage Transform</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          With this new tool is now possible to create custom bending
          of a selection just moving its vector frame control points.
          This is the result of one of our Google Summer of Code 2010
          students.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Cage Transform</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/new-cage-tool.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Improved Text Tool</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The text tool has been enhanced to support in-place text
          writing and the possibility to change the single char
          attributes.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Improved text tool</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/improved-text-tool.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>New layer groups</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It is now possible to group set of layers and treat them
          like a entity. It is possible to switch a group on or off an
          to move the group in the layers dialog. It is easy to add /
          remove existings layers to a group or to create / delete a
          layer inside the group and it is even possible to create
          nested groups of groups. To a group is possible apply a
          layer mode as it was with a single layer. All this greatly
          improve the workflow with complex multilayer images making
          them easier to manage.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>New layer groups</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/image-layer-groups.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Rotating brushes</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Brushes can now be rotated at will, acting on the brush
	  option <quote>Angle</quote>.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Rotating brushes</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/rotating-brushes.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Minor changes</term>
      <listitem>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
	      The default Quick Mask color is now configurable.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      The text tool improved the RTL mode.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Allow specifying the written language in the Text
	      Tool. This helps with choosing an appropriate font, or
	      appropriate glyphs for the selected language.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added optional diagonal guides to the crop tool.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added <quote>Rule of fifths</quote> crop guide overlay.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      A Cairo based PDF exporter was implemented. While being
	      somewhat simplistic the exporter saves text, embedding
	      fonts into the final PDF file, and attempts to convert
	      all flat filled areas to vector objects.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added support arbitrary affine transforms of brushes. 
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added plug-in for loading JPEG2000 images. 
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added added plug-ins for X11 Mouse Cursor import and
	      export support.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added fundamental OpenRaster (.ora) import and export
	      support.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      Added RGB565 support to the csource plug-in.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
	      A Web-page plug-in was added to render any web page into
	      an image using Webkit.
            </para>
          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Under the Hood</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><acronym>GEGL</acronym></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The porting of the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> core towards the
          new high bit-depth and non-destructive editing GEGL <xref
          linkend="bibliography-online-gegl"/> library has done big
          steps and now more than 90% of the task is already finished.
        </para>
        <para>
          In addition to porting color operations to
          <acronym>GEGL</acronym>, an experimental GEGL Operation tool
          has been added, found in the Tools menu. It enables applying
          <acronym>GEGL</acronym> operations to an image and it gives
          on-canvas previews of the results. The screenshot below
          shows this for a Gaussian Blur.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title><acronym>GEGL</acronym> operation</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/experimental-gegl-tool.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>

      <term>Cairo porting</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Started with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 2.6, it is now
	  completed the port to <xref
	  linkend="bibliography-online-cairo"/> of all tools rendering
	  on canvas. It provide smooth antialiased graphics and update
	  the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> look &amp; feel. All but a few
	  plug-ins have been upgraded to Cairo as well. Additionally
	  all tools now use an on-canvas progress indicator instead of
	  the one in the statusbar.
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Progress indicator</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/using/cairo-progress-indicator.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>

    <title>Miscellaneous</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>License change</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  The GIMP license has been changed to (L)GPLv3+.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>New script API</term>
      
      <listitem>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      A lot of GIMP APIs have been refactored to simplify
	      developing new scripts.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      To further enhances its scripting abilities, have been made
	      API changes to support layer groups.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Backwards Compatibility</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    To address the needs to migrate from the old tools presets
	    system to the new one there is a Python <ulink
	    url="http://wiki.gimp.org/index.php/Mindstorm:Preset_converter">script</ulink>
	    downloadable from the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> wiki
	    site. However, the old tools presets are not 100%
	    convertible to the new tool presets. For instance, brush
	    scale from 2.6 can't be converted to brush size in 2.8.
          </para>
        </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
      <term>Known Problems</term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Working with graphics tablets could be problematic due to
	  the GTK+2 library in use. If in this case either use the
	  older version 2.6 or wait for the up coming version 3.0
	  for the full GTK+3 support.
	</para>
      </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  </variablelist>

</sect1>
