<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-introduction-whats-new' lang="en;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">What's New in The GIMP?</title>
  <title lang="fr">Quoi de neuf dans Gimp?</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">GIMP 的新特性</title>

  <para lang='en'>
    GIMP 1.0 evolved gradually into the very stable and widely used
    1.2 release. Three years later, as the GIMP development came closer
    to the next stable release, they decided that
    the level of fundamental change to the inner workings of the
    program justified calling the new stable version 2.0.  GIMP
    2.0.0 was released on March 23, 2004.  For GIMP 2.2, the
    developers aimed at a short cycle, adding a number of important
    features that did not require instability-inducing low level
    changes.  GIMP 2.2.0 was released on December 19, 2004.  This
    section briefly describes the new features that were added in
    GIMP 2.2, as well as the features that were introduced in GIMP
    2.0. 
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
    Gimp 1.0 a évolué progressivement vers la version stable 1.2 largement 
    répandue. Trois ans plus tard, l'équipe de développement a estimé que 
    Gimp était à nouveau proche de la stabilité et présentait suffisamment 
    de changements pour justifier une nouvelle version stable 2.0. Voyons 
    quels sont ces améliorations. 
  </para>
  <para lang="zh_CN">
    GIMP 1.0 慢慢发展为非常稳定和被广泛使用的 1.2 版本。三年后，当 GIMP 的开发临近下一次稳定版的发行时，它们再三衡量觉得对程序内部基本功能修改的程度已经可以叫作 2.0 版本了。GIMP 2.0.0 最终在 2004 年 5 月 23 号发行。对于 GIMP 2.2，开发者们的目标是在一个短周期，增加一些重要的特性，它们不需要可能导致不稳定的对最底层代码的改变。GIMP 2.2.0 在 2004 年 12 月 19 号发行。该章节将简要地介绍 GIMP 2.2 中添加的特性。
  </para>

  <sect2 lang='en;zh_CN'>
    <title lang='en'>New in GIMP 2.2</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">GIMP 2.2 的新特性</title>
    <para lang='en'>
      Here is a brief summary of some of the most important
      new features introduced in GIMP 2.2.  There are many other
      smaller changes that long-time users will notice and appreciate
      (or complain about!).  There are also important changes at the
      level of plugin programming and script-fu creating that are not
      covered here.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      这里是关于 GIMP 2.2 的一些最重要特性的简明摘要。许多长期使用的用户会发现和称赞(或报怨)的比较小的变化，以及关于插件编程和 Script-Fu 创建方面的重要改变就没有包含在这里了。
    </para>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Interoperability and standards support</title>
      <title lang="zh_CN">互用性和标准支持</title>
      <para lang='en'>
        You can drag-and-drop or copy-and-paste image data from the GIMP
        to any application which support image/png drops (currently
        <application>Abiword</application> is the only one we know of)
        and image/xml+svg drops 
        (<application>Inkscape</application> supports this one). So
        you can copy-and-paste curves 
        into the GIMP from Inkscape, and then drag a selection into
        Abiword to include it inline in your document.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您可以在 GIMP 和其它支持图像/PNG接入的程序(当前只知道 <application>Abiword</application>)以及支持图像/xml+svg接入的程序(当前只知道 <application>Inkscape</application>)中拖放或粘贴拷贝图像数据。这样您可以从 Inkscape 中拷贝粘贴曲线到 GIMP 中，然后拖动一个选区到 Abiword 中使其插入到您的文档中。
      </para>

      <para lang='en'>
        Patterns can now be any <code>GtkPixbuf</code> supported
        format, including png, jpeg, xbm and others. 
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        图案可以是任何 <code>GtkPixbuf</code> 所支持的格式，包括 png, jpeg, xbm 和其它。
      </para>
        
      <para lang='en'>
        GIMP can load gradients from SVG files, and palettes from ACT
        and RIFF files. 
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        GIMP 能从 SVG 文件中加载渐变，从 ACT 和 RIFF 文件中加载色板。
      </para>

      <para lang='en'>
        Drag-and-drop support has been extended. You can now drop file
        and URIs onto an image window, where they will be opened in
        the existing image as new layers. 
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        拖放支持被扩展。现在您可以拖放文件和 URI 到图像窗口中，它们会作为现有图像的一个新图层被打开。
      </para>
    </simplesect>
   
    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Shortcut editor</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>快捷键编辑器</title>
      <para lang='en'>
        You can now edit your shortcuts in a dedicated dialog, as well
        as continue to use the little-known dynamic shortcuts feature
        (which has been there since 1.2). 
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        现在您能够在专门的对话框中编辑您的快捷键，同时还可以继续使用鲜为人知的动态快捷键功能(自从 1.2 版本以来该功能就存在)。
      </para>
    </simplesect>
   
    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Plug-in previews</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>插件预览</title>
      <para lang='en'>
        We have provided a standard preview widget for plug-in authors
        which greatly reduces the amount of code required to support
        previews. David Odin has integrated this widget into all the
        current filters, so that now many more filters in the GIMP include
        a preview which updates in real time, and the various previews
        behave much more consistently. 
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        我们提供给插件作者标准的预览构件，它可以极大地减少需要支持预览的代码数量。David Odin 将该构件整合到当前所有的滤镜中，这样 GIMP 的许许多多滤镜就包含可以实时更新的预览，并且这些预览的表现也更加统一。
      </para>
    </simplesect>
   
    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Real-time previews of transform operations</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>变换操作的实时预览</title>
      <para lang='en'>
        The transform tools (shear, scale, perspective and rotate) can
        now show a real-time preview of the result of the operation when
        the tool is in "Traditional" mode.  Previously, only a
        transforming grid was shown.
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        现在当变换工具(切变，缩放，透视和旋转)呈“传统”模式时，它们可以显示操作结果的实时预览。以前只有变换网格时才会显示。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>GNOME Human Interface Guide conformance</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>遵循 GNOME 人机界面手册</title> 
      <para lang='en'>
        A lot of work has been done on making the GIMP's interface
        simpler and more usable for newcomers. Most dialogs now
        follows the GNOME HIG to the best of our knowledge. In
        addition, dialogs have separated out or removed many
        "Advanced" options, and replaced them with sane defaults or
        hidden them in an expander. 
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        我们做了许多工作简化 GIMP 的界面并使其对新手有更高的可用性。大部分对话框都尽量遵循 GNOME HIG。另外许多对话框中的“高级”选项被拆开或移除，取而代之的是合理的默认值或隐藏在扩展部分中。
      </para>
    </simplesect>
   
    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>GTK+ 2.4 migration</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>GTK+ 2.4 整合</title>
      <itemizedlist lang='en'>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Menus use the <code>GtkUIManager</code> to generate menu
            structure dynamically from XML data files.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A completely revamped File Chooser is used everywhere in
            the GIMP for opening or saving files.  The best thing
            about it is that it lets you create a set of "bookmarks",
            making it possible to navigate quickly and easily to
            commonly used directories.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP now Supports fancy ARGB cursors when they are
            available on the system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist lang='zh_CN'>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            菜单使用 <code>GtkUIManager</code> 从 XML 数据文件中动态地生成菜单结构。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            一个重新改良的文件选择器在 GIMP 中各处用作打开和保存文件。它最大的优点就是让您生成一系列“书签”，这样就能快速轻松地在常用目录间浏览。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            GIMP 现在支持花哨的 ARGB 光标(当它们在系统中可用时)。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Basic vector support</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>基本的矢量支持</title>
      <para lang='en'>
        Using the GFig plug-in, the GIMP now supports the basic
        functionality of vector layers. The GFig plug-in supports a
        number of vector graphics features such as gradient fills,
        Bezier curves and curve stroking. It is also the easiest way
        to create regular or irregular polygons in the GIMP. In the
        GIMP 2.2, you can create GFig layers, and re-edit these layers
        in GFig afterwards. This level of vector support is still
        quite primitive, however, in comparison to dedicated
        vector-graphics programs such as
        <application>Inkscape</application>. 
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        GIMP 现在使用 GFig 插件支持矢量图层的基本功能。GFig 插件支持一些矢量图形特性如渐变填充，Bezier 曲线和曲线勾画。它也是在 GIMP 中创建规则或不规则多边形的最简单的方法。在 GIMP 2.2 中您能创建 GFig 图层，然后在 GFig 中再编辑这些图层。尽管如此，和专门的矢量图形程序如 <application>Inkscape</application> 相比，这种矢量支持还显得比较简单。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title lang='en'>Also . . .</title>
      <title lang='zh_CN'>还有...</title>
      <para lang='en'>
        There are many other smaller user-visible features. A
        rapid-fire list of some of those features is below. 
      </para>
      <para lang='zh_CN'>
        还有许多相对小的用户可能发现的特性。下面就是一部分这些特性的简明列表。
      </para>

      <itemizedlist lang='en'>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            It is now possible to run the GIMP in batch mode without
            an X server. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            We have a GIMP binary (gimp-console) which is not linked
            to GTK+ at all. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Improved interface for extended input devices
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Editable toolbox:  You can now decide which tools should
            be shown in the Toolbox, and their order.  In particular,
            you can add any or all of the Color Tools to the Toolbox
            if you wish to. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Histogram overlays R, G and B histograms on the Value
            histogram, and calculates the histogram only for the
            contents of the selection. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Shortcuts are now shared across all GIMP windows.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist lang='zh_CN'>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            现在可以使 GIMP 在批处理模式下运行而不需要 X server。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            包含一个完全没有和 GTK+ 链结的 GIMP 二进制文件 (gimp-console)。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            加强了扩展输入设备的界面。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            可编辑的工具箱：现在您可以选择将在工具箱中显示的工具及其顺序。尤其是如果您愿意就可以添加任何或所有的颜色工具到工具箱中。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            直方图中可以看到 R，G 和 B 直方图覆盖在亮度直方图上。基于选区内容计算直方图。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            现在快捷键在所有 GIMP 窗口中共享。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 lang="en;fr">
    <title lang="en">New in GIMP 2.0</title>
    <title lang="fr">Quoi de neuf dans Gimp 2.0?</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      First, a statistic: the Gimp code base contains about 230,000
      lines of C code, and most of these lines were rewritten in the
      evolution from 1.2 to 2.0. From the user's point of view,
      however, Gimp 2 is fundamentally similar to Gimp 1; the features
      are similar enough that Gimp 1 users won't be lost. As part of
      the restructuring work, the developers cleaned up the code
      greatly, an investment that, while not directly visible to the
      user, will ease maintenance and make future additions less
      painful. Thus, the Gimp 2 code base is significantly better
      organized and more maintainable than was the case for Gimp 1.2. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Tout d'abord quelques chiffres: la base de code Gimp contient à peu 
      près 230.000 lignes de code C, et la plupart de ces lignes ont été 
      réécrites depuis la version 1.2. Néanmoins, l'utilisateur de Gimp 1.2 
      ne sera pas désorienté. Les développeurs ont beaucoup nettoyé le code, 
      investissement qui, s'il n'est pas immédiatement visible pour 
      l'utilisateur, facilite la maintenance et rendra les additions futures 
      moins pénibles.  
    </para>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Basic tools</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Outils de base</title>
    <para lang='en'>
      The basic tools in GIMP 2 are not very different from their
      predecessors in GIMP 1. The "Select Regions by Color" tool is now
      shown in the GIMP toolbox, but was already included in GIMP 1 as
      a menu option in the Select menu. The Transform tool has been
      divided into several specialized tools: Rotation, Scale,
      Shearing and Perspective. Color operations are now associated
      with layers in the menu "Layer ->Colors", but this is merely a
      cleanup: they were already present in the Image menu
      (illogically, since they are layer operations). Thus no
      completely new tools appear in this release, but two of the
      tools have been totally revamped compared to the older versions:
      the Text tool and the Path tool. More on this below. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les outils de base de Gimp 2 ne sont pas très différents de ceux de 
      ceux de gimp 1. L'outil «Sélection de régions par couleur» se trouve 
      maintenant dans la Boîte à outils, mais il existait déjà dans le menu 
      Sélection. L'outil Transformation a été scindé en plusieurs outils 
      spécialisés: Rotation, Changer d'échelle, Cisaillement et Perspective
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The user interface for tools has also changed significantly. The
      "Tool Options" dialog box was modified to not resize itself when
      a new tool is chosen. Most users felt that the window changing
      size when a new tool was selected was annoying. Now, by default
      the "Tool Options" dialog is constantly open and docked under
      the toolbox, where it can easily be found. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'interface utilisateur des outils a aussi changé significativement. 
      La fenêtre "Options des outils" reste maintenant constamment ouverte 
      même si on change d'outil et elle peut être attachée en permanence 
      sous la Boîte à outils.
    </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Tool options</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Options des outils</title>
    <para lang='en'>
      The "Tool Options" for many tools have new possibilities that
      weren't available in GIMP 1. Without being exhaustive, here are
      the most noticeable improvements. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les «Options des outils» ont plusieurs possibilités nouvelles:
    </para> 

    <para lang='en'>
      All selection tools now have mode buttons: Replace, Add,
      Subtract and Intersect. In GIMP 1 the only way to change the
      selection mode was to use the Ctrl or Shift buttons, which could
      get very confusing because those buttons also had other
      functions. For example, pressing and holding the Shift key while
      using the Rectangle selection tool forces the rectangle to be a
      square. Thus, to add a square selection you would first press
      Shift, then click the mouse, then release Shift, then press
      Shift again, then sweep out the selection with the mouse, then
      release Shift. It can now be done more easily. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Tous les outils de sélection ont maintenant trois boutons pour changer 
      de mode: Remplacer, Ajouter, Soustraire et Intersection ce qui est 
      plus pratique que le jeu de touches complexe antérieur.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      For transformation tools, buttons now control which object
      (layer, selection or path) is affected by the
      transformation. You can for example transform a rectangular
      selection to various quadrilateral shapes. Path transformation
      in particular is now easier than it was before. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Avec les outils de transformation, les boutons permettent de choisir 
      sur quel objet, calque, sélection ou chemin, portera la transformation.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      "Fade out" and "Paint Using Gradient" are now available for all
      drawing tools. In fact, all drawing tools now have their own
      individual brush, gradient and pattern settings, in contrast to
      GIMP 1 where there was a single global setting that applied to
      all drawing tools. Now you can select different brushes for
      the Pencil and the Paint Brush, or different patterns for the
      Clone and Fill tools. You can change these setting by using your
      mouse wheel over the relevant resource button (this is most
      useful for quickly and easily choosing a brush). 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les outils de dessin ont maintenant leurs propres paramètres de 
      brosse, de dégradé et de motif. L'utilisation la roue de la souris sur 
      l'aperçu de brosse y fait défiler l'ensemble des brosses.
    </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>User Interface</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Interface utilisateur</title>
    <para lang='en'>
      The most visible changes in GIMP 2 concern the user
      interface. GIMP now uses the GTK2+ graphical toolkit in place of
      GTK+. One of the nice features brought by the new libraries is
      dockable dialogs, and tab navigation between dialogs docked in
      the same window -- a feature present in several popular web
      browsers. GIMP 1 was famous for opening dialogs anywhere on your
      screen; GIMP 2 can be told to use fixed boxes. Dialogs now
      include a little tab-customization menu, which provides maximum
      flexibility in organizing your workspace. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Gimp2 utilise maintenant l'ensemble de librairies GTK2+. L'une des 
      caractéristiques les plus intéressantes est la possibilité d'avoir 
      plusieurs dialogues réunis au sein d'onglets dans une même fenêtre. 
      On peut avoir des boîtes de dialogue fixes sur l'écran. Les boîtes de 
      dialogue offrent un petit menu de personnalisation qui vous donne plus 
      de flexibilité dans l'organisation de votre espace de travail 
    </para> 

    <para lang='en'>
      The Image window has some interesting new features. These are
      not necessarily activated by default, but they can be checked as
      options in the "Preferences->Interface->Image Windows"
      menu. "Show Brush Outline", for example, allows you to see the
      outline of the brush when using drawing tools. In the
      "Appearance" sub-section, you can toggle whether a menu bar is
      present at the top of image windows. You can set an option to
      work with the new fullscreen mode. Viewing options are also
      available from all image windows using right click to bring up
      the menu, then selecting "View". The so-called "image" menu is
      also available by clicking on a little triangle in the top left
      corner of the drawing space. The setting you choose in the
      "Preferences" dialog is used as the default value, and options
      you set from an image are used only for that image. (You can
      also toggle fullscreen mode by using the F11 key; the Esc key
      also exits fullscreen mode). 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      La fenêtre d'image offre de nouvelles fontionnalités. Elles ne sont 
      pas activée par défaut mais peuvent l'être dans le menu 
      «Préférences/Interface/Fenêtres d'images». Par exemple «Afficher le 
      contour de la brosse» vous permet ce voir le contour de la brosse 
      quand vous utilisez un outil de dessin. Dans la sous-section 
      «Apparence» vous pouvez décider si une barre de menu est présente ou 
      non en haut de la fenêtre d'image. Vous pouvez choisir de travailler 
      en mode plein-écran. Les options de visibilité sont également 
      disponibles par un clic droit sur l'image faisant apparaître un menu 
      local avec l'entrée «Affichage». On peut aussi accéder à ce menu en 
      cliquant sur le petit bouton marqué d'un triangle en haut à gauche de 
      la fenêtre d'image. Les options choisies dans Préférences sont des 
      options utilisées par défaut pour toutes les images. Les mêmes options 
      fixées à partir du menu local ne sont valables que pour l'image 
      actuelle. (La touche F11 permet de basculer le mode plein-écran)
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      GIMP 2 features keyboard accelerators to ease menu access. If
      you find that navigating through menus using your mouse is
      onerous, the solution may be to use the keyboard. For example,
      if the menu bar is present, to create a new image just hit
      Alt-F-N. Without the menu bar, hit Shift-F10 to open the
      top-left menu, and use direction keys or F then N to create the
      new image. Keyboard accelerators are different from shortcuts:
      accelerators are useful to navigate through menus, whereas
      shortcuts call a specific menu item directly. For example,
      Ctrl-N is a shortcut, and the quickest way to open a new image. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Les accélérateurs clavier de Gimp 2 facilitent l'accès aux menus. Par 
      exemple, si la barre de menus est présente, tapez Alt-F-N pour créer 
      une nouvelle image. Sans barre de menus, tapez Shift-F10 pour ouvrir 
      le menu local qui reproduit les entrées de la barre de menus, et 
      utilisez les touches fléchées ou F puis N pour créer la nouvelle 
      image. Les accélérateurs clavier sont différents des raccourcis 
      clavier: les accélérateurs permettent de naviguer dans les menus 
      tandis que les raccourcis permettent d'accéder directement à une 
      fonction. Par exemple, le raccourci Ctrl-N est la façon la plus rapide 
      de créer une nouvelle image.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      To ease access to your most commonly used menu items, the GIMP
      has provided dynamic shortcuts for many years. When a menu is
      open, you can hover over the desired menu item and hold down
      your shortcut combination. This feature is still present, but is
      deactivated by default in the GIMP 2.0, to avoid accidental
      re-assigning of existing shortcuts. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Pour faciliter l'accès à vos commandes les plus utilisées, Gimp a 
      fourni depuis longtemps la possibilité de créer vos propres raccourcis 
      clavier: quand un item de menu est sélectionné, il suffisait de taper 
      les touches voulues pour le raccouci pour qu'il soit créé. Cette 
      possibilité existe toujours mais a été désactivée par défaut dans 
      Gimp 2 afin d'éviter les conflits accidentels avec les raccourcis 
      existants.  
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The GIMP also ships with a number of sets of key-bindings for
      its menus. If you would like to replace the default GIMP
      keybindings by Photoshop bindings, for example, you can move the
      file "menurc" in your user data directory to "oldmenurc", and
      rename "ps-menurc" to "menurc". 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Gimp possède ses propres combinaisons de touches pour les entrées de 
      ses menus. Si vous voulez remplacer ces combinaisons par celle de 
      Photoshop, renommez le «menurc» de votre répertoire utilisateur en 
      «oldmenurc» et renommez «ps-menurc» en «menurc».
    </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Handling Tabs and Docks</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Gérer les Onglets et les fenêtres attachables</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The GIMP 2.0 introduces a system of tabbed dialogs to allow you
      to make your workspace look the way you want it to be. Almost
      all dialogs can be dragged to another dialog window and dropped
      to make a tabbed dialog set. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Gimp 2 introduit un système de dialogues en onglets vous permettant de 
      regrouper plusieurs dialogues dans une même fenêtre. Presque toutes 
      les boîtes de dialogue peuvent être glissées-déposées dans une autre 
      fenêtre de dialogue et y apparaître sous forme d'onglet.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Furthermore, at the bottom of each dialog, there is a dockable
      area: drag and drop tabs here to attach dialogs beneath the
      bottom tab group. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En outre, en bas de chaque boîte de dialogue se trouve une barre 
      d'attachement des dialogues où vous pouvez déposer les dialogues 
      attachables sous le groupe d'onglets du haut. 
    </para>

    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Scripting</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Rédaction de scripts</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      "Python-fu" is now the standard external scripting interface for
      GIMP 2. This means that you can now use GIMP functions in Python
      scripts, or conversely use Python to write GIMP plug-ins. Python
      is relatively easy to understand even for a beginner, especially
      in comparison to the Lisp-like Scheme language used for
      Script-fu in GIMP 1. The Python bindings are augmented by a set
      of classes for common operations, so you are not forced to
      search through the complete GIMP Procedural Database in order to
      carry out basic operations. Moreover, Python has integrated
      development environments and a gigantic library, and runs not
      only on Linux but also on Microsoft Windows and Macintosh OS
      X. The biggest drawback, for GIMP 2.0, is that the standard user
      interface offered in Python-fu does not use the complete power
      of the Python language. The interface is currently designed to
      support simple scripts, but a more sophisticated version is a
      goal of future development. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      «Python-fu» est maintenant l'interface d'écriture extene standard de 
      Gimp. Cel signifie que vous pouvez utiliser des fonctions Gimp en 
      Python ou inversement utiliser Python pour écrire des greffons Gimp. 
      Python est relativement facile à comprendre même par les débutants, 
      surtout si on le compare au langage Sheme, qui rappelle LISP, 
      précédemment utilisé par Gimp 1.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      GIMP-Perl is no longer distributed with the standard GIMP 2
      distribution, but is available as a separate package. Currently,
      GIMP-Perl is supported only on Unix-like operating systems. It
      includes both a simple scripting language, and the ability to
      code more polished interfaces using the Gtk2 perl module. Direct
      pixel manipulation is available through the use of PDL. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Gimp-Perl n'est plus livré avec la distribution standard de Gimp 2, 
      mais il reste disponible dans un paquetage à part. Gimp-Perl n'est 
      accepté que par les systèmes Unix. Il inclut à la fois un langage 
      d'écriture simple et la possibilité de coder des interfaces plus 
      polies grâce au module perl Gtk2. La manipulation directe des pixels 
      est disponible à travers PDL.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Script-fu, based on Scheme, has the same drawbacks as before:
      not intuitive, hard to use and lacking a real development
      environment. It does, however, have one major advantage compared
      to Python-fu: Script-fu scripts are directly interpreted by GIMP
      and do not require any additional software
      installation. Python-fu requires that you install a package for
      the Python language. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Script-fu, basé sur Scheme, a les mêmes inconvénients qu'avant: peu 
      intuitif, difficile à utiliser et manquant d'un environnement de 
      développement véritable. Il a néanmoins un avantage majeur par rapport 
      à Python-fu: Les scripts Script-fu sont interprétés directement par 
      Gimp sans avoir besoin d'installer un logiciel complémentaire. 
      Python-fu, lui, necessite l'installation d'un paquetage pour le 
      langage Python.
    </para>

    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>The Text Tool</title>
    <title lang='fr'>L'Outil Texte</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The big problem with the standard text tool in GIMP 1 was that
      text could not be modified after it was rendered. If you wanted
      to change anything about the text, all you could do was "undo"
      and try again (if you were lucky enough to have sufficient undo
      history available, and then of course you would also undo any
      other work you had done in the meantime). In GIMP 1.2 there was
      also a "dynamic text" plugin that allowed you to create special
      text layers and keep them around indefinitely, in a modifiable
      form, but it was buggy and awkward to use. The second generation
      Text tool is an enhanced combination of the old Text tool and
      the Dynamic Text plugin. Now all options are available in the
      "Tool Options": font, font size, text color, justify,
      antialiasing, indent, spacing. To create a new text item, click
      in the image and a little editor pops up. Text appears on the
      image while you are editing (and carriage returns are handled
      properly!). A new dedicated layer is created; this layer resizes
      dynamically to match the text you key in. You can import plain
      text from a file, and you can even do things like writing from
      right to left in Arabic. If you select a text layer, clicking on
      it opens the editor, and you can then modify your text. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le grand problème avec l'outil Texte dans Gimp 1 était que le texte ne 
      plus être modifié un fois produit. Dans Gimp 1 il y avait aussi un 
      greffon «Texte dynamique» qui permettait de créer des calques texte 
      spéciaux que vous pouviez conserver pour les modifier, mais il était 
      bogué et affreux à utiliser
    </para>

    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>The Path Tool</title>
    <title lang='fr'>L'outil Chemins</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      The second generation Path tool has a completely new
      interface. The first major difference you notice is that paths
      are no longer required to be closed. A path can be made up of a
      number of disjoint curve segments. The next major difference is
      that now the path tool has three different modes, Design, Edit
      and Move. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le nouvel outil Chemins a une interface entièrement nouvelle. Les 
      chemins n'ont plus besoin d'être fermés. Un chemin peut être formés de 
      plusieurs composants distincts. Trois modes différents sont possibles: 
      Tracer, Édition, Déplacer. 
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      In Design mode, you can create a path, add nodes to an existing
      path and modify the shape of a curve either by dragging edges of
      the curve or dragging the "handles" of a node. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En mode Tracer, vous pouvez créer un chemin, ajouter des nœuds à un 
      chemin existant et modifier la forme de la courbe en glissant les 
      segments ou en glissant les poignées d'un nœud.  
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      In Edit mode, you can add nodes in the middle of curve edges,
      and remove nodes or edges, as well as change the shape of the
      curve. You can also connect two path components. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En mode Éditer, vous pouvez ajouter ou supprimer un nœud sur un 
      segment, changer la forme de la courbe ou raccorder deux composants. 
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      The third mode, Move, is, as you might expect, used to move path
      components. If your path has several components, you can move
      each path component separately. To move all components at once,
      use the Shift key. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      En mode Déplacer, vous pouvez déplacer les composants du chemin, 
      ensemble ou séparément.
    </para>

    <para lang='en'>
      Two other path-related features are new in the GIMP 2.0. The
      GIMP can not only import an SVG image as a raster image, but can
      also keep SVG paths intact as GIMP paths. This means that the
      GIMP is now more able than ever to complement your favourite
      vector drawing tool.  The other feature which has made the path
      tool much better is the introduction of vector-based
      stroking. In previous versions, stroking paths and selections
      was a matter of drawing a brush-stroke along the path. This mode
      is still available, but it is now possible to stroke a curve
      accurately, using the vector library libart. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      L'outil chemin comporte deux autres nouveautés. Non seulement Gimp 2 
      peut importer les images SVG mais il peut aussi garder les chemins SVG 
      intacts comme chemins Gimp. Cela signifie que Gimp peut collaborer 
      avec votre outil de dessin vectoriel favori. L'autre nouveauté qui a 
      amélioré l'outil Chemins est la possibilité de «tracer» 
      automatiquement un chemin avec la brosse de votre choix.
    </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
    <title lang='en'>Other improvements</title>
    <title lang='fr'>Autres améliorations</title>

    <para lang='en'>
      Some other improvements in brief:
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Quelques autres améliorations, en bref:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      Higher-quality antialiasing in some places -- most notibly in
      the Text tool. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Haute qualité de lissage, surtout dans l'outil Texte.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      Icons and menus are skinnable. You can create your own icon set
      and apply it to the toolbox using the "Preference->Interface"
      menu option. A theme called "small" is included with the
      standard distribution.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      On peut changer le décor des icônes et des menus. Vous pouvez créer 
      votre propre lot d'icônes et l'appliquer à la Boîte à outils en 
      utilisant l'option Interface du menu Préférences. Un thème «small» 
      (petit) est inclus dans la distribution standard.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      An image can be saved as a template and used to create new images.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Une image peut être enregistrée comme modèle et être utilisée à créer 
      de nouvelles images.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      There are four new combination modes for layers that lie one on
      top of another within an image: Hard Light, Soft Light, Grain
      Extract and Grain Merge. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Il y a quatre nouveaux modes de fusion des calques qui gisent l'un au 
      dessus de l'autre: Lumière dure, Lumière douce, Extraction de grain, 
      Fusion de grain. 
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      If there is an active selection, you can crop the image directly
      to the selection size using image menu "Image->Crop". 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      S'il y a une sélection active, vous pouvez découper l'image à la 
      taille de cette sélection par l'option Image/Découper.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      As well as being able to create guides, there's now a grid
      functionality in GIMP. It is complimentary to the guides
      functionality and makes it easier to position objects so that
      they align perfectly. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Gimp a maintenant une grille , complémentaire des guides, rendant plus 
      facile le positionnement des objets.     
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      The Layers dialog is more coherent, in that there are no more
      hidden functions accessed only with right click on the miniature
      image of the layer that appears there. You can now handle layer
      operations directly from the image menu: Layer Mask,
      Transparency, Transformation and Layer Color operations are
      directly in Layer submenu. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Le dialogue des Calques est plus cohérent, en ce qu'il n'y a plus de 
      fonctions cachées, accessibles uniquement par le menu local. Toutes 
      les fonctions concernant les calques sont accessibles par le sous-menu 
      Calque.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      Color display filters are now available from the image menu
      "View->Display Filters". Using them, you can simulate different
      gamma values, different contrasts, or even color deficient
      vision, without altering your original image. This actually has
      been a feature of the GIMP developer versions for a long time,
      but it has never been stable enough to appear in a stable
      version of the GIMP before. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Les filtres d'affichage couleur sont maintenant disponibles via le 
      menu Affichage/Filtres d'affichage: ils vous permmettent de modifier 
      l'affichage des couleurs sur votre écran, sans modifier l'image 
      elle-même. Cela est utile aux personnes ayant un problème de vision 
      des couleurs. 
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      The color selection dialog has a new CMYK mode, associated with
      the printer icon. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Le dialogue de sélection des couleurs possède un mode CMJN associé à 
      l'onglet représentant une imprimante. 
    </para></listitem>

     <listitem lang="en"><para>
      Data stored in EXIF tags by digital cameras are now handled in
      read and write mode for JPEG files. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Les méta-données EXIF des appareils photo numériques sont maintenant 
      gérées en mode lecture et écriture pour les fichiers JPEG.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      MNG animations are now supported. The MNG file format can be
      considered as animated PNG. It has all the advantages of PNG
      over GIF, such as more colors, 256 levels of transparency, and
      perhaps most importantly, lack of patent encumbrance. The format
      is a web standard and all recent popular web browsers support
      it. 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Les animations MNG sont maintenant gérées. le format MNG peut être 
      considéré comme un PNG animé. Il a tous les avantages du PNG sur le 
      GIF, tels le nombre plus grand de couleurs, 256 niveaux de 
      transparence, et , peut-être plus important, l'absence de problème de 
      licence. C'est un standard Web, et les navigateurs les plus répandus 
      l'acceptent.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      The GIMP Animation package now does onion-skinning, a bluescreen
      feature was added as well as audio support. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Je n'ai pas su traduire. Désolé!
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem lang="en"><para>
      A channel mixer filter, previously available from the web as an
      add-on, appears in "Filters->Colors". 
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem lang="fr"><para>
      Un mixeur de canaux est apparu dans Filtres/Couleurs.
    </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
  </sect2>
</sect1> 
 
