<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  
 -->
<sect1 id="gimp-introduction-whats-new">
  <title>What's new in GIMP 2.10.18? </title>
  
  <para>
    GIMP-2.10.16 release was skipped, due to a critical bug. It has been fixed.
    Here are GIMP-2.10.18 release highlights:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tools are now grouped in the toolbox by default: 
            <xref linkend="gimp-toolbox-icons"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Sliders now use a compact style with improved user interaction: 
            <xref linkend="sliders"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Vastly improved user experience for the transformation preview:
          <xref linkend="composited-preview"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Dockable areas now highlighted when a dockable dialog is being dragged.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          New 3D Transform tool to rotate and pan items: 
            <xref linkend="gimp-tool-transform-3d"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Much smoother brush outline preview motion on the canvas.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Symmetry painting enhancements
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Faster loading of ABR brushes: GIMP now spends a lot less time loading 
          Photoshop’s brushes (ABR). So if you use a lot of those, the startup 
          time will become pleasantly smaller, by order of a magnitude. The 
          technical explanation is that GIMP used to read the stream of ABR data 
          byte by byte, and now it uses scanline reading instead.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          PSD support improvements: PSD support improvements PSD files now load 
          faster mostly by eliminating excessive copies between the original
          file and the project representation inside GIMP. For large PSD files, 
          the loading is now ~1.5 to ~2 times faster.\n
          Moreover, GIMP is now capable of loading CMYK(A) PSD files (only 8-bit 
          per channel for now). It does so by converting pixels to RGB(A) float 
          using sRGB as the profile which, we know, is not good enough for serious 
          work. However, the plug-in is already using BABL formats to specify and 
          communicate CMYK pixel format encodings with GIMP. This is a good first 
          step towards better CMYK support. It can be improved both on its own as 
          well as integrate with the ongoing work enabling general color-space 
          support for BABL formats in the development branch.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Consolidated user interface for merging down and anchoring layers:
            <xref linkend="gimp-layers-merge"/>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Update check to notify users of new releases available
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</sect1>
