<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<sect1 id='gimp-introduction-what-is-gimp'>
  <title lang="en">What is GIMP?</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">The GIMP</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">WhatIs</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    GIMP is an acronym for GNU Image Manipulation Program. It is a
    freely distributed program for such tasks as photo retouching,
    image composition and image authoring.
  </para>
  <para>
    It has many capabilities. It can be used as a simple paint
    program, an expert quality photo retouching program, an online
    batch processing system, a mass production image renderer, an
    image format converter, etc. 
  </para>
  <para>
    GIMP is expandable and extensible. It is designed to be augmented
    with plug-ins and extensions to do just about anything. The
    advanced scripting interface allows everything from the simplest
    task to the most complex image manipulation procedures to be
    easily scripted.  
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Features and Capabilities</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This is only a brief list of Gimp features:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Full suite of painting tools including brushes, a pencil, an
        airbrush, cloning, etc. 
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Tile-based memory management so image size is limited only by
        available disk space 
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Sub-pixel sampling for all paint tools for high-quality
        anti-aliasing 
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Full Alpha channel support
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Layers and channels
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        A procedural database for calling internal Gimp functions from
        external programs, such as Script-Fu 
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Advanced scripting capabilities
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Multiple undo/redo (limited only by disk space)
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Transformation tools including rotate, scale, shear and flip
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        File formats supported include GIF, JPEG, PNG, XPM, TIFF, TGA,
        MPEG, PS, PDF, PCX, BMP and many others 
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Load, display, convert and save to many file formats
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Selection tools including rectangle, ellipse, free, fuzzy,
        bezier and intelligent 
      </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem lang="en">
      <para>
        Plug-ins that allow for the easy addition of new file formats
        and new effect filters 
      </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Authors</title>
    <para lang="en">
      The first version of the Gimp was written by Peter Mattis and
      Spencer Kimball. Many other developers have contributed more
      recently, and thousands have 
      provided support and testing. Gimp releases are currently being
      orchestrated by Sven Neumann. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
 
