<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<glossary id="glossary">
  <title lang="en">Glossary</title>
  <title lang="de">Glossar</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Glossary</primary>
    <primary lang="de">Glossar</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>A</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-alpha'>
      <glossterm>Alpha</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para lang="en">
          Refers to transparency. An Alpha Channel allows transparency
	  control. Certain image formats may only contain a single
	  Alpha Channel allowing a transparency of on or off. Other formats
          allow a variable level of transparency.
        </para>
        <para lang="de">
	  Der Alphawert gibt die Deckkraft des Pixels an. So ist es mit dem
	  Alpha-Wert möglich, transparente Pixel (Alpha-Wert: 0) oder
	  deckende Pixel (Alpha-Wert: 100) anzugeben.  Je kleiner der
	  Alphawert eines Pixels ist, desto mehr werden die Schichten
	  unterhalb des Pixels sichtbar.
        </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id='glossary-antialiasing'>
      <glossterm>Antialiasing</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para lang="en">
	  Antialiasing is the process of reversing an alias.  Antialiasing
	  produces smoother curves by adjusting the boundary betweenthe
	  background and the pixel region that is being antialiased.
	  Generally, pixel intensities or opacities are changed so a
	  smoother merge with the background is achieved. With selections,
	  the selection edge is affected so that the selection edge opacity
	  is lowered.
        </para>

        <para lang="de">
	  Antialiasing ist eine Maßnahme gegen Aliasing. Beim
	  Antialiasing werden Kanten zur angrenzenden Farbe so berechnet,
	  dass diese keinen störenden Treppeneffekt bilden. In der
	  Regel werden Intensitäten oder Deckungen so angegaßt,
	  daß ein weicherer Übergang zum Hintergrund hergestellt
	  wird. Bei Auswahlen wird die Deckung der Kanten entsprechend
	  reduziert.
        </para>

        <para>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/glossary/alias.png' format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata
                fileref='../images/glossary/antialias.png' format='PNG'
              />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>B</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-bitmap'>
      <glossterm>Bitmap</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para lang="en">
	  " From The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing (13 Mar 01) :
	  bitmap A data file or structure which corresponds bit for bit
	  with an image displayed on a screen, probably in the same format
	  as it would be stored in the display's video memory or maybe as a
	  device independent bitmap. A bitmap is characterised by the width
	  and height of the image in pixels and the number of bits per
	  pixel which determines the number of shades of grey or colours it
	  can represent. A bitmap representing a coloured image (a
	  "pixmap") will usually have pixels with between one and eight
	  bits for each of the red, green, and blue components, though
	  other colour encodings are also used. The green component
	  sometimes has more bits that the other two to cater for the human
	  eye's greater discrimination in this component. "  
	</para>

	<para lang="de">
	  FIXME
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>C</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-channels'>
      <glossterm>Channels</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para lang="en">
	  Each image is divided up into separate channels and then
	  recombined before being sent to the output device.  An output
	  device is most usually a screen. The channels that are used when
	  rendering images to a screen are Red, Green, and Blue.  Other
	  output devices may use different channels.
	</para>

	<para lang="de">
	  Jedes Bild kann in separaten Kanälen aufgeteilt werden.
	  Für die Ausgabe werden alle seperierten Kanäle wieder
	  zu einem Bild zusammengefügt. Ausgegeben können Bilder
	  neben den Monitor auch auf einem Drucker oder einem Plotter. Die
	  Kanäle, die für den Monitor wichtig sind, ergeben sich
	  aus Rot, Grün und Blau.  Andere Ausgabegeräte, zum
	  Beispiel professionelle Druckmaschienen, benutzen andere
	  Kanäle um das Bild zusammenzufügen.
	</para>

	<para lang="en">
	  Channels can be useful when working on images that need
	  adjustment to one particular color. If, for example, the removal
	  of "red-eye" is the goal, work on the Red channel is most
	  obviously a ready solution. Channels can be seen as masks that
	  allow or restrict the output of the color that the channel
	  represents.  By running filters against this channel information,
	  many varied and subtle effects can be put in to play by the
	  experienced GIMP user.
	</para>     

	<para lang="de">
	  Nützlich erweisen sich Kanäle vor allem dann, wenn man
	  Bildoperationen nur für eine bestimmte Farbe
	  durchführen lassen möchte. Als beliebtes Beispiel
	  lässt sich hier, dass retuschieren an roten Augen
	  anführen. Gerade bei Anwendung von Filtern auf bestimmten
	  Kanälen, lassen sich sehr subtile Effekte erzielen. Dem
	  Benutzer sei es überlassen, dies auszuprobieren.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard">
      <glossterm>Clipboard</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Clipboard is the term used to describe a temporary area of
	  memory that is used to transfer data between applications or
	  documents.  The GIMP uses slightly different clipboard
	  approaches when used under differnt operating systems. Under
	  Linux/XFree, the XFree clipboard is used for text and The
	  GIMP internal image clipboard is used for images that are
	  being transferred between image documents.  When The GIMP is
	  used with other operating systems, differences may be
	  apparent. Any differences should be outlined in the operating
	  system specific documentation for the individual GIMP
	  package.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The most fundamental operations provided by a clipboard
	  interface allow for Cut, Copy, and Paste. Cut is used to
	  denote the removal of an item that is sent to the clipboard.
	  Copy leaves the item in the document and copies it to the
	  clipboard. Paste copies to the document whatever happens to
	  be in the clipboard. The GIMP will make an intelligent
	  decision about what to paste depending upon the target. If
	  the target is a canvas, then paste operation will use the
	  image clipboard. If the target is a text entry box, then the
	  paste operation will use the text clipboard.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>D</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-dithering'>
      <glossterm>Dithering</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Dithering refers to the math and voodoo involved in rendering an
	  image that has few colors seem like it has many. Dithering is
	  accomplished in different ways depending on the output device and
	  the program. One particularly effective method is clustering
	  pixels of color together in an attempt to simulate another color.
	  This is achieved by the human eye and the tendency for it to mix
	  colors while viewing complex color patterns. A common dithering
	  effect is seen on television screens or in newspaper print. From
	  a distance the images seem to be constructed of many varied
	  colors or shades, but upon closer inspection this is certainly
	  not the case. A color television uses only three colors clustered
	  together in various states of on or off. A black and white
	  newspaper uses only black ink, yet pictures in newspapers appear
	  to be constructed of grey tones. Furthermore, there are
	  techniques used to achieve greater success in dithering.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  The GIMP can utilize the Floyd-Steinberg dithering technique, for
	  example.  This dithering method is simply put, a mathematical way
	  of clustering the pixels to accomplish better results than other
	  dithering methods. Of course, there are always exceptions and
	  there are many different dithering models that are in use today.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>F</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-fileformat'>
      <glossterm>File Format</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  A way that an image is written. You should select a file format
	  which is suitable for your situation. JPEG  and PostScript are
	  examples of file formats.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry id='glossary-feathering'>
      <glossterm>Feathering</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Feathering is a process by which the edges of a region are softly
	  blended with the background.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata
		fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
		/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry id='glossary-floatingselection'>
      <glossterm>FLoating Selection</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Floating selections are similar in function to  layers  except
	  that floating selections must be anchored before work can resume
	  on any other layers in the image. While a selection is floating,
	  any number of functions can be used to alter the image data
	  contained within the float.
	</para>
	<para>
	  There are two methods available for anchoring a float. The first,
	  and most useful, is to change the float into a new layer. This is
	  achieved by creating a new layer while the float is active. The
	  second method involves anchoring the float to an already existing
	  layer. This is done by clicking anywhere on the image except on
	  the float. Doing so will merge the float with the background
	  layer.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Any pasted selection will be first rendered as a floating
	  selection. 
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry id='glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering'>
      <glossterm>Floyd-Steinberg Dithering</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  This method of dithering looks at the current pixel color and
	  retrieving the closest values from the palette. These colors are
	  then distributed to the pixel areas below and to the right of the
	  original pixel. 
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>G</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-gnu'>
      <glossterm>GNU</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  GNU's Not Unix, an organization devoted to the creation and support
	  of Open Source software. GIMP is an official GNU application.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry id='glossary-guides'>
      <glossterm>Guides</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Guides are a convenient way to help you align layers and tool
	  functions on your drawable image, layer, or selection. Guides are
	  created manually by clicking and dragging from either the top or
	  left rulers in to the image area. They appear as blue dashed
	  lines. They do not print. There are some useful options available
	  to the user to help utilize guides efficiently, such as  Snap to
	  Guides ,  Toggle Guides , and  Center Guide .
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>H</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-hextriplet'>
      <glossterm>Hextriplet</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  A way of representing color in the form #rrggbb
	  where "rr"
	  represents red, "gg" green, and "bb" blue. Commonly
	  used in web
	  design.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry id='glossary-hsv'>
      <glossterm>HSV</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Hue Saturation Value, a way of representing color. The Hue
	  is the color like red or blue, the Saturation is how strong
	  the color is and the Value is the brightness. This is
	  sometimes called HSB or Hue Saturation Brightness. 
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>I</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-imagehose'>
      <glossterm>Image Hose</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Image Hoses are special brushes that contain many different
	  frames. An exmaple of this might be a footstep brush that
	  contains two images. One of a left footprint and one of a right
	  footprint. During the application of this hypothetical hose
	  brush, one would see the left footprint followed by that of the
	  right in a continuous fashion. This method of animation for
	  brushes is very powerful.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id='glossary-incremental'>
      <glossterm>Incremental, paint mode</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  This paint mode renders each brush stroke directly onto the
	  active layer. If incremental mode is not set, there is a
	  canvas buffer that is composited with the active layer.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata
		fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
		format='PNG'/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata
		fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
		format='PNG' />
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The two images above were created using a brush with spacing
	  set to sixty. The image on the left shows non-incremental
	  painting and the image on the right shows the difference that
	  incremental painting can produce. Incremental paint mode
	  results in each brush application, through the duration of a
	  stroke, being rendered in addition to any previous brush
	  renderings.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id='glossary-interpolation'>
      <glossterm>Interpolation</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para lang="en">
	  Interpolation is the means by which the pixels of an image are
	  rendered to represent changes in an image size or angle.
	  Interpolation methods in <application>The GIMP</application> are
	  labelled with a speed marker. Faster methods lead to lower quality
	  transformations whereas slower methods lead to higher quality
	  transformations.
	</para>

	<para lang="de">
	  Als Interpolation bezeichnet man die Abbildung von Pixeln in
	  einem Bild auf die darzustellende Vergrößerung auf
	  dem Bildschirm.
	  Als Interpolationsverfahren in <application>GIMP</application>
	  kann zwischen verschiedenen Geschwindigkeitsmarken gewählt
	  werden. Schnelle Verfahren resultieren in einer niedrigeren
	  Qualität während langsamere Verfahren einer
	  höherqualitativen Darstellung dienen.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>M</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-marching-ants'>
      <glossterm>Marching Ants</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  The name for the dotted line which delineates a selection.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id='glossary-layermodes'>
      <glossterm lang="en">Layer Modes</glossterm>
      <glossterm lang="de">Ebenen Modi</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para lang="en">
	  There are fifteen available layer modes. Selecting
	  a layer mode
	  changes the way that layer or paint application is
	  viewed based
	  on the layer or layers beneath it.
	</para>

	<para lang="de">
	  <application>GIMP</application> bietet 20 Blendenmodi
	  für die Ebenen. Der Blendenmodus wird auf die Ebenen
	  angewendet, die unter der ausgewählten Ebene liegen.
	  Gibt es nur eine Ebene, hat die Blende keinen Effekt. So
	  liegt es nahe, dass für die Blendenmodi mindestens 2
	  übereinanderliegende Ebenen gebraucht werden. Die
	  Beispielbilder zeigen die Auswirkungen bei Anwendung des
	  jeweiligen Modus. Das link Bild ist der normale Zustand, dass
	  rechte gibt das Blendergebnis wieder.
	</para>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Normal</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject> <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal.png'
		      format='PNG' /> 
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		This is the default layer mode. The layer
		will be viewed normally.
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Das ist der normale Blendenmodus der Ebene. Die oberste
		Ebene verdeckt alle unteren Ebenen. 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Dissolve</term> 
	    <term lang="de">Vernichtend</term> 
	    <listitem>
	      <para lang="en">
		The Dissolve layer mode dissolves the
		layer into the layer beneath it. It does so by
		dispersing pixels.  This can best be seen ina
		close-up screenshot.  
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Bei dem <guilabel>Vernichtend</guilabel> Blendenmodus 
		werden die Pixel verstreut.
		Dies wird vor allem sichtbar, bei Kanten des Bildes. 
	      </para>

	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject> <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal.png'
		      format='PNG' /> </imageobject>
		  </inlinemediaobject> <inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject> <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-dissolve.png'
		      format='PNG' /> </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		The image on the left illustrates a normal layer mode
		and the image on the right shows the same two layers in
		dissolve mode.
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Das linke Bild gibt das Bild vergrössert, ohne
		Blende wieder. Rechts wurde der Blendenmodus
		angewendet, wo deutlich zu sehen ist, wie die Pixel
		verstreut werden.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Multiply</term>
	    <term lang="de">Multiplizieren</term> 
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject> 
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' /> 
		  </imageobject> 
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject> 
		  <imageobject> 
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-multiply.png'
		      format='PNG' /> 
		  </imageobject> 
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		This mode multiplies the pixel values of the layer with
		those that are visible beneath it.  
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Dieser Blendenmodus multipliziert alle Farbwerte der
		oberen und unteren Ebene. Das Ergebnis ist meist ein
		dunkleres Bild. Weiße Ebenen verändern den
		Hintergrund nicht, schwarze hingegen ergeben ein
		komplett schwarzes Ergebnis.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Divide</term>
	    <term lang="de">Division</term> 
	    <listitem lang="de">
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' /> 
		  </imageobject> 
		</inlinemediaobject>

		<inlinemediaobject> 
		  <imageobject> 
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-divide.png'
		      format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject> 
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Der Blendenmodus <guilabel>Division</guilabel> ist eine
		Art invertierter Multiplikationsmodus. Anstatt die
		Farbwerte der Pixel zu multiplizieren, werden diese
		dividiert. Das Ergebnis ist meist ein helleres Bild.
		<!-- Color dodge -->
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Screen</term>
	    <term lang="de">Bildschirm</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-screen.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME - screen is the opposite of multiply mode
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Der <guilabel>Bildschirm</guilabel> Modus ist das
		Gegenteil zum Multiplikationsmodus. Die Farbwerte beider
		Ebenen, werden invertiert, dann multipliziert und das
		Ergebnis wieder invertiert. Das Ergebnis ist meist ein
		helleres Bild. Aussnahmen bilden hierbei schwarze Ebenen,
		die den Hintergrund nicht verändern. Weiße
		Ebenen ergeben ein Weisses Bild.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Overlay</term>
	    <term lang="de">Überlagern</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-overlay.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Der <guilabel>Überlagern</guilabel> Modus ist eine
		Kombination aus <guilabel>Multiplikation</guilabel> und
		<guilabel>Screen</guilabel> Modus. Abhängig ist
		dies von das Ausgangsfarbe.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Dodge</term>
	    <term lang="de">Abwedeln</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>

		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-dodge.png'
		      format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME 
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Bei dem Blendenmodus <guilabel>Abwedeln</guilabel>,
		werden die Farbwerte der zweiten Ebene vorerst
		invertiert.  Danach werden die Werte dividert. So ist
		dieser Blendenmodus ähnlich eines invertierten
		Multiplikationsmodus.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Burn</term>
	    <term lang="de">Nachbelichten</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-burn.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>

	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME
	      </para>

	      <para lang="de">
		Ähnlich dem Modus <guilabel>Abwedeln</guilabel>,
		wird der Blendenmodus
		<guilabel>Nachbelichten</guilabel> berechnet (die
		Farbwerte der oberen Ebene werden invertiert). Der
		Unterschied hierbei ist, dass sich der Modus
		ähnlich dem <guilabel>Bildschirm</guilabel> Modus
		verhält, anstatt der
		<guilabel>Multiplikation</guilabel>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Hard Light</term>
	    <term lang="de">Harte Kanten</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-hardlight.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Dieser Blendenmodus ist eine Kombination aus
		<guilabel>Bildschirm</guilabel> und
		<guilabel>Multiplikation</guilabel>. Abhängig ist
		dies von dem Wert der Ergebnisfarbe.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Soft Light</term>
	    <term lang="de">Weiche Kanten</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-softlight.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="en">
		FIXME
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Dieser Blendenmodus hat bis auf seinem Namen nichts mit dem
		<guilabel>Harte Kanten</guilabel> Modus gemeinsam. Das
		Ergebnis dieses Blendenmodus ist ähnlich dem
		<guilabel>Überlagern</guilabel> Modus.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Grain Extract</term> 
	    <term lang="de">Grain Extract</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-grainextract.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para>
		FIXME 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Grain Merge</term>
	    <term lang="de">Grain Merge</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-grainmerge.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para>
		FIXME
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Difference</term>
	    <term lang="de">Unterschied</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-difference.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Bei diesem Blendenmodus werden die Farbwerte voneinander
		subtrahiert und ein Absolutwert gebildet.  In
		Abhängigkeit von den Ausgangsebenen, wirkt das
		Ergebnis etwas absonderlich. Anwendung findet es vor
		allem zum invertieren von Bildelementen.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Addition</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-addition.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Ein einfacher Blendenmodus, der einfach beide Farbwerte
		miteinander addiert.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Substract</term>
	    <term lang="de">Subtraktion</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		FIXME
	      </para>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-subtract.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Darken Only</term>
	    <term lang="de">Nur Abdunkeln</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-darken.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Beide Farbwerte werden bei diesem Blendenmodus
		miteinander verglichen und der kleinere Werte wird
		benutzt. Komplett weisse Ebenen verändern nichts an
		dem Ergebnisbild, komplett schwarze ergeben ein schwarzes
		Bild.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Lighten Only</term>
	    <term lang="de">Nur Aufhellen</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-lighten.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para> 
	      <para lang="de">
		Im Unterschied zur <guilabel>Nur Abdunkeln</guilabel>
		wird bei diesem Blendenmodus der grössere Farbwert
		bevorzugt. So verändern komplett schwarze Ebenen
		nicht das Bild, sondern nur komplett weisse Ebenen. Diese
		färben das Ergebnisbild weiss.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Hue</term>
	    <term lang="de">Farbton</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-hue.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Hier wird bei der Überblendung der Farbton des
		Blendenbildes benutzt, sowie Sättigung und Lichtwerte
		des Ausgangsbildes.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Saturation</term>
	    <term lang="de">Sättigung</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-saturation.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Hier wird bei der Überblendung die Sättigung des
		Blendenbildes benutzt, sowie Farbton und Lichtwerte
		des Ausgangsbildes.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Color</term>
	    <term lang="de">Farbe</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-color.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Hier wird bei der Überblendung der Farbton und die
		Sättigung des
		Blendenbildes benutzt, sowie Lichtwerte
		des Ausgangsbildes.
	      </para>

	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term lang="en">Value</term>
	    <term lang="de">Wert</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para lang="en">
		The image on the left illustrates a normal
		layer
		mode and the image on the right shows thesame
		two layers in value mode.
	      </para>
	      <para lang="de">
		Hier wird bei der Überblendung der Farbton und
		Lichtwert des
		Blendenbildes benutzt, sowie Sättigung
		des Ausgangsbildes.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/modes-normal2.png'
		      format='PNG' />
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
		<inlinemediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		    <imagedata
		      fileref='../images/glossary/modes-value.png' format='PNG'/>
		  </imageobject>
		</inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>


      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>S</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-samplemerge'>
      <glossterm>Sample Merge</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  Sample Merge is a technique useful when working with more than one
	  layer where operations that affect one layer may take advantage of
	  color or pixel information on all visible layers. Consider selection
	  by color as an example of a time that this function may be useful.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>

  <glossdiv>
    <title>U</title>
    <glossentry id='glossary-url'>
      <glossterm>URL</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  FIXME
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>
