<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--version history
  2008-06-03 prokoudine: yet another shot at Russian content
  2007-02-28 prokoudine: proofreading of translation into Russian
  2007-02-28 lexa: minor review
  2006-01-26 lexa: fixed link to the gpl homepage
  2006-11-27 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 add Korean translation by Dust
  2005-12-11 reviewed de by lexa
  2005-11-01 Addition en;fr in Language by julien hardelin
-->
<sect1 id="introduction-gimp">
  <title>Welcome to GIMP</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a multi-platform tool to create and edit
    images of all kinds. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is an acronym for
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> Image Manipulation Program.
  </para>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has many capabilities. It can be used as a
    simple paint program, an expert quality photo retouching program, a tool
    to create digital art, an online batch processing system, a mass production
    image renderer, an image format converter, etc.
  </para>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is expandable and extensible. It is designed
    to be augmented with plug-ins and custom data to do just about anything.
    The advanced scripting interface allows everything from the simplest task
    to the most complex image manipulation procedures to be scripted.
  </para>
  <para>
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a Free Software application covered by the
    General Public License version 3 <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gpl"/>.
    The <acronym>GPL</acronym> provides users with the freedom to access and
    alter the source code that makes up computer programs.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="introduction-platforms">
    <title>Known Platforms</title>
    <para>
      One of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s strengths is its free availability on a
      wide range of operating systems and architectures.
      Most <acronym>GNU</acronym> / <application>Linux</application>
      distributions include <acronym>GIMP</acronym> as a standard application.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is also available for other operating systems such
      as <productname>Microsoft Windows</productname> or Apple's
      <productname>macOS</productname> (<application>Darwin</application>).
      The platforms on which <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has been known to work
      include:
    </para>
    <para>
      <productname><acronym>GNU</acronym>/Linux</productname>,
      <productname>Apple macOS</productname>,
      <productname>Microsoft Windows</productname>,
      <productname>OpenBSD</productname>, <productname>NetBSD</productname>,
      <productname>FreeBSD</productname>, <productname>Solaris</productname>,
      <productname>SunOS</productname>, <productname>AIX</productname>,
      <productname>HP-UX</productname>, <productname>Tru64</productname>,
      <productname>Digital UNIX</productname>,
      <productname>OSF/1</productname>, <productname>IRIX</productname>,
      <productname><acronym>GNU</acronym>/Hurd</productname>,
      <productname>OS/2</productname>, <productname>BeOS</productname>, and
      its successor <productname>Haiku</productname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is easily ported to other
      operating systems because of its source code availability. For further
      information visit the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developers homepage.
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-dev"/>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="authors">
    <title>History of GIMP</title>
    <para>
      The first version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was written by Peter Mattis
      and Spencer Kimball in 1995. Over the years
      <ulink url="https://www.gimp.org/about/authors.html">many other
      people</ulink> have contributed by helping with development, testing,
      providing support, translating and writing documentation.
      A short history of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is available
      <ulink url="https://www.gimp.org/about/#gimp-history">online</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="introduction-help">
    <title>GIMP's Help system</title>
    <para>
      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Documentation Team provides the information
      that tries to help you understand how to use <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      The User Manual is an important part of this help. The latest version is
      always available on the website of the Documentation Team
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-gimp-docs"/> in HTML format.
      When using <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, context sensitive help is available
      by pressing the <keycap>F1</keycap> key while the mouse is on top of
      a menu item or other part of GIMP's interface. Most dialogs will also
      show a help button that you can use to access the relevant part of the
      manual.
    </para>
    <para>
      The manual in HTML format can also be installed locally on your computer.
      Installers are
      <ulink url="https://docs.gimp.org/download.html">available for
      Windows</ulink>, and on Linux your package manager may have a gimp-help
      package available.
      Though if your internet speed and bandwidth allow it, using the online
      manual is recommended since it is usually more up-to-date.
      When installing the local manual, you will have to adjust your
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-help">help preferences</link> to make use of
      the local copy.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="introduction-features">
    <title>Features and Capabilities</title>
    <para>
      The following list is a short overview of some of the features and
      capabilities which <acronym>GIMP</acronym> offers you:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A full suite of painting tools including brushes, a pencil, an
          airbrush, cloning, etc.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Tile-based memory management, so image size is limited only by
          available disk space.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Sub-pixel sampling for all paint tools for high-quality
          anti-aliasing.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Full Alpha channel support for working with transparency.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Layers and channels.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A procedural database for calling internal <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          functions from external programs, such as Script-Fu.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Advanced scripting capabilities.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Multiple undo/redo (limited only by disk space).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Transformation tools including rotate, scale, shear and flip.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for a wide range of file formats, including JPEG, PNG, GIF,
          PSD, DDS, XPM, TIFF, TGA, MPEG, PS, PDF, PCX, BMP and many others.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Selection tools, including rectangle, ellipse, free, fuzzy, bezier
          and scissors.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Plug-ins that allow for the easy addition of new file formats and
          new effect filters.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
