<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-04-23 j.h: update to v2.10.10
  2017-04-29 j.h: added links to Diagonal neighbors and antialiasing
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">
  <title>Bucket Fill</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Bucket Fill</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Bucket Fill</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    This tool fills a selection with the current foreground color. If you
    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>+click and use the Bucket tool, it will use the
    background color instead. Depending on how the tool options are set, the
    Bucket Fill tool will either fill the entire selection, or only parts
    whose colors are similar to the point you click on. The tool options also
    affect the way transparency is handled.
  </para>
  <para>
    The amount of fill depends on what Fill Threshold you have specified. The
    fill threshold determines how far the fill will spread (similar to the way
    in which the <link linkend="gimp-tool-fuzzy-select">Fuzzy Select</link>
    tool works). The fill starts at the point where you
    click and spreads outward until the color or alpha value becomes
    <quote>too different</quote>.
  </para>
  <para>
    When you fill objects in a transparent layer (such as letters in a text
    layer) with a different color than before, you may find that a border of
    the old color still surrounds the objects. This is due to a low
    fill-threshold in the Bucket Fill options dialog. With a low threshold,
    the bucket tool won't fill semi-transparent pixels, and they will stand
    out against the fill because they have kept their original color.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you want to fill areas that are totally transparent, you have to make
    sure that the <quote>Lock</quote> option (in the Layers dialog) is
    unchecked. If this option is checked, only the non-transparent parts of
    the layer will be filled.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Bucket Fill</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-bucket-fill.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>
          keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, similarly to paint tools, allows you to pick
          surrounding colors on canvas without having to switch to
          <emphasis>Color Picker tool</emphasis>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><keycap>Shift</keycap> toggles the use of Fill Similar Color or
          Fill Whole Selection on the fly.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> toggles Fill type between FG and BG colors.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-bucket-fill.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="../about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode</term>
        <term>Opacity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            See <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Paint Tools</link>
            for help with options that are common to all these tools. Only
            options that are specific to the Bucket Fill tool are
            explained here.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fill Type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><acronym>GIMP</acronym> provides three fill types:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>FG Color Fill</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  sets the fill color to the currently selected foreground
                  color.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>BG Color Fill</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  sets the fill color to the currently selected background
                  color.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Pattern Fill</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  sets the fill color to the currently selected pattern. You
                  can select the pattern to use in a drop-down list.
                </para>
                <para>
                  This drop-down list allows the user to select one of many
                  fill patterns to use on the next fill operation. The manner
                  in which the list is presented is controlled by the four
                  buttons at the bottom of the selector.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Affected Area</term>
        <listitem>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Fill whole selection</guilabel> makes GIMP fill a
                pre-existent selection or the whole layer. A quicker approach
                to do the same thing could be to click and drag the
                foreground, background or pattern color, leaving it onto the
                selection. Also, pressing <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key allows
                you to pick a color on the image as foreground color.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Fill similar colors</guilabel>: this is the default
                setting: the tool fills the area with a color near the pixel
                onto you have clicked. The color similarity is defined by options
                in Finding Similar Colors. Click and drag to fill.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Fill by line art detection</guilabel>: This allows
                you to fill areas
                surrounded by <quote>line arts</quote>, trying to leave no
                unfilled pixels near the lines, and closing potential zones.
              </para>
              <para>
                Line art detection is also known as Smart Colorization. The
                author describes clearly problems he met in
                  <ulink
            url="https://girinstud.io/news/2019/02/smart-colorization-in-gimp/"/>.
                Options are described below.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Finding Similar Colors</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          These options appear when the <guilabel>Fill similar colors</guilabel>
          option is checked:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The option <guilabel>Fill Transparent Areas</guilabel>
                offers the possibility of filling areas with low opacity.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Sample merged</guilabel>:
                If you enable this option, sampling is not calculated only
                from the values of the active layer, but from all visible layers.
              </para>
              <para>
                For more information, see the
                <link linkend="glossary-samplemerge">Glossary entry</link>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                To understand what diagonal neighbors are, please refer to
                <link linkend="diagonal-neighbors">Diagonal-neighbors</link>
                in Fuzzy Select tool.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Please refer to <link
                linkend="glossary-antialiasing">Anti-aliasing</link> in
                Glossary.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The <guilabel>Threshold</guilabel> slider sets the level at
                which color weights are measured for fill boundaries. A higher
                setting will fill more of a multi colored image and conversely,
                a lower setting will fill less area.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                With the <guilabel>Fill by</guilabel> option you can choose
                which component of the image GIMP shall use to calculate the
                similarity and to determine the borders of filling.
              </para>
              <para>
                The components you can choose from are
                <guimenuitem>Composite</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>Red</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>Green</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>Blue</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>HSV Hue</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>HSV Saturation</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>HSV Value</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>LCh Lightness</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>LCh Chroma</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>LCh Hue</guimenuitem>,
                <guimenuitem>Alpha</guimenuitem>.
              </para>
              <para>
                This option is not easy to understand. You have chosen,
                for example, the Red channel. When you click on any pixel,
                the tool searches for contiguous pixels similar for
                <emphasis>the red channel</emphasis> to the clicked pixel,
                according to the set threshold. Here is an example:
              </para>
              <para>
                Original image: three strips with gradients of pure
                colors. Red (255;0;0), Green (0;255;0), Blue
                (0;0;255). We are going to use the Bucket-fill tool
                with the magenta color and a Threshold set to 15.
              </para>
              <para>
                Image 1: Fill By = Composite. We successively clicked in the
                three color strips. Every strip is filled according
                to the threshold.
              </para>
              <para>
                Image 2: Fill By = Red. We clicked in the red strip. The
                tool searches for contiguous pixels which have a similar
                value in the red channel, according to the set
                threshold. Only a narrow area corresponds to these
                standards. In the green and the blue strip, the value
                of pixels in the red channel is 0, very much different from
                the red channel value of the clicked pixel: the color
                doesn't spread to them.
              </para>
              <para>
                Image 3: Fill By = Red. We clicked in the green strip.
                There, the value of the clicked pixel in the red channel is
                0. All pixels in the green and the blue strips have the
                same red channel value (0): they are all painted.
              </para>
              <figure>
                <title>Example for <quote>Fill By</quote></title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-0.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para>Original image</para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-1.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para>Image 1</para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-2.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para>Image 2</para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-3.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para>Image 3</para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Line Art Detection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          These options appear when the <guilabel>Fill by line art detection</guilabel>
          option is checked:
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title><quote>Fill by line art detection</quote> example</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/bucket-fill-ex-origin.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/bucket-fill-ex-default.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  Bucket fill tool applied by click-and-drag with default
                  options. They don't well fit this image, especially on
                  eyebrows that are almost wiped off.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Source</guilabel>: by default, information for line
                art computation is taken from
                <guilabel>All visible layers</guilabel>. You can also select
                the <guilabel>Selected layer</guilabel>, the
                <guilabel>Layer below the selected one</guilabel>, or the
                <guilabel>Layer above the selected one</guilabel> as the source.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Detect opacity rather than grayscale</guilabel>: fills completely
                transparent regions.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Line art detection threshold</guilabel>: threshold to
                detect contour (higher values will detect more pixels).
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Line Art Closure</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          These options appear when the <guilabel>Fill by line art detection</guilabel>
          option is checked:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Automatic closure</guilabel>: When this option is enabled,
                <guilabel>Maximum gap length</guilabel> defines the maximum gap (in
                pixels) in line art which can be closed.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Manual closure in fill layer</guilabel>: when
                enabled, consider pixels of the selected line art source layer
                that are using the selected fill color as line art closure.
              </para>
              <para>
                This setting is only enabled when the line art source is
                <guilabel>Layer below the selected one</guilabel>, or
                <guilabel>Layer above the selected one</guilabel>.
              </para>
              <para>
                When your line art sketch has holes, you can fill these holes
                with a brush in the fill color on a layer above or below it,
                before using bucket fill on your color layer. Especially on
                larger images this can be faster than selecting
                <guilabel>All visible layers</guilabel> as source.
              </para>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Layer below the selected one</guilabel> would be
                most useful when you are coloring a scanned sketch, while
                <guilabel>Layer above the selected one</guilabel> can be used
                when you are sketching yourself and filling the colors below
                the sketch.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fill borders</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          These options appear when the <guilabel>Fill by line art detection</guilabel>
          option is checked:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Maximum growing size</guilabel>: maximum number of
                pixels grown under the line art. Increasing this value makes
                lines thinner.
              </para>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/toolbox/bucket-fill-ex-grow.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    To improve eyebrows in the example, <guilabel>Maximum
                    growing size</guilabel> is reduced to 1.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Feather edges</guilabel>: feathers fill edges.
              </para>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/toolbox/bucket-fill-ex-feather.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Stroke borders</guilabel>: stroke fill borders with
                the stroke options of the paint tool selected in the dropdown
                below.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Fill a feathered selection</title>
    <para>
      By clicking repeatedly in a selection with feathered edges, you
      progressively fill the feathered border:
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Example for <quote>Fill a feathered Selection</quote></title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/fill-feathered-1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/fill-feathered-2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            After clicking 3 times more with the Bucket-Fill tool
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
