<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2018-10-14 j.h: update to v2.10
  2009-03-16 j.h: reviewed for v2.6. No change.
  2008-02-05 j.h : updated fr to v2.4 and enhanced align modes
                   examples for 'en' and 'fr'
  2008-01-18 ude: enhanced(?) align mode examples
  2007-05-23 Rebuilt Alignment section by j.h
  2006-02-05 fr revised; shortcut modified in "en" by j.h
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by figure by lexa
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-clone">
  <title>Clone</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Clone</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Clone</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The Clone tool uses the current brush to copy from an image or pattern.
    It has many uses: one of the most important is to repair problem areas in
    digital photos, by <quote>painting over</quote> them with pixel data from
    other areas. This technique takes a while to learn, but in the hands of a
    skilled user it is very powerful. Another important use is to draw
    patterned lines or curves: see
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-patterns">Patterns</link> for examples.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you want to clone from an image, instead of a pattern, you must tell
    GIMP which image you want to copy from. You do this by holding down the
    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key and clicking in the desired source image.
    Until you have set the source in this way, you will not be able to paint
    with the Clone tool: the tool cursor tells you this by showing
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-clone-modifier-bad.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you clone from a pattern, the pattern is <emphasis>tiled</emphasis>;
    that is, when the point you are copying from moves past one of the
    edges, it jumps to the opposite edge and continues, as though the pattern
    were repeated side-by-side, indefinitely. When you clone from an image
    this does not happen: if you go beyond the edges of the source, the Clone
    tool stops producing any changes.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can clone from any drawable (that is, any layer, layer mask, or
    channel) to any other drawable. You can even clone to or from the
    selection mask, by switching to Quick Mask mode. If this means copying
    colors that the target does not support (for example, cloning from an RGB
    layer to an Indexed layer or a layer mask), then the colors will be
    converted to the closest possible approximations.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Clone</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-clone.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the <keycap>C</keycap> keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <para>
      See the <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint-modifiers">Paint tools key
      modifiers</link> for a description of key modifiers that have the same
      effect on all paint tools.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key is used to select the source, if
            you are cloning from an image: it has no effect if you are
            cloning from a pattern. You can clone from any layer of any
            image, by clicking on the image display, with the
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key held down, while the layer is active
            (as shown in the Layers dialog). If Alignment is set to
            <guilabel>None</guilabel>, <guilabel>Aligned</guilabel>, or
            <keycap>Fixed</keycap> in tool options, then the point you
            click on becomes the origin for cloning: the image data at that
            point will be used when you first begin painting with the Clone
            tool. In source-selection mode, the cursor changes to a reticle
            cross symbol
            <guiicon>
              <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/cursor-clone-modifier-select.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject>
            </guiicon>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-clone.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Normally, tool options are displayed in a window attached under the
      Toolbox as soon as you activate a tool. If they are not, you can access
      them from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Windows</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tool Options</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> which opens the option window of the selected tool.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mode</term>
        <term>Opacity</term>
        <term>Brush</term>
        <term>Size</term>
        <term>Aspect Ratio</term>
        <term>Angle</term>
        <term>Spacing</term>
        <term>Hardness</term>
        <term>Force</term>
        <term>Dynamics</term>
        <term>Dynamics Options</term>
        <term>Apply Jitter</term>
        <term>Smooth Stroke</term>
        <term>Lock brush to view</term>
        <term>Expand Layers</term>
        <listitem>
          <xi:include href="about-common-paint-options.xml"/>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Patterns</primary>
            <secondary>Clone</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            The choice you make here determines whether data will be copied
            from the pattern shown above, or from one of the images you have
            open.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Image</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  If you choose <guilabel>Image source</guilabel>, you must
                  tell <acronym>GIMP</acronym> which layer to use as the
                  source, by <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-clicking on it, before
                  you can paint with the tool.
                </para>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Sample merged</guilabel>:
                  If you enable this option, sampling is not calculated only
                  from the values of the active layer, but from all visible layers.
                </para>
                <para>
                  For more information, see the
                  <link linkend="glossary-samplemerge">Glossary entry</link>.
                </para>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/toolbox/clone-ex-sample-merged-example.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para>
                      Example image showing the cloned pixels in the upper left
                      corner.
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/toolbox/clone-ex-sample-merged-dialog.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para>
                      Layers dialog showing the new layer with the cloned pixels.
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Pattern</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Clicking on the pattern symbol brings up the Patterns
                  dialog, which you can use to select the pattern to paint
                  with. This option is only relevant if you are cloning from a
                  Pattern source.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Alignment</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Alignment mode defines the relation between the brush
            position and the source position.
          </para>
          <para>
            In the following examples, we will use a source image where the
            sample to be cloned will be taken, and a destination image where
            the sample will be cloned (it could be a layer in the source
            image)
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Original images for clone alignment</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/clone-source.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  We will use the largest brush with the Pencil tool. The
                  source is represented here with a ringed cross.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/toolbox/clone-dest.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  An image with a solid background only. We shall draw three
                  cloning strokes successively.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>None</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  In this mode, each brushstroke is treated separately. For
                  each stroke, the point where you first click is copied from
                  the source origin; there is no relationship between one
                  brush stroke and another. In non-aligned mode, different
                  brush strokes will usually clash if they intersect each
                  other.
                </para>
                <para>
                  Example below: At every new brush stroke, the source goes
                  back to its first position. The same sample is always
                  cloned.
                </para>
                <figure>
                  <title><quote>None</quote> clone alignment</title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/clone-none.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Aligned</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  In this mode, the first click you make when painting sets
                  the offset between the source origin and the cloned result,
                  and all subsequent brushstrokes use the same offset. Thus,
                  you can use as many brushstrokes as you like, and they will
                  all mesh smoothly with one another.
                </para>
                <para>
                  If you want to change the offset, select a new source origin
                  by clicking with the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key pressed.
                </para>
                <para>
                  In the example below, at every new brush stroke, the source
                  keeps the same offset it had with the previous brush stroke.
                  So, there is no cloning offset for the first brush stroke.
                  Here, for the following strokes, the source ends up out of
                  the source image canvas; hence the truncated aspect.
                </para>
                <figure>
                  <title><quote>Aligned</quote> clone alignment</title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/clone-aligned.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Registered</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The <quote>Registered</quote> mode is different from the
                  other alignment modes. When you copy from an image, a
                  <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-click will register a source layer.
                  Then painting in a target layer will clone each
                  corresponding pixel (pixel with the same offset) from the
                  source layer. This is useful when you want to clone parts
                  of an image from one layer to another layer within the same
                  image. (But remember that you can also clone from one image
                  to another image.)
                </para>
                <para>
                  At every brush stroke, the source adopts the position of the
                  mouse pointer in the destination layer. In the following
                  example, the destination layer is smaller than the source
                  layer; so, there is no truncated aspect.
                </para>
                <figure>
                  <title><quote>Registered</quote> clone alignment</title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/clone-registered.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Fixed</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Using this mode you will paint with the source origin,
                  unlike the modes <guilabel>None</guilabel> or
                  <guilabel>Aligned</guilabel> even when drawing a line. The
                  source will not be moved.
                </para>
                <para>
                  See that the source remains fixed. The same small sample is
                  reproduced identically in a tightened way:
                </para>
                <figure>
                  <title><quote>Fixed</quote> clone alignment</title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/clone-fixed.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hard edge</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option gives a hard contour to the cloned area.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="filter-and-history-brushes">
    <title>Further Information</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Transparency</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The effects of the Clone tool on transparency are a bit
            complicated. You cannot clone transparency: if you try to clone
            from a transparent source, nothing happens to the target. If you
            clone from a partially transparent source, the effect is weighted
            by the opacity of the source. So, assuming 100% opacity and a hard
            brush:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent black onto white produces gray.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent black onto black produces black.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent white onto white produces white.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Cloning translucent white onto black produces gray.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            Cloning can never increase transparency, but, unless <quote>keep
            transparency</quote> is turned on for the layer, it can reduce
            it.
            Cloning an opaque area onto a translucent area produces an opaque
            result; cloning a translucent area onto another translucent area
            causes an increase in opacity.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><quote>Filter</quote> brushes</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Brushes</primary>
            <secondary>Filter brush</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            There are a few non-obvious ways to use the Clone tool to obtain
            powerful effects. One thing you can do is to create <quote>Filter
            brushes</quote>, that is, create the effect of applying a filter
            with a brush. To do this, duplicate the layer you want to work
            on, and apply the filter to the copy. Then activate the Clone
            tool, setting Source to <quote>Image source</quote> and Alignment
            to <quote>Registered</quote>. <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-click on the
            filtered layer to set it as the source, and paint on the original
            layer: you will then in effect be painting the filtered image
            data onto the original layer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>History brush</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Brushes</primary>
            <secondary>History brush</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
            You can use a similar approach to imitate Photoshop's
            <quote>History brush</quote>, which allows you to selectively
            undo or redo changes using a brush. To do this, start by
            duplicating the image; then, in the original, go back to the
            desired state in the image's history, either by undoing or by
            using the Undo History dialog. (This must be done in the
            original, not the copy, because duplicating an image does not
            duplicate the Undo history.) Now activate the Clone tool,
            setting Source to <quote>Image source</quote> and Alignment to
            <quote>Registered</quote>. <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-click on a layer
            from one image, and paint on the corresponding layer from the
            other image. Depending on how you do it, this gives you either
            an <quote>undo brush</quote> or a <quote>redo brush</quote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
