<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- comments:
  This is at the moment a suggestion. Hoping somebody will enhance it.
	Kolbjoern
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-dynamics">
  <title>Dynamics</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Dynamics</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dynamics</primary>
  </indexterm>

	<para>
    The dynamics apply a more <quote>real feeling</quote> to the brush by
		connecting one or more of the brush parameters to the use of the brush. 
		You may for instance let the width of the pencil vary according to the speed of 
		the stylus or the mouse, make the color saturation depending on the stylus 
		pressure, make the color changing as the direction of the brush changes on the 
		canvas, and so on. You may choose among several presets or define your own. The 
		dynamics are created for use together with drawing tablets, but some are available 
		using the mouse.
  </para>
  <para>
		The dynamics will make some of the behaviours of the drawing tools act more 
		like the physical (<quote>real</quote>) tools. 
  </para>	
	
  <figure>
    <title>Dynamics in Tool Options </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-options.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
    The dynamics area in the tools option dialog shows from left to right, the 
		button to open the list containing the available dynamic presets, a field 
		displaying the name of the current preset, and rightmost the edit button.		
		Click on the button 
		<guiicon>
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-folders-dynamics-22.png"/>
    </guiicon>
		to open the dialog window displaying the available dynamics presets to select 
		another preset.
  </para>

	<sect3>
    <title>The Paint Dynamics Selection Dialog</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The Paint Dynamics Selection Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-select.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
		<para>
			The paint dynamics dialog can be opened
		</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the image-menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Paint Dynamics</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
      </listitem>				
      <listitem>
        <para>
          or by clicking on the button <guibutton>Open the dynamics selection</guibutton> 
					in the list of dynamics presets.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
		<para>
		  The <guilabel>Dynamics Selection</guilabel> dialog is a dockable dialog; see 
			the section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on 
			manipulating it.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <para>
			  From this dialog you can select from all the available presets, just 
				as from the list of dynamic presets. In addition there are five 
				buttons:			  
			</para>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Edit dynamics: Click on this to edit the selected dynamics. 
        </para>
      </listitem>		
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create a new dynamics: Do just that.
        </para>
      </listitem>
			<listitem>
        <para>
          Duplicate this dynamics: Make a copy of the selected dynamics.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Delete this dynamics: Delete the selected dynamics.
        </para>
      </listitem>	
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Refresh dynamics: Update the dynamics list.
        </para>
      </listitem>				
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect3>
	
	<sect3>
    <title>Editing Paint Dynamics</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Editing Paint Dynamics</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-edit.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
		  <para>
			  The paint dynamics edit dialog can be called from
			</para>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          the edit button in the Tool options dialog,
        </para>
      </listitem>		
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the Paint Dynamics Selection dialog by either clicking the 
					button <guibutton>Edit Dynamics</guibutton> or the button <guibutton>Create a New 
					Dynamics</guibutton>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
	  <para>
		  You select the desirable behavior by clicking in the small squares. 
			Clicking a second time unselect the marking. 
		</para>		
    <note>
      <para>
        If you open a dynamics in the edit dialog it is usually grayed out 
				meaning you are not allowed to change the settings. To edit the 
				options you have to work on a copy made from one of the preinstalled 
				dynamics or create a new dynamics.
      </para>
    </note>
		
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
		<title>The Paint Dynamics Matrix</title>
		<para>
      The main part of the edit dialog is a table where you can decide 
			which brush parameters should be affected by the way you use the stylus or the 
			mouse. You may enable as many parameters and parameter combinations as you wish
			but usually the fewer the better.
    </para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
		  <para>
			  Each column in the table represents a stylus or mouse action except the 
				random and the fade functions.
			</para>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: This is only meaningful if you are
					using a graphic tablet. It allows you to decide which aspects of the
					tool's action should be affected by the press of the stylus
					against the tablet.
        </para>
      </listitem>		
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: This is the speed of the stylus or the 
					mouse. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: This is the direction of the stylus or the mouse.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Tilt</guilabel>: This is only meaningful if you are using a 
					graphic tablet. The behavior of the function depends on the tilting
					of the stylus.
        </para>
      </listitem>	
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Wheel</guilabel>: This is only meaningful if you are using a 
					graphic tablet. The output depends on the rotation of the stylus or 
					the setting of the wheel on the airbrush pen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The selected option will change at random. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: The selected option will be faded in or out 
					depending on the settings of the fade options in the Dynamic Options
					menu.
        </para>
      </listitem>			
    </itemizedlist>
		
		<para>
			Each line shows a brush parameter and seven check-boxes, one for each action.
			You connect the parameters to the actions by clicking the appropriate boxes. 
			Clicking on a box a second time will unselect the connection.
    </para>
		<variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Opacity</term>
        <listitem>
					<para>
            <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: Press harder to make the drawing less transparent.
					</para>	
					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: The opacity decrease as the speed of the 
						stylus increase. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: The opacity depends on the direction of the 
						stylus or the mouse. The effect seems to have a touch of randomness built in. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Tilt</guilabel>: The opacity depends on the tilt of the stylus.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Wheel</guilabel>: TO DO 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The opacity change at random in the interval set by the 
						opacity slider in the tool options dialog. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: Starting with full transparency and ending with the
						opacity set by the opacity slider in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
			
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Size</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
            <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: Press harder to make the brush wider.
					</para>	
					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: Increasing speed decrease the width of the brush. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: The size of the brush depends on the direction of the 
						stylus or the mouse. The effect seems to have a touch of randomness built in. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Tilt</guilabel>: The size of the brush depends on the tilt of the stylus.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Wheel</guilabel>:  
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The size of the brush change at random up to the size  
						set in the brush size slider in the tool options dialog. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: Fades from a narrow brush to the size set in the brush
						size slider in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Angle</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
            TO DO 
					</para>						
        </listitem>				
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Color</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						By default the color is picked from the foreground color in the toolbox.
						However, if the color is activated in the dynamics editor, the 
						color is instead collected from the active gradient.
					</para>

					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: At slow speeds the color is collected from the right 
						side of the gradient. As the speed increase the color is picked more and more 
						from the left side of the gradient. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: The direction determine where on the gradient the 
						color is picked from. The effect seems to have work a bit on random.  
					</para>

					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The color is picked at random from the gradient. 
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: The start color is collected from the left side of the 
						gradient and then more and more from the right side during the stroke. 
						The behavior of the fading is set in the fade options in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
				<term>Hardness</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The hardness option is useful only for fuzzy brushes.
					</para>				

					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: At slow speed the brush is hard and become more fuzzy 
						as the speed increase. 
					</para>

					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The fussiness of the brush varies at random.  
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: The brush become less fuzzy during the stroke. 
						The behavior of the fading is set in the fade options in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>					
      </varlistentry>
			
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Force</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            TO DO
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Aspect Ratio</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The Aspect Ratio Slider in the Tool Options must be set to other values than 
						the default value of 0.00 to activate the dynamics. If the aspect ratio slider
						is set to a negative value the height of the brush is constant but the width
						of the brush will vary. If the slider is set to a positive value only the 
						height of the brush will vary.
					</para>				
	
					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: The aspect ratio of the brush (width / height) 
						varies with the speed.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: The aspect ratio of the brush varies with the 
						moving direction of the brush. The effect seems to have a touch of randomness built in. 
					</para>

					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The aspect ratio of the brush varies at random.   
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>:  
						If the Aspect Ratio Slider is set to a positive value the brush will 
						fade from full height at the start of the stroke to the height set by the 
						aspect ratio slider. If the slider is set to a negative value the brush 
						fades from full width to the width set by the aspect ratio slider.
						The behavior of the fading is set in the fade options in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>				
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Spacing</term>				
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Spacing is the distance between the marks set by the    
						brush when drawing lines. This option determines if the spacing is affected 
						and how, by the way the stylus is used.
					</para>				
	
					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: The spacing between the footprints of the brush 
						increase with increasing speed.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: The spacing varies with the moving direction 
						of the brush. The effect seems to have a touch of randomness built in. 
					</para>

					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The spacing varies at random.   
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>:  
						Starting with a wide spacing and gradually make the spacing narrower.
						The behavior of the fading is set in the fade options in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>					
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rate</term>				
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This option applies to the Airbrush, Convolve tool, and
						Smudge tool, all of which have time-based effects.
					</para>				
					<para>
            TO DO
					</para>	
        </listitem>					
      </varlistentry>	
			
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Flow</term>			
				<listitem>
					<para>
            TO DO
					</para>	
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Jitter</term>			
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Normally the brush draw a line by printing the brush marks close together. 
						Adding jitter means that the brush prints are scattered along the line. The
						amount of scattering depends on the setting of the jitter slider in the tool 
						options dialog window.
					</para>				
					<para>
            <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: 
					</para>	
					<para>
						<guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: At slow speed the brush prints are spread according 
						to the value set in the jitter amount slider. As the speed increase the 
						scattering amount decrease.
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: The jitter effect depends on the direction of the brush. The effect seems to have a touch of randomness built in. 
					</para>

					<para>
						<guilabel>Random</guilabel>: The jitter varies at random.   
					</para>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Fade</guilabel>:  
						Starting with no jitter and ending with the amount of jitter set in the 
						jitter amount slider. The behavior of the fading is set in the fade options 
						in the tool options dialog.
					</para>
        </listitem>				
      </varlistentry>			
		</variablelist>		
	</sect3>
	
	<sect3>
		<title>Fine Tuning the Dynamics</title>
		<figure>
      <title>Fine Tuning the Dynamics</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-tuning.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>		
		<para>
			If the current options do not suits you, you may fine-tune the settings from
			the Paint Dynamics Editor. Click on the down arrow to open the drop down menu 
			and then select what option to change.
		</para>
		
		<figure>
      <title>The Fine Tuning Curve</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-tuning-color.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>	
		<para>
			Click on one of the options to open the fine tuning dialog. The upper part of the
			dialog contains a curve where you can adjust the behaviour of the chosen parameters
			selected in the lower part of the dialog.		
		</para>
	</sect3>
	
<!-- ****** Dynamic Options: ****** -->	
	
	<sect3 id="gimp-tool-dynamic-options">
		<title>Dynamics Options</title>
		
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Tools</primary>
			<secondary>Dynamics Options</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Dynamics Options</primary>
		</indexterm>
	
		<figure>
      <title>Dynamics Options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/dynamics-options.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
		<para>
			Many of the dynamics behaviours also depends on the settings of the 
			Dynamics Options in the tool options dialog and vice versa. For example
			will the fading not work if it is not applied in the Dynamics section.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fade Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This slider determinds the length of the fading. What will
            actually happen depends on the setting of the Dynamic. If 
						set to act on the color for example, the color will be taken from 
						the current gradient starting from the left side of the gradient and 
						moving toward the right side of the gradient.
          </para>
					<para>
						The Fade Options has a drop down list determining how the
						fading is repeated.  
					</para>					
					<figure>
						<title>
						  Illustration of the effects of the three gradient-repeat
              options, for the <guilabel>Abstract 2</guilabel> gradient.
						</title>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata format="PNG"
									fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-normal.png"/>
							</imageobject>
							<caption>
                  <para>Abstract2 Gradient</para>
              </caption>
						</mediaobject>
						<mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-none.png"/>
              </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>None</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-sawtooth.png"/>
              </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>Sawtooth</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>						
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-triangular.png"/>
              </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>Triangular</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>						
					</figure>
					<para>
            This option determines what happens if a brush stroke extends
            farther than the Length specified by the slider. There are three
            possibilities:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>None</guilabel> means that the color from the end of
                the gradient will be used throughout the remainder of the
                stroke;
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Sawtooth wave</guilabel> means that the
                gradient will be restarted from the beginning, which
                will often produce a color discontinuity;
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Triangular wave</guilabel> means that the
                gradient will be traversed in reverse, afterwards bouncing
                back and forth until the end of the brush stroke.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>					
        </listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
        <term>Color Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Here you may choose which gradient to use as the color source when using the 
						brush with the color option set. Click on the box showing the gradient to 
						change to another one from the gradient list. 
          </para>
					<para>
					  If none of the color options are selected, the brush will use the
						foreground color set in the toolbox.
					</para>
        </listitem>				
			</varlistentry>	

		</variablelist>			
	</sect3>
</sect2>
