<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- Section history:
  2012-10-20 Created by Kolbjoern
-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-dynamics">
  <title>Dynamics</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Dynamics</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Dynamics</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The dynamics apply a more <quote>real feeling</quote> to the brush by
    connecting one or more of the brush parameters to the way of using the
    brush. You may for instance let the width of the pencil vary according to
    the speed of the stylus or the mouse, make the color saturation
    depending on the stylus pressure, make the color changing as the
    direction of the brush changes on the canvas, and so on. You may choose
    among several presets or define your own. The dynamics are created to be
    used together with drawing tablets, but some are available using the mouse.
  </para>
  <para>
    The dynamics will make some of the behaviors of the drawing tools act more
    like the physical (<quote>real</quote>) tools.
  </para>

  <para>
    The Dynamics area in the Tool Option dialog shows from left to right, the
    button to open the list containing the available dynamic presets, a field
    displaying the name of the current preset, and rightmost the edit button.
    Click on the
    <guiicon>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-dynamics.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </guiicon>
    button to open the dialog window displaying the available dynamics presets
    and select another preset.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dynamics-dialog">
    <title>The Paint Dynamics Dialog</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The Paint Dynamics Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-select.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The Paint Dynamics dialog window can be opened
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          from the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Paint Dynamics</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          or by clicking on the <guibutton>Open the dynamics
          selection</guibutton>
          button in the list of dynamics presets.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      This dialog is a dockable dialog; see the
      section <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-docks"/> for help on manipulating
      it.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <para>
        From this dialog you can select from all the available presets, just
        as from the list of dynamics presets.
      </para>
      <para>
         The button bar at the bottom offers the following functionality:
      </para>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-edit"/>
        <para>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gtk-edit.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <guilabel>Edit this dynamics</guilabel>: Clicking this will open the
          <link linkend="gimp-dynamics-editor-dialog">Paint Dynamics Editor</link> dialog
          where you will be able to edit the selected dynamics.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-new"/>
        <para>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/document-new.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <guilabel>Create a new dynamics</guilabel>: Do just that.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-duplicate"/>
        <para>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-duplicate.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <guilabel>Duplicate this dynamics</guilabel>: Make a copy of the
          selected dynamics.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-delete"/>
        <para>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/edit-delete.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <guilabel>Delete this dynamics</guilabel>: Delete the selected
          dynamics. Note: this button is disabled for the default dynamics
          that come with GIMP.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-refresh"/>
        <para>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/view-refresh.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <guilabel>Refresh dynamics</guilabel>: Update the dynamics list.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect4 id="gimp-dynamics-dialog-menu">
      <title>Dynamics Context Menu</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>Dynamics</primary>
        <secondary>Menu</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Overview</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              You can get the dynamics context menu by right clicking on a
              dynamics preset.
              Most of the operations on dynamics are also available through
              buttons at the bottom of the dynamics dialog. Those operations are
              documented <link linkend="gimp-dynamics-dialog">there</link>.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><guilabel>Edit Dynamics…</guilabel></term>
                <term><guilabel>New Dynamics</guilabel></term>
                <term><guilabel>Duplicate Dynamics</guilabel></term>
                <term><guilabel>Delete Dynamics</guilabel></term>
                <term><guilabel>Refresh Dynamics</guilabel></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    See
                    <link linkend="gimp-dynamics-dialog">Dynamics Dialog</link>.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Copy Dynamics Location</term>
                <listitem>
                  <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-copy-location"/>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Copy Dynamics Location</guilabel> allows you to
                    copy the path of the selected Dynamics preset to the
                    clipboard.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Show in File Manager</term>
                <listitem>
                  <anchor id="gimp-dynamics-show-in-file-manager"/>
                  <para>
                    <guilabel>Show in File Manager</guilabel> opens the
                    location of the Dynamics preset in the default
                    File Manager on your system.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect4>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dynamics-editor-dialog">
    <title>Editing Paint Dynamics</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Paint Dynamics Editor dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-edit.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The Paint Dynamics Editor can be called from:
      </para>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          the edit button in the Tool Options dialog,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          the Paint Dynamics selection dialog by clicking either the
          <guibutton>Edit Dynamics</guibutton> button or the <guibutton>Create
          a New Dynamics</guibutton> button.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      You select the desired behaviors by clicking in the small squares.
      Clicking a second time will unselect the marking.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Pre-installed dynamics are disabled as you cannot change their
        settings. To edit the options you have to work on a copy
        made from one of the pre-installed dynamics or create a new dynamics.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>The Paint Dynamics Matrix</title>
    <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Dynamics Matrix</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Dynamics Matrix</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The main part of the edit dialog is a table where you can decide
      which brush parameters should be affected by the way you use the stylus
      or the mouse. You can enable as many parameters and parameter
      combinations you want, but usually the fewer the better.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Each column in the table represents a stylus or mouse action except
        the random and the fade functions. All functions works with graphic
        tablet. Some of the functions are also available using the mouse. These
        functions are marked in the tables. The descriptions are using the
        default settings of all functions
      </para>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: It allows you to decide which
          aspects of the tool's action will be affected by pressing the
          stylus against the tablet.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) This is the speed of
          the brush.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) This is the moving direction
          of the brush.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Tilt</guilabel>: The behavior of the function depends
          on the tilting of the stylus.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Wheel</guilabel>: The output depends on the rotation of
          the stylus or the setting of the wheel on the airbrush pen.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The selected option will
          change at random.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) The selected option will be
          faded in or out depending on the settings of the fade options in
          the Dynamic Options menu of the Tools Option dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Each row shows a brush parameter and seven checkboxes, one for
      each action. You connect the parameters to the actions by clicking
      the appropriate boxes. Clicking on a selected box will unselect the
      connection.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Opacity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: Press harder to make the drawing
            less transparent.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) The opacity decreases as
            the speed of the stylus increases.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) The opacity depends on
            the direction of the stylus or the mouse. The effect seems to
            have a touch of randomness built in.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Tilt</guilabel>: The opacity depends on the tilt of
            the stylus.
          </para>
          <!-- TODO / FIXME: Document Wheel -->
          <para>
            <guilabel>Wheel</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The opacity changes at
            random in the interval set by the opacity slider in the Tool
            Options dialog.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) Starting with full transparency
            and ending with the opacity set by the opacity slider in the
            Tool Options dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: Press harder to make the brush
            wider.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) Increasing speed decreases
            the width of the brush.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) The size of the brush
            depends on the moving direction of the stylus or the mouse. The
            effect seems to have a touch of randomness built in.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Tilt</guilabel>: The size of the brush depends on the
            tilt of the stylus.
          </para>
          <!-- TODO / FIXME: Document Wheel -->
          <para>
            <guilabel>Wheel</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The size of the brush
            changes at random up to the size set in the brush size slider
            in the Tool Options dialog.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) Fades from a narrow brush to
            the size set by the brush size slider in the Tools Options dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Angle</term>
        <listitem>
          <!-- TODO / FIXME: Document Angle -->
          <para>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By default the color is picked from the foreground color in the
            toolbox. However, if the color is activated in the dynamics
            editor, the color is instead collected from the active gradient.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) At slow speeds the color
            is collected from the right side of the gradient. As the speed
            increase the color is picked more and more from the left side
            of the gradient.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) The direction determine
            where on the gradient the color is picked from. The effect seems
            to work a bit on random.
          </para>

          <para>
            <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The color is picked at
            random from the gradient.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) The start color is collected
            from the left side of the gradient and then more and more from
            the right side during the stroke. The behavior of the fading is
            set in the Fade Options in the Tool Options Dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hardness</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The hardness option is useful only for fuzzy brushes.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) At slow speed the brush
            is hard and become more fuzzy as the speed increase.
          </para>

          <para>
          <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The fussiness of the brush
          varies at random.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) The brush become less fuzzy
            during the stroke. The behavior of the fading is set in the Fade
            Options in the Tool Options Dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Force</term>
        <listitem>
          <!-- TODO / FIXME: Document Force -->
          <para>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Aspect Ratio</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Aspect Ratio Slider in the Tool Options Dialog must be set
            to other values than the default value of 0.00 to activate the
            dynamics. If the aspect ratio slider is set to a negative value
            the width of the brush will vary while the height of the brush
            is constant. If the slider is set to a positive value only the
            height of the brush will vary.
          </para>

          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) The aspect
            ratio of the brush (width / height) varies with the speed of
            the brush.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) The aspect ratio of the
            brush varies with the moving direction of the brush. The effect
            seems to have a touch of randomness built in.
          </para>

          <para>
            <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The aspect ratio of the
            brush varies at random.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) If the Aspect Ratio Slider
            is set to a positive value the brush will fade from full height
            at the start of the stroke to the height set by the aspect ratio
            slider. If the slider is set to a negative value the brush fades
            from full width to the width set by the aspect ratio slider. The
            behavior of the fading is set in the Fade Options in the Tool
            Options Dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Spacing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Spacing is the distance between the marks set by the brush when
            drawing lines. With this option set the spacing is affected by how
            the stylus or mouse is used.
          </para>

          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) The spacing between the
            footprints of the brush increases with increasing speed.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) The spacing varies with
            the moving direction of the brush. The effect seems to have a
            touch of randomness built in.
          </para>

          <para>
            <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse) The spacing varies at random.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) Starting with a wide spacing
            and gradually make the spacing narrower. The behavior of the
            fading is set in the Fade Options in the Tool Options Dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rate</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option applies to the Airbrush, Blur/Sharpen tool, and
            Smudge tool, all of which have time-based effects.
          </para>
          <para>
            The actions of these tools are more or less quick. The amount
            of Rate depends on the setting of the Rate slider in the Tool
            Options dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Flow</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Significant only for the Airbrush: more or less paint is delivered.
            The amount of flow depends on the setting of the Flow slider in the
            Tool Options dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Jitter</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Normally the brush draws a line by printing the brush marks close
            together. Adding jitter means that the brush prints are scattered
            along the line. The amount of scattering depends on the setting
            of the jitter slider in the Tool Options dialog window.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Pressure</guilabel>: At low pressure the brush prints
            are spread according to the value set in the jitter amount
            slider. As the pressure increases the scattering amount decreases.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Velocity</guilabel>: (mouse) At slow speed the brush
            prints are spread according to the value set in the jitter amount
            slider. As the speed increase the scattering amount decrease.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Direction</guilabel>: (mouse) The jitter effect depends
            on the direction of the brush. The effect seems to have a touch
            of randomness built in.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Random</guilabel>: (mouse)The jitter varies at random.
          </para>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Fade</guilabel>: (mouse) Starting with no jitter
            and ending with the amount of jitter set in the jitter amount
            slider. The behavior of the fading is set in the fade options
            in the Tool Options dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Customizing the Dynamics</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Customizing the Dynamics</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-tuning.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      If the current options do not suits you, you may fine-tune the settings
      from the Paint Dynamics Editor. Click on the down arrow to open the
      drop-down menu and then select what option to change.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title>The Fine Tuning Curve</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-tuning-color.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Click on one of the options to open the customizing dialog. The upper
      part of the dialog contains a curve where you can adjust the behaviour
      of the chosen parameters selected in the lower part of the dialog. You
      can drag the curve by pointing on it with the mouse pointer, holding
      down the left mouse button and the move the curve wherever you want
      inside the diagram.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Dynamics Examples</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Dynamics Options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-fade-example-1.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            The brush strokes examples
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-fade-example-2.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Image 5: Brush size: Fade curve
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-fade-example-3.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Image 6: Color: Fade curve
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The examples shown are very brief, but will perhaps give you an idea
      of how to use this functions. Feel free to try other combinations. In
      these examples the foreground color is set to blue (#0000ff) and the
      background color to yellow (#ffff00). Fading: 200 pixels. Paintbrush
      size: 72. All other settings are the default values except for those
      values changed
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Example 1 shows the result when the brush size is connected to the
          fading. Default options. The brush size starts as zero and increase
          to the size set in the brush size slider in the Tools Options Dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In example 2 the brush size is still connected to the fade tool,
          but the fade curve is set as in image 5. The brush size starts at
          zero, fades up to full size and then fades down to zero again.
        </para>
        <para>
          The full fade length is set along the x-axis from left to right. The
          y-axis determines the size of the brush. At the bottom the brush size
          is zero, and at the top of the diagram the brush is set to the full
          size according to the size set in the slider in the Brush Options
          Dialog. Study the example and the curve to see the relationship.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In example 3 the brush size is disconnected from the fade tool. The
          color is connected with the fade option with the curve set as in
          image 6. At the start of the drawing the color is picked from the
          left side of the gradient, then gradually more from the right side
          of the gradient and then finally fading back to the left side again.
        </para>
        <para>
          As usual the x-axis is the total fade length. When the curve is
          near the bottom of the diagram the color is picked from the left
          side of the gradient. With the curve at the top of the diagram
          the color is picked from the right side of the gradient.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The last example shows a combination of these two settings. Both
          the size of the brush and the color are connected to the fading
          function with the curves set as in image 5 and 6.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

<!-- ****** Dynamic Options: ****** -->

  <sect3 id="gimp-tool-dynamic-options">
    <title>Dynamics Options</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Tools</primary>
      <secondary>Dynamics Options</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Dynamics Options</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <figure>
      <title>Dynamics Options</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/paint-dynamics-options.png"
          format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Many of the dynamics behaviors also depends on the settings of the
      Dynamics Options in the Tool Options dialog and vice versa. For example
      the fading will not work if it is not applied in the Dynamics section.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fade Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This slider determines the length of the fading. What will
            actually happen depends on the setting of the Dynamic. If
            set to act on the color for example, the color will be taken from
            the current gradient starting from the left side of the gradient
            and moving toward the right side of the gradient.
          </para>
          <para>
            The Fade Options has a drop-down list determining how the
            fading is repeated.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>
              Illustration of the effects of the three gradient-repeat
              options, for the <guilabel>Abstract 2</guilabel> gradient.
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-normal.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                  <para>Abstract2 Gradient</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-none.png"/>
              </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>None</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-sawtooth.png"/>
              </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>Sawtooth</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/tool-options/brush-gradient-triangular.png"/>
              </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>Triangular</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>
            This option determines what happens if a brush stroke extends
            farther than the Length specified by the slider. There are three
            possibilities:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>None</guilabel> means that the color from the end of
                the gradient will be used throughout the remainder of the
                stroke;
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Sawtooth wave</guilabel> means that the
                gradient will be restarted from the beginning, which
                will often produce a color discontinuity;
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Triangular wave</guilabel> means that the
                gradient will be traversed in reverse, afterwards bouncing
                back and forth until the end of the brush stroke.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Color Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Here you can choose the gradient to use as color source
            when using the brush with the color option set. Click on the box
            showing the gradient to change to another one from the gradient
            list.
          </para>
          <para>
            If no color option is selected in the currently used
            dynamics, the brush will use the foreground color set in the
            toolbox.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
