<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='gimp-image-window-qmask-button'>
  <title lang="en">QuickMask</title>
  <title lang="fr">Masque rapide</title>
  <title lang="sv">Snabbmask</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">QuickMask</primary>
    <primary lang="fr">Masque Rapide</primary>
    <primary lang="sv">Snabbmask</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/dialogs/dialogs-channel-quickmask.png' format='png'/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <para lang="en">
    The <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">selection tools</link> 
	sometimes show their limits when they have to be used for creating 
	a complex selection. In these cases, 
	using the QuickMask can make things much easier.  Simply put,
	the QuickMask allows you to paint a selection instead of just
	tracing its outline.                             
  </para>
  <para lang="fr">
	  Les <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">outils de sélection</link> 
		montrent parfois leurs limites lorsqu'il s'agit de créer des sélections 
		aux contours complexes, voir progressifs. Dans ce cas l'utilisation du 
		Masque rapide s'avère particulièrement efficace.
  </para>
  <para lang="sv">
    Ibland visar <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">Markeringsverktygen</link>
    sina gränser för kompliserade målningar progressivt.
    Om detta är fallet, då är snabbmask en god idé att använda vilket
    kan ge goda resultat.
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <title lang="sv">Översikt</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <listitem lang="en">
	  <para>
	    Normally when you create a selection in Gimp, you see it
	    represented by the "marching ants" that trace along its
	    outline.  But really there may be a lot more to a
	    selection than the marching ants show you: in Gimp a
	    selection is actually a full-fledged grayscale channel,
	    covering the image, with pixel values ranging from 0
	    (unselected) to 256 (fully selected).  The marching ants
	    are drawn along a contour of half-selected pixels.  Thus,
	    what the marching ants show you as either-or---inside or
	    outside the boundary---is really just a slice through a
	    continuum. 
	  </para>
          <para>
	    The QuickMask is Gimp's way of showing you the full
            structure of the selection.  Activating it also gives you
            the ability to interact with the selection in new, and
            substantially more powerful, ways.  To activate the
            QuickMask,  click on the small red-outlined button at the
            lower left of the image window.  The button is a toggle,
            so clicking it again will return you to normal
            marching-ant mode.  You can also activate the QuickMask by
            selecting in the image
            window menu  <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>elect/Toggle
            <accel>Q</accel>uickMask</guimenuitem>, or by using
            the <keycap>Shift+Q</keycap> shortcut. 
          </para>
          <para>
	    Activating the QuickMask shows you the selection as though
            it were a translucent screen overlying the image, whose
            transparency at each pixel indicates the degree to which
            that pixel is selected.  By default the mask is shown in
            red, but you can change this if another mask color would
            be more convenient.  The less a pixel is selected, the
            more it is obscured by the mask.  Fully selected pixels
            are shown completely clear.
           </para>
	  <para>
	    When you are in QuickMask mode, many image manipulations
	    act on the selection channel rather than the image
	    itself.  This includes, in particular, paint tools.
	    Painting with white causes the painted pixels to be
	    selected; painting with black causes them to be
	    unselected.  You can use any of the paint tools, as well
	    as the bucket fill and gradient fill tools, in this way.
	    Advanced users of the Gimp learn that "painting the
	    selection" is the easiest and most effective way to
	    delicately manipulate it.
	  </para>
          <tip>
            To save in a channel the selection done with the Quickmask
            select in the image menu 
            <guimenuitem>Select/Save to Channel</guimenuitem>
          </tip>
          <tip>
	    When QuickMask is active, Cut and Paste act on the
	    selection rather than the image.  You can sometimes make
	    use of this as the most convenient way of transferring a
	    selection from one image to another.
          </tip>
          <para>
            You can learn more on <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quickmask</link> 
						and <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Selection masks</link> 
						in the section dedicated to the channel dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	      <listitem lang="fr">
	        <para>
            Pour activer le Masque rapide cliquez sur le button en bas à gauche 
						tel qu'indiqué en rouge dans la capture d'écran ci-dessus ou sélectionnez 
						dans le menu d'image <guimenuitem><accel>S</accel>élection/(Dés)Activer le mas
						<accel>q</accel>ue rapide</guimenuitem>. 
						Il peut aussi être activé à l'aide du raccourci clavier <keycap>Maj+Q</keycap>.
	        </para>
	        <para>
					  Cette commande génère un canal temporaire 8-bit (0-255) sur lequel le travail 
						de sélection progressivement établi est peu à peu enregistré. 
						Si une sélection est déjà présente, le masque est initialisé avec le 
						contenu de la sélection. Une fois le Masque Rapide activé, l'image est 
						recouverte d'un voile rouge semi-transparent. Celui-ci représente les pixels 
						non-sélectionnés de l'image. N'importe quel 
						<link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">outil de dessin</link> peut être utilisé 
						pour modifier ce masque et créer la sélection résultante. Ces outils devraient 
						être utilisés uniquement en niveaux de gris, conformément à la nature des canaux, 
						le blanc permettant de définir la future zone à sélectionner. 
						Cette sélection ne sera affichée que lorsque le Masque rapide sera desactivé. 
						Mais à partir de ce moment, le canal temporaire est définitivement perdu et 
						seul un retour immédiat au mode masque permet de la récupérer.
          </para>
          <tip>
            Pour sauvegarder dans un canal la sélection créée avec le masque rapide, sélectionnez dans le
            menu d'image <guimenuitem>Sélection/Enregister dans un canal</guimenuitem>
          </tip>
          <para>
            Vous pourrez en apprendre bien plus sur le 
						<link linkend="gimp-qmask">masque rapide</link> 
						et les <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">masques de selection</link> 
						dans la section dédiée au dialogue des canaux.
          </para>
	      </listitem>
        <listitem lang="sv">
          <para>
            För att aktivera snabbmask, klicka på ikonen som visas i rött 
            som skrämdumpen ovanför visar eller gå via bildfönstrets meny 
            <guimenuitem><accel>V</accel>älj/Visa sna<accel>b</accel>bmask</guimenuitem>. 
            Det går även att aktivera snabbmask med snabbtangenterna 
            <keycap>Skift+Q</keycap>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Vad som händer nu är att det skapas en temporär 8-bit (0-255) kanal
            där den progressiva markeringen lagras. Om det redan finns en
            markering så kommer masken att använda markeringens innehåll. När
            snabbmask är aktiverad kommer bilden att fyllas med en röd
            semi-transparent grund. De röda delarna är de icke markerade
            pixlarna. För att skapa en markering i snabbmasken går det att
            använda vilket <link linkend="gimp-tool-paint">målarverktyg</link>
            som helst. Färg användning ska vara gråskalig för att markeringarna
            ska bli korrekta, använd vit färg för att ta bort snabbmask och
            skapa markering runt om det vita. Markeringen visas så fort
            snabbmask är avstängd, kanalen för snabbmask kommer inte längre att
            finnas kvar efter det att markeringen syns.
          </para>
          <tip>
            Du kan spara markeringen gjord efter snabbmask till en ny kanal genom att välja
            <guimenuitem>Välj/Spara till kanal</guimenuitem>
          </tip>
          <para>
            Du kan lära dig mer om <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Snabbmask</link>
            och <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Markeringsmasker</link>
            i sektionen skriven för kanal fönstret.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Properties</title>
    <para lang="en">
	There are two QuickMask properties you can change by
	right-clicking on the QuickMask button.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem lang="en">
	  <para>
	    Normally the QuickMask shows unselected areas "fogged
	    over" and selected areas "in clear", but you can reverse
	    this by choosing "Mask Selected Areas" instead of the
	    default "Mask Unselected Areas".
	  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem lang="en">
	  <para>
	    By choosing "Configure Color and Opacity", you can bring
	    up a dialog that allows you to set these to values other
	    than the defaults, which are red at 50% opacity.
	  </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Usage</title>
    <title lang="fr">Utilisation</title>
    <title lang="sv">Hantering</title>
    <para lang="en"></para>
    <para lang="fr"></para>
    <para lang="sv"></para>
    <procedure lang="en">	
	<step>
	    Open an image or begin a new document;
	</step>
	<step>
	    Activate the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the
	    image window.  If a selection is present the mask is
	    initialized with the content of the selection; 
	</step>
	<step>
	    Choose any drawing tool and use it with greyscale colors on
	    the QuickMask; 
	</step>
	<step>
	    Toggle off the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in
	    the image window; 
	</step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure lang="fr">
	<step>
	    Ouvrir une image ou commencer un nouveau document;
	</step>
	<step>
	    Activer le Masque Rapide en utilisant le bouton Masque
	    rapide en bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image. Si une
	    sélection est présente, le masque est initialisé avec le
	    contenu de la sélection;     
	</step>
	<step>
	    Choisissez et paramétrez un outil de dessin dans la boite
	    à outils puis utilisez cet outil pour dessiner sur le
	    masque en niveaux de gris; 
	</step>
	<step>
	    Désactiver le Masque Rapide en utilisant le bouton Masque 
	    rapide en bas à gauche de la fenêtre d'image;    .
	</step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure lang="sv">
      <step>
        Öppna en bild eller skapa en ny;
      </step>
      <step>
        Aktivera snabbmask genom att klicka på ikonen för snabbmask i
        bildfönstret. Om det redan finns en markering kommer snabbmask att
        följa denna och inte lägga någon mask i markeringen;
      </step>
      <step>
        Välj ett verktyg för att måla och använd gråskaliga färger för snabbmask;
      </step>
      <step>
        Inaktivera snabbmask genom att klicka på samma ikon i bildfönstret.
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
