<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-11-21 j.h: initial version
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-view-show-all">
  <title>Show All</title>
  
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Show All</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Show All</guimenuitem> command
    makes all pixels visible that are outside the canvas and that are
    normally not part of the image. This allows you to drag new layers and
    images outside the canvas temporarily to work with them.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Command</title>
    <para>
      You can access this command from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Show All</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Basic principles about the <quote>Show All</quote> Command</title>
    <para>
      When you just open an image, the canvas size is the same as the image
      size, and applying the <quote>Show all</quote> command, of course, gives
      nothing since there is no pixel outside the canvas. So, enlarge the
      layer using the <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scale tool</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      This default behavior of <quote>Show All</quote> being disabled when
      opening a new image window, can be changed in the
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window">Image Window Preferences</link>,
      by changing the default for <quote>Show All</quote>.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Show All</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/menus/view/show_all-ex-no.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Layer enlarged. Command not checked.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/menus/view/show_all-ex-with.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>
            Layer enlarged. Command checked. 
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      When the <quote>Show all</quote> command is unchecked, pixels spilling 
      off the canvas boundary are not visible.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the command is checked, all pixels outside the canvas are visible 
      (if the layer size is enough). You can see:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The canvas boundary as a <emphasis>red dotted line</emphasis>. 
            You can paint outside the canvas, in the limit of the layer. 
            Changes made outside the canvas are not exported with the image, 
            unless you enlarge the canvas size using <link 
            linkend="gimp-image-resize">Canvas Size</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The layer boundary as a <emphasis>yellow dotted line</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A large <emphasis>checkerboard area</emphasis> indicating there is 
            no pixel.
          </para>
          <para>
            The checkerboard area is infinite: whatever the image window size, 
            it persists.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3>
    <title>Using the <quote>Show All</quote> command</title>
    <para>
      We will clone from a new image onto the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Open your image, check <quote>Show All</quote>, and enlarge layer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Open the new image. A new layer is created for this new image. 
            Click and drag this new layer onto your image. Use Move tool to 
            put the new image outside canvas.
          </para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="JPG"
                fileref="images/menus/view/show_all-ex-newimg.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Make new layer active. Use Clone tool and 
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-click on the new image to make it the 
            source.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Make image layer active. Paint on your image to clone the source. 
            You see that pixels in checkerboard area are cloned.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/menus/view/show_all-ex-clone.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
