<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-02 j.h: update to v2.8
  2009-01-16 j.h: updated to v2.6
  2007-12-19 ude: renamed id "gimp-view-zoom-fit-to" to "gimp-view-zoom-fill"
  2005/10/23 reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="gimp-view-zoom">
  <title>Zoom</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Zoom</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The <guimenuitem>Zoom</guimenuitem>
    submenu contains various commands which affect the magnification of the
    image in the image window (zooming). Enlarging an image (zooming in) is
    useful if you need to work with high precision, making pixel-level image
    modifications or precise selections. On the other hand, reducing an image
    (zooming out) is handy for getting an overall impression of the image and
    seeing the results of changes which affect the entire image. Please note
    that zooming is not undoable, since it does not affect the image data,
    only the way it is displayed.
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      Besides the entries in this submenu, there is also a zoom pull-down menu
      at the bottom edge of the image window (if the
      <link linkend="gimp-view-show-statusbar">status bar</link> is
      displayed), where several preset zoom levels are available.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also make settings regarding zooming in the
      <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Navigation dialog</link>. You
      can also use the <link linkend="gimp-tool-zoom">Zoom</link> tool
      which lets you zoom a particular area of the image.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Submenu</title>
    <para>
      You can access this submenu from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Zoom</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>.
      Note that the <quote>Zoom</quote> label on the <quote>View</quote>
      menu shows the current zoom factor, for example,
      <guilabel>Zoom (100%)</guilabel>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Contents of the <quote>Zoom</quote> submenu</title>
    <para>
      The various <quote>Zoom</quote> submenu commands are described below,
      along with their default keyboard shortcuts, if any.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Revert Zoom</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-revert"/>
          <para>
            (Shortcut: <keycap>`</keycap> [grave
            accent,<quote>backtick</quote>]) This command will reset the zoom
            factor to the previous value, which is also shown by this label,
            for example <guilabel>Revert Zoom (100%)</guilabel>. If you never
            changed the zoom factor of the active image, this entry is
            disabled.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Zoom Out</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-out"/>
          <para>
            (Shortcut: <keycap>-</keycap>)  Each time <quote>Zoom Out</quote>
            is used, the zoom factor is decreased by about 30%.  There is a
            minimum zoom level of 0.39%.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Zoom In</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-in"/>
          <para>
            (Shortcut: <keycap>+</keycap>)
            Each time <quote>Zoom In</quote> is used, the zoom factor is
            increased by about 30%.  The maximum possible zoom level is
            25600%.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              The keyboard shortcut for <quote>Zoom In</quote> has been
              somewhat controversial because this is a very common operation
              and on English keyboards, the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key must
              be pressed to use it. (This is not the case for European
              keyboards.) If you would like to have a different keyboard
              shortcut, you can create a dynamic shortcut for it; see the
              help section for <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">User
              Interface Preferences</link> for instructions.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fit Image in Window</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-fit-in" xreflabel="Fit Image in Window"/>
          <para>
            (Shortcut:
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>J</keycap>
            </keycombo>).
            This command zooms the image to be as large as possible, while
            still keeping it completely within the window.  There will
            usually be padding on two sides of the image, but not on all
            four sides.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fill Window</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-fill" xreflabel="Fill Window"/>
          <para>
            This command zooms the image as large as possible without
            requiring any padding to be shown. This means that the image
            fits the window perfectly in one dimension, but usually
            extends beyond the window borders in the other dimension.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Zoom to Selection</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-selection" xreflabel="Zoom to Selection"/>
          <para>
            This command zooms the image so that the selection fits the 
            smallest dimension of the image window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>A:B (X%)</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-100"/>
          <para>
            With these commands, you can select one of the pre-set zoom
            levels. Each of the menu labels gives a ratio, as well as a
            percentage value. Please note that each zoom pre-set has its own
            keyboard shortcut. The current zoom is marked with a large dot.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Other zoom factor…</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-view-zoom-other"/>
          <para>
            This command brings up a dialog which allows you to choose any
            zoom level you would like, within the range of 1:256 (0.39%) to
            256:1 (25600%).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <tip>
      <para>
        When you are working at the pixel level, you can use the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-new">New view</link> command. This
        allows you to see what is happening to the image at its normal size
        at the same time.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
