<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-colortoalpha' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Color to Alpha</title>
  <title lang="cs">Barva do alfy</title>
  <title lang="fr">Couleur vers Alpha</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">颜色到 Alpha</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Color</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Alpha</tertiary>

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Barvy</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">Barva do alfy</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Couleur</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Alpha</tertiary>

    <primary lang="zh_CN">滤镜</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">颜色</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="zh_CN">Alpha</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-color-colortoalpha.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="cs">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-color-colortoalpha.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="fr">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/fr/filters-color-colortoalpha.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <mediaobject lang="zh_CN">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/zh_CN/filters-color-colortoalpha.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>


  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Colors</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Color to Alpha</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. 
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Color to Alpha filter makes transparent all pixels with a
      selected color. An Alpha channel is created.  It will attempt to
      preserve antialiasing information by using a partially
      intelligent routine that replaces weak color information with
      weak alpha information. In this way, areas that contain an
      element of the selected color will maintain a blended appearence
      with their surrounding pixels.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit volbou
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Filtry</guimenu><guisubmenu>Barvy</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Barva do alfy</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
      z nabídky okna obrázku.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr barva do alfy učiní všechny pixely se zvolenou barvou průhlednými.
      Pokud ještě neexistuje, vytvoří se alfa kanál. Filtr se pokusí zachovat
      vyhlazování pomocí polointeligentního algoritmu, který místa s barvami
      podobnými zvolené barvě učiní částečně průhledné, průsvitné. Zůstane tak
      zachován plynulý přechod do okolních oblastí.
    </para>

    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre se trouve à
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Couleurs</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Couleur vers Alpha</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>. 
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Le filtre Couleur vers Alpha rend transparents tous les pixels
      ayant une certaine couleur sélectionnée. Un canal Alpha est
      créé. Il utilise un algorithme permettant de préserver les
      transitions entre les couleurs de façon à conserver un
      dégradé entre les pixels de la couleur sélectionnée et les
      pixels environnants, ainsi que l'anticrénelage des contours.
    </para> 

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该滤镜在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;滤镜/颜色/颜色到 Alpha</guimenuitem>。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      颜色到 Alpha 滤镜使所有包括指定颜色的像素变透明，同时会产生一个 Alpha 通道。它使用一种半智能的方式保存边缘平滑信息，即用弱 Alpha 信息替代弱的颜色信息。这样，包含指定颜色的区域将出现与周围像素相混合的现象。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Color</term>
        <term lang="cs">Barva</term>
        <term lang="fr">Couleur</term>
        <term lang="zh_CN">颜色</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Clicking on the <guilabel>From</guilabel> color swatch
            provides a color selection dialog where you can select a
            color. If selection of a precise color is required, use
            the Color Picker then drag and drop the selected color
            from the color picker to the From color swatch. Right
            clicking on the color will display a menu where you can
            select Foreground or Background colors, White or Black.
          </para>
          <para lang="cs">
            Kliknutím na barevné pole označené <guilabel>Z</guilabel> se
            otevře dialog pro výběr barvy. Pokud je třeba zvolit přesný
            barevný odstín, vyberte ho před použitím filtru Barevnou pipetou
            a pak přetáhněte barvu popředí z Panelu nástrojů myší na barevné
            pole v dialogu filtru Barva do alfy. Kliknutím pravým tlačítkem
            myši na barevné pole v dialogu filtru se otevře nabídka,
            umožňující přímo zadat barvu popředí, pozadí, černou nebo bílou.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            Le fait de cliquer sur la boîte d'échantillon
            <guilabel>Depuis</guilabel> affiche une fenêtre de
            dialogue permettant la sélection d'une couleur. Si une
            couleur précise est nécessaire, servez-vous de la
            pipette, et faites glisser la couleur sélectionnée pour
            aller la déposer dans la boîte d'échantillon
            «Depuis». Le clic droit sur la boîte d'échantillon
            développe un menu permettant de choisir la couleur de
            Premier-plan, d'Arrière-plan, le Blanc ou le Noir.
          </para>
          <para lang="zh_CN">
            点击<guilabel>从</guilabel>颜色条会唤出颜色选择对话框。当要选取一个精确的颜色时，使用颜色拾取工具，然后将颜色拾取中的颜色拖拉到该颜色条中。在该颜色条上点击右键会出现一个可以选择背景色，前景色，白色和黑色的菜单。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
