<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-semiflatten' lang="en;cs;fr;zh_CN">
  <title lang="en">Semi-Flatten</title>
  <title lang="cs">Částečně zploštit</title>
  <title lang="fr">Aplatir à moitié</title>
  <title lang="zh_CN">半平整</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Filter</primary>
    <secondary lang="en">Color</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="en">Flatten</tertiary>

    <primary lang="cs">filtry</primary>
    <secondary lang="cs">Barvy</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="cs">Částečně zploštit</tertiary>

    <primary lang="fr">Filtre</primary>
    <secondary lang="fr">Couleur</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="fr">Aplatir</tertiary>

    <primary lang="zh_CN">滤镜</primary>
    <secondary lang="zh_CN">颜色</secondary>
    <tertiary lang="zh_CN">平整</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="cs">Přehled</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">概述</title>

    <para lang="en">
      This filter is found in the image menu via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Colors</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Semi-Flatten</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      It is available if your image holds an Alpha channel 
      (Image&gt;Layers/Transparency/Add an alpha channel). 
      Otherwise, it is greyed out.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Semi-flatten filter helps those in need of a solution to 
      anti-aliasing indexed images with transparency. The GIF indexed format 
      supports complete transparency (0 or 255 alpha value), but not 
      semi-transparency (1 - 254): semi-transparent pixels will be 
      transformed to no transparence or complete transparence, ruining 
      anti-aliasing you applied to the logo you want to put onto your Web 
      page.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Before applying the filter, it's essential that you should know the 
      background color of your Web page. Use the color-picker to determine 
      the exact color. Click and drag this color from the Web 
      page to the Toolbox ForeGround color. Invert FG/BG colors so that BG 
      color is the same as Web background color.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Semi-flatten process will combine FG color to layer (logo) color, 
      proportionally to corresponding alpha values, and will rebuild correct 
      anti-aliasing. Completely transparent pixels will not take the color. 
      Very transparent pixels will take a few color and weakly transparent 
      will take much color.
    </para>

    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr lze spustit z nabídky okna obrázku volbou
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filtry</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Barvy</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Částečně zploštit</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Je dostupný pouze v případě vrstev obsahujících alfa kanál.
      Jinak je položka zašedlá a filtr je nepřístupný.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr Částečně zploštit je užitečný pro vyhlazování obrázků ve formátu
      GIF s průhledností. Formát GIF podporuje úplnou průhlednost a plné krytí
      (alfa hodnoty 0 a 255), nikoliv však částečnou průhlednost (1-254):
      částečně průhledné pixely jsou převedeny na zcela průhledné nebo zcela
      neprůhledné, čímž se zničí veškeré vyhlazení okrajů obrázku.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Před aplikací filtru je nutné znát barvu pozadí webové stránky (nejlépe
      zjistit barevnou pipetou).
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Filtr Částečně sploštit nahradí průhlednost v částečně průsvitných
      oblastech barvou popředí, zcela průhledné oblasti ponechá beze změny.
      Tak zůstane vyhlazení zachováno i u obrázků GIF určených púro web.
    </para>

   <para lang="fr">
     On accède à ce filtre par le menu d'image en suivant
     <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Filtres</guimenu>
       <guisubmenu>Couleurs</guisubmenu>
       <guimenuitem>Aplatir à moitié</guimenuitem>
     </menuchoice> 
     Il n'est disponible que si votre image possède un canal Alpha 
     (Image&gt;Calques>/Transparence/Ajouter un canal alpha). 
     Sinon, il est en grisé.
   </para>
   <para lang="fr">
     Il est utile lors de la création d'images GIF pour le Web. Le format 
     indexé GIF gère certes la transparence (valeur alpha 0 ou 255), mais 
     pas la semi-transparence (1 - 254): lors de l'enregistrement au 
     format GIF, les pixels semi-transparents sont transformés en noir ou 
     en totalement transparents, ce qui peut ruiner l'anti-crénelage que 
     vous avez appliqué au logo que vous voulez déposer sur la page Web. Le  
     filtre Aplatir à moitié contourne cette difficulté.
   </para>
   <para lang="fr"> 
     Mais avant d'appliquer ce filtre il vous faut impérativement connaître 
     la couleur de fond de votre page Web. Servez-vous de la pipette pour 
     déterminer avec précision cette couleur. Faites glisser la couleur pour 
     aller la déposer comme couleur de Premier-Plan dans la Boîte à outils. 
     Inversez les couleurs PP/AP de  façon à ce que la couleur d'AP devienne 
     aussi la couleur de fond Web.
   </para>
   <para lang="fr">
     Le processus de semi-aplatissement va combiner la couleur d'AP avec la 
     couleur du calque (le logo) en proportion des valeurs du canal alpha, 
     reconstituant ainsi un anti-crénelage correct. 
     Les pixels complètement transparents ne prendront pas la couleur. Les 
     pixels très transparents prendront peu de couleur, et les peu 
     transparents beaucoup de couleur.
   </para>

    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该滤镜在<guimenuitem>图像&gt;滤镜/颜色/半平整</guimenuitem>，只有当图像有 Alpha 通道时才可用。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      半平整滤镜可以用作使带透明度的索引图像其边缘平滑。GIF 索引图像支持完全透明 (Alpha 值为 0 或 255)，但不支持半透明 (1-254): 半透明的像素会被转换为不透明或完全透明，这就会使您准备放到网上的徽标中的边缘平滑信息丢失。
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      在应用该滤镜前一件重要的事就是先要知道您的网页的背景色。用颜色拾取得到准确的颜色，点击并拖动该颜色到工具栏的前景色中，然后将前景和背景色反转，这样背景色就和网页中的背景色相同。           background color.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      半平整操作会将前景色和图层(徽标)颜色组合，其比例和相应的 Alpha 值成比例，并重新产生正确的边缘平滑效果。完全透明就不再添加颜色，比较透明组合少许颜色，而很弱的透明则组合多的颜色。
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="cs">Volby</title>
    <title lang="fr">Options</title>
    <title lang="zh_CN">选项</title>

    <para lang="en">
      This filter has no options.
    </para>
    <para lang="cs">
      Tento filtr nemá žádné možnosti nastavení.
    </para>
    <para lang="fr">
      Ce filtre n'a pas d'option.
    </para>
    <para lang="zh_CN">
      该滤镜没有选项。
    </para>
  </simplesect>
</sect2>
