<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<glossdiv lang="de;en;fr;sv;zh_CN">
  <title>A</title>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-feathering-de' lang='de'>
    <glossterm lang='de'>Ausblenden</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </para>
      <para>
        Beim Ausblenden werden die Kanten einer Region weich
        mit dem Hintergrund überblendet.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id='glossary-feathering-fr' lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Adoucir</glossterm>    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Méthode permettant de fondre les bords d'une région dans l'arrière
        plan.
      </para>      
      <para lang="fr">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-alpha'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Alpha</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Alpha</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="sv">Alpha</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Alpha</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Alpha</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Refers to transparency. An Alpha Channel allows transparency
        control. Certain image formats may only contain a single Alpha
        Channel allowing a transparency of on or off. Other formats allow a
        variable level of transparency.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Alphawert gibt die Deckkraft des Pixels an. Je kleiner der
        Alphawert eines Pixels ist, desto mehr wird die Farbe darunter
        sichtbar. Ein Pixel mit Alphawert 0 ist vollkommen transparent.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Se rapporte à la transparence. Un canal Alpha permet de contrôler la
        transparence. Certain formats d'image n'acceptent qu'un seul canal
        alpha autorisant ou non la transparence. D'autres formats permettent
        de gérer le niveau de transparence.
      </para>      
      <para lang="sv">
        Hänvisar till genomskinlighet. En alfakanal tillåter genomskinlig
        kontroll. Ett visst bildformat må endast innehålla en enda
        alfakanal som tillåter genomskinlighet på eller av. Andra format
        tillåter variabel nivåer av genomskinlighet.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	跟透明度有关。Alpha 通道用于控制透明度。某些图像格式可能仅包含单个 Alpha 通道，该通道可以设置打开或关闭透明度。其他格式的图像则支持多级别的透明度设置。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-antialiasing'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Anticrénelage</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="sv">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Antialiasing(边缘平滑)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Antialiasing is the process of reversing an alias. Antialiasing
        produces smoother curves by adjusting the boundary betweenthe
        background and the pixel region that is being antialiased.
        Generally, pixel intensities or opacities are changed so a
        smoother merge with the background is achieved. Withselections,
        the selection edge is affected so that the selection edge
        opacity
        is lowered.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="de">
        Antialiasing ist eine Maßnahme gegen Aliasing. Beim
        Antialiasing werden Kanten zur angrenzenden Farbe so berechnet,
        dass diese keinen störenden Treppeneffekt bilden. In der
        Regel werden Intensitäten oder Deckungen so angegaßt,
        daß ein weicherer Übergang zum Hintergrund hergestellt
        wird. Bei Auswahlen wird die Deckung der Kanten entsprechend
        reduziert.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Reportez-vous à 
        <link linkend='glossary-antialiasing-fr'>Lissage</link>
      </para>
      
      <para lang="sv">
        Kantutjämning kallas processen då kanter jämnas ut.  Kantutjämning
        skapar jämnare kanter genom att justera dess yttre gräns mellan
        bakgrunden och pixel regionen som blir utjämnad. I allmänhet ändras
        en pixels styrka eller opacitet så det blir en jämnare förening mot
        bakgrunden. Vid markering så ändras markeringskanten,
        markeringskantens opacitet minskas.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	边缘平滑也叫反锯齿，是用于处理锯齿的。边缘平滑通过调整背景和被反锯齿的象素区域之间的界线，使曲线更平滑。通常在完成对边界的平滑操作后，象素的亮度或不透明度也会随之改变。对于选区，其边界将会受到影响，其不透明度将会降低。
      </para>
      <para lang="en;de;sv;zh_CN">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata lang="en;zh_CN" 
              fileref='../images/glossary/alias.png' format='PNG' />
            <imagedata lang="de" 
              fileref='../images/glossary/alias.png' format='PNG' />
            <imagedata lang="sv" 
              fileref='../images/glossary/alias.png' format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
             <imagedata lang="en;zh_CN"
                fileref='../images/glossary/antialias.png' format='PNG' />
             <imagedata lang="de"
                fileref='../images/glossary/antialias.png' format='PNG' />
             <imagedata lang="sv"
                fileref='../images/glossary/antialias.png' format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry lang="cs" id='glossary-alpha'>
    <glossterm lang="cs">Alfa</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Označuje průhlednost. Alfa kanál umožňuje ovládání průhlednosti.
        Některé obrazové souborové formáty neumožňují průhlednost ukládat
        vůbec nebo ukládat jen průhlednost typu ano/ne (pixel je zcela
        průhledný nebo zcela neprůhledný). Jiné formáty umožňují ukládat
        i různé stupně částečné průhlednosti.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry lang="cs" id='glossary-antialiasing'>
    <glossterm lang="cs">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Též vyhlazování. Potlačení vjemu zubatosti šikmých a oblých
        hran rastrové grafiky (tzv. aliasu). Dosahuje se přiřazením
        přechodových odstínů obrysovým pixelům tak, aby lépe splývaly
        s pozadím. V případě výběrů je zvýšena průhlednost okrajových
        pixelů výběru.
      </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata lang="cs" 
              fileref='../images/glossary/alias.png' format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
             <imagedata lang="cs"
                fileref='../images/glossary/antialias.png' format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
