<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2006-05-13 added Korean translation by Dust
     2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
     050611 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;sv;zh_CN">
  <title>A</title>
 
  <!-- Please, translate from de(or fr) to En -->
  <!--No! feathering En is in the F section-->
  <glossentry id='glossary-feathering-de' lang='de'>
    <glossterm lang='de'>Ausblenden</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Beim Ausblenden werden die Kanten einer Region weich
        in den Hintergrund überblendet.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
                       />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-feathering-fr' lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Adoucir</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Méthode permettant de fondre les bords d'une région dans l'arrière
        plan.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
                      />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
 
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-alpha'>
    <glossterm lang="cs">Alfa</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="en;de;sv;fr">Alpha</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="es">Alfa</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="it">Alfa</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="ko">Alpha(알파)</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="no">Alfa</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Alpha</glossterm>
    
    <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Alfa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en;de;sv;fr"><primary>Alpha</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it;es"><primary>Alfa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>Alpha(알파)</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Alfa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>Alpha</primary></indexterm>
    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Označuje průhlednost. Alfa kanál umožňuje ovládání průhlednosti.
        Některé obrazové souborové formáty neumožňují průhlednost ukládat
        vůbec nebo ukládat jen průhlednost typu ano/ne (pixel je zcela
        průhledný nebo zcela neprůhledný). Jiné formáty umožňují ukládat
        i různé stupně částečné průhlednosti.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Refers to transparency. An Alpha Channel allows transparency
        control. Certain image formats may only contain a single Alpha
        Channel allowing a transparency of on or off. Other formats allow a
        variable level of transparency.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Alphawert gibt die Deckkraft des Pixels an. Je kleiner der
        Alphawert eines Pixels ist, desto stärker wird die Farbe der darunter
        liegenden Ebene sichtbar. Ein Pixel mit dem Alphawert 0 ist vollkommen
        transparent.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alphakanal">Fachartikel</ulink>,
        welcher sich ausführlich mit dem Thema beschäftigt, findet sich bei
        <ulink url="http://de.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Se refiere a la transparencia.  Un canal alfa permite
        controlar la transparencia.  Algunos formatos de imagen tienen
        sólo un canal alfa que permiten que haya sectores de la imagen
        con transparencia completa o con opacidad completa (sin
        intermedios).  Otros formatos admiten transparencia variable.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Se rapporte à la transparence. Un canal Alpha permet de contrôler la
        transparence. Certain formats d'image n'acceptent qu'un seul canal
        alpha autorisant ou non la transparence. D'autres formats permettent
        de gérer le niveau de transparence.
      </para>
      <para lang="sv">
        Hänvisar till genomskinlighet. En alfakanal tillåter genomskinlig
        kontroll. Ett visst bildformat må endast innehålla en enda
        alfakanal som tillåter genomskinlighet på eller av. Andra format
        tillåter variabel nivåer av genomskinlighet.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Referito alla trasparenza. Un canale alfa permette il controllo della
        trasparenza. Certi formati immagine possono contenere solo un singolo
        canale alfa che permette una trasparenza di tipo acceso spento. Altri
        formati permettono un livello variabile di trasparenza.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko"> 
        투명도를 참고해라. 알파 채널은 투명도를 조절한다.
        몇몇 이미지 
        포맷들은 단지 하나의 알파 채널만 있어 투명하게 하거나 불투명하게
        하거나만 결정할 수 있지만, 다양한 단계의 투명도를 지원하는 포맷도
        있다. 
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Alfaverdien fortel kor gjennomsiktig laget eller biletet er. Dess
        lågare alfaverdi, dess meir gjennomsiktig er biletpunktet. Med
        verdien 0 er punktet fullstendig gjennomsiktig. Ikkje alle
        biletformat har støtte for alfa. Noen format kan bare ha
        gjennomsiktige eller ugjennomsiktige pikslar (biletpunkt), medan
        andre format kan ha varierande grad av gjennomsikt.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        跟透明度有关。Alpha 通道用于控制透明度。某些图像格式可能仅包含单个 Alpha
        通道，该通道可以设置打开或关闭透明度。其他格式的图像则支持多级别的透明度设置。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-imagehose-cs' lang="cs">
    <glossterm lang="cs">Animovaná stopa</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Animované stopy jsou speciální stopy obsahující řadu různých políček.
        Příkladem může být stopa ve tvaru lidských šlápot – levé a pravé. Při
        použití stopy se pak obě šlápoty střídají. Animované stopy jsou velmi
        silným nástrojem a umožňují zajímavé a užitečné triky.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-antialiasing' lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;sv;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="cs">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="en">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="es">Antidentado</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Anticrénelage</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="it">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="ko">안티알리아싱(Antialiasing)</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="sv">Antialiasing</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Antialiasing(边缘平滑)</glossterm>
    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Viz <link linkend="glossary-antialiasing-cs">Vyhlazování</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Antialiasing is the process of reversing an alias. Antialiasing
        produces smoother curves by adjusting the boundary betweenthe
        background and the pixel region that is being antialiased.
        Generally, pixel intensities or opacities are changed so a
        smoother merge with the background is achieved. Withselections,
        the selection edge is affected so that the selection edge
        opacity
        is lowered.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Antialiasing ist eine Maßnahme gegen Aliasing. Beim
        Antialiasing werden Kanten zur angrenzenden Farbe so berechnet,
        dass diese keinen störenden Treppeneffekt bilden. In der
        Regel werden Intensitäten oder Deckkraft so angepasst,
        dass ein weicherer Übergang zum Hintergrund erreicht wird.
        Bei Auswahlen wird die Deckkraft der Kanten entsprechend reduziert.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Traducción aproximada del término inglés
        <quote>Antialiasing</quote>, más conocido.  Es el proceso de
        revertir el <quote>aliasing</quote>, los artefactos de una
        imagen.  Produce curvas suaves ajustando la frontera entre el
        fondo y la región de pixeles que es desdentada.  En general,
        lo que es cambiado es la intensidad o la opacidad del pixel,
        logrando un transición suave (menos cortante).  En las
        selecciones, el borde de la selección es afectado disminuyendo
        la opacidad.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Reportez-vous à
        <link linkend='glossary-antialiasing-fr'>Lissage</link>
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Antialiasing è il processo contro l'effetto alias. Antialiasing
        produce curve morbide intervenendo sui bordi tra lo sfondo e la
        regione di pixel che deve essere soggetta alla procedura di
        antialiasing.
        Generalmente l'intensità o l'opacità dei pixel viene modificata in
        maniera tale da ottenere una sfumatura morbida con lo sfondo.
        Con le selezioni, il bordo della selezione viene modificato in modo
        tale
        da abbassarne l'opacità.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko"> 
        안티알리아싱은 알리아싱의 반대 작업으로, 배경과 그림 사이의 경계를
        부드럽게 처리하는 것이다. 일반적으로 
픽셀의 농도나 불투명도가 
        변경되어 배경과 부드럽게 합쳐지게 된다. 선택의 경우에는 선택의 경계에
        영향을 주어 경계의 불투명도가 낮아진다.
      </para>
      <para lang="sv">
        Kantutjämning kallas processen då kanter jämnas ut.  Kantutjämning
        skapar jämnare kanter genom att justera dess yttre gräns mellan
        bakgrunden och pixel regionen som blir utjämnad. I allmänhet ändras
        en pixels styrka eller opacitet så det blir en jämnare förening mot
        bakgrunden. Vid markering så ändras markeringskanten,
        markeringskantens opacitet minskas.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        边缘平滑也叫反锯齿，是用于处理锯齿的。边缘平滑通过调整背景和被反锯齿的象素区域之间的界线，使曲线更平滑。通常在完成对边界的平滑操作后，象素的亮度或不透明度也
        会随之改变。对于选区，其边界将会受到影响，其不透明度将会降低。
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en;de;es;it;ko;sv;zh_CN">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata lang="en;de;es;it;ko;sv;zh_CN"
              fileref='../images/glossary/alias.png' format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
             <imagedata lang="en;de;es;it;ko;sv;zh_CN"
                fileref='../images/glossary/antialias.png' format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para lang="de">
        Ein <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antialiasing">Fachartikel</ulink>,
        welcher sich ausführlich mit dem Thema beschäftigt, findet sich bei
        <ulink url="http://de.wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</ulink>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-incremental-no' lang="no">
    <glossterm>Aukande, malemodus</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Denne malemåten teiknar kvart penselstrøk direkte på det aktive
        laget. Dersom dette ikkje er vald, vil du male på ei teikneflate
        som blir blanda saman med det aktive laget. For kvart malingstrok
        aukar dekkevna heilt til maksimal dekkevne er oppnådd.
      </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
                      format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
                      format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Dei to bileta er streka opp med same penselen med avstand sett til
        60 pikslar. På biletet til venstre er <emphasis>Aukande</emphasis>
        slått av og på biletet til høgre slått på.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
</glossdiv>
