<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-20 j.h: added Alpha channel entry
  2007-01-14 lexa: added de entry for dodge (abwedeln)
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: patch from julien that includes suggestions by Sally
  2006-05-13 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-06-11 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;ru;sv;zh_CN">
  <title>A</title><anchor id="glossary-a" />

  <glossentry id="glossary-dodge" lang="de">
    <glossterm>
      <!-- en MARK: see glossterm "dodge" -->
      <phrase lang="de">Abwedeln</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Abwedeln</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="de">
        Durch den Vorgang des Abwedelns (auch: Abhalten) wird bei der
        Verarbeitung fotografischer Materialien mit Hilfe eines Vergrößerers
        die Belichtung partiell reduziert. Abwedeln ist eine Möglichkeit, zu
        hohe Negativkontraste auszugleichen oder besondere gestalterische
        Effekte zu erzielen.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Fachartikel, welcher sich ausführlich mit dem Thema beschäftigt,
        findet sich bei Wikipedia
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-dodge" />.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-feathering" lang="fr">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Adoucir</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>
        Adoucir les bords d'une sélection
      </primary>
    </indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Méthode permettant de fondre les bords d'une sélection (de l'image
        s'il n'y a pas de sélection) dans l'arrière-plan.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/feather.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para>
        Comparez avec <link linkend="glossary-antialiasing">Lissage</link>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-alpha" lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;sv;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="cs">Alfa</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en;de;fr;sv">Alpha</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Alfa</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Alfa</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">Alpha(알파)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Alfa</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Alpha</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Alfa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en;de;sv;fr"><primary>Alpha</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it;es"><primary>Alfa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ko"><primary>Alpha(알파)</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Alfa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="zh_CN"><primary>Alpha</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Označuje průhlednost. Alfa kanál umožňuje ovládání průhlednosti.
        Některé obrazové souborové formáty neumožňují průhlednost ukládat
        vůbec nebo ukládat jen průhlednost typu ano/ne (pixel je zcela
        průhledný nebo zcela neprůhledný). Jiné formáty umožňují ukládat i
        různé stupně částečné průhlednosti.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
         An Alpha value indicates the transparency of a pixel. The smaller
         the alpha value of a pixel, the more visible the colors below it.
         A pixel with an alpha value of 0 is completely transparent.
       </para>
       <para lang="en">
         Within <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, Alpha values can be associated
         with the image as a whole (the Alpha Channel) and with individual
         layers (a Layer Mask). You can view these by using the Channels
         dialog and the Layers dialog, respectively.
       </para>
       <para lang="en">
         With some image
         <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file formats</link>,
         you can only specify that a pixel is completely transparent or
         completely opaque. Other file formats allow a variable level of
         transparency.
       </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Der Alphawert gibt die Deckkraft des Pixels an. Je kleiner der
        Alphawert eines Pixels ist, desto stärker wird die Farbe der darunter
        liegenden Ebene sichtbar. Ein Pixel mit dem Alphawert 0 ist vollkommen
        transparent.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Fachartikel, welcher sich ausführlich mit dem Thema beschäftigt,
        findet sich bei Wikipedia
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-alphakanal" />.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Se refiere a la transparencia. Un canal alfa permite controlar la
        transparencia. Algunos formatos de imagen tienen sólo un canal alfa
        que permiten que haya sectores de la imagen con transparencia completa
        o con opacidad completa (sin intermedios). Otros formatos admiten
        transparencia variable.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Se rapporte à la transparence. Un canal Alpha permet de contrôler la
        transparence des pixels. Plus la valeur de l'alpha est faible, et plus
        le pixel est transparent. Un pixel avec une valeur Alpha à 0 est
        complètement transparent.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        La transparence peut s'appliquer à l'ensemble de l'image (canal Alpha)
        ou à un calque particulier (Masque de calque). Vous pouvez voir, dans
        les fenêtres de dialogue des Canaux et des Calques, si un canal Alpha
        ou un masque de calque existe.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Certains formats d'image, le format GIF et le format PNG indexé en 255
        couleurs, ne permettent qu'une transparence à deux niveaux:
        complètement transparent ou complètement opaque.
      </para>

      <para lang="sv">
        Hänvisar till genomskinlighet. En alfakanal tillåter genomskinlig
        kontroll. Ett visst bildformat må endast innehålla en enda alfakanal
        som tillåter genomskinlighet på eller av. Andra format tillåter
        variabel nivåer av genomskinlighet.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Riferito alla trasparenza. Un canale alfa permette il controllo della
        trasparenza. Certi formati immagine possono contenere solo un singolo
        canale alfa che permette una trasparenza di tipo acceso spento. Altri
        formati permettono un livello variabile di trasparenza.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        투명도를 참고해라. 알파 채널은 투명도를 조절한다. 몇몇 이미지 포맷들은 단지 하나의 알파 채널만 있어 투명하게 하거나
        불투명하게 하거나만 결정할 수 있지만, 다양한 단계의 투명도를 지원하는 포맷도 있다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Alfaverdien fortel kor gjennomsiktig laget eller biletet er. Dess
        lågare alfaverdi, dess meir gjennomsiktig er biletpunktet. Med verdien
        0 er punktet fullstendig gjennomsiktig. Ikkje alle biletformat har
        støtte for alfa. Noen format kan bare ha gjennomsiktige eller
        ugjennomsiktige pikslar (biletpunkt), medan andre format kan ha
        varierande grad av gjennomsikt.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        跟透明度有关。Alpha 通道用于控制透明度。某些图像格式可能仅包含单个 Alpha
        通道，该通道可以设置打开或关闭透明度。其他格式的图像则支持多级别的透明度设置。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-alpha-channel" lang="en;de"><!--en added 070620-->
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Alpha Channel</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Alphakanal</phrase>
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Canal Alpha" -->
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Transparency</primary>
        <secondary>Alpha channel</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Alpha Channel</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="de">
        <primary>Transparenz</primary>
        <secondary>Alphakanal</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Alphakanal</primary></indexterm>

      <para lang="en">
        An Alpha Channel represents the transparency of the image. Imagine
        you can see through the image. This Alpha Channel is automatically
        added to the image as soon as you add a second layer. You can see it
        in the Channels Dialog. It gives the possibility to be transparent to
        layers. But this possibility is not given to the background layer :
        for this, you must use the <quote>Add an Alpha Channel</quote>
        command.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can also consider that an Alpha channel, although not visible, is
        added to every layer, except to the background layer. The image
        Alpha channel is the sum of the Alpha channels of layers.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Alphakanal repräsentiert die Transparenz eines Bildes oder einer
        Ebene. Für jede Ebene außer der Hintergrundebene wird automatisch
        ein Alphakanal hinzugefügt. Im Kanaldialog kann man das sehr schön
        sehen. Der Alphakanal ermöglicht es, Ebenen bzw. Bereiche von Ebenen
        transparent oder teilweise transparent zu machen. (Deshalb hat die
        Hintergrundebene standardmäßig keinen Alphakanal.)
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Alphakanal des Bildes ist sozusagen die Summe der Alphakanäle
        aller Ebenen:
      </para>

      <formalpara>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="en">Example for Alpha channel</phrase>
          <phrase lang="de">Beispiel zum Alphakanal</phrase>
        </title>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">Alpha channel example: Basic image</phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">Alphakanal-Beispiel: Ausgangsbild</phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/alpha-channel-0.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  This image has three layers painted with pure 100% opaque
                  Red, Green, and Blue. In the Channel Dialog, you can see
                  that an alpha Channel has been added. It is white because
                  the image is not transparent since there is at least one
                  100% opaque layer. The current layer is the red one : since
                  it is painted with pure red, there is no green and no blue
                  and the corresponding channels are black.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Das Ausgangsbild besteht aus drei nicht-transparenten Ebenen
                  in Rot, Grün bzw. Blau. Im Kanaldialog wird ein Alphakanal
                  angezeigt. Die weiße Farbe steht hier für volle Deckkraft
                  (d.h. keine Transparenz). Die rote Ebene ist die aktive
                  Ebene, und da sie keine grünen oder blauen Farbanteile
                  enthält, sind die entsprechenden Kanäle schwarz dargestellt. 
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Alpha channel example: One layer transparent
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Alphakanal-Beispiel: Eine transparent Ebene
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/alpha-channel-1.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  The left part of the first layer has been made transparent
                  (Rectangular selection, Edit/Clear). The second layer,
                  green, is visible. The Alpha channel is still white, since
                  there is an opaque layer in this part of the image.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Die linke Hälfte der obersten Ebene wurde transparent
                  gemacht (Rechteckige Auswahl, Beabeiten/Löschen). Die
                  zweite, grüne Ebene wird dort sichtbar. Im Kanaldialog ist
                  der Alphakanal immer noch weiß, da in diesem Teil des
                  Bildes weiterhin eine vollständig deckende Ebene existiert.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Alpha channel example: Two layers transparent
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Alphakanal-Beispiel: Zwei transparente Ebenen
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/alpha-channel-2.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  The left part of the second layer has been made
                  transparent. The third layer, blue, is visible through the
                  first and second layers. The Alpha channel is still white,
                  since there is an opaque layer in this part of the image.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Jetzt wurde der linke Teil der zweiten Ebenen transparent
                  gemacht. Die dritte, blaue Ebene wird an dieser Stelle
                  sichtbar. Der Alphakanal wird weiterhin mit Weiß für
                  <quote>nicht-transparent</quote> dargestellt.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Alpha channel example: Three layers transparent
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Alphakanal-Beispiel: Drei transparente Ebenen
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/alpha-channel-3a.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  The left part of the third layer has been made transparent.
                  The Alpha channel is still white and the left part of the
                  layer is white, opaque! The background layer has
                  no Alpha channel. In this case, the Clear command works
                  like the Eraser and uses the Background color of Toolbox.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Nun wurde auch der linke Teil der dritten Ebenen transparent
                  gemacht. Das Bild wird an dieser Stelle weiß, genauer gesagt
                  wird zum Löschen die aktive Hintergrundfarbe verwendet, da
                  die Hintergrundebene standardmäßig keinen Alphakanal hat.
                  Daher zeigt auch der Alphakanal weiterhin
                  <quote>nicht-transparent</quote> an.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <title>
              <phrase lang="en">
                Alpha channel example: Alpha channel added to the Background
              </phrase>
              <phrase lang="de">
                Alphakanal-Beispiel: Alphakanal zur Hintergrundebene
                hinzugefügt
              </phrase>
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/alpha-channel-3b.png"
                  format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                  We used the
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Transparency</guimenuitem>
                    <guisubmenu>Add Alpha Channel</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>
                  command, which is active on the Background layer only.
                  Now, the left part of the image is fully transparent and
                  has the color of the page the image is lying on. The left
                  part of the Alpha Channel thumbnail is black (transparent)
                  in the Channel Dialog.
                </para>
                <para lang="de">
                  Zum Schluß wird auf die Hintergrundebene das Kommando
                  <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Ebene</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Transparenz</guimenuitem>
                    <guisubmenu>Alphakanal hinzufügen</guisubmenu>
                  </menuchoice>
                  angewendet. Jetzt ist die linke Hälfte des Bildes
                  vollständig transparent und das darunterliegende Bild ist
                  sichtbar. Im Kanaldialog ist die linke Hälfte des
                  Miniaturbildes schwarz, was für vollständige Transparenz
                  steht.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-imagehose-cs" lang="cs">
    <glossterm lang="cs">Animovaná stopa</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Animované stopy jsou speciální stopy obsahující řadu různých políček.
        Příkladem může být stopa ve tvaru lidských šlápot – levé a pravé. Při
        použití stopy se pak obě šlápoty střídají. Animované stopy jsou velmi
        silným nástrojem a umožňují zajímavé a užitečné triky.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-antialiasing" lang="cs;en;de;es;it;ru;sv;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="cs">Antialiasing</phrase>
      <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Vyhlazování" -->
      <phrase lang="en">Antialiasing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Antialiasing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Alisado</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Anticrénelage</phrase>
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Lissage" -->
      <phrase lang="it">Antialiasing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">안티알리아싱(Antialiasing)</phrase>
      <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Kantutjamning" -->
      <phrase lang="ru">Сглаживание</phrase>
      <phrase lang="sv">Antialiasing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Antialiasing(边缘平滑)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Antialiasing</primary><secondary>Explanation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Antialiasing</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ru">
      <primary>Сглаживание</primary><secondary>Пояснение</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Viz <link linkend="glossary-antialiasing-cs">Vyhlazování</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Antialiasing is the process of reversing an alias, that is,
        reducing the <quote>jaggies</quote>. Antialiasing
        produces smoother curves by adjusting the boundary between the
        background and the pixel region that is being antialiased. Generally,
        pixel intensities or opacities are changed so that a smoother
        transition to the background is achieved. With selections, the
        opacity of the edge of the selection is appropriately reduced.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Antialiasing ist eine Maßnahme gegen Aliasing. Beim Antialiasing
        werden Kanten zur angrenzenden Farbe so berechnet, dass diese keinen
        störenden Treppeneffekt bilden. In der Regel werden Intensitäten oder
        Deckkraft so angepasst, dass ein weicherer Übergang zum Hintergrund
        erreicht wird. Bei Auswahlen wird die Deckkraft der Kanten
        entsprechend reduziert.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        En inglés <quote>antialiasing</quote>, más conocido.  Es el proceso de
        reducir los artefactos de una imagen.  Produce curvas más suaves
        ajustando la frontera entre el fondo y la región de pixeles que es
        suavizada.  En general, se cambia la intensidad o la opacidad de los
        píxeles para lograr un transición suave (menos cortante).  En las
        selecciones, el borde es afectado disminuyendo la opacidad.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Antialiasing è il processo contro l'effetto alias. Antialiasing
        produce curve morbide intervenendo sui bordi tra lo sfondo e la
        regione di pixel che deve essere soggetta alla procedura di
        antialiasing. Generalmente l'intensità o l'opacità dei pixel viene
        modificata in maniera tale da ottenere una sfumatura morbida con lo
        sfondo. Riferito ad una selezione, il bordo della stessa viene
        modificato in modo tale da abbassarne l'opacità.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        안티알리아싱은 알리아싱의 반대 작업으로, 배경과 그림
        사이의 경계를 부드럽게 처리하는 것이다. 일반적으로 픽셀의 농도나
        불투명도가 변경되어 배경과 부드럽게 합쳐지게 된다. 선택의 경우에는
        선택의 경계에 영향을 주어 경계의 불투명도가 낮아진다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Сглаживание это процесс смягчение зубчатых краёв непрямых контуров.
        Сглаживание производит более плавные кривые, нивелируя границу фона и
        сглаживаемой области. Обычно меняются яркость и прозрачность точек,
        чтобы достичь более плавного перехода в фон. С выделениями,
        прозрачность точек границы выделения соответствующим образом
        уменьшается.
      </para>
      <para lang="sv">
        Kantutjämning kallas processen då kanter jämnas ut.  Kantutjämning
        skapar jämnare kanter genom att justera dess yttre gräns mellan
        bakgrunden och pixel regionen som blir utjämnad. I allmänhet ändras
        en pixels styrka eller opacitet så det blir en jämnare förening mot
        bakgrunden. Vid markering så ändras markeringskanten,
        markeringskantens opacitet minskas.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        边缘平滑也叫反锯齿，是用于处理锯齿的。边缘平滑通过调整背景和被反锯齿
        的象素区域之间的界线，使曲线更平滑。通常在完成对边界的平滑操作后，象
        素的亮度或不透明度也会随之改变。对于选区，其边界将会受到影响，其不透
        明度将会降低。
      </para>

      <para lang="en;de;es;it;ko;sv;zh_CN">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata lang="en;de;es;it;ko;sv;zh_CN"
              fileref="../images/glossary/alias.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata lang="en;de;es;it;ko;sv;zh_CN"
              fileref="../images/glossary/antialias.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Ein Fachartikel, welcher sich ausführlich mit dem Thema beschäftigt,
        findet sich bei Wikipedia
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-antialiasing" />.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-incremental-no" lang="no">
    <glossterm>Aukande, malemodus</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Denne malemåten teiknar kvart penselstrøk direkte på det aktive laget.
        Dersom dette ikkje er vald, vil du male på ei teikneflate som blir
        blanda saman med det aktive laget. For kvart malingstrok aukar
        dekkevna heilt til maksimal dekkevne er oppnådd.
      </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
        Dei to bileta er streka opp med same penselen med avstand sett til
        60 pikslar. På biletet til venstre er <emphasis>Aukande</emphasis>
        slått av og på biletet til høgre slått på.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-feathering-de" lang="de">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Ausblenden</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>Ausblenden</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Beim Ausblenden werden die Kanten einer Region weich in den
        Hintergrund überblendet.
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/feather.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard" lang="it">
    <glossterm lang="it">Appunti</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="it">
        Gli Appunti (clipboard in inglese) è il termine usato per descrivere
        una parte di memoria temporanea usata per trasferire dati tra
        applicazioni o documenti. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> usa un'approccio
        leggermente differente
        con gli appunti a seconda del sistema operativo su cui gira. Sotto
        Linux/XFree vengono usati gli appunti di XFree per il testo mentre gli
        appunti interni di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vengono usati per
        trasferire le immagini tra i
        documenti. Se <acronym>GIMP</acronym> viene usato con altri sistemi
        le differenze possono
        essere notevoli. Qualsiasi differenza dovrebbe essere evidenziata
        dalle pagine della documentazione specifica per quella particolare
        versione di <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Le operazioni principali fornite dall'interfaccia appunti permettono
        le operazioni di taglia, copia e incolla. Il comando Taglia viene
        usato per la rimozione di un insieme che viene copiato negli appunti.
        Il comando Copia lascia l'insieme nel documento e lo copia negli
        appunti. Il comando Incolla copia nel documento il contenuto degli
        appunti. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> prenderà una decisione intelligente
        a seconda
        dell'obbiettivo. Se l'obbiettivo è un disegno, l'operazione di incolla
        userà gli appunti dell'immagine. Se invece l'obbiettivo è un ingresso
        dati di testo allora verranno presi i contenuti degli appunti di
        testo.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
