<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-13 ude: added de bezier curve; sorted entries
  2007-01-31 alessandro falappa: some italian translations added
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: patch from julien that includes suggestions by Sally
  2006-05-13 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-09-04 de added bumpmapping by axel.wernicke
  2005-06-11 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;ru;sv;zh_CN">
  <title>B</title><anchor id="glossary-b" />

  <glossentry id="glossary-path" lang="no">
    <glossterm>Bane</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="no">
        Ein <emphasis>bane</emphasis> er ei eindimensjonal kurve som kan
        setjast saman til mangekantar, sirkelsegment eller kva du måtte
        ønskje. I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> blir banar stort sett brukte til
        å lage omriss for markeringar eller for å lage synlege strekar på
        eit bilete. Ein bane som ikkje er streka opp, vil vere usynleg på
        ei utskrift, og blir heller ikkje lagra i andre filformat enn XCF.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Sjå <link linkend="gimp-concepts-paths">Banekonseptet</link>
        og <link linkend="gimp-using-paths">Å bruke banar</link> for
        grunnleggande informasjon om banar, og i kapitlet om 
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">baneverktøyet</link> for nærare om
        korleis du kan lage og bruke banar. Du kan bestemma eigenskapar
        for banane ved hjelp av <link
        linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Banedialogen</link>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-pdb-fr" lang="fr">
    <glossterm lang="fr">Base de procédures</glossterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Base de procédures</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans la <emphasis>Base De Procédures</emphasis> sont stockées toutes
        les fonctions que <acronym>GIMP</acronym> et ses greffons mettent à
        notre disposition.
        Les développeurs peuvent y trouver d'utiles informations sur les
        fonctions fournies.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-bezier-curve" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;no">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Bezier curve</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bézierkurve</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Bézier (curvas de)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Bézier (Courbes de -)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Bezier (Curva di -)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Bézierkurve</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A spline is a curve which is defined mathematically and has a set
        of control points. A Bezier spline is a cubic spline which has
        four control points, where the first and last control points
        (knots or anchors) are the endpoints of the curve and the inner
        two control points (handles) determine the direction of the curve
        at the endpoints.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Spline ist in der Mathematik eine bestimmte Art von Funktion mit
        einer Menge von Kontrollpunkten. Eine Bézierkurve ist ein kubischer
        Spline mit 4 Kontrollpunkten, wobei der erste und der letzte
        Kontrollpunkt (Knoten, Anker) die Endpunkte der Kurve bilden und die
        beiden inneren Kontrollpunkte (Griffpunkte) die Richtung der Kurve in
        den Endpunkten festlegen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Es un tipo de curva que se define matemáticamente como un conjunto de
        puntos de control.  Una curva de Bézier es una curva de orden cúbico
        que tiene cuatro puntos de control, en los que el punto inicial y
        final corresponden a las puntas o extremos, y los otros dos son los
        puntos de control, o anclas, que determinan la dirección con que la
        curva ingresa a los extremos.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Une courbe spline est une courbe définie par des points de contrôle.
        Une courbe de Bézier a quatre points de contrôle, où le premier et
        le dernier points sont fixes (ancres) et les deux autres les points
        de contrôle proprement dits, déterminant le trajet de la courbe.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Una spline è una curva che è definita matematicamente ed è dotata di
        un insieme di punti di controllo. Una spline di Bezier è una spline
        cubica dotata di quattro punti di controllo dove il primo e l'ultimo
        dei punti di controllo (nodi o ancore) sono le estremità della curva
        e i due punti di controllo intermedi (maniglie) determinano la
        direzione della curva alle estremità
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Ei <quote>spline</quote> er ei matematisk definert kurve med eit
        sett av kontrollpunk. Ei bézierkurve er ei kubisk spline med fire
        kontrollpunkt. Det første og det siste kontrollpunktet 
        (ankerpunkta) er endepunkt for kurva. Dei to indre 
        kontrollpunkta (handtaka) definerer retninga for kurva ved
        endepunkta.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        In the non-mathematical sense, a spline is a flexible strip of
        wood or metal used for drawing curves. Using this type of spline
        for drawing curves dates back to shipbuilding, where weights were
        hung on splines to bend them. The outer control points of a
        Bezier spline are similar to the places where the splines are
        fastened down and the inner control points are where weights are
        attached to modify the curve.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Im nicht-mathematischen Sinne ist ein Spline eine biegsame
        (Holz-)Latte, die zum Zeichnen von Kurven verwendet wird. Diese
        Verwendung stammt aus dem Schiffbau, wo man Gewichte an die Splines
        hängte, um sie zu biegen. Die äußeren Kontrollpunkte einer
        Bézierkurve entsprechen in etwa den Aufhängepunkten der Splines, die
        inneren Kontrollpunkte in etwa den Stellen, an denen die Gewichte zum
        Biegen befestigt wurden.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <quote>Spline</quote> est un nom anglais, signifiant <quote>latte
        </quote> et se rapportant à la construction navale, où des poids
        étaient suspendus à des lattes pour les courber. Les points
        d'extrémité correspondent aux points de fixation des lattes et les
        points de contrôles aux points où étaient attachés les poids
        destinés à courber la latte.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Nel senso non-matematico, una spline è una striscia flessibile di
        legno o metallo utilizzata per disegnare curve. L'utilizzo di questo
        strumento per disegnare le curve deriva da vecchi metodi per la
        costruzione di barche dove le travature venivano curvate appendendovi
        dei pesi. I punti di controllo esternidi una curva di bezier sono
        simili ai punti in cui le spline venivano fissate e i punti di
        controllo interni sono i pesi attaccati per modificarne la curvatura.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        I den ikkje-matematiske verda er ei spline eit bøyeleg tre- eller 
        metallstykke som blir brukt som linjal for å teikne avrunda kurver.
        Denne bruken daterer seg tilbake til skipsbygginga då det blei hengd
        høvelege lodd på ei passeleg fjøl for å få den rette bogen. Dei ytre
        kontrollpunkta på bézierkurva tilsvarar festepunkta for fjøla, medan
        dei indre kontrollpunkta tilsvarar der lodda blei plasserte.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        Bezier splines are only one way of mathematically representing
        curves. They were developed in the 1960s by Pierre Bezier, who
        worked for Renault.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Bézierkurven sind nur eine von mehreren Möglichkeiten, Kurven
        mathematisch zu beschreiben, und wurden in den 1960er Jahren von
        Pierre Bézier bei Renault entwickelt.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les courbes de Bézier sont une représentation mathématique
        particulière de ces courbes, développées dans les années 60 par
        Pierre Bézier, ingénieur chez Renault.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Le curve di Bezier sono solo un modo per rappresentare le curve.
        Furono inventate negli anni 60 da Pierre Bézier, ingegnere della
        Renault.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Bézierkurver er ein av mange måtar å beskrive kurver matematisk.
        Beskrivinga blei utvikla i 1960-åra av Pierre Bézier som arbeidde
        for Renault.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        Bezier curves are used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> as component
        parts of <link linkend="glossary-path">Paths</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> werden Bézierkurven als Komponenten von
        <link linkend="glossary-path-de">Pfaden</link> verwendet.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Las curvas de Bézier se utilizan en el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> para
        representar las partes componentes de una <link
        linkend="glossary-path">ruta</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans GIMP, les courbes de Bézier composent les
        <link linkend="glossary-path-fr">Chemins</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Le curve di Bezier sono utilizzate in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> come
        parti costituenti dei <link linkend="glossary-path">Tracciati</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Bézierkurver blir brukte i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> for å lage 
        <link linkend="glossary-path">Banar</link>.
      </para>

      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/bezier-curve.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The image above shows a Bezier curve. Points P0 and P3 are points
        on the Path, which are created by clicking with the mouse. Points
        P1 and P2 are handles, which are automatically created by
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> when you click on the line between P0 and
        P3 and stretch it. They change position when you stretch the
        curve in different ways. You can also create and move the handles
        by dragging them out of the anchor points to bend the curves in
        the desired direction.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die obige Abbildung zeigt eine Bézierkurve. Die Punkte
        P<subscript>0</subscript> und P<subscript>3</subscript> liegen auf dem
        Pfad, der durch Mausklicks erstellt wurde. Die Punkte
        P<subscript>1</subscript> und P<subscript>2</subscript> sind
        Griffpunkte, die automatisch von <acronym>GIMP</acronym> erzeugt
        werden, sobald Sie zwischen P<subscript>0</subscript> und
        P<subscript>3</subscript> auf die Linie klicken und ziehen. Sie
        verändern ihre Position, wenn Sie die Kurve biegen.
        <!-- FIXME: de  don't know how to "drag them out" -->
        <!-- Sie können die Griffpunkte auch erstellen, und bewegen, indem
        Sie sie durch [Was-auch-immer] aus den Ankerpunkten herausziehen.-->
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        La imagen de arriba muestra una curva de Bézier.  Los puntos P0 y P3
        están sobre la ruta, y se crean haciendo clic con el ratón.  Los
        puntos P1 y P2 son las anclas, creadas automáticamente por el
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> cuando hace clic sobre el segmento formado por
        P0 y P3 para curvarlo.  También puede crear y mover las anclas
        arrastrándolas hacia afuera de los nodos para curvar el segmento de la
        manera deseada.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        L'image ci-dessus montre une courbe de Bézier. Les points P0 et P3
        ont été obtenus en cliquant sur le chemin. Les points P1 et P2 sont
        les poignées qui sont créées automatiquement par GIMP quand vous
        cliquez sur le chemin entre P0 et P3 et tirez dessus. Vous pouvez
        déplacer les poignées par un cliquer-glisser pour courber le
        chemin à votre gré.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        L'immagine sopra mostra una curva di Bezier. I punti P0 e P3 sono
        punti sul Tracciato e sono creati premendo il tasto sinistro del
        mouse. I punti P1 e P2 sono maniglie e sono create automaticamente
        da <acronym>GIMP</acronym> quando si preme il tasto sinistro del mouse
        sulla linea tra P0 e P3 e la si stira. Cambiano posizione quando si
        stira la curva in direzioni diverse. Si possono anche creare e
        muovere le maniglie estraendole dai punti ancora in modo da piegare
        le curve nella direzione desiderata.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Biletet ovanfor viser ei bézierkurve. Punkta P0 og P3 er punkt på
        banen. Desse er laga ved å klikke med datamusa. Punkta P1 og P2 er
        handtak. Desse blir laga automatisk av <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        når du klikkar på kurva mellom P1 og P2 og drar linja ut til sida. Du
        kan også få fram og handtere handtaka ved å dra dei ut frå 
        ankerpunkta for å bøye kurva slik du ønskjer.
      </para>

      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/path-with-anchors.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The image above shows a path which consists of two components,
        having both straight and curved segments, being worked on with the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path tool</link>. Here, the open
        circle indicates the selected anchor and the two open squares are
        the two handles which are associated with this anchor from the
        curves on either side of it.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Diese Abbildung zeigt einen Pfad, der aus zwei Komponenten mit geraden
        und gekrümmten Segmenten besteht und der gerade mit dem <link
        linkend="gimp-tool-path">Pfadwerkzeug</link> bearbeitet wird. Der
        kleine offene Kreis zeigt den ausgewählten Ankerpunkt an, und die
        beiden offenen Quadrate sind die zwei Griffpunkte, die jeweils zum
        Anker (als Endpunkt) der Kurven auf beiden Seiten gehören.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        La imagen de arriba muestra una ruta que tiene dos componentes, ambos
        con segmentos de curva rectos y oblicuos.  Aquí, el círculo blanco
        indica el nodo seleccionado, y los dos cuadrados blancos son sus
        anclas.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        L'image ci-dessus montre un chemin composé de deux composants. Ils
        ont tous deux des segments droits et des segments courbes,
        travaillés avec l'outil
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Chemins</link>. Le cercles vide
        indique l'ancres sélectionnée et les deux carrés vides sont les
        poignées associées, de chaque côté, à cette ancre.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        L'immagine sopra mostra un tracciato composto da due componenti che
        hanno sia segmenti lineari che segmenti curvi durante la fase di
        modifica con lo <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">strumento
        tracciati</link>. In questo caso il cerchio vuoto indica l'ancora
        selezionata e i due quadratini vuoti sono le due maniglie associate
        all'ancora nei due segmenti di cui essa fa parte.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Biletet ovanfor viser ein bane som det blir arbeidd på med 
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">baneverktøyet</link>. Banen er sett
        saman av to komponentar med både rette og kurva segment. Den
        opne sirkelen viser det valde ankerpunktet, og dei to opne
        kvadrata er dei to handtaka som høyrer saman med dette
        ankerpunktet, eitt på kvar side.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-imagehose-de" lang="de">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Bilderschlauch</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Bilderschläuche sind spezielle Pinselformen, welche aus mehreren
        Bildern bestehen. Ein Beispiel hierfür wäre ein Pinsel für Fußspuren,
        der aus zwei Bildern besteht, einem für den linken Fußabdruck und
        einem für den rechten. Würde man mit dieser Pinselform malen, so
        würde zunächst ein linker Fußabdruck, dann ein rechter, dann wieder
        ein linker und so weiter gemalt werden. Derartige Pinselformen sind
        sehr mächtig — probieren Sie es einmal aus!
      </para>
      <para>
        Oftmals werden Bilderschläuche auch als <quote>animierte
        Pinsel</quote> oder <quote>animierte Pinselspitzen</quote> bezeichnet.
        Im Pinseldialog sind sie übrigens durch durch ein kleines, rotes
        Dreieck rechts unten im Pinselsymbol gekennzeichnet.
      </para>
      <para>
        Was Sie wissen müssen, um eine animierte Pinselspitze selbst zu
        erstellen, finden Sie in
        <xref linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes" /> und
        <xref linkend="gimp-using-brushes" />.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
<!-- Yes, I know I should not introduce this new ID, but I get
 validating error if using 'id="glossary-bumpmapping" lang="no" '.
 How to avoid this error? -->
  <glossentry id="glossary-bumpmapping-no" lang="no">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="no">Biletpunktkopling</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="no">
        Biletpunktkopling (eng.: <quote>Bumpmaping</quote> er ein
        teknikk for å beskrive ekstremt detaljrike objekt utan å auke
        den geometriske kompleksiteten i biletet, spesielt i
        3-dimensjonale framstillingar. Trikset er å plassere all
        nødvendig informasjon i ein tekstur og deretter overføre
        sjatteringane frå denne teksturen til det endelege biletet.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Denne metoden er ein av mange metodar for å simulere 
        irregulære overflater med eit mønster som ikkje inngår som
        ein del av geometrien i modellen. Biletpunktkoplinga er
        rekna for å vere svært effektiv.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-bitmap" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;ko;sv;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en;de;fr;it;sv">Bitmap</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Bits, mapa de</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">Bitmap(비트맵)</phrase>
      <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Punktgrafikk" -->
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Bitmap(位图)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        From
        <emphasis>
          The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing (13 Mar 01)
        </emphasis>:
        <blockquote>
          <para>
            bitmap — A data file or structure which corresponds bit for bit
            with an image displayed on a screen, probably in the same format
            as it would be stored in the display's video memory or maybe as a
            device independent bitmap. A bitmap is characterised by the width
            and height of the image in pixels and the number of bits per pixel
            which determines the number of shades of grey or colours it can
            represent. A bitmap representing a coloured image (a
            <quote>pixmap</quote>
            ) will usually have pixels with between one and eight bits for
            each of the red, green, and blue components, though other colour
            encodings are also used. The green component sometimes has more
            bits than the other two to cater for the human eye's greater
            discrimination in this component.
          </para>
        </blockquote>
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Eine Rastergrafik oder Pixelgrafik (Englisch Bitmap) speichert die
        Information für jeden erfassten Punkt (Pixel) eines Bildes. Im
        Gegensatz dazu beschreibt eine Vektorgrafik das Bild durch
        mathematische Funktionen und legt nur die Funktionsparameter ab.
        Typische Formate für Rastergrafiken sind z.B. BMP (Rastergrafikformat
        der Firma Microsoft), GIF (Graphics Interchange Format), JPEG (Joint
        Photographics Expert Group), TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) und PNG
        (Portable Network Graphics)
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-rastergfx" />.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Traducción del
        <emphasis>The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</emphasis>
        (13 Mar 01):
        <blockquote>
          <para>
            Un bitmap o mapa de bits es un archivo de datos o estructura con
            bits que se corresponden con una imagen mostrada en una pantalla,
            probablemente en el mismo formato que se almacena en la memoria de
            video de la pantalla o tal vez como un mapa de bits independiente
            del dispositivo. Un mapa de bits se caracteriza por el ancho y el
            alto de la imagen en pixeles y por el número de bits por pixel que
            determina la cantidad de matices de gris o de colores que puede
            representar. Un mapa de bits que representa una imagen a color (un
            <quote>pixmap</quote>
            ) usualmente tendrá entre uno y ocho bits para cada componente de
            rojo, verde y azul, aunque otras codificaciones de color son
            utilizadas. El componente verde aveces tiene más bits que los
            otros dos colores debido a la mayor distinción de este componente
            que realiza el ojo humano.
          </para>
        </blockquote>
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Extrait de
        <emphasis>The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</emphasis>
        (13 mars 2001) :
        <blockquote>
          <para>
            Le bitmap est un fichier ou une structure de données qui
            correspond bit pour bit à une image affichée sur un écran.
            Généralement le format est celui dans lequel il serait conservé
            dans la mémoire vidéo d'un écran ou bien celui d'une image
            indépendante du type d'écran. Un bitmap se caractérise par la
            largeur et la hauteur en pixel de l'image et le nombre de bits par
            pixel qui détermine le nombre de nuances de gris ou de couleur
            qu'il peut représenter. Un bitmap représentant une image en
            couleur (un <quote>pixmap</quote>
            ) aura généralement de 1 à 8 bits par pixel pour chacune des
            couleurs rouge verte et bleue, bien qu'il existe d'autres type
            d'encodages de la couleur. Il arrive que la composante verte ait
            plus de bits que les autres pour prendre en compte la plus grande
            sensibilité de l'oeil humain à ces tons.
          </para>
        </blockquote>
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Dall'enciclopedia libera wikipedia
        (http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitmap) al 04/04/2005:
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        "Nelle immagini digitali di tipo bitmap (vedi informatica) le
        informazioni sono memorizzate come una sequenza di pixel colorati.
        Nella maggior parte dei casi l'immagine viene vista come una
        scacchiera e ad ogni elemento della scacchiera viene associato uno
        specifico colore.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">Il colore può essere definito con due tecniche:</para>
      <itemizedlist lang="it">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            se l'immagine contiene pochi colori (massimo 256) si crea un
            elenco dei colori da utilizzare e nella scacchiera viene inserito
            l'indice che punta allo specifico colore del pixel;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            nel caso si vogliano utilizzare molti più colori il singolo pixel
            non definisce più l'indice ad una tavolozza di colori ma definisce
            il colore direttamente.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para lang="it">
        Il colore viene definito come una unione delle componenti blu, rossa e
        verde. Questo non è l'unico modo di definire un colore, esistono molti
        modi che vengono chiamati spazi di colore ma nel caso delle immagini
        generate al computer il sistema RGB (RED Rosso, GREEN verde BLUE Blu)
        è il più diffuso dato che le schede grafiche lo utilizzano nativamente
        per generare il segnale da visualizzare con il monitor."
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        "2001년 3월 13일, The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing 에 따르면
        비트맵은 스크린에 나타나는 이미지와 비트단위로 일치되는 구조, 혹은
        데이터 파일이다. 이는 비디오 메모리에 저장되는 것이나, 장치에
        비의존적인 비트맵과 같은 형식이다. 비트맵은 픽셀에서 이미지의 너비와
        높이에 의해 결정되고, 픽셀당 비트수는 회색이나 표현가능한 색의
        농도 수에 의해 결정된다.
        색이 있는 이미지(pixmap)의 비트맵 표현은
        8비트의 값을 가지는 빨강, 녹색, 파랑으로 이루어진 픽셀로 표현된다
        (물론 다른 색상 조합이 쓰이기도 한다). 간혹 녹색 성분은 조금더 나은
        표현을 위해 더많은 비트를 가지기도 한다."
      </para>

      <para lang="sv">
        Taget ifrån
        <emphasis>Free On-line Dictionary of Computing</emphasis>
        (13 Mars 01) :
        <blockquote><para>
        bitmap en data fil eller struktur som stämmer överens bit för bit med
        en bild som visas på skärmen, antagligen i samma format som det skulle
        vara lagrat i bildskärmens videominne eller kanske som en enhetsfri
        bitmap. En bitmap betecknas med hjälp utav bredd och höjd av en bild i
        pixlar och antal nummer av bitar per pixel som avgör antal nummer grå
        nyans eller färg som det kan representera. En bitmap som representerar
        en färg bild (en <quote>pixmap</quote>) har oftast pixlar mellan ett
        och åtta bitar
        för varje röd, grön och blå komponent, fast även andra färgkoder
        används också. Den gröna komponenten har ibland fler bitar än de andra
        två, detta för att kompensera ögats extra känslighet för gröna
        nyanser.</para>
        </blockquote>
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        “摘自《The Free On-line Dictionary of Computing》（01 年 3 月 13

        日）：位图一种数据文件或结构，以一个一个字节来代表显示在屏幕上的图像，它可能以相同的格式存储在显存中或成为独立于设备的字节图。位图是通过图像的宽度和高度像素
        和每个像素中的决定灰色或其他可显示颜色的阴影数的字节来区分的。显示彩色图像的位图（“像素图”）通常每个红，绿，蓝成分有 1 到 8
        字节像素，虽然其他色彩编码也同时使用。绿色部分有时比其他两种颜色拥有更多字节，用来适应人眼睛对该颜色的辨识特性。”
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-bmp" lang="en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;sv;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <anchor id="file-bmp-load" xreflabel="BMP" />
      <anchor id="file-bmp-save" xreflabel="BMP" />
      <phrase>BMP</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>BMP</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        BMP is an uncompressed image
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        designed by Microsoft and mainly used in Windows. Colors are
        typically represented in 1, 4 or 8 bits, although the format also
        supports more. Because it is not compressed and the files are large,
        it is not very well suited for use in the internet.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Ein unkomprimiertes Dateiformat von Microsoft, welches hauptsächlich
        in Windows verwendet wird. Typischerweise wird es mit Farbtiefen von
        1, 4 oder 8 Bit verwendet. Das Format unterstützt aber auch höhere
        Farbtiefen. Wegen der fehlenden Komprimierung, und den daraus
        resultierenden Dateigrößen, ist es jedoch für die Verwendung im
        Internet ungeeignet.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Fachartikel , welcher sich ausführlich mit dem Format beschäftigt,
        findet sich bei Wikipedia
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-bmp" />.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Un formato de mapa de bits no comprimido usado por Microsoft Windows
        para visualizar gráficos. La profundidad del color es típicamente de
        1, 4, u 8 bits, aunque el formato admite más.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Format bitmap (mode point), non comprimé, utilisé par Microsoft
        Windows pour l'affichage graphique. La profondeur de couleur est
        habituellement de 1, 4 ou 8 bits bien que le format puisse accepter
        plus.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Un formato immagine non compresso usato da Microsoft Windows per la
        visualizzazione. La profondità di colore è normalmente di 1, 4 o 8 bit
        anche se il formato ne supporta di più.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        마이크로소프트사의 윈도우즈에서 사용되는 비압축 비트맵 포맷이다. 보통 1, 4, 혹은 8비트의 색상을 사용한다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Eit ukomprimert biletformat nytta av Microsoft i blant anna Windows.
        Fargedjupna er oftast 1, 4 eller 8 bits, sjølv om BMP-formatet
        støtter fleire fargar.
      </para>
      <para lang="sv">
        TO BE WRITTEN<!-- FIXME: sv -->
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        Microsoft Windows 上使用显示图形的一种非压缩位图格式。颜色深度一般为 1，4 或 8 位，虽然也支持更多位。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-imagehose" lang="fr">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Brosses GIH</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Ce sont des brosses spéciales qui contiennent plusieurs calques. On
        pourrait imaginer une brosse <quote>empreinte de pas</quote>
        qui contiendrait 2 calques. L'une de l'empreinte du pied gauche,
        l'autre de celle du pied droit. Pendant l'utilisation d'une telle
        brosse, on verrait se dessiner alternativement une empreinte gauche
        puis une empreinte droite. Cette technique d'animation des brosses est
        très performante. Dans <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
        ces brosses sont marquées d'un triangle rouge en bas à droite.
      </para>
      <para>
        Vous trouverez comment créer vos propres brosses animées dans
        <link linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes">Utilisation des brosses
          animées</link> et
        <link linkend="gimp-using-brushes">Utilisation des brosses</link>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-bumpmapping" lang="en;de;ru">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Bump mapping</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Bumpmapping</phrase>
      <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Biletpunktkopling" -->
      <phrase lang="ru">Рельеф</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Bump mapping is a technique for displaying extremely detailed objects
        without increasing the geometrical complexity of the objects. It is
        especially used in 3-dimensional visualization programs. The trick is
        to put all the necessary information into a texture, with which
        shadowing is shown on the surface of the object.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Bump mapping is only one (very effective) way of simulating surface
        irregularities which are not actually contained in the geometry of the
        model.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Bumpmapping ist eine Technik zur Darstellung von extrem detailreichen
        Objekten, ohne die Geometriekomplexität des Objekts zu erhöhen, die
        vor allem in 3D-Visualisierungsprogrammen zum Einsatz kommt. Der Trick
        dabei: die nötigen Informationen werden in eine Textur gepackt, mit
        deren Hilfe Schattierungen auf eine Oberfläche gezeichnet werden.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Bumpmapping ist somit nur ein (sehr wirksamer)
        Darstellungs-<quote>Trick</quote>,
        der Oberflächenunebenheiten simuliert, die in der Geometrie des
        Modells gar nicht vorhanden sind
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-bumpmap" />.
      </para>

      <para lang="ru">
        Рельеф - это техника рисования детализированных объектов без
        увеличения их геометрической сложности. Эта техника особенно
        распростанена в приложениях трёхмерного отображения. Трюк заключается
        в сохранении всей необходимой информации в текстуре, которая рисуется
        на объекте с тенями.
      </para>
      <para lang="ru">
        Это только одна из техник для имитации неровностей поверхности,
        которые не имеют под собой геометрии модели.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
