<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossdiv>
  <title>C</title>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-channels-fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Canaux</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Chaque image est divisée en différent canaux et recombinée avant
        d'être envoyée sur le périphérique de sortie (la plupart du temps
        l'écran). Les canaux employés pour l'affichage écran sont le rouge,
        le vert et le bleu. D'autres périphériques de sortie peuvent utiliser
        des canaux différents.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">      
        Les canaux peuvent être utiles lors de l'ajustement d'une couleur
        particulière d'une image. Par exemple, si le but est de supprimer les
        yeux rouges, un travail sur le canal rouge est sans doute la solution.
        Les canaux peuvent être vus comme des masques qui autoriseraient ou non
        l'affichage de la couleur qu'ils représentent. En appliquant des filtres
        sur les informations des canaux, de nombreux effets subtiles et variés
        peuvent être accomplis par l'utilisateur averti de Gimp.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry> 
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-channels'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Channels</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Channels</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="sv">Channels</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Each image is divided up into separate channels and then
        recombined before being sent to the output device.  An output
        device is most usually a screen. The channels that are usedwhen
        rendering images to a screen are Red, Green, and Blue.  Other
        output devices may use different channels.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="de">
        Jedes Bild kann in separaten Kanälen aufgeteilt werden.
        Für die Ausgabe werden alle seperierten Kanäle wieder
        zu einem Bild zusammengefügt. Ausgegeben können Bilder
        neben den Monitor auch auf einem Drucker oder einem Plotter.Die
        Kanäle, die für den Monitor wichtig sind, ergeben sich
        aus Rot, Grün und Blau.  Andere Ausgabegeräte, zum
        Beispiel professionelle Druckmaschienen, benutzen andere
        Kanäle um das Bild zusammenzufügen.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="sv">
        Varje bild är uppdelad i olika sorters kanaler och sätts
        sedan ihop innan de skickas till enheten för utdata. En enehet
        för utdata är oftast en skärm. De kanaler som används när
        en bild renderas till skärmen är Röd, Grön och Blå. Andra
        enheter för utdata använder ibland andra sorters kanaler.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        Channels can be useful when working on images that need
        adjustment to one particular color. If, for example, theremoval
        of "red-eye" is the goal, work on the Red channel is most
        obviously a ready solution. Channels can be seen as masks that
        allow or restrict the output of the color that the channel
        represents.  By running filters against this channel
        information,
        many varied and subtle effects can be put in to play by the
        experienced GIMP user.
      </para>
       
      
      <para lang="de">
        Nützlich erweisen sich Kanäle vor allem dann, wenn man
        Bildoperationen nur für eine bestimmte Farbe
        durchführen lassen möchte. Als beliebtes Beispiel
        lässt sich hier, dass retuschieren an roten Augen
        anführen. Gerade bei Anwendung von Filtern auf bestimmten
        Kanälen, lassen sich sehr subtile Effekte erzielen. Dem
        Benutzer sei es überlassen, dies auszuprobieren.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="sv">
        Kanaler kan vara användbara vid arbete av bilder där en färg
        behöver justeras. Om, till exmpel, borttagning av"röda-ögon"
        är målet, arbete mot den Röda kanalen är oftast det
        förutsatta valet.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard">
    <glossterm lang="en">Clipboard</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Clipboard is the term used to describe a temporary area of
        memory that is used to transfer data between applications or
        documents.  The GIMP uses slightly different clipboard
        approaches when used under differnt operating systems. Under
        Linux/XFree, the XFree clipboard is used for text and The
        GIMP internal image clipboard is used for images that are
        being transferred between image documents.  When The GIMP is
        used with other operating systems, differences may be
        apparent. Any differences should be outlined in the operating
        system specific documentation for the individual GIMP
        package.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        The most fundamental operations provided by a clipboard
        interface allow for Cut, Copy, and Paste. Cut is used to
        denote the removal of an item that is sent to the clipboard.
        Copy leaves the item in the document and copies it to the
        clipboard. Paste copies to the document whatever happens to
        be in the clipboard. The GIMP will make an intelligent
        decision about what to paste depending upon the target. If
        the target is a canvas, then paste operation will use the
        image clipboard. If the target is a text entry box, then the
        paste operation will use the text clipboard.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-colormodel">
    <glossterm lang="en">Color modes</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">RGB : Red Green Blue</term>
          <listitem lang="en">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                 fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-additive.png' format='PNG'
                />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>
              This model is used to represent colors on computers and television
              monitors. These colors are emitted by screen phosphors and not
              reflected as they are on paints. The resulting color is a
              combination of the three primary RGB colors, with different degrees
              of lightness. If you look at your television screen closely,
              whose pitch is less than that of a computer screen, you
              can see the red, green and blue phosphors differently enlighted. It
              is said that this color model is <emphasis>additive</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>
              GIMP uses an eight bits (8-bit) channel for each primary color
              and so 256 intensities (Values) are available resulting in
              256x256x256 = 16,777,216 colors (called True Color).
            </para>
            <para>
              It is not evident why these combinations produce rather unexpected
              colors. Why, for instance, 229R+205G+229B gives a kind of pink? This
              depends on our eye and our brain. There is no color in Nature, only
              a continuous variation of the light wavelength. In retina are three
              kinds of cones. The same wavelength acting on the three types of
              cones stimulates them differently and mind has learned after several
              millions of years of Evolution how to recognize a color in these
              differences.
            </para>
            <para>
              You can easily understand that no light (0R+0G+0B) gives complete
              darkness, black, and full light (255R+255G+255B) gives white. Equal
              intensity in all channels gives a gray level. So you can have only
              256 gray levels.
            </para>
            <para>
              Mixing two <emphasis>primary colors</emphasis> in RGB mode gives a
              <emphasis>Secondary color</emphasis> that is a color of the CMY
              mode. So combining Red and Green gives Yellow, Green and Blue give
              Cyan, Blue and Red give Magenta. Don't mistake secondary colors for
              <emphasis>Complementary colors</emphasis> which are diametrically
              opposed to a primary color in the chromatic circle:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata
                    fileref='../images/glossary/colorcircle-en.png' format='PNG'
                  />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              Mixing a primary color with its complementary color gives gray
              (neutral color).
            </para>
            <para>
              It is important to know what happens when you handle colors. The
              rule to remember is that decreasing a primary color results in
              increasing the saturation of the complementary color (and
              conversely). Here is the explanation: When you decrease a channel
              value, for instance the Green one, you increase the relative
              importance of other both, here Red and Blue. Now combination of
              these two channels gives the secondary color, Magenta, that is quite
              the complementary color of Green.
            </para>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Exercise</emphasis>:
              You can check this. Create a new image with only a white background
              (255R+255G+255B). Open the Tools/Color Tools/Levels dialog and
              select the the Red channel. If necessary, check the preview box.
              Move the white slider to the left to decrease the Red value. You
              will notice that the background of you image turns more and more to
              Cyan. Now, decrease the Blue channel: only the Green will persist.
              As a training go backwards, add color and try to guess what hue will
              appear.
            </para>
            <para>
              The <link linkend='gimp-tool-color-picker'>Color Picker</link> tool
              allows you to know the RGB values of a pixel and the HTML
              <link linkend='glossary-hextriplet'>hextriplet</link> for the color.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">HSV: Hue Saturation Value</term>
          <listitem lang="en">
            <para>
              The RGB mode is well adapted to computer screens but it doesn't
              allow to describe what we see in every day life: a light green, a
              pale pink, a dazzling red... The HSV mode accounts for these
              features. HSV and RGB are not independant. You can see that with
              the color-picker: when you change one the other is also modified.
              Brave can read Grokking the Gimp which explains their relations.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Hue</guilabel>: It's the color itself, 
                  resulting from the combination of primary colors. All color shades
                  (except greylevels) are represented in a <emphasis>chromatic
                  circle</emphasis>: Yellow, Blue, and also purple, orange...
                  It goes from 0° to 360°. ("Color" term is often used instead of
                  "Hue". RGB colors are "Primary colors").
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Saturation</guilabel>: This parameter describes
                  how pale the color is, as when you add white in a can of paint: a
                  completely saturated hue will be pure. If less saturated, it will
                  be pastel. Very saturated is almost white. Saturation ranges from
                  0 to 100, from white to the purest color.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <guilabel>Value</guilabel>: It is merely Luminosity, the 
                  luminous intensity. It's the amount of light emitted by a color.
                  You notice this change of luminosity when a color goes from shadow
                  to sun or when you increase the luminosity of your screen. It
                  ranges from 0 to 100. Pixels values in the three channels are also
                  luminosities: "Value" is the vectorial sum of these elementary
                  values in the RGB space.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">CMYK: Cyan Magenta Yellow blacK</term>
          <listitem lang="en">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png' format='PNG'
                />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>
              Let us say first that Gimp doesn't support the CMYK mode.
              (An experimental plugin providing rudimentary CMYK support can
              be found at www.blackfiveservices.co.uk/separate.shtml.)
            </para>
            <para>
              This mode is that of printing, that of your printer whose
              cartridges contain these colors. It's the mode of painting and
              of all the objects around us, where light is not emitted but
              reflected. Objects absorb apart of the light wave and we see
              only the reflected part. Notice that our eye with its cones sees
              this reflected light in RGB mode. An object is red because Green
              and Blue have been absorbed. Now, Green and Blue combination is
              Cyan. So, Cyan is absorbed when you add Red. Conversely, if you
              add Cyan the complementary Red is absorbed: this system is
              <emphasis>substractive</emphasis>. If you add Yellow, you
              decrease Blue and if you add Magenta, you decrease Green.
            </para>
            <para>
              You could logically think that by mixing Cyan, Magenta and
              Yellow you substract Red, Green and Blue, and so that the eye
              sees no light at all, that's to say Black. The question is more
              complex. In fact you will see a dark brown. That's why this mode
              has also the Black color and why your printer has a Black
              cartridge. That's finally cheaper: the printer has not to mix
              the three other colors to create an imperfect black. It has only
              to add some Black.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Graylevel</term>
          <listitem lang="en">
            <para>
              When you create a new image you can choose the graylevel mode
              (that you can colorize later by transforming it to the RGB mode).
              You can also transform an existing image to graylevel (but all
              formats do not accept this transformation) thanks to the command
              <link linkend='gimp-image-mode'>Graylevel</link>.
            </para>
            <para>
              As we have explained in RGB mode, Gimp 24-bit images cann't have
              more than 256 gray levels, coded on 8-bit. If you switch from
              graylevel to RGB mode you give your image a RGB structure with
              three color channels but of course your image remains gray.
            </para>
            <para>
              Graylevel image files (8-bit) are smaller than RGB files.
            </para>
            <para>
              You can also transform a RGB image to graylevel by desaturating it
              thanks to the HSV option of the
              <link linkend='plug-in-decompose'>Decompose</link> filter, the
              <link linkend='gimp-tool-colorize'>Colorize</link> tool, or the
              <link linkend='gimp-tool-hue-saturation'>Hue-Saturation</link>
              filter.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Indexed colors</term>
          <listitem lang="en">
            <para>
              The indexed mode has been invented by Compuserve at the
              beginning of the Web to create small color image files, that
              could be easily transmitted. GIF (Graphic Interchange Format)
              was the first indexed format.
            </para>
            <para>
              The principle is to code each pixel color in a table attached
              to the image, all pixels with the same color have the same code.
            </para>
            <para>
              You can see this palette when you have opened a GIF image thanks
              to the Dialogs / Indexed Palette <!--link to be done-->.
              It allows you to edit and modify each color.
            </para>
            <para>
              In a GIF image, transparency is coded on one bit: transparent or
              not.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
