<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossdiv>
  <title>C</title>
  <glossentry id='glossary-channels'>
    <glossterm>Channels</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Each image is divided up into separate channels and then
        recombined before being sent to the output device.  An output
        device is most usually a screen. The channels that are usedwhen
        rendering images to a screen are Red, Green, and Blue.  Other
        output devices may use different channels.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="de">
        Jedes Bild kann in separaten Kanälen aufgeteilt werden.
        Für die Ausgabe werden alle seperierten Kanäle wieder
        zu einem Bild zusammengefügt. Ausgegeben können Bilder
        neben den Monitor auch auf einem Drucker oder einem Plotter.Die
        Kanäle, die für den Monitor wichtig sind, ergeben sich
        aus Rot, Grün und Blau.  Andere Ausgabegeräte, zum
        Beispiel professionelle Druckmaschienen, benutzen andere
        Kanäle um das Bild zusammenzufügen.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="sv">
        Varje bild är uppdelad i olika sorters kanaler och sätts
        sedan ihop innan de skickas till enheten för utdata. En enehet
        för utdata är oftast en skärm. De kanaler som används när
        en bild renderas till skärmen är Röd, Grön och Blå. Andra
        enheter för utdata använder ibland andra sorters kanaler.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        Channels can be useful when working on images that need
        adjustment to one particular color. If, for example, theremoval
        of "red-eye" is the goal, work on the Red channel is most
        obviously a ready solution. Channels can be seen as masks that
        allow or restrict the output of the color that the channel
        represents.  By running filters against this channel
        information,
        many varied and subtle effects can be put in to play by the
        experienced GIMP user.
      </para>
       
      
      <para lang="de">
        Nützlich erweisen sich Kanäle vor allem dann, wenn man
        Bildoperationen nur für eine bestimmte Farbe
        durchführen lassen möchte. Als beliebtes Beispiel
        lässt sich hier, dass retuschieren an roten Augen
        anführen. Gerade bei Anwendung von Filtern auf bestimmten
        Kanälen, lassen sich sehr subtile Effekte erzielen. Dem
        Benutzer sei es überlassen, dies auszuprobieren.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="sv">
        Kanaler kan vara användbara vid arbete av bilder där en färg
        behöver justeras. Om, till exmpel, borttagning av"röda-ögon"
        är målet, arbete mot den Röda kanalen är oftast det
        förutsatta valet.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard">
    <glossterm>Clipboard</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Clipboard is the term used to describe a temporary area of
        memory that is used to transfer data between applications or
        documents.  The GIMP uses slightly different clipboard
        approaches when used under differnt operating systems. Under
        Linux/XFree, the XFree clipboard is used for text and The
        GIMP internal image clipboard is used for images that are
        being transferred between image documents.  When The GIMP is
        used with other operating systems, differences may be
        apparent. Any differences should be outlined in the operating
        system specific documentation for the individual GIMP
        package.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The most fundamental operations provided by a clipboard
        interface allow for Cut, Copy, and Paste. Cut is used to
        denote the removal of an item that is sent to the clipboard.
        Copy leaves the item in the document and copies it to the
        clipboard. Paste copies to the document whatever happens to
        be in the clipboard. The GIMP will make an intelligent
        decision about what to paste depending upon the target. If
        the target is a canvas, then paste operation will use the
        image clipboard. If the target is a text entry box, then the
        paste operation will use the text clipboard.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-colormodel" lang="en">
    <glossterm>Color model</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        TODO
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-additive.png' format='PNG'
          />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png' format='PNG'
          />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
