<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-01-11 ciampix: channel entry rearranged
  2007-08-18 alex falappa: fixed link to Alpha Channel example
  2007-07-21 alessandro falappa: italian translation of aplha channel added
  2007-02-01 alessandro falappa: some italian translations added
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: patch from julien that includes suggestions by Sally
  2006-05-14 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-08-26 lexa: de added CMYK by axel.wernicke
  2005-06-11 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>C</title><anchor id="glossary-c"/>

  

  


  


  <glossentry id="glossary-channels">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Channels</phrase>
      <!-- cs MARK: see glossentry "Kanály" -->
      <!-- de MARK: see phrase "Kanäle" -->
      
      
      
      
      <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Kanalar" -->
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Channel</primary>
      <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A Channel is a single component of a pixel's color. For a colored
        pixel in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, these components are usually Red,
        Green, Blue and sometimes transparency (Alpha). For a
        <link linkend="glossary-graylevel">Grayscale</link> image, they are
        Gray and Alpha and for an
        <link linkend="glossary-indexedcolors">Indexed</link> color image,
        they are Indexed and Alpha.
      </para>
      <para>
        The entire rectangular array of any one of the color components for
        all of the pixels in an image is also referred to as a Channel. You
        can see these color channels with the Channels dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        When the image is displayed, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puts these
        components together to form the pixel colors for the screen, printer,
        or other output device. Some output devices may use different
        channels from Red, Green and Blue. If they do,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s channels are converted into the
        appropriate ones for the device when the image is displayed.
      </para>
      <para>
        Channels can be useful when you are working on an image which needs
        adjustment in one particular color. For example, if you want to
        remove <quote>red eye</quote> from a photograph, you might work on
        the Red channel.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can look at channels as masks which allow or restrict the output
        of the color that the channel represents. By using Filters on the
        channel information, you can create many varied and subtle effects
        on an image. A simple example of using a Filter on the color
        channels is the
        <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Channel Mixer</link>
        filter.
      </para>
      <para>
        In addition to these channels, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also allows
        you to create other channels (or more correctly, Channel Masks),
        which are displayed in the lower part of the Channels dialog. You
        can convert a selection to a channel mask by using the <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">Save to Channel</link>
        command. You can also create a channel by right-clicking in the
        Channels dialog and using the <link linkend="gimp-channel-new">New
        channel</link> command.  See the glossary entry on <link linkend="glossary-masks">Masks</link> for more information about
        Channel Masks.
      </para>

      
      

      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      
      

      
      

      
      

      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  

  


  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Clipboard</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Zwischenablage" -->
      <!-- es MARK: see glossterm "Portapapeles" -->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Presse-papier" -->
      <!-- it MARK: see glossterm "Appunti" -->
      
      <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Utklippstavle" -->
      
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        The Clipboard is a temporary area of memory which is used to
        transfer data between applications or documents. It is used when you
        Cut, Copy or Paste data in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The clipboard is implemented slightly differently under different
        operating systems. Under Linux/XFree, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses
        the XFree clipboard for text and the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        internal image clipboard for transferring images between image
        documents. Under other operating systems, the clipboard may work
        somewhat differently. See the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> documentation
        for your operating system for further information.
      </para>
      
      

      <para>
        The basic operations provided by the clipboard are
        <quote>Cut</quote>, <quote>Copy</quote>, and <quote>Paste</quote>.
        Cut means that the item is removed from the document and copied to
        the clipboard. Copy leaves the item in the document and copies it to
        the clipboard. Paste copies the contents of the clipboard to the
        document. The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes an intelligent decision
        about what to paste depending upon the target. If the target is a
        canvas, the Paste operation uses the image clipboard. If the target
        is a text entry box, the paste operation uses the text clipboard.
      </para>
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-colordepth">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Color depth</phrase>
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Color depth</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>bpp</primary>
    </indexterm>

    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Color Depth is simply the number of bits used to represent a color
        (bits per pixel : bpp). There are 3 channels for a pixel (for Red,
        Green and Blue). <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can supprt 8 bits per
        channel, referred as <emphasis>eight-bit color</emphasis>. So, GIMP
        color depth is 8 * 3 = 24, which allows 256 * 256 * 256 =  16,777,216
        possible colors (8 bits allow 256 colors).
      </para>
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-colormodel">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Color model</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see phrase "Farbmodelle" -->
      
      
      
      
      <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Fargemodus" -->
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Color model</primary></indexterm>
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        <!-- Reorganised "color models" to be more like de. There's no need
             to repeat the information again.  scb -->
        A color model is a way of describing and specifying a color. The term
        is often used loosely to refer to both a color space system and the
        color space on which it is based.
      </para>
      
      

      <para>
        A color space is a set of colors which can be displayed or
        recognized by an input or output device (such as a scanner, monitor,
        printer, etc.). The colors of a color space are specified as values
        in a color space system, which is a coordinate system in which the
        individual colors are described by coordinate values on various axes.
        Because of the structure of the human eye, there are three axes in
        color spaces which are intended for human observers. The practical
        application of that is that colors are specified with three
        components (with a few exceptions). There are about 30 to 40 color
        space systems in use. Some important examples are:
      </para>
      

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link></para>
          
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><link linkend="glossary-hsv">HSV</link></para>
          
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="glossary-cmyk">CMY(K)</link>
          </para>
          
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><link linkend="glossary-yuv">YUV</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><link linkend="glossary-ycbcr">YCbCr</link></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      
      

      

      

      

      

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-cmyk">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>CMY, CMYK</phrase>
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>CMYK</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Subtractive color synthesis</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        CMYK is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Cyan, Magenta, Yellow and Black. It is a
        subtractive color model, and that fact is important when an image
        is printed. It is complementary to the
        <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link> color model.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        The values of the individual colors vary between 0% and 100%, where 0%
        corresponds to an unprinted color, and 100% corresponds to a
        completely printed area of color. Colors are formed by mixing the
        three basic colors.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        The last of these values, K (Black), doesn't contribute to
        the color, but merely serves to darken the other colors.  The
        letter K is used for Black to prevent confusion, since B usually
        stands for Blue.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <figure float="0">
        <title>
          <phrase>Subtractive color model</phrase>
          
          
          
          
        </title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> does not currently support the CMYK model.
        (An experimental plug-in providing rudimentary CMYK support can be
        found <xref linkend="bibliography-online-plugin-separate"/>.)
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        This is the mode used in printing. These are the colors in the ink
        cartridges in your printer. It is the mode used in painting and in all
        the objects around us, where light is reflected, not emmitted. Objects
        absorb part of the light waves and we see only the reflected part.
        Note that the cones in our eyes see this reflected light in RGB mode.
        An object appears Red because Green and Blue have been absorbed. Since
        the combination of Green and Blue is Cyan, Cyan is absorbed when you
        add Red. Conversely, if you add Cyan, its complementary color, Red, is
        absorbed. This system is <emphasis>subtractive</emphasis>.
        If you add Yellow, you decrease Blue, and if you add Magenta, you
        decrease Green.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        It would be logical to think that by mixing Cyan, Magenta and Yellow,
        you would subtract Red, Green and Blue, and the eye would see no light
        at all, that is, Black. But the question is more complex. In fact, you
        would see a dark brown. That is why this mode also has a Black value,
        and why your printer has a Black cartridge. It is less expensive that
        way. The printer doesn't have to mix the other three colors to create
        an imperfect Black, it just has to add Black.
      </para>
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  


  
</glossdiv>
