<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-17 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-06-13 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;de;en;es;it;ko;zh_CN">
  <title>D</title><anchor id="glossary-d" />

  <glossentry id="glossary-fileformat" lang="de">
    <glossterm lang="de">Dateiformat</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Dateiformat oder Dateityp bestimmt die Form der Abspeicherung von
        Computerdaten. Die Notwendigkeit hierfür entspringt aus der Tatsache,
        dass für ein Betriebssystem Dateien gewöhnlich nur eindimensionale
        Aneinanderreihungen von Bytes sind. Solche beschränkten, linearen
        Strukturen können aber viele Arten von real anfallenden Daten nicht in
        einer offensichtlichen Weise beschreiben, so dass Konventionen ihre
        Interpretation als Repräsentanten von komplexeren Daten bestimmen.
        Eine Gesamtheit solcher Konventionen für eine <quote>Art</quote>
        von Dateien wird als Dateiformat bezeichnet
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-fileformat" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Typische Dateiformate zur Abspeicherung von Bildern sind JPEG, TIFF,
        PNG und GIF. Welches Dateiformat zur Abspeicherung am geeignetsten ist,
        hängt vom Verwendungszweck des Bildes ab. Im Internet beispielsweise
        spielt die Dateigröße eine entscheidende Rolle, im Druckbereich
        dagegen sind höchste Auflösungen und Qualität entscheidende Merkmale.
        Eine Übersicht dazu finden Sie unter
        <xref linkend="gimp-using-fileformats" />.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-dithering" lang="cs;en;es;it;ko;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="cs;en;it">Dithering</phrase>
      <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Rozptylování" -->
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Farbrasterung" -->
      <phrase lang="es">Difuminado (aproximación de colores)</phrase>
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Tramage" -->
      <phrase lang="ko">디더링(Dithering)</phrase>
      <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Utjamning" -->
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Dithering(抖动)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="cs;en;it"><primary>Dithering</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Dithering</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Difuminado</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Viz <link linkend="glossary-dithering-cs">Rozptylovaní</link>.
      </para>
      <!--<para lang="no">
        Sjå <link linkend="glossary-dithering-no">Utjamning</link>.
      </para>-->

      <para lang="en">
        Dithering is a technique used in computer graphics to create the
        illusion of more colors when displaying an image which has a low
        <link linkend="glossary-colordepth">color depth</link>. In a
        dithered image, the missing colors are reproduced by a certain
        arrangement of pixels in the available colors. The human eye
        perceives this as a mixture of the individual colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">Gradient</link> tool uses
        dithering. You may also choose to use dithering when you convert an
        image to <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Indexed</link>
        format. If you are working on an image with indexed colors, some
        tools (such as the pattern fill tool) may also use dithering, if the
        correct color is not available in the colormap.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <link linkend="plug-in-newsprint">Newsprint</link> filter
        uses dithering as well. You can use the
        <link linkend="plug-in-nlfilt">NL Filter</link> (Non Linear filter)
        to remove unwanted dithering noise from your image.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Also note that although <acronym>GIMP</acronym> itself uses 24-bit
        colors, your system may not actually be able to display that many
        colors. If it doesn't, then the software in between
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and your system may also dither colors while
        displaying them.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        El difuminado es una técnica empleada en los gráficos de computadora
        para crear la ilusión de que una imagen con pocos colores aparente
        tener muchos.  El difuminado se puede lograr de varias formas,
        dependiendo del dispositivo de salida y del programa.  Un método
        particularmente efectivo consiste en colocar píxeles de diferentes
        colores juntos para simular un nuevo color (como el puntillismo en la
        pintura).  A cierta distancia el ojo humano mezcla estos colores.
        Este efecto puede observarse a menudo en las pantallas de televisión o
        en las hojas de un periódico.  Un televisor a color utiliza sólo tres
        colores agrupados en celdas, los cuales pueden estar encendidos o
        apagados.  Un periódico en general es impreso con tinta negra, pero
        con este método se logran varios tonos de gris, colocando puntos
        negros espaciados.  Además hay otras técnicas para lograr mejores
        tipos de difuminado.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Il <quote>dithering</quote> si riferisce a quel misto di matematica
        e magia riguardante la resa di un'immagine con pochi colori facendo
        sembrare che ne abbia molti di più. Il dithering si ottiene in modi
        differenti a seconda del programma e della periferica
        utilizzati. Un metodo particolarmente efficace è il raggruppamento
        di punti colorati per simulare un altro colore. Questo metodo è
        efficace grazie ad una caratteristica dell'occhio umano che tende a
        mescolare i colori in presenza di strutture di colore complesse.
        Un effetto molto noto lo si può osservare guardando la televisione
        o un giornale. Nella distanza le immagini possono sembrare formate
        da molti colori o sfumature ma osservando da vicino ci si accorge
        che non è così. La televisione a colori usa solo tre colori
        raggruppati e con varie intensità. Un giornale in bianco e nero usa
        solo l'inchiostro nero anche se le immagini sembrano sfumate in
        vari toni di grigio.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        디더링은 수학적인 방법으로 적은 색상을 가진 이미지를 좀더 풍부한
        색상을 가진 이미지처럼 표현하는 것이다. 디더링은 출력 장치에
        의존하는 방법들과 다른 방법으로 이를 표현한다. 특히 효과적인 방법
        중 하나는 다른 색상들을 섞어서 또다른 색상을 만들어내는 것이다.
        이것은 인간의 눈과 복잡한 색상 무늬를 볼때 일어나는 착시등에 근거한
        것이다. 일반적인 디더링 효과는 텔레비전이나 신문을 볼때 일어난다.
        이미지를 보는 거리로 인해 많은 색상들이나 그림자가 생긴다.
        하지만
        정확히 예는 아니다. 텔레비젼의 색상은 단지 세가지 색상만의 조합으로
        표현되는 것이다. 그리고 흑백 신문은 단지 검정 잉크만을 사용한다.
        그리고 신문의 그림은 회색톤으로 표현된다. 디더링에는 이보다 훨씬
        더 큰 효과를 가지는 많은 기술들이 있다.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        抖动特指使用数学和巫术8=) 显示出看上去有很多颜色然而实际颜色很少的图
        像。抖动的结果因输出设备和程序的不同而不同。一个特别而有效的方法是把
        色彩的像素聚合在一起试图模拟另一种色彩。人眼可以达到这一点，以及当看
        到复杂色彩图案时有混合色彩的趋势。通常的抖动效果可以在电视屏幕或报纸
        印刷上看到。在一定距离外看，图像看上去是由许多不同的色彩或阴影组成的，
        但近距离观察，情况明显就不是这样的。彩色电视只使用三种颜色, 但由于其
        不同的组合而显示多种颜色。黑白的报纸只使用黑墨水，而报纸上的图片却显
        像是由灰色色调组成的。另外，达到抖动的成功使用有几个技术。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        See also the glossary entry on
        <link linkend="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">Floyd-Steinberg
        dithering</link>, which is used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Vea también la entrada
	<link linkend="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">difuminado
	Floyd-Steinberg </link>, que es utilizado en el
	<acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> usa per esempio il metodo di
        dithering <link
        linkend="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">Floyd-Steinberg</link>.
        Questo è, semplificando, un metodo matematico di raggruppamento dei
        punti, e quello che ottiene il miglior risultato tra i vari
        dithering disponibili. Naturalmente ci sono delle eccezioni e
        oggigiorno ci sono molti modelli di dithering differenti in uso.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        김프는 Floyd-Steinberg 디더링 기술을 사용할 수 있다. 이 디더링법은
        단순하지만 수학적인 방법으로 픽셀들을 조합함으로써 다른 방법들보다
        나은 결과를 보여준다. 물론 항상 예외적인 경우도 있고, 굉장히 많은
        디더링 모델들이 있다.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        例如，GIMP 能使用 Floyd-Steinberg 抖动技术。抖动方法是简单的，使用一
        种聚合像素的数学方法来达到比其他抖动方法更好的效果。当然，总也有例外
        的情况并且现今使用很多种不同的抖动模型。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-feathering" lang="es">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="es">Difuminado (suavizado de bordes)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Difuminado</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="es">
        El difuminado de bordes es el proceso por el cual se realiza una
        transición suave entre una región y el fondo.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/feather.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        En el <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, se puede difuminar el borde de una
        selección. Las brochas también pueden tener bordes difuminados.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

</glossdiv>
