<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<glossdiv lang="en;zh_CN">
  <title>D</title>
  <glossentry id='glossary-dithering'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Dithering</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Dithering(抖动)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Dithering refers to the math and voodoo involved in rendering an
        image that has few colors seem like it has many. Dithering is
        accomplished in different ways depending on the output device
        and the program. One particularly effective method is clustering
        pixels of color together in an attempt to simulate another
        color.  This is achieved by the human eye and the tendency for
        it to mix colors while viewing complex color patterns. A common
        dithering effect is seen on television screens or in newspaper
        print.From a distance the images seem to be constructed of many
        varied colors or shades, but upon closer inspection this is
        certainly not the case. A color television uses only three
        colors clustered together in various states of on or off. A
        black and white newspaper uses only black ink, yet pictures in
        newspapersappear to be constructed of grey tones. Furthermore,
        there are techniques used to achieve greater success in
        dithering.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	抖动特指使用数学和巫术8=)显示出看上去有很多颜色然而实际颜色很少的图像。抖动的结果因输出设备和程序的不同而不同。一个特别而有效的方法是把色彩的像素聚合在一起试图模拟另一种色彩。人眼可以达到这一点，以及当看到复杂色彩图案时有混合色彩的趋势。通常的抖动效果可以在电视屏幕或报纸印刷上看到。在一定距离外看，图像看上去是由许多不同的色彩或阴影组成的，但近距离观察，情况明显就不是这样的。彩色电视只使用三种颜色,但由于其不同的组合而显示多种颜色。黑白的报纸只使用黑墨水，而报纸上的图片却显像是由灰色色调组成的。另外，达到抖动的成功使用有几个技术。
     </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        The GIMP can use the Floyd-Steinberg dithering technique, for
        example.  This dithering method is simply put, a mathematical way
        of clustering the pixels to accomplish better results thanother
        dithering methods. Of course, there are always exceptions and
        there are many different dithering models that are in usetoday.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	 例如，GIMP 能使用 Floyd-Steinberg 抖动技术。抖动方法是简单的，使用一种聚合像素的数学方法来达到比其他抖动方法更好的效果。当然，总也有例外的情况并且现今使用很多种不同的抖动模型。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
