<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-06-14 alex falappa: updated italian translation
  2007-04-14 jh: added link to File format
  2007-02-28 jh: corrected Floating Selection en;fr
  2006-09-18 lexa: moved de translation of floating selection to 'S'
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-18 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by KolSt
  2005-12-29 de added german content for floating selection
  050826 de split up Farbmodelle into different glossary entries by axel.wernicke
  050611 de added Farmodelle by axel.wernicke
  -->
<glossdiv>
  <title>F</title><anchor id="glossary-f"/>

  
  
    
  
  


  

  
  
  
  
  <glossentry id="glossary-fileformat">
    <glossterm>
      <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Souborový formát" -->
      <phrase>File Format</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Dateiformat" -->
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>File format</primary></indexterm>
    
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A file format or file type is the form in which computer data is
        stored. Since a file is stored by an operating system as a linear
        series of bytes, which cannot describe many kinds of real data in
        an obvious way, conventions have been developed for interpreting
        the information as representations of complex data. All of the
        conventions for a particular <quote>kind</quote> of file constitute
        a file format.
      </para>
      <para>
        Some typical file formats for saving images are JPEG, TIFF, PNG and
        GIF. The best file format for saving an image depends upon how the
        image is intended to be used. For example, if the image is intended
        for the internet, file size is a very important factor, and if the
        image is intended to be printed, high resolution and quality have
        greater significance. See
        <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Format types</link>.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


<!-- TODO all:  glossary entry "Filter"
  <glossentry id="glossary-filter" lang="xx">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="xx">Filter</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="xx"><primary>Filter</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="xx">
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
-->

  <glossentry id="glossary-feathering">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Feathering</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Ausblenden" -->
      <!-- es MARK: see glossterm "Difuminado (suavizado de bordes)" -->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Adoucir" -->
      <!-- it MARK: see glossterm "Margini sfumati" -->
      <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Mjuke kantar" -->
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Feathering selection border</primary>
    </indexterm>
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses the process of Feathering to make a
        smooth transition between a region and the background by softly
        blending the edges of the region.
      </para>
      
      
      

      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/feather.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you can feather the edges of a
        selection. Brushes can also have feathered edges.
      </para>
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  

  <glossentry id="glossary-floatingselection">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Floating Selection</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Schwebende Auswahl" -->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Sélection Flottante" -->
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Floating selection</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A floating selection (sometimes called a <quote>floating layer</quote>)
        is a type of temporary layer which is similar in function to a
        normal layer, except that a floating selection must be anchored
        before you can resume working on any other layers in the image. You
        can use various operations to change the image data on the floating
        selection. There can only be one floating selection in an image at a
        time.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        <!--TODO es ko zh_CN-->
        You can anchor a floating selection in various ways. First, you can
        create a <link linkend="gimp-layer-new">New layer</link>. If
        you create a new layer while there is a floating selection, the
        floating selection is anchored to it. Second, you can anchor the
        floating selection to the current layer, the selection is
        originating from. To do this, click anywhere on the image except
        on the floating selection. This merges the floating selection with
        the current layer. You can also anchor the floating selection to
        the current layer by clicking on the anchor button of the Layers
        dialog or using the
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">Anchor layer</link> command
        (<keycombo moreinfo="none"><keycap moreinfo="none">Ctrl</keycap><keycap moreinfo="none">H</keycap></keycombo>).
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      

      <para>
        There are also various ways to create a floating selection. The
        first is to convert an existing selection into a floating selection
        with the <link linkend="gimp-selection-float">Float</link> command.
        The <quote>paste</quote> operations,
        <link linkend="gimp-buffer-dialog">Paste Named Buffer</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Paste</link> or
        <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste-into">Paste Into</link>, also
        create a floating selection. In addition, the Transform tools,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-flip">Flip</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-shear">Shear</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scale</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-rotate">Rotate</link> and
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-perspective">Perspective</link>,
        create a floating selection when they are used on a selection,
        rather than a layer. When the <guilabel moreinfo="none">Affect</guilabel> mode is
        <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis> and a selection already exists,
        these tools transform the selection and create a floating selection
        with the result. If a selection does not exist, they transform the
        current layer and do not create a floating selection. (If the
        <guilabel moreinfo="none">Affect</guilabel> mode is
        <emphasis>Transform Selection</emphasis>, they also do not create a
        floating selection.) You can also create a floating selection by
        clicking on a selection and dragging it.
      </para>
      <para><!--added 060919-->
        Floating selections are a rest of the time when GIMP did not use
        layers. They have no practical use, but you must know what you have to
        do with them.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      
      

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Floyd-Steinberg Dithering</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Floyd-Steinberg</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Floyd-Steinberg dithering is a method of
        <link linkend="glossary-dithering">dithering</link> which was first
        published in 1976 by Robert W. Floyd and Louis Steinberg. The
        dithering process begins in the upper left corner of the image. For
        each pixel, the closest available color in the palette is chosen and
        the difference between that color and the original color is computed
        in each RGB channel. Then specific fractions of these differences
        are dispersed among several adjacent pixels which haven't yet been
        visited (below and to the right of the original pixel). Because of
        the order of processing, the procedure can be done in a single pass
        over the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        When you convert an image to
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Indexed</link>
        mode, you can choose between two variants of Floyd-Steinberg
        dithering.
      </para>
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
