<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<glossdiv lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title>F</title>
  <glossentry id='glossary-farbmodelle' lang='de'>
    <glossterm>Farbmodelle</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Man unterscheidet subtraktive und additive Farbmischung.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-additive.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id='glossary-dithering-de' lang='de'>
    <glossterm lang='de'>Farbrasterung</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Die Farbrasterung ist ein Process um Bilder mit wenigen Farben
        so aussehen zu lassen, als hätten Sie viele. So gibt es
        verschiedene Rasterungsmethoden; manche nur für eine bestimmte
        Anzahl von Farben gedacht.  Die Farbrasterung macht sich eine
        Eigenschaft des menschlichen Auges zu Nutze: zusammenhängende
        Farben aus komplexen Farbmustern zu erkennen. Das beste Beispiel
        ist wohl der Farbfernsehr, der ansich einen Mix von 3
        Grundfarben (Rot Grün Blau) darstellt, aber in weiter Entfernung
        ein normales Farbbild ausstrahlt.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-fileformat-fr' lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Formats de fichiers</glossterm>    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Manière d'enregistrer des données, en l'occurence des images. Vous
        devez choisir le format de fichier qui convient à votre situation.
        JPEG et PostScript sont des exemples de format de fichier.
      </para>      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-fileformat' lang='en;zh_CN'>
    <glossterm lang="en">File Format</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">File Format(文件格式)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A way that an image is written. You should select a file format
        which is suitable for your situation. JPEG  and PostScript are
        examples of file formats.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	编写图像的方法。应当根据情况选择一个适当的文档格式。例如 JPEG 或 PostScript。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-feathering' lang='en;zh_CN'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Feathering</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Feathering(羽化)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Feathering is a process by which the edges of a region are softly
        blended with the background.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	羽化操作使图层区域的边界柔化地同背景相融合。
      </para>
      <para lang="en;de;zh_CN">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-floatingselection' lang="en">
    <glossterm>FLoating Selection</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Floating selections are similar in function to  layers  except
        that floating selections must be anchored before work can resume
        on any other layers in the image. While a selection is floating,
        any number of functions can be used to alter the image data
        contained within the float.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are two methods available for anchoring a float. The first,
        and most useful, is to change the float into a new layer. This is
        achieved by creating a new layer while the float is active. The
        second method involves anchoring the float to an already existing
        layer. This is done by clicking anywhere on the image except on
        the float. Doing so will merge the float with the background
        layer.
      </para>
      <para>
        Any pasted selection will be first rendered as a floating
        selection. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id='glossary-floatingselection' lang="zh_CN"> 
    <glossterm>FLoating Selection(浮动选区)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        浮动选择在功能上与图层相似，除了浮动选区在继续在其他图层上工作前必须先固定。当一个选区是浮动时，任何功能可以用来改变包含在浮点中的图像数据。
      </para>
      <para>
        固定浮点有两种可行的方法。第一种，也是最管用的，是把浮动改为一个新的图层,这可以通过在创建浮动后创建一个新图层来完成。第二种方法是把浮动固定到一个已存在的图层中。这可以通过点击除浮动上的图像的任何地方来完成。这样做可以使背景图层与浮动合并。
      </para>
      <para>
        任何被粘贴的选区都先变为一个浮动选区。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering' lang="en">
    <glossterm>Floyd-Steinberg Dithering</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        This method of dithering looks at the current pixel color and
        retrieving the closest values from the palette. These colors are
        then distributed to the pixel areas below and to the right of
        the original pixel. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id='glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering' lang='zh_CN'>
    <glossterm>Floyd-Steinberg(抖动)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        这种抖动方法是浏览当前的像素颜色并从调色板中找出最接近的色彩浓淡。然后把这些颜色应用到原像素下面和右方的区域。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
