<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<glossdiv>
  <title>F</title>
  <glossentry id='glossary-farbmodelle' lang='de'>
    <glossterm>Farbmodelle</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Man unterscheidet subtraktive und additive Farbmischung.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-additive.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              fileref='../images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id='glossary-fileformat-fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Formats de fichiers</glossterm>    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Manière d'enregistrer des données, en l'occurence des images. Vous
        devez choisir le format de fichier qui convient à votre situation.
        JPEG et PostScript sont des exemples de format de fichier.
      </para>      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-fileformat'>
    <glossterm lang="en">File Format</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A way that an image is written. You should select a file format
        which is suitable for your situation. JPEG  and PostScript are
        examples of file formats.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-feathering'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Feathering</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Feathering is a process by which the edges of a region are softly
        blended with the background.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/feather.png' format='PNG'
            />
          </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry lang="en" id='glossary-floatingselection'>
    <glossterm>FLoating Selection</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Floating selections are similar in function to  layers  except
        that floating selections must be anchored before work can resume
        on any other layers in the image. While a selection is floating,
        any number of functions can be used to alter the image data
        contained within the float.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are two methods available for anchoring a float. The first,
        and most useful, is to change the float into a new layer. This is
        achieved by creating a new layer while the float is active. The
        second method involves anchoring the float to an already existing
        layer. This is done by clicking anywhere on the image except on
        the float. Doing so will merge the float with the background
        layer.
      </para>
      <para>
        Any pasted selection will be first rendered as a floating
        selection. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry lang="en" id='glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering'>
    <glossterm>Floyd-Steinberg Dithering</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        This method of dithering looks at the current pixel color and
        retrieving the closest values from the palette. These colorsare
        then distributed to the pixel areas below and to the right of
        the
        original pixel. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>*
  
</glossdiv>
