<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-14 alex falappa: updated italian translation
  2007-04-14 jh: added link to File format
  2007-02-28 jh: corrected Floating Selection en;fr
  2006-09-18 lexa: moved de translation of floating selection to 'S'
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-18 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by KolSt
  2005-12-29 de added german content for floating selection
  050826 de split up Farbmodelle into different glossary entries by axel.wernicke
  050611 de added Farmodelle by axel.wernicke
  -->
<glossdiv lang="en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title><anchor id="glossary-f" />F</title>

  <glossentry id="glossary-colormodel" lang="de;no">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="de">Farbraum, Farbmodell</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Fargemodus</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbmodell</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fargemodus</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Farbraum ist eine Menge von Farben, die von einem Ein- oder
        Ausgabegerät (Scanner, Bildschirm, Drucker etc.) oder unter
        spezifischen Bedingungen erkannt beziehungsweise dargestellt werden
        können. Die Farben eines Farbraumes werden durch ein Farbraumsystem
        quantifiziert. Ein Farbraumsystem ist ein Koordinatensystem, in dem
        die einzelnen Farben durch Basiskoordinaten auf verschiedenen Achsen
        charakterisiert werden. Bedingt durch den Aufbau des menschlichen
        Auges sind es bei für menschliche Betrachter gedachten Farbräumen in
        den allermeisten Fällen drei Achsen. Verwendung finden etwa 30-40
        Farbraumsysteme. Prominente Beispiele sind
        <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link>,
        <link linkend="glossary-hsv">HSV</link>,
        <link linkend="glossary-cmyk">CMY(K)</link>,
        <link linkend="glossary-yuv">YUV</link> und
        <link linkend="glossary-ycbcr">YCbCr</link>.
        Häufig wird ein Farbraumsystem und der entsprechende
        Farbraum, auf dem das System basiert, nicht unterschieden, sondern
        zusammengefasst als Farbmodell bezeichnet
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-colorspace" />.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Med fargemodus meiner ein her ei samling fargar som blir brukte for
        å bestemma fargar på ein biletskjerm eller skrivar, eller frå ein
        skannar. Fargane er sett i ei eller anna form for system, og blir
        også brukt når ein skal blanda fargar, anten det nå er på skjermen
        eller i malingspannet. For å beskriva ein bestemt farge bruker ein
        gjerne eit koordinatsystem, som oftast med tre hovudaksar. Sidan dette
        systemet er tredimensjonalt, blir det gjerne kalla eit fargerom. Det
        finst mange ulike fargesystem. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bruker meir
        eller mindre tre av desse systema, nemleg
        <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link>,
        <link linkend="glossary-hsv">HSV</link> og
        <link linkend="glossary-cmyk">CMY(K)</link>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-dithering" lang="de">
    <glossterm lang="de">Farbrasterung</glossterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Farbrasterung</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="de">
        Die Farbrasterung, auch als Dithering (engl.
        <foreignphrase>dither</foreignphrase>: schwanken, zittern)
        bezeichnet, ist eine Technik in der Computergrafik, um bei
        Bildern mit geringer Farbtiefe die Illusion einer größeren Farbtiefe
        zu erzeugen. Bei einem <quote>gedithertem</quote> Bild werden die
        fehlenden Farben durch eine bestimmte Pixel-Anordnung aus verfügbaren
        Farben nachgebildet. Das menschliche Auge nimmt diese als Mischung der
        einzelnen Farben wahr
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-dithering" />.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-fileformat" lang="en;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Souborový formát" -->
      <phrase lang="en">File Format</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Dateiformat" -->
      <phrase lang="es">Formato de archivo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Formats de fichiers</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Formato file</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">파일 포맷</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Filformat</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">File Format(文件格式)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en"><primary>File format</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Formato de archivo</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Format de fichier</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Formato file</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A file format or file type is the form in which computer data is
        stored. Since a file is stored by an operating system as a linear
        series of bytes, which cannot describe many kinds of real data in
        an obvious way, conventions have been developed for interpreting
        the information as representations of complex data. All of the
        conventions for a particular <quote>kind</quote> of file constitute
        a file format.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Some typical file formats for saving images are JPEG, TIFF, PNG and
        GIF. The best file format for saving an image depends upon how the
        image is intended to be used. For example, if the image is intended
        for the internet, file size is a very important factor, and if the
        image is intended to be printed, high resolution and quality have
        greater significance. See
        <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Format types</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        La forma en que la imagen es escrita en el archivo. Debes seleccionar
        un formato que se adecúe a tu imagen. JPEG y PostScript son ejemplos
        de formatos de imagen.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Un format de fichier est une forme particulière d'enregistrement de
        données informatiques. Tous ne sont qu'une suite de 0 et de 1, et ils
        diffèrent par la façon d'organiser les données.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les formats de fichier d'image les plus courants sont JPEG, TIFF, PNG,
        GIF. Le choix du format dépend du but visé. Si, par exemple, l'image
        est destinée au Web, la taille est un facteur très important. Si
        l'image doit être imprimée, alors la résolution et la qualité
        prennent le dessus. Voyez
        <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Types de formats</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        È in parole povere il modo in cui un'immagine viene scritta su disco.
        È utile selezionare un formato file adatto all'uso a cui è destinata
        l'immagine. JPEG e PostScript sono esempi di formati di file.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Alcuni formati noti per il salvataggio delle immagini sono JPEG, TIFF,
        PNG e GIF. Il formato di file migliore in cui salvare l'immagine
        dipende dall'uso che si deve fare della stessa. Ad esempio se si vuole
        pubblicare l'immagine su internet la dimensione del file assume una
        grande importanza mentre se si vuole stampare l'immagine alta risoluzione
        e qualità sono determinanti. Si veda anche 
        <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Tipi di formato</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        파일포맷은 이미지를 작성하는 방법이다. 따라서 상황에 맞게 적절한 포맷을 선택해 주어야 한다. 파일 포맷의 예로 JPEG이나
        PostScript가 있다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Måten eit bilete blir lagra på. Normalt vel ein filformatet ut frå kva
        biletet skal brukast til og kven som skal bruka det. JPEG og
        PostScript er eksempel på mykje brukte filformat.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        编写图像的方法。应当根据情况选择一个适当的文档格式。例如 JPEG 或 PostScript。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


<!-- TODO all:  glossary entry "Filter"
  <glossentry id="glossary-filter" lang="xx">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="xx">Filter</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="xx"><primary>Filter</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="xx">
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
-->

  <glossentry id="glossary-feathering" lang="en;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Feathering</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Ausblenden" -->
      <!-- es MARK: see glossterm "Difuminado (suavizado de bordes)" -->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Adoucir" -->
      <!-- it MARK: see glossterm "Margini sfumati" -->
      <phrase lang="ko">페더링(Feathering)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Fjørkantar</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Feathering(羽化)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Feathering selection border</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Fjørkantar</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses the process of Feathering to make a
        smooth transition between a region and the background by softly
        blending the edges of the region.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">페더링은 영역의 경계 부분을 배경화면과 섞어 부드럽게 만들어주는 작업이다.</para>
      <para lang="no">
        Kanskje eit merkeleg ord, men det kjem av at kantane på ei teikning
        blir mjuka opp og blanda med bakgrunnen omlag som om dei skulle vere
        behandla med ei fuglefjør. Studer kantane på biletet:
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">羽化操作使图层区域的边界柔化地同背景相融合。</para>

      <para lang="en;de;ko;no;zh_CN">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/feather.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you can feather the edges of a
        selection. Brushes can also have feathered edges.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-floatingselection" lang="en;es;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Floating Selection</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Schwebende Auswahl" -->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Sélection Flottante" -->
      <phrase lang="es">Flotante, selección</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Selezione fluttuante</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">떠있는 선택(Floating Selection)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Flytande markering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Floating Selection(浮动选区)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Floating selection</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Flotante, selección</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Selezione fluttuante</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Flytante markering</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A floating selection (sometimes called a <quote>floating layer</quote>)
        is a type of temporary layer which is similar in function to a
        normal layer, except that a floating selection must be anchored
        before you can resume working on any other layers in the image. You
        can use various operations to change the image data on the floating
        selection. There can only be one floating selection in an image at a
        time.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Las selecciones flotantes son parecidas a las capas en cuanto a su
        funcionalidad, excepto que deben ser <quote>ancladas</quote>
        antes de que se pueda proseguir el trabajo en otras capas de la
        imagen. Mientras una selección está flotando, se le pueden realizar
        cualquier tipo de operaciones a la imagen que contiene.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Una selezione fluttuante (talvolta chiamata anche <quote>livello
        fluttuante</quote>) è un livello temporaneo simili come funzione ai
        livelli normali eccetto nel fatto che deve essere ancorato prima di
        poter riprendere a lavorare su qualsiasi altro livello dell'immagine.
        Mentre una selezione è fluttuante, è possibile usare un qualsiasi
        numero di funzioni per modificare i dati dell'immagine all'interno della
        selezione. In ogni momento può esserci un'unica selezione fluttuante
        in un'immagine.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        떠있는 선택은 고정되기 전까지 이미지의 어떤 레이어에서도 다른
        작업을 할 수 없도록 된 레이어와 비슷하다. 선택이 떠있는 동안은
        어떤 작업도 그 선택이 있는 이미지를 변경할 수 없다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Flytande markeringar oppfører seg på same måten som eit lag, men med
        det unnataket at markeringa må forankrast før du kan arbeida på dei
        andre laga i biletet. Medan markeringa er flytande, kan du arbeide på
        ho med alle tilgjengelege verktøya.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        浮动选择在功能上与图层相似，除了浮动选区在继续在其他图层上工作前必须
        先固定。当一个选区是浮动时，任何功能可以用来改变包含在浮点中的图像数
        据。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        <!--TODO es ko no zh_CN-->
        You can anchor a floating selection in various ways. First, you can
        create a <link linkend="gimp-new-layer-dialog">New layer</link>. If
        you create a new layer while there is a floating selection, the
        floating selection is anchored to it. Second, you can anchor the
        floating selection to the current layer, the selection is
        originating from. To do this, click anywhere on the image except
        on the floating selection. This merges the floating selection with
        the current layer. You can also anchor the floating selection to
        the current layer by clicking on the anchor button of the Layers
        dialog or using the
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">Anchor layer</link> command
        (<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>).
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Hay dos métodos disponibles para anclar una selección. El primero, más
        útil, consiste en convertir la selección flotante en una nueva capa.
        Esto se consigue creando una nueva capa mientras la selección flotante
        está activa. El segundo método consiste en anclar la selección a una
        capa existente. Esto se hace clicando en un lugar de la imagen que
        esté fuera de la selección. De esta forma la selección flotante se
        agrega sobre la capa.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Due sono i metodi disponibili per àncorare una selezione fluttuante.
        Il primo e più utile consiste nel cambiare la selezione fluttuante in
        un <link linkend="gimp-new-layer-dialog">nuovo livello</link>.
        L'operazione può essere conseguita creando un nuovo
        livello mentre la selezione fluttuante è attiva. Il secondo metodo
        riguarda l'operazione di àncoraggio della selezione fluttuante su un
        livello esistente, eseguibile tramite un semplice clic su qualsiasi
        parte dell'immagine eccetto sopra la selezione. Così facendo verrà
        fusa la selezione con lo sfondo del livello interessato.
        Si può anche ancorare la selezione fluttuante al livello corrente
        tramite i pulsanti della finestra dei Livelli o utilizzando il comando
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">Ancora livello</link>
        (<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>).
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        떠있는 선택을 고정시키는 방법에는 두 가지가 있다. 가장 유용한
        첫번째는 떠있는 선택을 새로운 레이어로 바꾸는 것이다. 이것은
        떠있는 선택을 활성화시킨 상태에서 새로운 레이어를 만들면 된다.
        두번째 방법은 떠있는 선택을 기존의 레이어에 고정시켜 해당 레이어에
        포함시키는 것이다. 이것은 떠있는 선택의 바깥 부분을 클릭하면 된다.
        그러면 떠있는 선택은 활성화된 레이어에 합쳐진다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Du kan forankra ei flytande markering på to måtar. Den vanlegaste
        er å gjere om markeringa til eit nytt lag. Dette gjer du ved å
        lage eit nytt lag medan markeringa er aktiv. Den andre måten er å
        legge markeringa inn i eit eksisterande lag. Dette gjer du ved å
        klikke ein eller annan stad i laget utanom markeringa. Dette vil
        flette markeringa saman med bakgrunnslaget.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        固定浮点有两种可行的方法。第一种，也是最管用的，是把浮动改为一个新的
        图层, 这可以通过在创建浮动后创建一个新图层来完成。第二种方法是把浮动
        固定到一个已存在的图层中。这可以通过点击除浮动上的图像的任何地方来完
        成。这样做可以使背景图层与浮动合并。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        There are also various ways to create a floating selection. The
        first is to convert an existing selection into a floating selection
        with the <link linkend="gimp-selection-float">Float</link> command.
        The <quote>paste</quote> operations,
        <link linkend="gimp-buffer-dialog">Paste Named Buffer</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Paste</link> or
        <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste-into">Paste Into</link>, also
        create a floating selection. In addition, the Transform tools,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-flip">Flip</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-shear">Shear</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scale</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-rotate">Rotate</link> and
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-perspective">Perspective</link>,
        create a floating selection when they are used on a selection,
        rather than a layer. When the <guilabel>Affect</guilabel> mode is
        <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis> and a selection already exists,
        these tools transform the selection and create a floating selection
        with the result. If a selection does not exist, they transform the
        current layer and do not create a floating selection. (If the
        <guilabel>Affect</guilabel> mode is
        <emphasis>Transform Selection</emphasis>, they also do not create a
        floating selection.) You can also create a floating selection by
        clicking on a selection and dragging it.
      </para>
      <para lang="en"><!--added 060919-->
        Floating selections are a rest of the time when GIMP did not use
        layers. They have no practical use, but you must know what you have to
        do with them.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Una selección pegada será primero colocada como una selección
        flotante.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Esistono anche molti modi per creare una selezione fluttuante. Il primo
        è convertire una selezione esistente in una selezione fluttuante con
        il comando <link linkend="gimp-selection-float">Fluttuante</link>.
        Anche le operazioni di tipo <quote>incolla</quote>,
        <link linkend="gimp-buffer-dialog">Incolla con nome</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste">Incolla</link> o
        <link linkend="gimp-edit-paste-into">Incolla dentro</link>, creano una
        selezione fluttuante.
        Inoltre gli strumenti di trasformazione,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-flip">Riflessione</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-shear">Inclina</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-scale">Scala</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-rotate">Rotazione</link> and
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-perspective">Prospettiva</link>,
        creano una selezione fluttuante quando sono utilizzati su una selezione
        piuttosto che su un livello. Quando la modalità di
        <guilabel>Influenza</guilabel> è <emphasis>Trasforma livello</emphasis>
        ed è già presente una selezione, questi strumenti trasformano la
        selezione e creano una selezione fluttuante con il risultato. Se non è
        presente una selezione essi trasformano il livello attivo e non creano
        una selezione fluttuante (anche se la modalità di
        <guilabel>Influenza</guilabel> è <emphasis>Trasforma selezione</emphasis>
        essi non creano una selezione fluttuante).
        Si può creare una selezione fluttuante facendo clic e trascinando una
        selezione preesistente.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Qualsiasi selezione incollata verrà prima convertita in una selezione
        fluttuante.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">붙여지는 선택은 항상 먼저 떠있는 선택으로 구현된다.</para>
      <para lang="no">
        Når du limer inn ei markering, vil denne alltid bli ei flytande
        markering.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        任何被粘贴的选区都先变为一个浮动选区。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering" lang="en;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en;zh_CN">Floyd-Steinberg Dithering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Floyd-Steinberg (método de difuminado)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Floyd-Steinberg (Tramage de -)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">
        Floyd-Steinberg (metodo di
        <link linkend="glossary-dithering">dithering</link>)
      </phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">Floyd-Steinberg 디더링</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Floyd-Steinberg utjamning</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>Floyd-Steinberg</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Floyd-Steinberg dithering is a method of
        <link linkend="glossary-dithering">dithering</link> which was first
        published in 1976 by Robert W. Floyd and Louis Steinberg. The
        dithering process begins in the upper left corner of the image. For
        each pixel, the closest available color in the palette is chosen and
        the difference between that color and the original color is computed
        in each RGB channel. Then specific fractions of these differences
        are dispersed among several adjacent pixels which haven't yet been
        visited (below and to the right of the original pixel). Because of
        the order of processing, the procedure can be done in a single pass
        over the image.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When you convert an image to
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Indexed</link>
        mode, you can choose between two variants of Floyd-Steinberg
        dithering.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Floyd-Steinberg es un método de
	<link linkend="glossary-dithering">difuminado</link>, que se publicó
	inicialmente en 1976 por Robert W. Floyd y Louis Steinberg.  El
	proceso empieza en la esquina superior izquierda de la imagen.  Para
	cada píxel, se escoge el color más próximo disponible en la paleta, y
	se computa la diferencia con el color original en cada canal RGB.
	Luego se dispersan fracciones específicas de estas diferencias por los
	píxeles adjacentes que no han sido visitados (hacia abajo y hacia la
	derecha del píxel original).  Debido a al orden del proceso, puede
	hacerse en una sola pasada por la imagen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Cuando convierta una imagen al
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">modo indizado</link>, puede
        escoger entre dos variantes de Floyd-Steinberg.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Reportez-vous à<link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">
          Tramage couleur de Floyd-Sternberg
        </link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Denne metoden for utjamning arbeider ved at programmet ser i
        fargekartet etter fargar som liknar mest på det analyserte
        fargepunktet og legg dei funne fargane til høgre for og under det
        originale fargepunktet.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Questo metodo di dithering controlla il colore del pixel corrente e
        recupera dalla tavolozza i valori più vicini ad esso. Questi colori
        vengono poi distribuiti nelle aree in basso e a destra del pixel
        originale.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이 디더링 기술은
        현재 픽셀의 색상을 가지고 색상표에 가장 근접한
        값을 만들어내는 기술이다. 이러한 색상들은 픽셀 영역의 아래쪽과
        원래 픽셀의 오른쪽에 분포된다.현
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        这种抖动方法是浏览当前的像素颜色并从调色板中找出最接近的色彩浓淡。然
        后把这些颜色应用到原像素下面和右方的区域。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
