<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-01 alessandro falappa: some italian translations added
  2006-11-04 added a list of grayscale ways (reference used by Channel Mixer)
  by j.h
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-18 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-02-12 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-08-26 de added graylevel by axel.wernicke
  2005-08-07 de added gamma by axel.wernicke
  2005-06-11 de added Zwischenablage by axel.wernicke
  -->
<glossdiv lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title><anchor id="glossary-g" />G</title>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gamma" lang="en;de;fr;it;no">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en;fr;it">Gamma</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Gammawert</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Gammaverdi</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en;fr;it"><primary>Gamma</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Gammawert</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Gamma or gamma correction is a non-linear operation which is used to
        encode and decode luminance or color values in video or still image
        systems. It is used in many types of imaging systems to straighten out
        a curved signal-to-light or intensity-to-signal response. For example,
        the light emitted by a CRT is not linear with regard to its input
        voltage, and the voltage from an electric camera is not linear with
        regard to the intensity (power) of the light in the scene. Gamma
        encoding helps to map the data into a perceptually linear domain, so
        that the limited signal range (the limited number of bits in each RGB
        signal) is better optimized perceptually.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Gamma is used as an exponent (power) in the correction equation. Gamma
        compression (where gamma &lt; 1) is used to encode linear luminance or
        RGB values into color signals or digital file values, and gamma
        expansion (where gamma &gt; 1) is the decoding process, and usually
        occurs where the current-to-voltage function for a CRT is non-linear.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For PC video, images are encoded with a gamma of about 0.45 and
        decoded with a gamma of 2.2. For Mac systems, images are typically
        encoded with a gamma of about 0.55 and decoded with a gamma of 1.8.
        The sRGB color space standard used for most cameras, PCs and printers
        does not use a simple exponential equation, but has a decoding gamma
        value near 2.2 over much of its range.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, gamma is an option used in the brush tab
        of the <link linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>
        filter and in the <link linkend="plug-in-flame">Flame</link> filter.
        The <link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">display filters</link>
        also include a Gamma filter. Also see the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels Tool</link>, where you can
        use the middle slider to change the gamma value.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Gammawert beziehungsweise Gammakorrektur ist eine nicht-lineare Operation zum
        Kodieren und Dekodieren von Leuchtkraft oder Farben bei Video- oder
        Bildsystemen. Sie wird in vielen Arten von bilderzeugenden Systemen
        verwendet, um eine kurvenförmige Reaktion von Signal zu Licht oder
        Intensität zu Signal zu begradigen. Beispielsweise ist das Licht, das
        von einer Kathodenstrahlröhre (Bildröhre) ausgesendet wird, nicht
        linear von der Eingangsspannung abhängig, und die Spannung einer
        elektrischen Kamera nicht linear von der Lichtintensität.
        Gammakodierung hilft, die Daten auf einen linearen Wahrnehmungsbereich
        abzubilden, so dass der eingeschränkte Signalbereich (die limitierte
        Anzahl von Bits in jedem RGB-Signal) für die Wahrnehmung optimiert
        wird.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Gammawert wird in der Korrekturfunktion als Exponent verwendet
        <!-- TODO: de fix equation -->
        (A = E<superscript>&gamma;</superscript>).
        Gammakompression (mit Gamma &lt; 1) wird verwendet, um lineare
        Helligkeits- oder RGB-Werte in Farbsignale oder digitale Bytefolgen
        zu kodieren, Gammaexpansion (mit Gamma &gt; 1) ist der
        Dekodierungs-Prozess und geschieht normalerweise, wenn bei einer
        Bildröhre die Abbildung Strom zu Spannung nicht-linear ist.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Für PC-Videos werden Bilder mit einem Gamma von ungefähr 0,45 kodiert
        und mit einem Wert von ungefähr 2,2 dekodiert, für Mac-Systeme
        typischerweise mit Gamma von ungefähr 0,55 beziehungsweise 1,8. Der
        sRGB-Farbraum, der von den meisten Kameras, PCs und Druckern verwendet
        wird, verwendet zwar keine einfache Exponentialgleichung, hat aber für
        den Großteil des Wertebereichs ein Dekodierungsgamma von etwa 2,2.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ist Gamma eine Option, die im Reiter
        <quote>Pinsel</quote> des <link
        linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>-Filters und im
        <link linkend="plug-in-flame">Flammen</link>-Filter verwendet wird.
        Der <link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">Ansichtsfilter</link>
        enthält auch einen Gammafilter.  Im Werkzeug
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Werte</link> können Sie mit dem
        mittleren Schieberegler den Gammawert verändern.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        La <quote>Correction du gamma</quote> est une opération non linéaire
        utilisée pour encoder ou décoder l'intensité des couleurs des images
        et des vidéos. Cela tient au fait que chaque appareil répond
        différemment aux tensions électriques: sa réponse à une variation
        linéaire du voltage n'est pas linéaire.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le Gamma est en fait un exposant de puissance dans l'équation de
        correction. La compression Gamma (gamma &lt; 1) est utilisée pour
        encoder la luminance linéaire ou les valeurs RVB dans les signaux de
        couleur ou les valeurs des fichiers numériques. L'expansion gamma est
        le processus de décodage et se produit habituellement là où la
        fonction courant-voltage d'un tube cathodique n'est pas linéaire.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans les video PC, les images sont encodées avec un gamma d'environ
        0,45 et décodées avec un gamma de 2,2. Dans les systèmes Mac, les
        images sont encodées avec un gamma d'environ 0,55 et décodées avec
        un gamma de 1,8. L'espace de couleur sRVB utilisé dans les appareils
        photo numériques, les PC et les imprimantes couleur n'utilisent pas
        une équation exponentielle simple, mais ont une valeur de gamma de
        décodage proche de 2,2 sur la plus grande partie de leur intervalle.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Vous trouverez plus de données techniques sur le gamma dans la page
        <ulink url="http://fr-wikipedia.org/wiki/Gammakorrektur">Correction_gamma
        </ulink> de Wikipedia.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, gamma est une option utilisée dans
        l'onglet Brosse du filtre <link linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link> et dans le
        filtre <link linkend="plug-in-flame">Flammee</link>.
        La commande <link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">Filtres
          d'affichage</link> contient aussi une option de gamma, mais elle
        ne fait que montrer ce que sera la modification, sans modifier
        l'image. Enfin, le curseur médian de l'outil
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Niveaux</link>, permet de
        modifier le gamma de l'image, en fait les tons moyens.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        La gamma o la correzione gamma è una operazione non-lineare utilizzata
        per codificare e decodificare la luminanza o l'intensità dei colori
        nei sistemi video o fotografici.
        <!-- FIXME it: continue translation -->
        Gamma or gamma correction is a non-linear operation which is used to
        encode and decode luminance or color values in video or still image
        systems. It is used in many types of imaging systems to straighten out
        a curved signal-to-light or intensity-to-signal response. For example,
        the light emitted by a CRT is not linear with regard to its input
        voltage, and the voltage from an electric camera is not linear with
        regard to the intensity (power) of the light in the scene. Gamma
        encoding helps to map the data into a perceptually linear domain, so
        that the limited signal range (the limited number of bits in each RGB
        signal) is better optimized perceptually.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Gamma is used as an exponent (power) in the correction equation. Gamma
        compression (where gamma &lt; 1) is used to encode linear luminance or
        RGB values into color signals or digital file values, and gamma
        expansion (where gamma &gt; 1) is the decoding process, and usually
        occurs where the current-to-voltage function for a CRT is non-linear.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        For PC video, images are encoded with a gamma of about 0.45 and
        decoded with a gamma of 2.2. For Mac systems, images are typically
        encoded with a gamma of about 0.55 and decoded with a gamma of 1.8.
        The sRGB color space standard used for most cameras, PCs and printers
        does not use a simple exponential equation, but has a decoding gamma
        value near 2.2 over much of its range.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, gamma is an option used in the brush tab
        of the <link linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>
        filter and in the <link linkend="plug-in-flame">Flame</link> filter.
        The <link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">display filters</link>
        also include a Gamma filter. Also see the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels Tool</link>, where you can
        use the middle slider to change the gamma value.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Gammaverdien for biletskjermen er ein korrigeringsfaktor som bestemmer
        kor lys skjermen skal vere med bestemte inngangssignal. Dess høgare
        verdi, dess mørkare skjerm. Mac har standard gamma på 1,8 og gir
        såleis normalt ein lysare skjerm enn ein standard Windows PC som er
        sett til gammaverdien 2,2.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-gif" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      GIF
      <anchor id="file-gif-save" xreflabel="GIF" />
      <anchor id="file-gif-load" xreflabel="GIF" />
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        GIF je grafický souborový formát podporující až 8bitové indexované
        barvy a průhlednost (ale nikoliv částečnou průhlednost). Obrázek
        uložený ve formátu GIF tedy může obsahovat maximálně 256 barev.
        Podporuje také tvorbu jednoduchých animací a komentáře. Dříve se hodně
        používal pro tvorbu webové grafiky. Problémy s patenty však vedly
        k jeho nahrazování formátem <link
        linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>, který navíc ve většině
        případů poslouží lépe.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        <trademark>GIF</trademark> stands for Graphics Interchange Format.
        It is a <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        with good, lossless compression for images with low
        <link linkend="glossary-colordepth">color depth</link>
        (up to 256 different colors per image). Since GIF was developed, a
        new format called <link
        linkend="file-png-save-defaults">Portable Network Graphics (PNG)</link>
        has been developed, which is better than GIF in all respects, with
        the exception of animations and some rarely-used features.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        GIF was introduced by CompuServe in 1987. It became popular mostly
        because of its efficient, LZW compression. The size of the image
        files required clearly less disk space than other usual graphics
        formats of the time, such as PCX or MacPaint. Even large images could
        be transmitted in a reasonable time, even with slow modems. In
        addition, the open licensing policy of CompuServe made it possible
        for any programmer to implement the GIF format for his own
        applications free of charge, as long as the CompuServe copyright
        notice was attached to them.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Colors in GIF are stored in a color table which can hold up to 256
        different entries, chosen from 16.7 million different color values.
        When the image format was introduced, this was not a much of a
        limitation, since only a few people had hardware which could display
        more colors than that. For typical drawings, cartoons,
        black-and-white photographs and similar uses, 256 colors are quite
        sufficient as a rule, even today. For more complex images, such as
        color photgraphs, however, a huge loss of quality is apparent, which
        is why the format is not considered to be suitable for those purposes.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One color entry in the palette can be defined to be transparent.
        With transparency, the GIF image can look like it is non-rectangular
        in shape. However, semi-transparency, as in
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>, is not possible.
        A pixel can only be either entirely visible or completely
        transparent.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The first version of GIF was 87a. In 1989, CompuServe published an
        expanded version, called 89a. Among other things, this made it
        possible to save several images in one GIF file, which is especially
        used for simple animation. The version number can be distinguished
        from the first six bytes of a GIF file. Interpreted as ASCII symbols,
        they are <quote>GIF87a</quote> or <quote>GIF89a</quote>.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        <trademark>GIF</trademark>
        steht für Graphics Interchange Format und ist ein Dateiformat mit
        guter verlustfreier Komprimierung für Bilder mit geringer Farbtiefe
        (bis zu 256 verschiedene Farben pro Einzelbild). Inzwischen gibt es
        ein neues Format namens Portable Network Graphics (PNG), welches
        technisch in allen Belangen besser ist als GIF, abgesehen von
        Animationen und einigen kaum verwendeten Eigenschaften.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        GIF wurde 1987 von dem US-Onlinedienst CompuServe eingeführt. Es wurde
        vor allem wegen seiner effizienten Kompression LZW populär. Die
        entstandenen Bilddateien benötigten deutlich weniger Speicherplatz
        als andere zu der Zeit übliche Dateiformate wie PCX oder MacPaint.
        Selbst große Bilder konnten so in vernünftiger Zeit übertragen werden,
        auch mit langsamen Modems. Zudem ermöglichte die offene Lizenzpolitik
        von CompuServe jedem Programmierer, das GIF-Format für eigene
        Anwendungen kostenlos zu implementieren, sofern dieser einen Hinweis
        auf das Urheberrecht des Online-Dienstes anbrachte.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Bei GIF sind die Farbinformationen in einer Farbtabelle abgelegt.
        Diese kann bis zu 256 verschiedene Einträge enthalten, die frei aus
        16,7 Millionen möglichen Farbwerten auswählbar sind. Als das
        Dateiformat vorgestellt wurde, war dies keine wesentliche
        Einschränkung, da nur wenige Leute Hardware besaßen, die mehr Farben
        anzeigen konnte. Für typische Zeichnungen, Cartoons,
        Schwarz-Weiß-Fotografien und ähnliches sind 256 Farben in der Regel
        auch heute noch völlig ausreichend, bei komplexeren Bildern wie
        beispielsweise Farb-Fotos ist jedoch meist ein massiver
        Qualitätsverlust feststellbar, weshalb das Format dafür als
        ungeeignet gilt.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Ein Farbeintrag in der Palette kann als transparent definiert werden.
        Dadurch kann man den Eindruck erwecken, ein GIF-Bild hätte eine nicht
        rechteckige Form. Halbtransparenzen wie bei
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link> sind damit aber
        nicht möglich, ein Pixel kann entweder nur voll sichtbar oder komplett
        <quote>durchsichtig</quote> sein.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die erste GIF-Version war die Version 87a. 1989
        veröffentlichte CompuServe eine erweiterte Version, die 89a genannt
        wird. Diese ermöglicht u.a. das Speichern mehrerer Bilder in einer
        GIF-Datei, was vor allem für einfache Animationen verwendet wird. Man
        kann die Version an den ersten sechs Bytes einer GIF-Datei erkennen.
        Interpretiert man diese als ASCII-Zeichen, so steht dort
        <quote>GIF87a</quote> beziehungsweise <quote>GIF89a</quote>. (Quelle: <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIF">Wikipedia</ulink>)
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Marca registrada por CompuServe, con compresión LZW patentada por
        Unisys. El formato GIF utiliza color indexado de 8 bits y posee
        transparencia binaria (pero no semitransparencia). Pueden además ser
        cargadas de forma entrelazada por algunos programas. Este formato
        también admite animaciones y comentarios. Utiliza GIF para gráficos
        web con transparencia o con animaciones. Sin embargo, para la mayoría
        de los casos una mejor opción es el formato
        <!-- PENDING: es link linkend="file-png-save-defaults"-->PNG<!--/link-->.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        <acronym>GIF</acronym> est l'acronyme de Graphics Interchange
        Format. C'est un format de fichier sans perte mais qui ne permet que
        256 couleurs au plus dans une même image et deux niveaux de
        transparence. Depuis la création du format GIF, un autre format est
        sorti, le format
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">
          Portable Network Graphics (PNG)
        </link> bien plus performant.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        GIF a été introduit en 1987 par Compuserve. Il est devenu populaire
        grâce à l'excellence de LZW, un programme de compression qu'il
        utilise. Il donnait alors des fichiers de taille beaucoup plus réduite
        que ses concurrents, comme PCX ou MacPaint. Même de grandes images
        pouvaient être transmises avec des modems lents. Un moment bridé par
        des problèmes de licence, tout programmeur peut maintenant l'utiliser
        sans payer de droits, à condition de joindre la notice de copyright
        Compuserve. Il restera d'actualité tant que Internet Explorer ne
        gérera pas les niveaux de transparence multiples.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les couleurs GIF sont stockées dans une table de couleur appelée
        Palette indexée qui fournit 256 couleurs choisies parmi 16,7 millions.
        Quand ce format a été introduit, ce nombre limité de couleurs n'était
        pas gênant car le matériel ne permettait d'afficher plus.
        Actuellement, les logos, les dessins de bande dessinée, les photos en
        noir et blanc n'utilisent pas plus de couleurs. Mais GIF ne convient
        guère aux images plus complexes en couleurs comme les photographies.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Une des entrées de la palette (le bit 0 dans l'octet servant à coder
        les 256 couleurs) peut être réservée pour coder la transparence, avec
        seulement deux niveaux de transparence: complètement transparent ou
        complètement opaque. Le format PNG, lui, permet 256 niveaux de
        transparence, malheureusement toujours pas gérés par Internet
        Explorer.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        La première version de GIF était la 87a. En 1989, Compuserve a
        publié une version améliorée, appelée 89a. Elle permettait, entre
        autre, de stocker plusieurs images dans un même fichier GIF, ce qui
        autorisait des animations simples. Les versions peuvent être
        distinguées par les six premiers octets des fichiers, représentant,
        en code ASCII, <quote>GIF87a</quote> ou <quote>GIF89a</quote>.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Marchio registrato da CompuServe con l'algoritmo di compressione LZW
        brevettato da Unisys. Le immagini GIF sono a colori a 8 bit
        indicizzati con il supporto alla trasparenza (ma senza supporto alla
        semi-trasparenza). Possono essere caricate anche in forma
        interlacciata. Il formato GIF supporta anche l'animazione e i
        commenti. Usate il formato GIF solo per grafica Web con trasparenze e
        animazione. Il formato
        <!-- PENDING: it link linkend="file-png-save-defaults" -->PNG<!--/link-->
        può essere usato al posto del formato GIF e molto spesso è una scelta
        migliore.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Marchio registrato da CompuServe con l'algoritmo di compressione LZW
        brevettato da Unisys. Le immagini GIF sono a colori a 8 bit
        indicizzati con il supporto alla trasparenza (ma senza supporto alla
        semi-trasparenza). Possono essere caricate anche in forma
        interlacciata. Il formato GIF supporta anche l'animazione e i
        commenti. Usate il formato GIF solo per grafica Web con trasparenze e
        animazione. Il formato
        <!-- PENDING: it link linkend="file-png-save-defaults" -->PNG<!--/link-->
        può essere usato al posto del formato GIF e molto spesso è una scelta
        migliore.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        CompuServe 사의 대표적인 작품이며, Unisys 사의 LZW 압축기법을
        사용한다. GIF 이미지는 8 비트의 인덱스 색상과 이진 투명도를
        지원한다(반투명은 지원하지 못한다). 그리고 몇몇 프로그램에서
        인터레이스 로딩을 할 수 있다. 또 GIF 포맷은 애니메이션과 코멘트를
        지원한다. 이 때문에 투명한 웹그래픽스나 GIF 애니메이션 등으로 많이
        쓰이는 포맷이다. 현재는
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>
        포맷으로 대체되고 있다.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        GIF er eit varemerke for firmaet CompuServe. Kompresjonsmetoden LZW
        er patentert av firmaet Unisys. Formatet er i 8 bits indekserte
        fargar og støtter gjennomsikt av eller på, men ikkje delvis
        gjennomsiktig. Formatet støtter også merknader og animasjonar. Blir
        mykje brukt til transparente bilete og animasjonar for internett.
        Ofte vil kanskje likevel
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link> vere eit betre val.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        CompuServe 的商标，使用 Unisys 专利的 LZW 压缩算法。GIF 图像使用8位索引色并且支持透明(不支持半透明)，它能被一些程序交错扫描地载入。GIF 格式还支持动画和备注。它可用做透明网页图形和 GIF 动画。而 <link                    linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>是能够在大多数功能上代替 GIF 的不二选择。
      </para>

      <!-- TODO: en fr description for dialog should be moved from glossary
      to dialogs/export-file-dialog.xml -->
      <figure lang="en;fr">
        <title>
          <phrase lang="en">The GIF Save dialog</phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">
            La fenêtre de dialogue Enregistrer en GIF
          </phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject lang="en">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/gif-save-dialog.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject lang="fr">
            <imagedata fileref="../images/using/fr/gif-save-dialog.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <itemizedlist lang="en;fr">
        <title>
          <phrase lang="en">
            GIF Options
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">
            Options GIF
          </phrase>
        </title>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Interlace</guilabel> : when this option is checked,
            the image will be displayed progressively on the Web page. It
            was interesting when computers and modems were slow, as it
            allowed to stop loading an image of no interest.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Entrelacement</guilabel> : quand cette option est
            cochée, l'image s'affichera progressivement sur la page Web.
            Elle était surtout intéressante quand les ordinateurs et les
            modems étaient lents, en permettant d'interrompre le chargement
            d'une image sans intérêt.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>GIF comment</guilabel> : unactivate this option,
            because GIF supports 7-bits ASCII texts only, Gimp can't provide.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Commentaire</guilabel> : cette option doit être
            désactivée, car GIF ne tolère que les textes en ASCII 7bits
            que GIMP ne peut fournir.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist lang="en;fr">
        <title>
          <phrase lang="en">
            Animated GIF Options
          </phrase>
          <phrase lang="fr">
            Options d'animation GIF
          </phrase>
        </title>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Loop forever</guilabel> : when this option is checked
            the animation will start playing again repeatedly until you
            stop it.
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Boucle infinie</guilabel> : quand cette option est
            cochée, l'animation reprendra sans cesse au début jusqu'à ce
            que vous l'interrompiez.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Delay between frames if unspecified</guilabel> : you
            can set the delay, in millisecondes, between frames if it has
            not been set before. In this case, you can modify every delay
            in the Layer Dialog
            this opti
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Délai entre les images, lorsque non spécifié
            </guilabel> : Vous pouvez fixer là le délai d'affichage des
            images de l'animation, si cela n'a pas été déjà fait
            antérieurement. Dans ce cas, il est vous est possible de
            modifier chaque délai dans le dialogue des calques de l'image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Frame disposal when unspecified</guilabel> : If this
            has not been set before, you can set how frames will be
            superimposed. You can select among three options :
          </para>
          <para lang="fr">
            <guilabel>Disposition des images, lorsque non spécifié
            </guilabel> : Si cela n'a pas été déjà fait (cela reste
            possible dans le dialogue des calques), vous pouvez fixer la
            façon dont les images se superposeront. Vous avez le choix
            entre trois options :
          </para>
          <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>I don't care</guilabel> : you can use this
                option if all your layers are opaque. Layers will
                overwrite what is beneath.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Peu importe</guilabel> : Option à utiliser si
                tous vos calques sont opaques. Les calques écraseront ce
                qui est dessous.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>Cumulative Layers (combine)</guilabel> :
                previous frames will not be deleted when a new one is
                displayed.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Calques cumulatifs (combine)</guilabel> : les
                images du film précédentes ne seront pas effacées lors de
                l'affichage d'une nouvelle image du film.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                <guilabel>One frame per layer (replace)</guilabel> :
                previous frames will be deleted before displaying a new
                frame.
              </para>
              <para lang="fr">
                <guilabel>Une image par calque (remplace)</guilabel> :
                les images du film précédentes seront effacées lors de
                l'affichage d'une nouvelle image du film.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gnu" lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>GNU</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Rekurzivní zkratka z <foreignphrase>GNU's Not Unix</foreignphrase>
        (GNU není Unix). Označuje projekt pro vytvoření svobodného operačního
        systému unixového typu, který byl v roce 1983 zahájen nadací FSF
        (<foreignphrase>Free Software Foundation</foreignphrase>), jejímž
        posláním je tvořit a podporovat svobodný software. GIMP je oficiální
        součástí projektu GNU. Více se o projektu GNU dozvíte ve Wikipedii
        <ulink url="http://cs.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The GNU project was started in 1983 by Richard Stallman with the
        goal of developing a completely free operating system. It is
        especially well-known from the GNU General Public License (GPL) and
        GNU/Linux, a GNU-variant with a Linux kernel.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The name came about from the naming conventions which were in
        practice at MIT, where Stallman worked at the time.
        For programs which were similar to other programs, recursive
        acronyms were chosen as names. Since the new system was to be based
        on the widespread operating system, Unix, Stallman looked for that
        kind of name and came up with GNU, which stands for
        <quote>GNU is not Unix</quote>. In order to avoid confusion, the
        name should be pronounced with the <quote>G</quote>, not like
        <quote>new</quote>. There were several reasons for making GNU
        Unix-compatible. For one thing, Stallman was convinced that most
        companies would refuse a completely new operating system, if the
        programs they used wouldn't run on it. In addition, the architecture
        of Unix made quick, easy and distributed development possible,
        since Unix consists of many small programs that can be developed
        independently of each other, for the most part. Also, many parts of
        a Unix system were freely available to anyone and could therefore
        be directly integrated into GNU, for example, the typesetting
        system, TeX, or the X Window System. The missing parts were newly
        written from the ground up.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (GNU Image Manipulation Program) is an
        official GNU application.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Das GNU-Projekt wurde von Richard Stallman mit dem Ziel gegründet, ein
        vollständig freies Betriebssystem, das GNU-System, zu entwickeln.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Bekannt ist es insbesondere durch die GNU General Public License (GPL)
        und GNU/Linux, einer GNU-Variante mit Linux-Kernel.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Name GNU entstand aus der Namensgebung, die am MIT — dem Institut,
        an dem Stallman zu dieser Zeit arbeitete — verbreitet war. Für
        Programme, die anderen Programmen ähneln, wurden rekursive Akronyme
        als Namen gewählt. Da das neue System auf dem verbreiteten
        Betriebssystem UNIX aufbauen sollte, suchte Stallman einen solchen
        Namen und kam dabei auf GNU, was für <quote>GNU is not Unix</quote>
        steht. Der Name soll, um Verwechslungen zu vermeiden, wie das
        deutsche <quote>Gnu</quote>
        ausgesprochen werden, nicht wie im Englischen (also wie new). Die
        Entscheidung, GNU Unix-kompatibel zu machen, hatte mehrere Gründe. Zum
        einen war Stallman sicher, dass die meisten Firmen ein grundlegend
        neues Betriebssystem ablehnen würden, wenn die Programme, die sie
        benutzten, darauf nicht laufen würden. Andererseits ermöglichte die
        Architektur von Unix eine schnelle, einfache und verteilte
        Entwicklung, da Unix aus vielen kleinen Programmen besteht, die
        größtenteils unabhängig voneinander entwickelt werden können. Auch
        waren viele Bestandteile eines Unix-Systems frei für jeden erhältlich
        und konnten so direkt in GNU integriert werden, beispielsweise das
        Textsatzsystem <application>TeX</application> oder das Fenstersystem
        <application>X Window</application>. Die fehlenden
        Teile wurden von Grund auf neu geschrieben. (Quelle: <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU">Wikipedia</ulink>)
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Auch <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ist ein offizielles GNU-Programm.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        GNU's Not Unix (GNU No es Unix), es un proyecto para sistemas
        operativos libres de la familia Unix. El proyecto fue comenzado en el
        año 1983 gracias al esfuerzo de la Free Software Fundation, una
        organización dedicada a crear y promover el software libre. El
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> es una aplicación oficial de GNU.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Le projet GNU a été démarré en 1983 par Richard Stallman dans le but
        de développer un système opératoire complètement libre. On le
        connaît surtout par la licence publique générale GNU (GNU General
        Public License ou GPL) et Linux.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le nom résulte des conventions du MIT où Stallman travaillait: un
        acronyme récursif était utilisé pour désigner les programmes
        similaires à d'autres programmes. C'est ainsi que GNU signifie
        <quote>GNU is Not Unix</quote>. Il se prononce comme le gnou,
        l'animal africain. Plusieurs raisons ont présidé au choix d'un
        programme dérivé UNIX: des productions plus facilement
        diffusables; architecture UNIX, en petits programmes
        qui peuvent être développés indépendamment les uns des autres;
        nombreuses parties d'UNIX libres et pouvant être reprises
        dans GNU.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (GNU Image Manipulation Program) est une
        application GNU officielle.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        GNU's Not Unix, (trad.= <quote>GNU non è Unix</quote>) è un progetto
        di un
        sistema operativo libero di tipo Unix. Il progetto è partito nel
        1983, grazie allo sforzo della Free Software Fundation,
        un'organizzazione che ha come scopo la creazione ed il supporto al
        software libero. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> è un'applicazione GNU
        ufficiale.
        Una migliore ed esaustiva definizione la si può trovare sul sito di
        wikipedia <ulink url="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        GNU는 GNU's Not Unix 의 약자로, 자유 운영체제 프로젝트이다. 이
        프로젝트는 1983년에 자유 소프트웨어에 대한 제작과 지원을 하는 기관인
        Free Software Fundation 에서 시작되었다.
        김프는 공식적인 GNU 응용
        프로그램이다. 더 자세한 내용은 위키피아에서 확인할 수 있다.
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        GNU er eit prosjekt som arbeider med å utvikla eit Unix-liknande
        operastivsystem med støtte for gratis programvare.
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (GNU Image Manipulation Program) er eit
        slikt GNU-program. Du kan finne meir om dette i wikipedia under
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        GNU's Not Unix，是一个致力于开放源软件的发展和支持的机构。GIMP 是一个 GNU 官方应用程序。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-graylevel" lang="en;de;no">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Grayscale</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Graustufen</phrase>
      <!-- fr mark: voir "Niveaux de gris"-->
      <phrase lang="no">Gråskala</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Grayscale</primary>
      <secondary>Overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Graustufen</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Gråskala</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Grayscale is a mode for encoding the colors of an image which
        contains only black, white and shades of gray.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When you create a new image, you can choose to create it in
        Grayscale mode (which you can colorize later, by changing it to RGB
        mode). You can also change an existing image to grayscale by using
        the <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-grayscale">Grayscale</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-desaturate">Desaturate</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-decompose">Decompose</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Channel
        Mixer</link>, although not all formats will accept these changes.
        Although you can create images in Grayscale mode and convert images
        to it, it is not a color model, in the true sense of the word.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        As explained in <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB mode</link>, 24-bit
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> images can have up to 256 levels of gray. If
        you change from Grayscale to RGB mode, your image will have an RGB
        structure with three color channels, but of course, it will still be
        gray.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Grayscale image files (8-bit) are smaller than RGB files.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        <emphasis>Graustufen</emphasis> ist eine Methode, um die
        <quote>Farben</quote> eines Schwarzweißbildes zu kodieren.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn Sie ein neues Bild erstellen, können Sie als Modus
        <quote>Graustufen</quote> wählen (Sie können es später einfärben,
        indem Sie es in den RGB-Modus umwandeln). Ein existierendes Bild
        können Sie mit den Kommandos
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-grayscale">Graustufen</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-desaturate">Sättigung entfernen</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-decompose">Zerlegen</link> oder
        <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Kanalmixer</link>
        in ein Graustufenbild umwandeln, allerdings akzeptieren nicht alle
        Formate diese Änderung. Auch wenn Sie Bilder im Graustufenmodus
        erstellen oder in diesen umwandeln können, ist er im eigentlichen
        Sinn kein Farbmodell.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wie für das <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link>-Farbmodell
        angedeutet, können 24-Bit-Bilder in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bis zu
        256 Graustufen enthalten. Wenn Sie vom Graustufen- zum RGB-Modus
        wechseln, wird das Bild dann eine RGB-Struktur mit drei Farbkanälen
        haben, aber es bleibt natürlich weiterhin Schwarzweiß.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Graustufenbilder-Dateien (8 Bit) sind kleiner als RGB-Dateien.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Når du lagar eit bilete kan du velja å vise dette bare i gråtoner.
        Du kan eventuelt fargelegga dette seinare ved å skifte over til
        RGB-modus. I dei fleste biletformata kan du også omgjere eit
        fargebilete til gråskala med kommandoen <link
        linkend="gimp-image-mode">Gråskala</link>  frå biletmenyen.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Du kan også omforma eit RGB-bilete til gråskalabilete ved å
        <quote>avmetta</quote> biletet, altså gjera fargen mindre metta.
        Dette kan gjerast med filteret Bryt opp fargar, Fargeleggingsverktøyet
        eller filteret Kulør og metning. <!--      <link linkend="plug-in-decompose">Bryt opp fargar</link>, <link linkend="gimp-tool-colorize">Fargeleggingsverktøyet</link>
        eller filteret <link linkend="gimp-tool-hue-saturation">Kulør og
          metning</link>. -->
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Som forklart i <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link>-modus, kan
        eit 24-bits bilete i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bare ha 256 nivå av
        grått, koda som 8-bits kode. Skiftar du frå gråskala til RGB vil
        biletet få RGB-struktur med tre fargekanalar i grått. Sjølv om
        du finn denne kommandoen under menyen Modus, er gråskala eigentleg
        ikkje eit fargemodus.
      </para>

    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-guides" lang="en;es;fr;it;ko;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en;fr">Guides</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Guías</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Guide</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">안내선(Guides)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Guides(参考线)</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Vodítka" -->
    <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Hilfslinien" -->
    <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Hjelpelinjer" -->

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Guides</primary>
      <secondary>Using</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Guías</primary></indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="fr">
      <primary>Guides</primary>
      <secondary>Utilisation</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Guide</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Guides are lines you can temporarily display on an image while you
        are working on it. You can display as many guides as you would like,
        in either the horizontal or the vertical direction. These lines help
        you position a selection or a layer on the image. They do not appear
        when the image is printed.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        To create a guide, simply click on one of the rulers in the image
        window and pull out a guide, while holding the
        <mousebutton>mouse button</mousebutton> pressed. The guide is then
        displayed as a blue, dashed line, which follows the pointer. As soon
        as you create a guide, the <quote>Move</quote> tool is activated and
        the mouse pointer changes to the Move icon.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can also create a guide with the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-add">New Guide</link> command,
        which allows you to precisely place the guide on the image, the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-percent">New Guide (by Percent)</link>
        command, or the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-selection">New Guides from Selection</link>
        command.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The behavior of the guides depends upon the
        <guilabel>Affect</guilabel> mode of the <quote>Move</quote> tool.
        When <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis> mode is selected, the
        mouse pointer turns into a small hand as soon as it gets close to a
        guide. Then the guide is activated and it turns red, and you can
        move the guide or delete it by moving it back into the ruler. If
        <emphasis>Transform Selection</emphasis> mode is selected, you can
        position a guide, but you cannot move it after that.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        To make it easier for you to position image elements, you can
        <quote>magnetize</quote> the guides with the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">Snap to Guides</link>
        command. You can remove the guides with the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-remove">Remove all guides</link>
        command. You can enable and disable displaying the guides without
        removing them by using the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">Show Guides</link> command.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For more information about guides, see the
        <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-grid">Grids and Guides</link>
        section.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Para colocar una guía, haz clic en una regla manteniendo presionado el
        botón izquierdo del mouse y mueve el cursor hasta el lugar de la
        imagen en que quieras ubicarla. Luego suelta el botón. Puedes colocar
        guías horizontales o verticales. Aparecen como líneas de guiones en
        azul en la imagen. No se imprimen.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Las guías proporcionan una forma conveniente para posicionar una
        selección o una capa. Ni bien es creada una guía, la herramienta Mover
        es activada y el puntero del mouse cambia al ícono para mover.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        El comportamiento de las guías depende del modo Afectar
        seleccionado en la herramienta Mover.  Cuando el modo
        <emphasis>Transformar capa</emphasis> es seleccionado, el
        puntero del mouse se transforma en una mano cuando se aproxima
        a una guía, la que se vuelve roja y activa.  Ahí puedes
        moverla haciendo clic y arrastrar.  Cuando el modo
        <emphasis>Transformar selección</emphasis> es el seleccionado,
        puedes colocar una guía pero no moverla.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Para hacer más fácil el posicionamiento puedes
        <quote>imantar</quote> las guías activando la opción <!--link
        linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides"-->Ajustar a las
        guías<!--/link-->.  Puedes desactivar la visualización de las
        guías sin borrarlas mediante la opción <!--link
        linkend="gimp-view-show-guides"-->Mostrar guías<!--/link-->.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Pour mettre en place un guide, cliquez sur une des règles et, sans
        relâcher le bouton de la souris, faites glisser le pointeur sur
        l'image. Le guide apparu suit le pointeur. Vous pouvez ainsi placer
        deux guides, un horizontal et un vertical. Ils sont représentés par
        une ligne de tirets bleus. Ils ne seront pas imprimés.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les guides servent à positionner avec précision une sélection ou un
        calque. Dès qu'un guide est créé, l'outil déplacement est activé et le
        pointeur de la souris prend l'aspect de l'icône de déplacement.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le comportement des guides dépend du mode Affecte choisi
        pour l'outil Déplacement. Quand le mode
        <emphasis>Transformation du calque</emphasis> est
        sélectionné, le pointeur se transforme en une petite main
        quand il passe sur un guide qui devient rouge et activé.
        Vous pouvez alors le déplacer par un cliquer-glisser.
        Quand le mode <emphasis> Transformation de la
          sélection</emphasis> est sélectionné, vous pouvez placer
        un guide, mais vous ne pouvez plus le déplacer ensuite.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour faciliter le positionnement, vous pouvez magnétiser
        les guides avec l'option <link
        linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">Aligner sur les guides</link>
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Vous pouvez suspendre leur visualisation, sans les
        supprimer, avec l'option <link
        linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">Afficher les guides</link>
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Per inserire una guida, premere e mantenere premuto il tasto sinistro
        del mouse su un righello, poi trascinare il puntatore sull'immagine. È
        possibile inserire guide sia orizzontali che verticali. Esse
        appariranno come righe tratteggiate di colore blu e non verranno
        stampate.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Le guide sono una comodità per posizionare una selezione o un livello.
        Quando una guida viene creata, lo strumento di spostamento viene
        automaticamente selezionato ed il puntatore si trasforma nella forma
        dell'icona dello spostamento.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Il comportamento delle guide dipende dalla modalità di Influenza
        selezionata nelle opzioni dello strumento di spostamento.
        Quando viene selezionata la modalità <emphasis>Trasforma
          livello</emphasis>, il puntatore del mouse, quando raggiunge una
        guida, diventa una piccola mano; la guida diventa attiva
        di rosso. Per spostarla basta fare clic e trascinarla col mouse.
        Quando viene selezionata la modalità <emphasis>Trasforma
          selezione</emphasis> è possibile inserire una guida ma non sarà
        più possibile spostarla dopo l'inserimento (NdT: ma solo per la
        durata di questa modalità).
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Per facilitare il posizionamento è possibile
        "magnetizzare" le guide con l'opzione <!--link
        linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides" FIXME it -->Guide magnetiche<!--/link-->
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        È possibile disabilitare la visualizzazione delle guide senza
        rimuoverle con l'opzione <!--link
        linkend="gimp-view-show-guides" FIXME it -->Mostra le guide<!--/link-->
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        안내선을 사용하려면 눈금자에 마우스 포인터를 두고 좌버튼 클릭을
        한 후에 이미지로 드래그하면 안내선이 나타나 포인터를 따라간다.
        안내선은 수평 안내선과 수직 안내선이 있으며, 이들은 인쇄되지
        않는다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        안내선은 선택이나 레이어를 위치시키는데 편리한 도구이다. 안내선을
        만들면 이동도구가 선택되며 마우스 커서는 이동 아이콘으로 바뀐다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        안내선은 이동 도구의 영향 모드가 선택되어 있을 경우에만 움직일 수
        있다. <emphasis>레이어 변형</emphasis> 모드가 선택되어 있을
        경우에 마우스 포인터를 안내선에 가까이 가져가면 포인터가 작은
        손모양으로 변ㄴ하며 안내선은 빨간색으로 활성화된다. 이러면 안내선을
        클릭하여 이동시킬 수 있다.
        <emphasis>선택 변형</emphasis> 모드일 경우에는, 안내선을 한번
        위치시킨 후에 이동시킬 수 없다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        위치시키는 것을 쉽게 하기 위해서
        <!--PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">
          안내선에 맞추기</link> --> 안내선에 맞추기
        옵션을 통해 안내선에
        &apos;자성을 띄게&apos; 할 수도 있다.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <!--PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">
          안내선 표시</link> --> 안내선 표시
        옵션을 이용하면 안내선을 없애지
        않고도 보이지 않게 할 수 있다.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        要放置一个参考线，左键点击并按住一个标尺再拖动鼠标光标到图像中。一个参考线出现并跟着光标。您可以这样放置两个参考线，一个水平和一个垂直的。它们显示位蓝色虚线，并且不会被打印出来。
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        参考线是放置一个选区或图层的方便快捷键。随着一个参考线的创建，移动工具被选取而且鼠标光标也变为一个移动图标。
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        参考线的行为有移动工具选取的影响模式决定。当选取 <emphasis>变换图层</emphasis> 模式时，在鼠标光标移到一根参考线上，参考线会成为活动的并变为红色，而光标则呈一个小手形状。然后可以点击并拖动来移动它。当选取 <emphasis>变换选区</emphasis> 模式时，您能够放置参考线，但在退出后就不能再移动它了。
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        要使放置更容易，您可以使用<link linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">吸附到参考线</link>选项。
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您能够通过<link linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">显示参考线</link>选项中止显示参考线而不必移动它们。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
