<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<glossdiv lang="cs;en;de;fr;it;zh_CN">
  <title>G</title>

  <anchor id="file-gif-load" />

  <glossentry id="file-gif-save">
    <glossterm>GIF</glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="cs">
      <para>
        GIF je grafický souborový formát podporující až 8bitové indexované
        barvy a průhlednost (ale nikoliv částečnou průhlednost). Obrázek
        uložený ve formátu GIF tedy může obsahovat maximálně 256 barev.
        Podporuje také tvorbu jednoduchých animací a komentáře. Dříve se hodně
        používal pro tvorbu webové grafiky. Problémy s patenty však vedly
        k jeho nahrazování formátem <link
        linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>, který navíc ve většině
        případů poslouží lépe.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        Trademarked by CompuServe, with LZW compression patented by
        Unisys. GIF images are in 8 bit indexed color and support
        binary transparency (but not semi-transparency). They can also be
        loaded in interlaced form by some programs. The GIF format also
        supports animations and comments. Use GIF for transparent Web
        graphics and GIF animations.  For most purposes, though, <link
        linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link> can
        be used in place of GIF and is a better choice. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang='de'>
      <para>
        Markenrechtlich geschützt durch CompuServe welches die LZW
        Kompression patentiert von Unisys benutzt. Bilder im GIF Format
        unterstützen eine 8bit indexierte Farbpalette und Transparenz
        (jedoch nicht mehrstufige Transparenz wie das <link
        linkend='file-png-save-defaults'>PNG</link>). Ausserdem können
        GIF Bilder <emphasis>interlaced<footnote>
          <para>
            Wird das GIF als interlaced abgespeichert, wird das Bild in
            mehreren Durchgängen aufgebaut. Nützlich ist dies vor allem
            im Internet bei einer langsamen Verbindung.
          </para>
        </footnote></emphasis> von einigen
        Programmen geladen und gespeichert werden. Ausserdem unterstützt
        das GIF Animationen, sowie Kommentare als Dateiinformation. Zum
        Einsatz kommt das GIF meistenteils im Internet. Das <link
        linkend='file-png-save-defaults'>PNG</link> jedoch ist dem GIF
        vorzuziehen. Es hat die gleichen Vorteile des GIF, bei
        besserer Kompression und größerer Funktionalität.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        Format d'enregistrement d'image déposé par Compuserve, 
        utilisant la méthode de compression LZW brevetée par unisys. Les 
        images GIF sont en couleurs indexées sur 8 bits et acceptent la 
        transparence (mais pas la demi-transparence). Le format GIF permet 
        aussi de gérer animations et commentaires. Utilisez GIF pour les 
        images Web transparentes et les animations. Mais dans la plupart des 
        cas, le format <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link> est 
        plus performant.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="it">
      <para>
        Marchio registrato da CompuServe con l'algoritmo di compressione
        LZW brevettato da Unisys. Le immagini GIF sono a colori a 8 bit
        indicizzati con il supporto alla trasparenza (ma senza supporto
        alla semi-trasparenza). Possono essere caricate anche in
        forma interlacciata. Il formato GIF supporta anche l'animazione e i
        commenti. Usate il formato GIF solo per grafica Web con trasparenze
        e animazione. Il formato <!--link
        linkend="file-png-save-defaults"FIXME -->PNG<!--/link--> può essere
        usato al posto del formato GIF e molto spesso è una scelta migliore.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        CompuServe 的商标，使用 Unisys 专利的 LZW 压缩算法。GIF 图像使用8位索引色并且支持透明(不支持半透明)，它能被一些程序交错扫描地载入。GIF 格式还支持动画和备注。它可用做透明网页图形和 GIF 动画。而 <link
        linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>是能够在大多数功能上代替 GIF 的不二选择。
     </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-gnu'>
    <glossterm>GNU</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Rekurzivní zkratka z <foreignphrase>GNU's Not Unix</foreignphrase>
        (GNU není Unix). Označuje projekt pro vytvoření svobodného operačního
        systému unixového typu, který byl v roce 1983 zahájen nadací FSF
        (<foreignphrase>Free Software Foundation</foreignphrase>), jejímž
        posláním je tvořit a podporovat svobodný software. GIMP je oficialní
        součástí projektu GNU. Více se o projektu GNU dozvíte ve Wikipedii
        <ulink url="http://cs.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        GNU's Not Unix, is a project of a free (Unix like) operative system.
        The project was started back in 1983 thanks to the effort of the Free
        Software Fundation,
        an organization devoted to the creation and support of free software.
        GIMP is an official GNU application.
        You can find a better definition on the wikipedia site<ulink
        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        GNU steht für GNU's Not Unix und bezeichnet eine Organisation
        die sich der Unterstützung freier Software verschrieben hat. GNU
        wurde durch Richard Stallmann ins Leben gerufen.
        <acronym>Gimp</acronym> selber ist ein offizielles GNU Programm.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        GNU's Not Unix, est une organisation destinée à la création et au 
        soutien des logiciels libres. GIMP est une application GNU 
        officielle.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        GNU's Not Unix, (trad.= "GNU non è Unix") è un progetto di un
        sistema operativo libero di tipo Unix. Il progetto è partito nel
        1983, grazie allo sforzo della Free Software Fundation,
        un'organizzazione che ha come scopo la creazione ed il supporto al
        software libero. GIMP è un'applicazione GNU ufficiale.
        Una migliore ed esaustiva definizione la si può trovare sul sito di
        wikipedia <ulink url="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU"></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        GNU's Not Unix，是一个致力于开放源软件的发展和支持的机构。GIMP 是一个 GNU 官方应用程序。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
    
  <glossentry id='glossary-guides' lang="en;fr;it;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="en">Guides</glossterm>
    <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Hilfslinien" -->
    <glossterm lang="fr">Guides</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="it">Guide</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Guides(参考线)</glossterm>
		
    <glossdef lang='en'>
      <para>
        To place a guide, left-click-and-hold on a ruler and drag
        the mouse pointer in to the image. A guide appears and
        follows the pointer.  You can so place two guides, a
        horizontal one and a vertical one.  They appear as blue
        dashed lines. They do not print.
      </para>
      <para>
        Guides are a convenient way to position a selection or a
        layer.  As soon as a guide is created, the Move tool is
        selected and the mouse pointer turns to a move icon.
      </para>
      <para>
        Guide behaviour depends on the Affect mode selected in the
        Move tool.  When the <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis>
        mode is selected, the mouse pointer turns to a small hand
        when it reaches a guide that becomes red and active. You
        can then move it by a click and drag.  When the
        <emphasis>Transform Selection</emphasis> mode is selected
        you can place a guide, but you can no longer move it after
        quitting it.    
      </para>
      <para>
        To make positioning easier you can &apos;magnetize&apos;
        guides with the option <link
        linkend='gimp-view-snap-to-guides'>Snap to Guides</link>
      </para>
      <para>
        You can abort displaying guides without removing them by
        the option     <link linkend='gimp-view-show-guides'>Show
        Guides</link>
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="fr">  
      <para>
        Pour mettre en place un guide, cliquez sur une des règles
        et, sans relâcher le bouton de la souris, faites glisser
        le pointeur sur l'image. Le guide apparu suit le pointeur.
        Vous pouvez ainsi placer deux guides, un horizontal et un
        vertical. Ils sont représentés par une ligne de tirets
        bleus. Ils ne seront pas imprimés.
      </para>
      <para>
        Les guides servent à positionner avec précision une
        sélection ou un calque. Dès qu'un guide est créé, l'outil
        déplacement est activé et le pointeur de la souris prend
        l'aspect de l'icône de déplacement. 
      </para>
      <para>
        Le comportement des guides dépend du mode Affecte choisi
        pour l'outil Déplacement. Quand le mode
        <emphasis>Transformation du calque</emphasis> est
        sélectionné, le pointeur se transforme en une petite main
        quand il passe sur un guide qui devient rouge et activé.
        Vous pouvez alors le déplacer par un cliquer-glisser.
        Quand le mode <emphasis> Transformation de la
        sélection</emphasis> est sélectionné, vous pouvez placer
        un guide, mais vous ne pouvez plus le déplacer ensuite.  
      </para>
      <para>
        Pour faciliter le positionnement, vous pouvez magnétiser
        les guides avec l'option <link
        linkend='gimp-view-snap-to-guides'>Aligner sur les
        guides</link>
      </para>
      <para>
        Vous pouvez suspendre leur visualisation, sans les
        supprimer, avec l'option <link
        linkend='gimp-view-show-guides'>Afficher les guides</link> 
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang='it'>
      <para>
        Per inserire una guida, premere e mantenere premuto il tasto
        sinistro del mouse su un righello, poi trascinare il puntatore
        sull'immagine. È possibile inserire guide sia orizzontali
        che verticali. Esse appariranno come righe tratteggiate di colore
        blu e non verranno stampate.
      </para>
      <para>
        Le guide sono una comodità per posizionare una selezione o un
        livello. Quando una guida viene creata, lo strumento di spostamento
        viene automaticamente selezionato ed il puntatore si trasforma
        nella forma dell'icona dello spostamento.
      </para>
      <para>
        Il comportamento delle guide dipende dalla modalità di Influenza
        selezionata nelle opzioni dello strumento di spostamento.
        Quando viene selezionata la modalità <emphasis>Trasforma
        livello</emphasis>, il puntatore del mouse, quando raggiunge una
        guida, diventa una piccola mano; la guida diventa attiva colorandosi
        di rosso. Per spostarla basta fare clic e trascinarla col mouse.
        Quando viene selezionata la modalità <emphasis>Trasforma
        selezione</emphasis> è possibile inserire una guida ma non sarà più
        possibile spostarla dopo l'inserimento (NdT: ma solo per la durata
        di questa modalità).
      </para>
      <para>
        Per facilitare il posizionamento è possibile
        "magnetizzare" le guide con l'opzione <!--link
        linkend='gimp-view-snap-to-guides' FIXME -->Guide magnetiche<!--/link-->
      </para>
      <para>
        È possibile disabilitare la visualizzazione delle guide senza
        rimuoverle con l'opzione <!--link
        linkend='gimp-view-show-guides' FIXME -->Mostra le guide<!--/link-->
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="zh_CN"> 
      <para>
        要放置一个参考线，左键点击并按住一个标尺再拖动鼠标光标到图像中。一个参考线出现并跟着光标。您可以这样放置两个参考线，一个水平和一个垂直的。它们显示位蓝色虚线，并且不会被打印出来。
      </para>
      <para>
        参考线是放置一个选区或图层的方便快捷键。随着一个参考线的创建，移动工具被选取而且鼠标光标也变为一个移动图标。
      </para>
      <para>
        参考线的行为有移动工具选取的影响模式决定。当选取 <emphasis>变换图层</emphasis> 模式时，在鼠标光标移到一根参考线上，参考线会成为活动的并变为红色，而光标则呈一个小手形状。然后可以点击并拖动来移动它。当选取 <emphasis>变换选区</emphasis> 模式时，您能够放置参考线，但在退出后就不能再移动它了。
      </para>
      <para>
        要使放置更容易，您可以使用<link linkend='gimp-view-snap-to-guides'>吸附到参考线</link>选项。
      </para>
      <para>
        您能够通过<link linkend='gimp-view-show-guides'>显示参考线</link>选项中止显示参考线而不必移动它们。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
