<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-12-27 lexa: added gamut for en de
  2007-09-01 AntI: Added es (gamma)
  2007-02-01 alessandro falappa: some italian translations added
  2006-11-04 added a list of grayscale ways (reference used by Channel Mixer)
  by j.h
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-18 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-02-12 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-08-26 de added graylevel by axel.wernicke
  2005-08-07 de added gamma by axel.wernicke
  2005-06-11 de added Zwischenablage by axel.wernicke
  -->
<glossdiv>
  <title>G</title><anchor id="glossary-g"/>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gamut">
    <glossterm>Gamut</glossterm>
    <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "fargeomfang" -->

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Gamut</primary></indexterm>
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        In color reproduction, including computer graphics and photography,
        the gamut, or color gamut (pronounced /ˈgæmət/), is a certain complete
        subset of colors. The most common usage refers to the subset of colors
        which can be accurately represented in a given circumstance, such as
        within a given color space or by a certain output device. Another
        sense, less frequently used but not less correct, refers to the
        complete set of colors found within an image at a given time. In this
        context, digitizing a photograph, converting a digitized image to a
        different color space, or outputting it to a given medium using a
        certain output device generally alters its gamut, in the sense that
        some of the colors in the original are lost in the process.
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gamut"/>
      </para>
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-gamma">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Gamma</phrase>
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Gamma</primary></indexterm>
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Gamma or gamma correction is a non-linear operation which is used to
        encode and decode luminance or color values in video or still image
        systems. It is used in many types of imaging systems to straighten out
        a curved signal-to-light or intensity-to-signal response. For example,
        the light emitted by a CRT is not linear with regard to its input
        voltage, and the voltage from an electric camera is not linear with
        regard to the intensity (power) of the light in the scene. Gamma
        encoding helps to map the data into a perceptually linear domain, so
        that the limited signal range (the limited number of bits in each RGB
        signal) is better optimized perceptually.
      </para>
      <para>
        Gamma is used as an exponent (power) in the correction equation. Gamma
        compression (where gamma &lt; 1) is used to encode linear luminance or
        RGB values into color signals or digital file values, and gamma
        expansion (where gamma &gt; 1) is the decoding process, and usually
        occurs where the current-to-voltage function for a CRT is non-linear.
      </para>
      <para>
        For PC video, images are encoded with a gamma of about 0.45 and
        decoded with a gamma of 2.2. For Mac systems, images are typically
        encoded with a gamma of about 0.55 and decoded with a gamma of 1.8.
        The sRGB color space standard used for most cameras, PCs and printers
        does not use a simple exponential equation, but has a decoding gamma
        value near 2.2 over much of its range.
      </para>
      <para>
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, gamma is an option used in the brush tab
        of the <link linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>
        filter and in the <link linkend="plug-in-flame">Flame</link> filter.
        The <link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">display filters</link>
        also include a Gamma filter. Also see the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels Tool</link>, where you can
        use the middle slider to change the gamma value.
      </para>

      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-gif">
    <glossterm>GIF</glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>GIF</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      

      <para>
        <trademark class="trade">GIF</trademark> stands for Graphics Interchange Format.
        It is a <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        with good, lossless compression for images with low
        <link linkend="glossary-colordepth">color depth</link>
        (up to 256 different colors per image). Since GIF was developed, a
        new format called <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">Portable Network Graphics (PNG)</link>
        has been developed, which is better than GIF in all respects, with
        the exception of animations and some rarely-used features.
      </para>
      <para>
        GIF was introduced by CompuServe in 1987. It became popular mostly
        because of its efficient, LZW compression. The size of the image files
        required clearly less disk space than other usual graphics formats of
        the time, such as PCX or MacPaint. Even large images could be
        transmitted in a reasonable time, even with slow modems. In addition,
        the open licensing policy of CompuServe made it possible for any
        programmer to implement the GIF format for his own applications free
        of charge, as long as the CompuServe copyright notice was attached to
        them.
      </para>
      <para>
        Colors in GIF are stored in a color table which can hold up to 256
        different entries, chosen from 16.7 million different color values.
        When the image format was introduced, this was not a much of a
        limitation, since only a few people had hardware which could display
        more colors than that. For typical drawings, cartoons, black-and-white
        photographs and similar uses, 256 colors are quite sufficient as a
        rule, even today. For more complex images, such as color photographs,
        however, a huge loss of quality is apparent, which is why the format
        is not considered to be suitable for those purposes.
      </para>
      <para>
        One color entry in the palette can be defined to be transparent.
        With transparency, the GIF image can look like it is non-rectangular
        in shape. However, semi-transparency, as in
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>, is not possible.
        A pixel can only be either entirely visible or completely
        transparent.
      </para>
      <para>
        The first version of GIF was 87a. In 1989, CompuServe published an
        expanded version, called 89a. Among other things, this made it
        possible to save several images in one GIF file, which is especially
        used for simple animation. The version number can be distinguished
        from the first six bytes of a GIF file. Interpreted as ASCII symbols,
        they are <quote>GIF87a</quote> or <quote>GIF89a</quote>.
      </para>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      
      
      
      
      

      
      

      

      
      
      
      
      

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-gnu">
    <glossterm>GNU</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      

      <para>
        The GNU project was started in 1983 by Richard Stallman with the
        goal of developing a completely free operating system. It is
        especially well-known from the GNU General Public License (GPL) and
        GNU/Linux, a GNU-variant with a Linux kernel.
      </para>
      <para>
        The name came about from the naming conventions which were in
        practice at MIT, where Stallman worked at the time.
        For programs which were similar to other programs, recursive
        acronyms were chosen as names. Since the new system was to be based
        on the widespread operating system, Unix, Stallman looked for that
        kind of name and came up with GNU, which stands for
        <quote>GNU is not Unix</quote>. In order to avoid confusion, the
        name should be pronounced with the <quote>G</quote>, not like
        <quote>new</quote>. There were several reasons for making GNU
        Unix-compatible. For one thing, Stallman was convinced that most
        companies would refuse a completely new operating system, if the
        programs they used wouldn't run on it. In addition, the architecture
        of Unix made quick, easy and distributed development possible,
        since Unix consists of many small programs that can be developed
        independently of each other, for the most part. Also, many parts of
        a Unix system were freely available to anyone and could therefore
        be directly integrated into GNU, for example, the typesetting
        system, TeX, or the X Window System. The missing parts were newly
        written from the ground up.
      </para>
      <para>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        (GNU Image Manipulation Program) is an official GNU application
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gnu"/>.
      </para>

      
      
      
      

      

      
      
      

      

      

      
      
      
      

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-grayscale">
    <glossterm>
      <anchor id="glossary-graylevel" xreflabel="Grayscale"/>
      <phrase>Grayscale</phrase>
      
      <!-- it mark: scala di grigi -->
      <!-- fr mark: voir "Niveaux de gris"-->
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Grayscale</primary>
      <secondary>Overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Grayscale is a mode for encoding the colors of an image which
        contains only black, white and shades of gray.
      </para>
      <para>
        When you create a new image, you can choose to create it in
        Grayscale mode (which you can colorize later, by changing it to RGB
        mode). You can also change an existing image to grayscale by using
        the <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-grayscale">Grayscale</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-desaturate">Desaturate</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-decompose-registered">Decompose</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Channel
        Mixer</link>, although not all formats will accept these changes.
        Although you can create images in Grayscale mode and convert images
        to it, it is not a color model, in the true sense of the word.
      </para>
      <para>
        As explained in <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB mode</link>, 24-bit
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> images can have up to 256 levels of gray. If
        you change from Grayscale to RGB mode, your image will have an RGB
        structure with three color channels, but of course, it will still be
        gray.
      </para>
      <para>
        Grayscale image files (8-bit) are smaller than RGB files.
      </para>

      
      
      
      

      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  


  <glossentry id="glossary-guides">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Guides</phrase>
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>
    <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Vodítka" -->
    <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Hilfslinien" -->
    <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Hjelpelinjer" -->

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Guides</primary>
      <secondary>Using</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    

    

    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Guides are lines you can temporarily display on an image while you are
        working on it. You can display as many guides as you would like, in
        either the horizontal or the vertical direction. These lines help you
        position a selection or a layer on the image. They do not appear when
        the image is printed.
      </para>
      <para>
        To create a guide, simply click on one of the rulers in the image
        window and pull out a guide, while holding the
        <mousebutton moreinfo="none">mouse button</mousebutton> pressed. The guide is then
        displayed as a blue, dashed line, which follows the pointer. As soon
        as you create a guide, the <quote>Move</quote> tool is activated and
        the mouse pointer changes to the Move icon.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can also create a guide with the <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-add">New Guide</link> command, which
        allows you to precisely place the guide on the image, the <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-percent">New Guide (by Percent)</link>
        command, or the <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-selection">New
        Guides from Selection</link> command.
      </para>
      <para>
        The behavior of the guides depends upon the
        <guilabel moreinfo="none">Affect</guilabel> mode of the <quote>Move</quote> tool.
        When <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis> mode is selected, the
        mouse pointer turns into a small hand as soon as it gets close to a
        guide. Then the guide is activated and it turns red, and you can
        move the guide or delete it by moving it back into the ruler. If
        <emphasis>Transform Selection</emphasis> mode is selected, you can
        position a guide, but you cannot move it after that.
      </para>
      <para>
        To make it easier for you to position image elements, you can
        <quote>magnetize</quote> the guides with the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">Snap to Guides</link>
        command. You can remove the guides with the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-remove">Remove all guides</link>
        command. You can enable and disable displaying the guides without
        removing them by using the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">Show Guides</link> command.
      </para>
      <para>
        For more information about guides, see the
        <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-grid">Grids and Guides</link>
        section.
      </para>

      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      

      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
