<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-11-03 replaced hextriplet with HTML notation by j.h
  2007-03-06 de new translation of supersampling by ude
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-19 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-08-26 de reviewed hsv by axel.wernicke
  2005-08-08 de added histogram by axel.wernicke
  2005-06-14 de added Hilfslinien by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>H</title><anchor id="glossary-h"/>

  


  <glossentry id="glossary-histogram">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Histogram</phrase>
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Histogram</primary></indexterm>
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        In digital image processing, a histogram is a graph representing the
        statistical frequency of the gray values or the color values in an
        image. The histogram of an image tells you about the occurrence of
        gray values or color values, as well as the contrast range and the
        brightness of the image. In a color image, you can create one
        histogram with information about all possible colors, or three
        histograms for the individual color channels. The latter makes the
        most sense, since most procedures are based on grayscale images and
        therefore further processing is immediately possible.
      </para>
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  


  <glossentry id="glossary-hsv">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>HSV</phrase>
      
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        HSV is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Hue (the color, such as blue or red),
        Saturation (how strong the color is) and Value (the brightness).
      </para>
      <para>
        The RGB mode is very well suited to computer screens, but it doesn't
        let us describe what we see in everyday life; a light green, a
        pale pink, a dazzling red, etc. The HSV model takes these
        characteristics into account. HSV and RGB are not completely
        independent of each other. You can see that with the Color Picker
        tool; when you change a color in one of the color models, the other
        one also changes. Brave souls can read
        <emphasis>Grokking the GIMP</emphasis>, which explains their
        interrelationship.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel moreinfo="none">Hue</guilabel>:
            This is the color itself, which results from the
            combination of primary colors. All shades (except for the
            gray levels) are represented in a <emphasis>chromatic
            circle</emphasis>: yellow, blue, and also purple, orange,
            etc.  The chromatic circle (or <quote>color wheel</quote>)
            values range between 0° and 360°. (The term
            <quote>color</quote> is often used instead of
            <quote>Hue</quote>. The RGB colors are
            <quote>primary colors</quote>.)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel moreinfo="none">Saturation</guilabel>
            : This value describes how pale the color is. A completely
            unsaturated color is a shade of gray. As the saturation increases,
            the color becomes a pastel shade. A completely saturated color is
            pure. Saturation values go from 0 to 100, from white to the purest
            color.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel moreinfo="none">Value</guilabel>
            : This value describes the luminosity, the luminous intensity. It
            is the amount of light emitted by a color. You can see a change of
            luminosity when a colored object is moved from being in the shadow
            to being in the sun, or when you increase the luminosity of your
            screen. Values go from 0 to 100. Pixel values in the three
            channels are also luminosities: <quote>Value</quote> in the HSV
            color model is the maximum of these elementary values in the RGB
            space (scaled to 0-100).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      
      

      

      
      
      

      
      
      

      
      
      

      

      
      
      

      
      
      

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-html-notation">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>HTML notation</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>HTML notation</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Color</primary><secondary>HTML notation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A hex triplet is a way of encoding a color for a computer. The
        <quote>#</quote> symbol indicates that the numbers which follow it
        are encoded in hexadecimal. Each color is specified in two
        hexadecimal digits which make up a triplet (three pairs) of
        hexadecimal values in the form <quote>#rrggbb</quote>, where
        <quote>rr</quote> represents red, <quote>gg</quote> represents green
        and <quote>bb</quote> represents blue.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
