<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2007-03-06 ude: merged fr "Incrémentiel ..." to glossary-incremental
     2007-02-06 alessandro falappa: added reference for glossary-imagehose
     2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
     2006-05-19 added Korean translation by Dust
     2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
     2005-08-26 de added indexed colors by axel.wernicke
     2005-06-14 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
     -->
<glossdiv lang="en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title><anchor id="glossary-i" />I</title>

  <glossentry id="glossary-imagehose" lang="en;es;ko;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="en">Image Hose</glossterm>
    <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Animovaná stopa" -->
    <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Bilderschlauch" -->
    <glossterm lang="es">Image Hose</glossterm>
    <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Brosses GIH" -->
    <!-- it MARK: see glossterm "Pennelli animati" -->
    <glossterm lang="ko">이미지 호스(Image Hose)</glossterm>
    <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Mønsterpensel" -->
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Image Hose(图像管)</glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en;es"><primary>Image Hose</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        An image hose in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a special type of brush
        which consists of several images. For example, you could have a
        brush with footprints, which consists of two images, one for the
        left footprint and one for the right. While painting with this
        brush, a left footprint would appear first, then a right footprint,
        then a left one, etc. This type of brush is very powerful.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        An image hose is also sometimes called an <quote>image pipe</quote>
        or <quote>animated brush</quote>. An image hose is indicated in the
        Brushes dialog by a small red triangle in the lower right corner of
        the brush's symbol.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For information concerning creating an image hose, please see the
        <link linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes">Using Animated Brushes</link>
        and <link linkend="gimp-using-brushes">Using Brushes</link> sections.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이미지 호스는 여러개의 서로 다른 이미지들을 가진 특별한 브러쉬이다.
        예를 들어 발자국 브러쉬는 왼발자국과 오른발자국의 두 가지 이미지를
        가지고 있다. 이 가상의 호스 브러쉬를 사용하면 좌우발자국이 번갈아
        찍히는 것을 볼 수 있다. 브러쉬의 이러한 애니메이션 기법은 굉장히
        유용하다.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Son un tipo especial de brochas que tienen varios cuadros.  Un
        ejemplo puede ser una brocha que haga pasos, teniendo dos
        imágenes, una para el paso izquierdo y otra para el derecho.
        Al aplicar esta hipotética brocha, uno podría ver el paso
        izquierdo, luego el derecho, y así continuamente.  Este método
        de animación para las brochas puede es muy poderoso.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        图像管是包含许多不同框架的特殊画笔。包含两个图像的脚印画笔就是一种。
        一个是左脚印，一个是右脚印。在这种超现实画笔的应用过程中，可能会发现
        右脚印以连续的方式跟着左脚印。这种画笔的动画方法是很强大的。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-incremental" lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;ko;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="cs">Inkrementální, režim kreslení</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="en">Incremental, paint mode</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Inkrementeller Malmodus</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="es">Incremental, modo de pintura</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Incrémentiel (mode de dessin)</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="it">Incrementale, modalità disegno</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="ko">증가, 페인트 모드(Incremental, paint mode)</glossterm>
    <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Aukande, malemodus" -->
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Incremental(增值)，涂画模式</glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en;es"><primary>Incremental</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="cs"><primary>Inkrementální</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Inkrementeller Malmodus</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Incremental mode is a paint mode where each brush stroke is drawn
        directly on the active layer. When it is set, each additional stroke
        of the brush increases the effect of the brush, up to the maximum
        opacity for the brush.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        If incremental mode is not set, brush strokes are drawn on a canvas
        buffer, which is then combined with the active layer. The maximum
        effect of a brush is then determined by the opacity, and stroking
        with the brush repeatedly does not increase the effect beyond this
        limit.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Při použití inkrementálního režimu se každý tah štětcem okamžitě
        projevuje na aktivní vrstvě. Pokud tento režim použit není, je
        používán buffer.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Dieser Malmodus zeichnet jeden Pinselstrich direkt auf die aktive
        Ebene. Wenn er aktiviert ist, verstärkt jeder zusätzliche
        Pinselstrich die Wirkung bis zur maximalen Deckkraft des Pinsels.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn der inkrementelle Malmodus nicht aktiviert ist, wird auf
        einer Zeichenfläche gemalt, die dann mit der aktiven Ebene
        zusammengemischt wird. Die maximale Wirkung eines Pinsels wird dann
        durch seine Deckkraft bestimmt, weitere Pinselstriche haben keine
        Wirkung.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Este modo de pintura imprime cada trazo con la brocha
        directamente sobre la capa activa.  Si el modo incremental no
        es activado, hay un buffer del lienzo que es compuesto con la
        capa activa.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans ce mode chaque coup de brosse agit directement dans le calque
        actif. Si ce mode est désactivé, un canevas tampon est créé qui sera
        intégré au calque actif.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Questa modalità di disegno rende ogni <quote>pennellata</quote>
        direttamente sul livello attivo. Se la modalità incrementale non è
        attiva, viene usato una <quote>tela temporanea o di buffer</quote>
        composita con il livello attivo.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
       이 페인트 모드는 각 브러쉬 스트로크를 즉시 활성화된 레이어에
       표현한다. 증가 모드가 설정되어 있지 않으면, 활성화된 레이어에
       의해 만들어지는 캔버스 버퍼에 저장된다.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该涂画模式将每笔直接渲染到活动图层上。如果没有设置增值模式，将会使用
        一个和活动图层混杂在一起的画布缓冲区。
      </para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
               fileref="../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png"
               format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
               fileref="../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png"
               format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The two images above were created using a brush with spacing set to
        60 pixels. The image on the left shows non-incremental painting and
        the image on the right shows the difference with incremental painting.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Oba obrázky výše byly vytvořeny štětcem se stopou o rozestupu 60.
        Vlevo nebyl použit inkrementální režim, vpravo ano. V inkrementálním
        režimu je každý otisk stopy během tahu štětcem přidáván k předchozím.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die beiden Bilder wurden mit einem Pinsel erstellt, dessen
        <quote>Abstand</quote> auf 60 Pixel eingestellt war. Im linken Bild
        war der <emphasis>Inkrementelle Malmodus</emphasis> ausgeschaltet. Das
        rechte Bild zeigt den Unterschied durch den eingeschalteten
        <emphasis>Inkrementellen Malmodus</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Las dos imágenes de arriba fueron creadas usando una brocha
        con el espaciado puesto en 60.  La imagen de la izquierda
        muestra una pintura no incremental, mientras que la de la
        derecha muestra la diferencia que la pintura incremental puede
        producir.  El modo de pintura incremental hace que cada
        impresión de la brocha sea adicionado a las anteriores
        impresiones, a lo largo de un trazo.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les 2 images ci-dessus ont été réalisées avec une brosse dont
        l'espacement était réglé sur 6 sans mode incrémentiel pour celle de
        gauche, avec pour celle de droite. Le mode incrémentiel fait que,
        pendant toute la durée du tracé, chaque touche de la brosse s'ajoute
        à la précédente.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Le due immagini qui sopra esposte sono state create usando un
        pennello con spaziatura impostata a valore 60. L'immagine sulla
        sinistra mostra un esempio di disegno non-incrementale mentre
        quella a destra mostra uno di tipo incrementale. La modalità di
        disegno incrementale è efficace per ogni applicazione di un
        qualsiasi strumento di disegno e per tutta la durata del tratto. Il
        tratto viene così effettuato sommando man mano lo stesso al disegno
        del tratto precedente.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        위의 두 이미지는 60 크기의 브러쉬로 그린 것들이다. 왼쪽 그림은
        미증가 페인팅이고, 오른쪽 그림은 증가 페인팅이다. 각 브러쉬의
        증가 페인트 모드 결과는 스트로크의 지속시간 동안 그 전의 브러쉬
        모양에 추가되는 것된 모양으로 표현된다.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        上面两个图像用 6 号画笔创建。左边图像没有使用增值进行涂画而右边的则使用。
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Incremental mode is a tool option that is shared by several brush
        tools, except those which have a <quote>rate</quote> control, which
        automatically implies an incremental effect. You can set it by
        checking the <guilabel>Incremental</guilabel> checkbox in the
        toolbox for the tool (Paintbrush, Pencil and Eraser).
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-indexedcolors" lang="en;de;fr;no">
    <glossterm lang="en">Indexed Colors</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Indizierte Farben</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Indexées (Couleurs -)</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="no">Indekserte fargar</glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Indexed Colors</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="de"><primary>Indizierte farben</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="fr"><primary>Indexation</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Indekserte fargar</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para  lang="en">
        Indexed color mode is a mode for encoding colors in an image where
        each pixel in the image is assigned an 8-bit color number. The color
        which corresponds to this number is then put in a table (the palette).
        Changing a color in the palette changes all the pixels which refer
        to this palette color. Although you can create images in
        <emphasis>Indexed Color</emphasis> mode and can transform images to
        it, it is, strictly speaking, not a
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        See also the
        <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Indexed Palette</link>
        section and the <link
        linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Convert Image to Indexed
        Colors</link> command.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Das Prinzip der indizierten Farben ist, jedem Pixel eine
        Farbnummer (8 Bit) zu geben und dann in einer Tabelle die zu
        dieser Nummer gehörige Farbe zu hinterlegen. Obwohl in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        Bilder im Modus <quote>Indizierte Farben</quote> angelegt
        und in diesen umgewandelt werden können, ist dies im eigentlichen
        Sinn kein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Farbmodell</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Weitere Informationen finden Sie in
       <xref linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog" />.
      </para>

      <para  lang="fr">
        Le mode Couleurs indexées est une façon d'encoder les couleurs d'une
        image, où à chaque pixel de l'image est assigné un nombre codé sur
        8 bits. La couleur correspondant à ce nombre est alors déposée dans
        une table (la palette). Le fait de modifier une couleur de la
        palette changera tous les pixels se référant à cette couleur de la
        palette. Bien que vous puissiez créer des images dans ce mode et
        transformer des images en ce mode, il ne s'agit pas véritablement
        d'un <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Modèle de couleur</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Voyez aussi
        <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Palette indexée</link>
        et <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Convertir une image en
          couleurs indexées</link>.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        Når du bruker indekserte farger, blir det laga ein tabell over alle
        fargane i biletet. Denne tabellen kan ha opp til 256 ulike fargar.
        Kvar piksel i biletet får eit fargenummer som viser til ein farge i
        denne tabellen. Sjølv om <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har plassert dette
        valet under Modus, er <emphasis>Indekserte fargar</emphasis> eigentleg
        ikkje ein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Fargemodus</link>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-interpolation" lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="cs">Interpolace</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="en;de;fr">Interpolation</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="it">Interpolazione</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="es">Interpolación</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="ko">보간(Interpolation)</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="no">Interpolasjon</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Interpolation(插值)</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Při zvětšení obrázku se jeho jednotlivé pixely od sebe vzdálí a
        vzniklé mezery je nutné vyplnit. Chybějící pixely v mezerách jsou
        dopočítány z pixelů v okolí, metodou zvanou interpolace. Metody
        interpolace jsou v Gimpu označeny podle rychlosti – rychlejší
        interpolace dává horší výsledky, pomalejší interpolace je kvalitnější.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Interpolation means calculating intermediate values. When you
        enlarge (<quote>digitally zoom</quote>) or otherwise transform
        (rotate, shear or give perspective to) a digital image,
        interpolation procedures are used to compute the colors of the
        pixels in the transformed image. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> offers
        three interpolation methods, which differ in quality and speed. In
        general, the better the quality, the more time the interpolation
        takes. The methods are:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist lang="en">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>None</emphasis> (sometimes called <quote>Nearest
            Neighbor</quote>): The color of each pixel is copied from its
            closest neighboring pixel in the original image. This often
            results in aliasing (the <quote>stair-step</quote> effect) and a
            coarse image, but it is the fastest method.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Linear</emphasis> (sometimes called
            <quote>Bilinear</quote>): The color of each pixel is computed as
            the average color of the four closest pixels in the original
            image. This gives a satisfactory result for most images and is a
            good compromise between speed and quality.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Cubic</emphasis> (sometimes called
            <quote>Bicubic</quote>): The color of each pixel is computed as
            the average color of the eight closest pixels in the original
            image. This usually gives the best result, but it naturally takes
            more time.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses interpolation when you
        <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scale</link> an image,
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-scale">Scale</link> a layer, and when you
        <link linkend="gimp-tools-transform">Transform</link> an image. You
        can also set the default interpolation method in the <link
        linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Tools Options Preferences</link>
        dialog.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        In der Bildverarbeitung verwendet man Interpolationsverfahren, um
        gerasterte Bilder zu vergrößern (<quote>digitaler Zoom</quote>).
        Da diese Bilder
        aber nur eine begrenzte Bildauflösung haben, führt die Wiederholung
        von Bildpunkten zu dem bekannten <quote>Treppchen-Effekt</quote>.
        Das Phänomen ist
        allgemein auch als Aliasing bekannt. Interpoliert man stattdessen die
        hinzugefügten Bildpunkte aus den bekannten Nachbarpunkten
        (Antialiasing), so werden die Kanten glatter, was aber zu Lasten der
        Bildschärfe geht. Die optische Auflösung des Bildes wird durch die
        Interpolation nicht vergrößert. (Quelle: <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interpolation">Wikipedia</ulink>)
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bietet verschiedene Interpolationsverfahren,
        welche sich in Qualität und Geschwindigkeit unterscheiden. Dabei
        gilt: je besser die Qualität ist, umso länger dauert die Bearbeitung.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Cuando agrandas una imagen pixeles inexistentes deben ser
        agregados.  Éstos son calculados desde los pixeles previos,
        teniendo en cuenta sus pixeles vecinos, por interpolación.
        Los métodos de interpolación del <acronym>GIMP</acronym> están
        calificados según su velocidad.  Los métodos más rápidos
        realizan transformaciones de peor calidad que los métodos más
        lentos.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        Quand vous agrandissez une image, les pixels s'écartent. Quand vous
        la rétrécissez, des pixels se chevauchent. Le vide créé ou les
        pixels qui se chevauchent  sont remplacés par des pixels calculés à
        partir des pixels environnants, par interpolation.
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vous offre trois méthodes d'interpolation.
        Plus la méthode est lente et meilleur est le résultat:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist lang="fr">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Aucune</emphasis> (parfois appelée <quote>Plus proche
              voisin</quote>): la couleur de chaque pixels est déterminée à
            partir des pixels les plus proches. La méthode est la plus
            rapide, mais peut donner un aspect crénelé et une image
            grossière.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Linéaire</emphasis> (parfois appelée
            <quote>Bilinéaire</quote>): La couleur est calculée à partir des
            quatre pixels voisins. C'est le meilleur compromis entre la
            vitesse et la qualité.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Cubique</emphasis> (parfois appelée
            <quote>Bicubique</quote>): la couleur de chaque pixel est
            calculée à partir des huit pixels voisins. Donne le meilleur
            résultat, en plus de temps.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para lang="it">
        Quando si allarga un'immagine, se la risoluzione dell'immagine non
        è sufficiente, i pixel devono essere <quote>staccati</quote>.
        Questi pixel
        mancanti vengono rimpiazzati da pixel che vengono ricavati, per
        interpolazione, da un calcolo effettuato sui pixel adiacenti. I
        metodi di interpolazione in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sono
        catalogati in base alla loro velocità. I metodi più veloci
        comportano trasformazioni di minore qualità mentre viceversa i
        metodi più lenti hanno una resa di migliore di qualità.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이미지를 크게 할때, 이미지의 해상도가 충분치 않으면 픽셀들이 벌어지게
        된다. 이때 생기는 공간을 주변 픽셀에 근거하여 채우는 것이 보간이다.
        <application>김프</application>에서 보간법은 속도로 표시된다.
        빠른 방법은 낮은 품질의 변환이고, 느린 방법은 높은 품질의 변환이다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Når du forstørrar eit bilete vil biletpunkta bli liggjande eit
        stykke frå kvarandre dersom oppløysinga ikkje strekk til. Sidan vi
        ikkje kan operera med tomme punktområde, må altså desse områda
        fyllast. Måten dette blir gjort på, blir kalla interpolering og er
        rein matematikk. Det finst tre hovudmetodar for interpolering:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist lang="no">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Næraste</emphasis> (<quote>Nearest Neighbour</quote>).
            Kopierer pikslar frå dei næraste pikslane omkring. Gir eit grovt
            resultat, men er likevel som oftast den beste, og raskaste, måten
            for strekgrafikk i svart/kvitt.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Bilinært</emphasis> (<quote>Bilinear</quote>). Reknar ut
            gjennomsnittsverdien til dei 4 næraste pikslane. Gir som oftast eit
            tilfredsstillande resultat for dei fleste bileta.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Bikubisk</emphasis> (<quote>Bicubic</quote>). Reknar ut
            gjennomsnittsverdien til dei 8 næraste pikslane. Gir som oftast det
            beste resultatet, men krev naturleg nok mykje datakraft og tid. (Har
            ikkje noe med bikuber å gjere, men står for dobbelt kubisk).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para lang="no">
        I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er dei tre metodane merka med kor raske
        dei er. Rask interpolering gir dårlegast resultat, medan seine
        metodar gir betre kvalitet.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当您扩大图像而其分辨率不够时，原图像中的像素就会被分散，而那些扩大后
        增加的像素就通过插值根据周围像素计算而得到。
        在 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 中的插值功能上有一个速度标志。如
        果使用的速度比较快，则转变的质量比较差，相反速度慢，则质量会好。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-histogram" lang="it">
    <glossterm lang="it">Istogramma</glossterm>
    
    <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Istogramma</primary></indexterm>
    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="it">
        Nell'elaborazione digitale delle immagini un istogramma è un grafico
        che rappresenta la frequenza statistica dei valori di grigio o dei
        valori dei colori presenti in una immagine. L'istogramma di una
        immagine rivela la presenza dei valori di grigio o di colore come
        pure la gamma di contrasto e la brillantezza di una immagine. In
        una immagine a colori si può creare un'istogramma con le informazioni
        su tutti i colori oppure tre istogrammi per i singoli canali di colore.
        L'ultimo caso è quello più comune poiché la maggior parte delle
        elaborazioni si basa su immagini a scala di grigio e quindi ulteriori
        processamenti sono immediatamente possibili.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
