<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-01-13 ciampix: added it intento di rendering e colori indicizzati
  2007-03-06 ude: merged fr "Incrémentiel ..." to glossary-incremental
  2007-02-06 alessandro falappa: added reference for glossary-imagehose
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-19 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  2005-08-26 de added indexed colors by axel.wernicke
  2005-06-14 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>I</title><anchor id="glossary-i"/>

  <glossentry id="glossary-imagehose">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Image Hose</phrase>
      <!-- cs MARK: see glossterm "Animovaná stopa" -->
      <!-- de MARK: see glossterm "Bilderschlauch" -->
      
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossterm "Brosses GIH" -->
      <!-- it MARK: see glossterm "Pennelli animati" -->
      
      <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Mønsterpensel" -->
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Image Hose</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        An image hose in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a special type of brush
        which consists of several images. For example, you could have a
        brush with footprints, which consists of two images, one for the
        left footprint and one for the right. While painting with this
        brush, a left footprint would appear first, then a right footprint,
        then a left one, etc. This type of brush is very powerful.
      </para>
      <para>
        An image hose is also sometimes called an <quote>image pipe</quote>
        or <quote>animated brush</quote>. An image hose is indicated in the
        Brushes dialog by a small red triangle in the lower right corner of
        the brush's symbol.
      </para>
      <para>
        For information concerning creating an image hose, please see the
        <link linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes">Using Animated
        Brushes</link> and <link linkend="gimp-using-brushes">Using
        Brushes</link> sections.
      </para>
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-incremental">
    <glossterm>
      
      <phrase>Incremental, paint mode</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
      <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Aukande, malemodus" -->
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Incremental</primary></indexterm>
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Incremental mode is a paint mode where each brush stroke is drawn
        directly on the active layer. When it is set, each additional stroke
        of the brush increases the effect of the brush, up to the maximum
        opacity for the brush.
      </para>
      <para>
        If incremental mode is not set, brush strokes are drawn on a canvas
        buffer, which is then combined with the active layer. The maximum
        effect of a brush is then determined by the opacity, and stroking with
        the brush repeatedly does not increase the effect beyond this limit.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
        The two images above were created using a brush with spacing set to
        60 pixels. The image on the left shows non-incremental painting and
        the image on the right shows the difference with incremental painting.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      <para>
        Incremental mode is a tool option that is shared by several brush
        tools, except those which have a <quote>rate</quote> control, which
        automatically implies an incremental effect. You can set it by
        checking the <guilabel moreinfo="none">Incremental</guilabel> checkbox in the
        toolbox for the tool (Paintbrush, Pencil and Eraser).
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-indexedcolors">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Indexed Colors</phrase>
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Indexed Colors</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Color</primary><secondary>Indexed colors</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    

    
    

    
    

    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Indexed color mode is a mode for encoding colors in an image where
        each pixel in the image is assigned an 8-bit color number. The color
        which corresponds to this number is then put in a table (the palette).
        Changing a color in the palette changes all the pixels which refer
        to this palette color. Although you can create images in
        <emphasis>Indexed Color</emphasis> mode and can transform images to
        it, it is, strictly speaking, not a
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        See also the
        <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Indexed Palette</link>
        section and the <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Convert Image to Indexed
        Colors</link> command.
      </para>

      
      

      
      

      
      

      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  

  <glossentry id="glossary-interpolation">
    <glossterm>
      
      <phrase>Interpolation</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      
      <para>
        Interpolation means calculating intermediate values. When you
        enlarge (<quote>digitally zoom</quote>) or otherwise transform
        (rotate, shear or give perspective to) a digital image,
        interpolation procedures are used to compute the colors of the
        pixels in the transformed image. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> offers
        three interpolation methods, which differ in quality and speed. In
        general, the better the quality, the more time the interpolation
        takes. The methods are:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>None</emphasis> (sometimes called <quote>Nearest
            Neighbor</quote>): The color of each pixel is copied from its
            closest neighboring pixel in the original image. This often
            results in aliasing (the <quote>stair-step</quote> effect) and a
            coarse image, but it is the fastest method.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Linear</emphasis> (sometimes called
            <quote>Bilinear</quote>): The color of each pixel is computed as
            the average color of the four closest pixels in the original
            image. This gives a satisfactory result for most images and is a
            good compromise between speed and quality.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Cubic</emphasis> (sometimes called
            <quote>Bicubic</quote>): The color of each pixel is computed as
            the average color of the eight closest pixels in the original
            image. This usually gives the best result, but it naturally takes
            more time.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses interpolation when you
        <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scale</link> an image,
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-scale">Scale</link> a layer, and when you
        <link linkend="gimp-tools-transform">Transform</link> an image. You
        can also set the default interpolation method in the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Tools Options Preferences</link>
        dialog.
      </para>

      
      
      

      
      

      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  
</glossdiv>
