<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<glossdiv>
  <title>I</title>
  <glossentry id='glossary-imagehose'>
      <glossterm>Image Hose</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
        <para>
          Image Hoses are special brushes that contain many different
          frames. An exmaple of this might be a footstep brush that
          contains two images. One of a left footprint and one of a right
          footprint. During the application of this hypothetical hose
          brush, one would see the left footprint followed by that of the
          right in a continuous fashion. This method of animation for
          brushes is very powerful.
        </para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id='glossary-incremental'>
      <glossterm>Incremental, paint mode</glossterm>
      <glossdef>
	<para>
	  This paint mode renders each brush stroke directly onto the
	  active layer. If incremental mode is not set, there is a
	  canvas buffer that is composited with the active layer.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata
		fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
		format='PNG'/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
	  <inlinemediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata
		fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
		format='PNG' />
	    </imageobject>
	  </inlinemediaobject>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The two images above were created using a brush with spacing
	  set to sixty. The image on the left shows non-incremental
	  painting and the image on the right shows the difference that
	  incremental painting can produce. Incremental paint mode
	  results in each brush application, through the duration of a
	  stroke, being rendered in addition to any previous brush
	  renderings.
	</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>

    <glossentry id='glossary-interpolation'>
    <glossterm>Interpolation</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Interpolation is the means by which the pixels of an image are
        rendered to represent changes in an image size or angle.
        Interpolation methods in <application>The GIMP</application>are
        labelled with a speed marker. Faster methods lead to
        lowerquality
        transformations whereas slower methods lead to higher quality
        transformations.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="de">
        Als Interpolation bezeichnet man die Abbildung von Pixeln in
        einem Bild auf die darzustellende Vergrößerung auf
        dem Bildschirm.
        Als Interpolationsverfahren in <application>GIMP</application>
        kann zwischen verschiedenen Geschwindigkeitsmarken gewählt
        werden. Schnelle Verfahren resultieren in einer niedrigeren
        Qualität während langsamere Verfahren einer
        höherqualitativen Darstellung dienen.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
