<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<glossdiv lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title>I</title>
  <glossentry id='glossary-imagehose' lang="en;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="en">Image Hose</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Image Hose(图像管)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Image Hoses are special brushes that contain many different
        frames. An example of this might be a footstep brush that
        contains two images. One of a left footprint and one of a right
        footprint. During the application of this hypothetical hose
        brush, one would see the left footprint followed by that of the
        right in a continuous fashion. This method of animation for
        brushes is very powerful.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        图像管是包含许多不同框架的特殊画笔。包含两个图像的脚印画笔就是一种。一个是左脚印，一个是右脚印。在这种超现实画笔的应用过程中，可能会发现右脚印以连续的方式跟着左脚印。这种画笔的动画方法是很强大的。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id='glossary-incremental' lang="en;de;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="en">Incremental, paint mode</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang='de'>Inkrementeller Malmodus</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Incremental(增值)，涂画模式</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
       This paint mode renders each brush stroke directly onto the
       active layer. If incremental mode is not set, there is a
       canvas buffer that is composited with the active layer.
      </para>
      <para lang='de'>
        Fixme
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
	该涂画模式将每笔直接渲染到活动图层上。如果没有设置增值模式，将会使用一个和活动图层混杂在一起的画布缓冲区。
      </para>
      <para lang="en;zh_CN">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
            format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
            format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The two images above were created using a brush with spacing
        set to sixty. The image on the left shows non-incremental
        painting and the image on the right shows the difference that
        incremental painting can produce. Incremental paint mode
        results in each brush application, through the duration of a
        stroke, being rendered in addition to any previous brush
        renderings.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        上面两个图像用 6 号画笔创建。左边图像没有使用增值进行涂画而右边的则使用。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id='glossary-incremental-fr' lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Incrémentiel (mode de dessin)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans ce mode chaque coup de brosse agit directement dans le calque
        actif. Si ce mode est désactivé, un canevas tampon est créé qui sera
        intégré au calque actif.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
            format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
            fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
            format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les 2 images ci-dessus ont été réalisées avec une brosse dont
        l'espacement était réglé sur 6 sans mode incrémentiel pour celle de
        gauche, avec pour celle de droite. Le mode incrémentiel fait que, 
        pendant toute la durée du tracé, chaque touche de la brosse s'ajoute 
        à la précédente.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id='glossary-interpolation'>
    <glossterm lang="en">Interpolation</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="de">Interpolation</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Interpolation</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Interpolation(插值)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">            <!--changed 040915-->
        When you enlarge an image pixels become apart if image resolution is 
        not enough. These missing pixels are replaced by pixels that are 
        calculated from surrounding pixels, by interpolation.
        Interpolation methods in <application>The GIMP</application> are
        labelled with a speed marker. Faster methods lead to lower quality
        transformations whereas slower methods lead to higher quality
        transformations.
      </para>      
      <para lang="de">
        Als Interpolation bezeichnet man die Abbildung von Pixeln in
        einem Bild auf die darzustellende Vergrößerung auf
        dem Bildschirm.
        Als Interpolationsverfahren in <application>GIMP</application>
        kann zwischen verschiedenen Geschwindigkeitsmarken gewählt
        werden. Schnelle Verfahren resultieren in einer niedrigeren
        Qualität während langsamere Verfahren einer
        höherqualitativen Darstellung dienen.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quand vous agrandissez une image, les pixels s'écartent si la 
        résolution de l'image initiale est insuffisante. Ces pixels 
        manquants seront remplacés par des pixels calculés à partir des 
        pixels environnants, par interpolation. Chaque méthode 
        d'interpolation utilisée par GIMP est marquée d'un indicateur de 
        vitesse. Les méthodes rapides donnent de moins bons résultats que 
        les méthodes lentes.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当您扩大图像而其分辨率不够时，原图像中的像素就会被分散，而那些扩大后增加的像素就通过插值根据周围像素计算而得到。在 <application>GIMP</application> 中的插值功能上有一个速度标志。如果使用的速度比较快，则转变的质量比较差，相反速度慢，则质量会好。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
