<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv
          PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
     050826 de added indexed colors by axel.wernicke
     050614 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
     -->
<glossdiv lang="en;de;fr;no;zh_CN">
  <title>I</title>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-imagehose' lang="en;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="en">Image Hose</glossterm>
    <!-- de see: <glossterm lang="de">Bilderschlauch</glossterm> -->
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Image Hose(图像管)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Image Hoses are special brushes that contain many different
        frames. An example of this might be a footstep brush that
        contains two images. One of a left footprint and one of a right
        footprint. During the application of this hypothetical hose
        brush, one would see the left footprint followed by that of the
        right in a continuous fashion. This method of animation for
        brushes is very powerful.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        图像管是包含许多不同框架的特殊画笔。包含两个图像的脚印画笔就是一种。一个是左脚印，一个是右脚印。在这种超现实画笔的应用过程中，可能会发现右脚印以连续的方式跟着左脚印。这种画笔的动画方法是很强大的。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-incremental' lang="cs;de;en;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang="cs">Inkrementální, režim kreslení</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="en">Incremental, paint mode</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang='de'>Inkrementeller Malmodus</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Incremental(增值)，涂画模式</glossterm>
    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Při použití inkrementálního režimu se každý tah štětcem okamžitě
        projevuje na aktivní vrstvě. Pokud tento režim použit není, je
        používán buffer.
      </para>
      
      <para lang='de'>
        Dieser Malmodus zeichnes jeden Pinselstrich direkt auf die aktive
        Ebene. Wenn der inkrementelle Malmodus nicht aktiviert ist, wird auf
        einer Zeichenfläche gemalt, die dann mit der aktiven Ebene
        zusammengemischt wird.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        This paint mode renders each brush stroke directly onto the
        active layer. If incremental mode is not set, there is a
        canvas buffer that is composited with the active layer.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该涂画模式将每笔直接渲染到活动图层上。如果没有设置增值模式，将会使用一个和活动图层混杂在一起的画布缓冲区。
      </para>
      <para lang="cs;en;de;zh_CN">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
                      format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
                      format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      
      <para lang="cs">
        Oba obrázky výše byly vytvořeny štětcem se stopou o rozestupu 60.
        Vlevo nebyl použit inkrementální režim, vpravo ano. V inkrementálním
        režimu je každý otisk stopy během tahu štětcem přidáván k předchozím.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="de">
        Die beiden Bilder wurden mit einem Pinsel erstellt, dessen
        <quote>Abstand</quote> auf 60 Pixel eingestellt war. Im linken Bild
        war der <emphasis>Inkrementelle Malmodus</emphasis> ausgeschaltet. Das
        rechte Bild zeigt den Unterschied durch den eingeschalteten
        <emphasis>Inkrementellen Malmodus</emphasis>.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        The two images above were created using a brush with spacing
        set to sixty. The image on the left shows non-incremental
        painting and the image on the right shows the difference that
        incremental painting can produce. Incremental paint mode
        results in each brush application, through the duration of a
        stroke, being rendered in addition to any previous brush
        renderings.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        上面两个图像用 6 号画笔创建。左边图像没有使用增值进行涂画而右边的则使用。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-incremental-fr' lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Incrémentiel (mode de dessin)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Dans ce mode chaque coup de brosse agit directement dans le calque
        actif. Si ce mode est désactivé, un canevas tampon est créé qui sera
        intégré au calque actif.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png'
                      format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                      fileref='../images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png'
                      format='PNG' />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les 2 images ci-dessus ont été réalisées avec une brosse dont
        l'espacement était réglé sur 6 sans mode incrémentiel pour celle de
        gauche, avec pour celle de droite. Le mode incrémentiel fait que,
        pendant toute la durée du tracé, chaque touche de la brosse s'ajoute
        à la précédente.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="glossary-indexedcolors" lang="de;no">
    <glossterm lang="de">Indizierte Farben</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="no">Indekserte fargar</glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="de">
      <para>
        Das Prinzip der indizierten Farben ist, jedem Pixel eine
        Farbnummer (8 Bit) zu geben, und dann in einer Tabell die zu
        dieser Nummer gehörige Farbe zu hinterlegen. Obwohl in GIMP
        Bilder im Modus <emphasis>Indizierte Farben</emphasis> angelegt
        und in diesen umgewandelt werden können ist dies im eigentlichen
        Sinn kein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Farbmodell</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Weitere Informationen finden Sie im Abschnitt
        Farbtabelle.
        <!-- de PENDING: <link linkend='gimp-indexed-palette-dialog'>Farbtabelle</link>. -->
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        Når du bruker indekserte farger, blir det laga ein tabell over alle
        fargane i biletet. Denne tabellen kan ha opp til 256 ulike fargar.
        Kvar piksel i biletet får eit fargenummer som viser til ein farge i
        denne tabellen. Sjølv om <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har plassert dette
        valet under Modus, er <emphasis>Indekserte fargar</emphasis> eigentleg
        ikkje ein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel-no">Fargemodus</link>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-interpolation'>
    <glossterm lang="cs">Interpolace</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="en;de;fr">Interpolation</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="no">Interpolasjon</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Interpolation(插值)</glossterm>
    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Při zvětšení obrázku se jeho jednotlivé pixely od sebe vzdálí a
        vzniklé mezery je nutné vyplnit. Chybějící pixely v mezerách jsou
        dopočítány z pixelů v okolí, metodou zvanou interpolace. Metody
        interpolace jsou v Gimpu označeny podle rychlosti – rychlejší
        interpolace dává horší výsledky, pomalejší interpolace je kvalitnější.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">            <!--changed 040915-->
        When you enlarge an image pixels become apart if image resolution is
        not enough. These missing pixels are replaced by pixels that are
        calculated from surrounding pixels, by interpolation.
        Interpolation methods in <application>The GIMP</application> are
        labelled with a speed marker. Faster methods lead to lower quality
        transformations whereas slower methods lead to higher quality
        transformations.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        In der Bildverarbeitung verwendet man Interpolationsverfahren, um
        gerasterte Bilder zu vergrößern ("digitaler Zoom"). Da diese Bilder
        aber nur eine begrenzte Bildauflösung haben, führt die Wiederholung
        von Bildpunkten zu dem bekannten "Treppchen-Effekt". Das Phänomen ist
        allgemein auch als Aliasing bekannt. Interpoliert man stattdessen die
        hinzugefügten Bildpunkte aus den bekannten Nachbarpunkten
        (Antialiasing), so werden die Kanten glatter, was aber zu Lasten der
        Bildschärfe geht. Die optische Auflösung des Bildes wird durch die
        Interpolation nicht vergrößert. (Quelle: <ulink
        url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interpolation">Wikipedia</ulink>)
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bietet verschiedene Interpolationsverfahren,
        welche sich in Qualität und Geschwindigkeit unterscheiden. Dabei gilt
        je besser die Qualität ist, umso länger dauert die Bearbeitung.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quand vous agrandissez une image, les pixels s'écartent si la
        résolution de l'image initiale est insuffisante. Ces pixels
        manquants seront remplacés par des pixels calculés à partir des
        pixels environnants, par interpolation. Chaque méthode
        d'interpolation utilisée par GIMP est marquée d'un indicateur de
        vitesse. Les méthodes rapides donnent de moins bons résultats que
        les méthodes lentes.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Når du forstørrar eit bilete vil biletpunkta bli liggjande eit
        stykke frå kvarandre dersom oppløysinga ikkje strekk til. Sidan vi
        ikkje kan operera med tomme punktområde, må altså desse områda
        fyllast. Måten dette blir gjort på, blir kalla interpolering og er
        rein matematikk. Det finst tre hovudmetodar for interpolering:
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        1. <emphasis>Næraste</emphasis> (<quote>Nearest Neighbour</quote>).
        Kopierer pikslar frå dei næraste pikslane omkring. Gir eit grovt
        resultat, men er likevel som oftast den beste, og raskaste, måten
        for strekgrafikk i svart/kvitt.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        2. <emphasis>Bilinært</emphasis> (<quote>Bilinear</quote>). Reknar ut
        gjennomsnittsverdien til dei 4 næraste pikslane. Gir som oftast eit
        tilfredsstillande resultat for dei fleste bileta.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        2. <emphasis>Bikubisk</emphasis> (<quote>Bicubic</quote>). Reknar ut
        gjennomsnittsverdien til dei 8 næraste pikslane. Gir som oftast det
        beste resultatet, men krev naturleg nok mykje datakraft og tid. (Har
        ikkje noe med bikuber å gjere, men står for dobbelt kubisk).
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        I <acronym>GIMP</acronym> er dei tre metodane merka med kor raske
        dei er. Rask interpolering gir dårlegast resultat, medan seine
        metodar gir betre kvalitet.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当您扩大图像而其分辨率不够时，原图像中的像素就会被分散，而那些扩大后增加的像素就通过插值根据周围像素计算而得到。在 <application>GIMP</application> 中的插值功能上有一个速度标志。如果使用的速度比较快，则转变的质量比较差，相反速度慢，则质量会好。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
