<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-06-24 kost: rewritten 'no'
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-19 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-02-25 romanofski fixed broken image references
  050614 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title>J</title><anchor id="glossary-j" />

  <glossentry id="glossary-jpeg">
    <glossterm>JPEG</glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>JPEG</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        JPEG is a <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        which supports compression and works at all color depths. The
        image compression is adjustable, but beware: Too high a compression
        could severely reduce image quality, since JPEG compression is lossy.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Use JPEG to create web graphics or if you don't want your
        image to take up a lot of space. JPEG is a good format for
        photographs and for computer-generated images (CGI). It is not well
        suited for:
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        Tento formát podporuje ztrátovou kompresi a je vhodný pro obrázky
        v pravých barvách.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Das Dateiformat JPEG basiert auf der gleichnamigen Kompression. Die
        JPEG-Kompression ist für natürliche (Raster-)Bilder entwickelt worden.
        Das sind Bilder, wie man sie in der Fotographie oder bei
        computergenerierten Bilder (CGI) vorfindet. Ungeeignet ist JPEG für
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        JPEG er eit <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">filformat</link> med
        god støtte for brukarstyrt komprimering. Dessutan verkar det med alle 
        fargedjupner. Komprimeringa fører til tap av data, så ver litt forsiktig
        med sterk komprimering utan å ha reservekopi.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        JPEG blir helst brukt på nettbilete og andre stader når du har behov for 
        å lagra bilete utan å bruke mykje lagerplass. Formater fungerer svært
        godt for foto og andre digitale bilete. Det er derimot lite eigna for
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist lang="en;de;no">
        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            digitale Strichzeichnungen (z. B. Screenshots oder
            Vektorgrafiken), in denen es viele benachbarte Bildpunkte mit
            exakt identischen Farbwerten, wenige Farben und harte Kanten gibt;
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            digital line drawings (for example, screenshots or vector
            graphics), in which there are many neighboring pixels with the
            same color values, few colors and hard edges,
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            digitalt teikna linjer som for eksempel skjermdump eller
            vektorgrafikk der det er mange nærliggande pikslar med same
            fargeverdiane, få fargar og harde kantar.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">
            Schwarzweißbilder (nur Schwarz und Weiß, 1 bit pro Bildpunkt);
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Black and white images (only black and white, one bit per pixel)
            or
          </para>
          <para lang="no">
            bilete i bare svart og kvit, med ein bits per piksel
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang="de">gerasterte Bilder (Zeitungsdruck).</para>
          <para lang="en">half-toned images (newsprint).</para>
          <para lang="no">halvtonebilete. (Avistrykk).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para lang="en">
        Other formats, such as GIF, PNG or JBIG, are far better for these
        kinds of images.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In general, JPEG transformations are not reversible. Opening and
        then saving a JPEG file causes a new, lossy compression. Increasing
        the quality factor later will not bring back the image information
        which was lost.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        Für diese Bilder sind Formate wie GIF, PNG oder JBIG weitaus besser
        geeignet.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Eine JPEG-Transformation ist im Allgemeinen nicht reversibel. Das
        Öffnen und anschließende Speichern einer JPEG-Datei führt zu einer
        neuen verlustbehafteten Kompression. Ein nachträgliches Heraufsetzen
        des Qualitätsfaktors vergrößert zwar den Speicherbedarf der Bilddatei,
        bringt aber verlorene Bildinformation nicht mehr zurück 
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-jpeg" />.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        For denne typen bilete høver GIF, PNG og JBIG betre.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        I praksis er JPEG-omforming ikkje reversibel. Opnar du eit bilete i
        JPEG-format og deretter lagrar det med komprimering, vil det ikkje
        vere råd å få tilbake tapte data sjølv om du lagrar det på nytt med
        betre kvalitet på komprimeringa.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="es">
        Este formato tiene compresión y trabaja con todas las profundidades de
        color. La compresión de la imagen es ajustable, pero cuidado:
        demasiada compresión reduce severamente la calidad de la imagen, ya
        que la compresión JPEG realiza una pérdida de calidad. Utiliza JPEG
        para crear gráficos para la web en Color Verdadero, o si no quieres
        que tu imagen ocupe demasiado espacio. Es un buen formato para
        fotografías.
      </para>

      <para lang="fr">
        C'est un format de compression des images acceptant toutes les
        «profondeurs de couleurs». Le taux de compression est ajustable, mais,
        attention, une compression trop forte risque d'altérer sévèrement la
        qualité de l'image, car la compression JPEG n'est pas
        <quote>sans perte</quote>.
        Utilisez JPEG pour créer des images Web en Couleurs Vraies, ou si vous
        voulez économiser le poids de l'image. JPEG est un bon format pour les
        photographies.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        Questo formato supporta la compressione e lavora con tutte le
        profondità di colore. La compressione immagine è regolabile, ma
        attenzione: troppa compressione porta a ridurre drasticamente la
        qualità dell'immagine, dato che il tipo di compressione è
        <quote>con perdita</quote> (in inglese <quote>lossy</quote>). Usare
        il formato JPEG per creare
        grafica WEB in TrueColor oppure se semplicemente non si vuole occupare
        troppo spazio su disco. JPEG è in generale un buon formato per le
        fotografie.
      </para>

      <para lang="ko">
        이 포맷은 모든 비트의 색상에서 사용가능하며 압축을 지원한다.
        이미지 압축률은 조정가능하지만, JPEG 압축은 손실률이 크기 때문에
        너무 높은 비율의 압축은 이미지의 질저하를 가져올 수 있으므로
        조심해야 한다. JPEG 을 이용해 트루컬러의 웹 이미지를 만들거나
        단순히 이미지 용량을 줄이는데 사용할 수 있다. 또 JPEG 은 사진을
        다루는데 좋은 포맷이다.
      </para>

      <para lang="zh_CN">
        该文件格式支持压缩和全部颜色深度。色彩压缩是可以调节的，不过要注意：
        由于 JPEG 压缩是有损压缩，一个太高的压缩率会导致图形质量变差。JPEG
        被用作创建真彩色网页图形或节约图像所占空间，同时它也是数码照相时保存
        的格式。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
