<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<glossdiv>
  <title>J</title>
  <glossentry id='file-jpeg-save'>
    <glossterm>JPEG</glossterm>
    <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" />
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        This format supports compression and works at all color
        depths. The image compression is adjustable, but beware: Too
        high a compression could severely reduce image quality, since
        JPEG compression is lossy. Use JPEG to create TrueColor Web
        graphics, or if you don't want your image to take up a lot of
        space. JPEG is a good format for photographs. 
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg.  It
        is a very widely used format, because it compresses images very
        efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality.  No
        other format comes close to achieving the same level of
        compression.  It does not, however, support transparency, or
        multiple layers.  For this reason, saving images as JPEG often
        requires them to be exported.
      </para>
      <informalfigure pgwide="0">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/jpeg-save-dialog-en.png' format='png'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>The JPEG Save dialog</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
        When you save a file in JPEG format, you get a dialog that
        allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 1 to
        100.  Values above 95 are generally not useful, though.  The
        default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, butin
        many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
        lower without noticably degrading the image.  You can test the 
        effect of different quality settings by
        checking "Show Preview in image window" in the JPEG dialog.
        Checking this causes each change in quality (or any other JPEG
        parameter) to be visualized in the image display.  (This does
        not alter the image, though: it reverts back to its original
        state when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
      </para>
      <para>
        The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering
        number of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this
        documentation.  Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality
        parameter is probably the only one you will benefit from
        adjusting. 
      </para>
      <caution lang="en">
        After you save an image as a JPEG file, the image will nolonger
        be considered "dirty" by Gimp, so unless you make further
        changes to it, you will not receive any warning if you close
        it.  Because JPEG is lossy and does not support transparency or
        multiple layers, some of the information in the image mightthen
        be lost.  If you want to save all of the information in an
        image, use Gimp's native <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF
        format</link>.
      </caution>
      <para>
        JPEG files from many digital cameras contain extra information
        called EXIF data, specifying camera settings and other
        information concerning the circumstances under which the image
        was created.  Gimp's ability to handle EXIF data depends on
        whether the library "libexif" is available on your system; itis
        not automatically packaged with Gimp.  If Gimp has been built
        with libexif support, then EXIF data is preserved if you openan
        JPEG file, work with the resulting image, and then save as
        JPEG.  The EXIF data is not altered in any way when you do this
        (which means that certain fields within it are no longer
        valid).  If Gimp is not built with EXIF support, this does not
        prevent files with EXIF data from being opened, but it means
        that the EXIF data will not be present when the resulting image
        is later saved.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
