<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<glossdiv lang="en;de;fr;zh_CN">
  <title>J</title>

  <glossentry id='file-jpeg-save'>
    <glossterm>
      JPEG
      <anchor id="file-jpeg-load" />
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        This format supports compression and works at all color
        depths. The image compression is adjustable, but beware: Too
        high a compression could severely reduce image quality, since
        JPEG compression is lossy. Use JPEG to create TrueColor Web
        graphics, or if you don't want your image to take up a lot of
        space. JPEG is a good format for photographs. 
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg.  It
        is a very widely used format, because it compresses images very
        efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality.  No
        other format comes close to achieving the same level of
        compression.  It does not, however, support transparency, or
        multiple layers.  For this reason, saving images as JPEG often
        requires them to be exported.
      </para>

      <informalfigure pgwide="0">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/jpeg-save-dialog-en.png' format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>

          <caption>
            <para>The JPEG Save dialog</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
        When you save a file in JPEG format, you get a dialog that
        allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 1 to
        100.  Values above 95 are generally not useful, though.  The
        default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, but in
        many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
        lower without noticably degrading the image.  You can test the 
        effect of different quality settings by
        checking "Show Preview in image window" in the JPEG dialog.
        Checking this causes each change in quality (or any other JPEG
        parameter) to be visualized in the image display.  (This does
        not alter the image, though: it reverts back to its original
        state when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
      </para>
      <para>
        The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering
        number of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this
        documentation.  Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality
        parameter is probably the only one you will benefit from
        adjusting. 
      </para>
      <para>
        <caution lang="en">
          <para> 
            After you save an image as a JPEG file, the image will no
            longer be considered "dirty" by Gimp, so unless you make
            further changes to it, you will not receive any warning if you
            close it.  Because JPEG is lossy and does not support
            transparency or multiple layers, some of the information in
            the image mightthen be lost.  If you want to save all of the
            information in an image, use Gimp&apos;s native <link
            linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF format</link>.
          </para>
        </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG files from many digital cameras contain extra information
        called EXIF data, specifying camera settings and other
        information concerning the circumstances under which the image
        was created.  Gimp's ability to handle EXIF data depends on
        whether the library "libexif" is available on your system; it is
        not automatically packaged with Gimp.  If Gimp has been built
        with libexif support, then EXIF data is preserved if you open an
        JPEG file, work with the resulting image, and then save as
        JPEG.  The EXIF data is not altered in any way when you do this
        (which means that certain fields within it are no longer
        valid).  If Gimp is not built with EXIF support, this does not
        prevent files with EXIF data from being opened, but it means
        that the EXIF data will not be present when the resulting image
        is later saved.
      </para>
      <para><note>
        <para>Some information about the advanced settings:</para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>DCT Method</title>
          <para> 
            DCT is "discrete cosine transform", and is the first
            step in the JPEG algorithm going from spatial to frequency
            domain.  The choices are "float", "integer" (the default),
            and "fast integer".  The float method is very slightly more
            accurate than the int method, but is much slower unless your
            machine has very fast floating-point hardware. Also note
            that results of the floating-point method may vary slightly
            across machines, while the integer methods should give the
            same results everywhere. The fast integer method is much
            less accurate than the other two.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </note></para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang='de'>
      <para>
        Das JPEG Format benutzt eine spezielle Art von Bildkompression
        welches es geradezu ideal für das Internet macht. Es unterstützt
        zahlreiche Farbmodi, jedoch keinen indizierten Farbmodus, da das
        Format keine Farbtabelle speichern kann.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        C'est un format de compression des images acceptant toutes 
        les «profondeurs de couleurs». Le taux de compression est ajustable, 
        mais, attention, une compression trop forte risque d'altérer 
        sévèrement la qualité de l'image, car la compression JPEG n'est pas 
        «sans perte». Utilisez JPEG pour créer des images Web en Couleurs 
        Vraies, ou si vous voulez économiser le poids de l'image. JPEG est 
        un bon format pour les photographies.
      </para>
      <para>
        Les fichiers JPEG peuvent avoir l'extension .jpg, .JPG ou .jpeg.
        C'est un format très répandu, car il comprime très efficacement 
        les images avec une perte de détails réduite au minimum. Toutefois, 
        il n'accepte pas la transparence ni les calques multiples. C'est 
        pourquoi l'enregistrement en JPEG d'une image nécessite souvent de 
        l'«exporter» au préalable.
      </para>

      <informalfigure pgwide="0">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fr/jpeg-save-dialog-fr.png' format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>

          <caption>
            <para>La fenêtre de dialogue Enregistrer en JPEG</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
        Quand vous sauvegardez au format JPEG, une fenêtre de dialogue 
        s'ouvre, qui vous permet de régler le niveau de Qualité (de 1 à 100).
        Néanmoins, un niveau supérieur à 95 est rarement nécessaire. Un 
        niveau de 85 donne habituellement d'excellents résultats, mais il 
        est souvent possible de baisser ce niveau sans dégrader l'image de 
        manière sensible. Vous pouvez tester l'effet des différents réglages 
        en cochant la case <emphasis>Montrer l'aperçu dans la fenêtre 
        d'image</emphasis>: l'image n'est pour autant pas modifiée et 
        revient à son état d'origine si vous quittez le dialogue JPEG.
      </para>
      <para>
        L'algorithme de compression JPEG est très complexe et comporte un 
        nombre déconcertant d'options, au delà du champ de cette 
        documentation. A moins que vous ne soyez un spécialiste du JPEG, le 
        paramètre Qualité est probablement le seul dont vous aurez à vous 
        soucier.
      </para>
      <caution>
        <para>
        Si vous voulez conserver tous les paramètres de votre image (les 
        calques, la transparence...), utilisez le format natif de GIMP 
        <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>.
        </para>
      </caution>
      <para>
        Les fichiers JPEG de nombreux appareils photo numériques contiennent 
        des méta-informations (informations additionnelles) appelées données 
        EXIF, qui spécifient les paramètres de l'appareil et diverses 
        conditions de prise de vue. GIMP pourra gérer ces données EXIF si la 
        librairie «libexif» est présente sur votre système (elle n'est pas 
        automatiquement livrée avec GIMP). Si GIMP possède cette librairie, 
        les données EXIF seront préservées quand vous ouvrez une image JPEG 
        et que vous travaillez dessus et elles seront enregistrées avec 
        l'image résultante. Elles seront perdues si GIMP ne possède pas 
        cette librairie.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        该文件格式支持压缩和全部颜色深度。色彩压缩是可以调节的，不过要注意：由于 JPEG 压缩是有损压缩，一个太高的压缩率会导致图形质量变差。JPEG 被用作创建真彩色网页图形或节约图像所占空间，同时它也是数码照相时保存的格式。
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG 文件扩展名一般为.jpg，.JPG 或.jpeg。它使用非常广泛因为它压缩图像非常有效，并且最小化图像质量损失。没有其它格式能够达到一样的压缩程度。不过它不支持透明或多图层，这就意味着，图像常常需要导出后才能保存为 JPEG 格式。
      </para>
      <informalfigure pgwide="0">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/jpeg-save-dialog-en.png' format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para>JPEG 保存对话框</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
        当您保存一个文件为 JPEG 格式时，会出现一个允许输入1到100的质量等级的对话框。默认85常常产生最完美的效果，不过一些情况下，大幅度降低质量值也不会明显降低图像质量，而95以上的值常被认为是没用的。您可以勾选 JPEG 对话框中的“Preview in image window”来测试不同的效果，它使任何对质量(或其它任何 JPEG 参数)的更改立即在图像显示上反映出来。(它不会改变图像内容：当 JPEG 对话框关闭时，图像将回到原来的状态。)
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG 算法相当复杂，有一系列让人迷惑的选项，这些已经不在该文档讨论范围内。除非您是个 JPEG 专家，不然也许调节质量参数是唯一能让您受益的参数。
      </para>
      <para>
      <caution>
        <para>
        在保存一个图像为 JPEG 文件后，GIMP 不再认为图像是“脏”的了，因此您关闭它时不会有任何提示信息。由于 JPEG 是有损的而且不支持透明或多图层，可能图像中有些信息就在丢失。要保存图像中所有信息就需要使用 GIMP 内建的 <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF 格式</link>。
        </para>
      </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        从许多数码相机中保存的 JPEG 文件包含相机设置和图像创建的细节的附加信息，叫做 EXIF 数据。GIMP 处理 EXIF 数据的能力依赖“libexif”这个函数库，它需要单独安装。如果 GIMP 被编译为支持 libexif，则在您打开 JPEG 文件，处理最终图像和另存为 JPEG 时 EXIF 数据都被保留。EXIF 数据在您做这些事时不会有任何改变(也就是说它的一定地方不再有效)。如果编译 GIMP 时没加入 EXIF 支持，虽然并不影响带 EXIF 数据的文件被打开，但是当最终图像被另存时 EXIF 数据就没有了。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
