<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<!-- 2006-02-25 romanofski fixed broken image references -->
<!-- 050614 de reviewed by axel.wernicke -->
<glossdiv lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;no;zh_CN">
  <title>J</title>

  <glossentry id='file-jpeg-save'>
    <glossterm>JPEG<anchor id="file-jpeg-load" /></glossterm>
    
    <glossdef lang="cs">
      <para>
        Tento formát podporuje ztrátovou kompresi a je vhodný pro obrázky
        v pravých barvách.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        This format supports compression and works at all color
        depths. The image compression is adjustable, but beware: Too
        high a compression could severely reduce image quality, since
        JPEG compression is lossy. Use JPEG to create TrueColor Web
        graphics, or if you don't want your image to take up a lot of
        space. JPEG is a good format for photographs. 
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG files usually have an extension .jpg, .JPG, or .jpeg.  It
        is a very widely used format, because it compresses images very
        efficiently, while minimizing the loss of image quality.  No
        other format comes close to achieving the same level of
        compression.  It does not, however, support transparency, or
        multiple layers.  For this reason, saving images as JPEG often
        requires them to be exported.
      </para>

      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="en">The JPEG Save dialog</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/jpeg-save-dialog.png'
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        When you save a file in JPEG format, you get a dialog that
        allows you to set the Quality level, which ranges from 1 to
        100.  Values above 95 are generally not useful, though.  The
        default quality of 85 usually produces excellent results, but in
        many cases it is possible to set the quality substantially
        lower without noticably degrading the image.  You can test the 
        effect of different quality settings by
        checking "Show Preview in image window" in the JPEG dialog.
        Checking this causes each change in quality (or any other JPEG
        parameter) to be visualized in the image display.  (This does
        not alter the image, though: it reverts back to its original
        state when the JPEG dialog is closed.)
      </para>
      <para>
        The JPEG algorithm is quite complex, and involves a bewildering
        number of options, whose meaning is beyond the scope of this
        documentation.  Unless you are a JPEG expert, the Quality
        parameter is probably the only one you will benefit from
        adjusting. 
      </para>
      <para>
        <caution lang="en">
          <para> 
            After you save an image as a JPEG file, the image will no
            longer be considered "dirty" by Gimp, so unless you make
            further changes to it, you will not receive any warning if you
            close it.  Because JPEG is lossy and does not support
            transparency or multiple layers, some of the information in
            the image mightthen be lost.  If you want to save all of the
            information in an image, use Gimp&apos;s native <link
            linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF format</link>.
          </para>
        </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG files from many digital cameras contain extra information
        called EXIF data, specifying camera settings and other
        information concerning the circumstances under which the image
        was created.  Gimp's ability to handle EXIF data depends on
        whether the library "libexif" is available on your system; it is
        not automatically packaged with Gimp.  If Gimp has been built
        with libexif support, then EXIF data is preserved if you open an
        JPEG file, work with the resulting image, and then save as
        JPEG.  The EXIF data is not altered in any way when you do this
        (which means that certain fields within it are no longer
        valid).  If Gimp is not built with EXIF support, this does not
        prevent files with EXIF data from being opened, but it means
        that the EXIF data will not be present when the resulting image
        is later saved.
      </para>
      <para><note>
        <para>Some information about the advanced settings:</para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>DCT Method</title>
          <para> 
            DCT is "discrete cosine transform", and is the first
            step in the JPEG algorithm going from spatial to frequency
            domain.  The choices are "float", "integer" (the default),
            and "fast integer".  The float method is very slightly more
            accurate than the int method, but is much slower unless your
            machine has very fast floating-point hardware. Also note
            that results of the floating-point method may vary slightly
            across machines, while the integer methods should give the
            same results everywhere. The fast integer method is much
            less accurate than the other two.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </note></para>
    </glossdef>
    
    <glossdef lang='de'>
      <para>
        Das Dateiformat JPEG basiert auf der gleichnamigen Kompression.
        Die JPEG-Kompression ist für natürliche (Raster-)Bilder entwickelt
        worden. Das sind Bilder, wie man sie in der Fotographie oder bei
        computergenerierten Bilder (CGI) vorfindet. Ungeeignet ist JPEG für
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              digitale Strichzeichnungen (z. B. Screenshots oder
              Vektorgraphiken), in denen es viele benachbarte Bildpunkte mit
              exakt identischen Farbwerten, wenige Farben und harte Kanten
              gibt.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Schwarzweißbilder (nur Schwarz und Weiß, 1 bit pro Bildpunkt).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              gerasterte Bilder (Zeitungsdruck)
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Für diese Bilder sind Formate wie GIF, PNG oder JBIG weitaus besser
        geeignet.
      </para>
      <para>
        Eine JPEG-Transformation ist im Allgemeinen nicht reversibel. Das
        Öffnen und anschließende Speichern einer JPEG-Datei führt zu einer
        neuen verlustbehafteten Kompression. Ein nachträgliches Heraufsetzen
        des Qualitätsfaktors vergrößert zwar den Speicherbedarf der Bilddatei,
        bringt aber verlorene Bildinformation nicht mehr zurück. (Quelle: 
        <ulink url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPEG">Wikipedia</ulink>)
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        Este formato tiene compresión y trabaja con todas las
        profundidades de color.  La compresión de la imagen es
        ajustable, pero cuidado: demasiada compresión reduce
        severamente la calidad de la imagen, ya que la compresión JPEG
        realiza una pérdida de calidad.  Utiliza JPEG para crear
        gráficos para la web en Color Verdadero, o si no quieres que
        tu imagen ocupe demasiado espacio.  Es un buen formato para
        fotografías.
      </para>
      <para>
        Los archivos JPEG usualmente tienen la extensión .jpg, .JPG, o
        .jpeg.  Es un formato ampliamente utilizado, porque comprime
        imágenes muy eficientemente, minimizando la pérdida de
        calidad.  Ningún otro formato se le acerca a lograr el mismo
        nivel de compresión.  No obstante, no soporta transparencia,
        ni múltiples cuadros.  Por esta razón, guardar imágenes en
        este formato normalmente implica exportarlas desde otro.
      </para>

      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="es">El diálogo de guardar para JPEG</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/jpeg-save-dialog.png'
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Al guardar un archivo en formato JPEG verás un diálogo que te
        permite ajustar el nivel de calidad, que tiene un rango de 1 a
        100.  Valores por sobre 95 no son necesarios generalmente.  La
        calidad por defecto es 85 y usualmente produce excelentes
        resultados, pero en algunos casos es posible colocar la
        calidad sustancialmente baja sin que la imagen se vea
        notablemente afectada.  Puedes probar el resultado de
        diferentes calidades activando la opción "Mostrar vista previa
        en la ventana de la imagen" en el diálogo.  Esto hace que cada
        cambio en cualquier parámetro del diálogo JPEG sea visualizado
        en la imagen en pantalla (esto no altera la imagen, sino que
        vuelve al estado original una vez que el diálogo es cerrado).
      </para>
      <para>
        El algoritmo JPEG es bastante complejo, y en él intervienen un
        gran número de opciones, cuyo significado está más allá del
        objetivo de esta documentación.  A menos que seas un experto
        en JPEG, el parámetro de calidad es probablemente el único que
        te será útil.
      </para>
      <para>
        <caution lang="es">
          <para> 
            Luego de que guardes una imagen como un archivo JPEG, ésta
            ya no será considerada como "modificada" por el
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, así que a menos que realizes
            cambios en la misma, no obtendrás un aviso de precaución
            si la cierras.  Como JPEG tiene pérdida de calidad y no
            admite transparencia ni múltiples cuadros, algo de la
            información de la imagen puede perderse.  Si lo que
            quieres es guardar toda la información de la imagen, usa
            el formato nativo del <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, <!--link
            linkend="gimp-xcf-save"-->XCF<!--/link-->.
          </para>
        </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        Los archivos JPEG que provienen de muchas cámaras digitales
        contienen información extra denominada datos EXIF.  Ésta
        especifica los ajustes de la cámara y otra información
        concerniente a las circunstancias en que la fotografía fue
        tomada.  La habilidad del <acronym>GIMP</acronym> para
        administrar datos EXIF depende de la disponibilidad de una
        biblioteca llamada "libexif" en el sistema.  Esta biblioteca
        no viene empaquetada con el <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Si
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> fue construído con capacidad libexif,
        los datos EXIF son preservados si abres un archivo JPEG,
        trabajas con la imagen y luego la guardas.  Los datos EXIF no
        se alteran de ninguna manera si realizas esto (lo que
        significa que algunos campos de los datos EXIF dejarán de ser
        válidos).  Si el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> no es construído con
        capacidad libexif, todavía puedes abrir imágenes con estos
        datos, pero los mismos no estarán presentes si la imagen
        abierta es luego guardada.
      </para>
      <para><note>
        <para>Algo de información sobre las opciones avanzadas:</para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Método DCT</title>
          <para> 
            DCT es "transformada discreta del coseno" y es el primer
            paso que realiza el algoritmo JPEG para ir del dominio
            espacial al de frecuencias.  Las opciones son "coma
            flotante", "entero" (por defecto), y "entero rápido".  El
            método de coma flotante es mucho más preciso que el método
            entero, pero a la vez es mucho más lento a menos que tu
            computadora tenga hardware que trabaje rápido con estos
            números.  Además nota que los resultados del método de
            coma flotante pueden variar un poco de una computadora a
            otra, mientras que los métodos de enteros deberían dar el
            mismo resultado siempre.  El método de entero rápido es
            mucho menos preciso que los otros dos.
          </para>
        </formalpara>
      </note></para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        C'est un format de compression des images acceptant toutes 
        les «profondeurs de couleurs». Le taux de compression est ajustable, 
        mais, attention, une compression trop forte risque d'altérer 
        sévèrement la qualité de l'image, car la compression JPEG n'est pas 
        «sans perte». Utilisez JPEG pour créer des images Web en Couleurs 
        Vraies, ou si vous voulez économiser le poids de l'image. JPEG est 
        un bon format pour les photographies.
      </para>
      <para>
        Les fichiers JPEG peuvent avoir l'extension .jpg, .JPG ou .jpeg.
        C'est un format très répandu, car il comprime très efficacement 
        les images avec une perte de détails réduite au minimum. Toutefois, 
        il n'accepte pas la transparence ni les calques multiples. C'est 
        pourquoi l'enregistrement en JPEG d'une image nécessite souvent de 
        l'«exporter» au préalable.
      </para>

      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="fr">
            La fenêtre de dialogue Enregistrer en JPEG
          </phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/fr/jpeg-save-dialog-fr.png'
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Quand vous sauvegardez au format JPEG, une fenêtre de dialogue 
        s'ouvre, qui vous permet de régler le niveau de Qualité (de 1 à 100).
        Néanmoins, un niveau supérieur à 95 est rarement nécessaire. Un 
        niveau de 85 donne habituellement d'excellents résultats, mais il 
        est souvent possible de baisser ce niveau sans dégrader l'image de 
        manière sensible. Vous pouvez tester l'effet des différents réglages 
        en cochant la case <emphasis>Montrer l'aperçu dans la fenêtre 
        d'image</emphasis>: l'image n'est pour autant pas modifiée et 
        revient à son état d'origine si vous quittez le dialogue JPEG.
      </para>
      <para>
        L'algorithme de compression JPEG est très complexe et comporte un 
        nombre déconcertant d'options, au delà du champ de cette 
        documentation. A moins que vous ne soyez un spécialiste du JPEG, le 
        paramètre Qualité est probablement le seul dont vous aurez à vous 
        soucier.
      </para>
      <para>
      <caution>
        <para>
        Si vous voulez conserver tous les paramètres de votre image (les 
        calques, la transparence...), utilisez le format natif de GIMP 
        <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>.
        </para>
      </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        Les fichiers JPEG de nombreux appareils photo numériques contiennent 
        des méta-informations (informations additionnelles) appelées données 
        EXIF, qui spécifient les paramètres de l'appareil et diverses 
        conditions de prise de vue. GIMP pourra gérer ces données EXIF si la 
        librairie «libexif» est présente sur votre système (elle n'est pas 
        automatiquement livrée avec GIMP). Si GIMP possède cette librairie, 
        les données EXIF seront préservées quand vous ouvrez une image JPEG 
        et que vous travaillez dessus et elles seront enregistrées avec 
        l'image résultante. Elles seront perdues si GIMP ne possède pas 
        cette librairie.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        Dette er eit mykje brukt formatet fordi det kan ta alle brukte
        fargemengder i tillegg til at formatet kan komprimerast. JPEG blir
        mykje brukt for å laga fullfarge bilete til vising på Internett,
        eller dersom du vil at eit bilete ikkje skal ta op for mykje plass.
        Det er eit godt format for fotografi.
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG-filene har til vanleg endingane .jpg, .JPG eller .jpeg, og er
        mykje brukt fordi metoden som blir nytta for å komprimera filene gir
        eit svært godt resultat utan at det går særleg merkbart ut over
        kvaliteten så lenge komprimeringa er moderat. Det er likevel ingen
        andre format som kjem opp mot JPEG. Ulempen er at formatet ikkje
        støttar transparente bilete, og heller ikkje samansette lag. Difor
        må bilete som skal lagrast som JPEG i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ofte
        eksporterast i staden for å bli lagra direkte.
      </para>
      
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="no">Lagringsdialogen for JPEG</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/no/jpeg-save-dialog.png'
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Når du lagrar eit bilete i JPEG-format, dukkar det opp eit
        dialogvindauge der du kan setje kvalitetsnivået på ein skala frå 1
        til 100, sjølv om verdiane over 95 ikkje er særleg brukbare.
        Normalverdien er 85, men ofte kan du setje verdien mykje lågare utan
        å gjere kvaliteten merkbart dårlegare. Dette kan du kontrollera ved
        å markere for <quote>Førehandsvising i biletvindauget</quote>. Du
        endrar ikkje noe på sjølve biletet før du lagrar det, så metoden er
        trygg.
      </para>
      <para>
        Algoritmen for JPEG er nokså kompleks, men det einaste du eigentleg
        har bruk for, er å justera kvaliteten, og altså kompresjonen. Resten
        er for JPEG-ekspertane.
      </para>
      <para>
        <caution lang="no">
          <para>
            Etter at biletet er lagra som JPEG-fil, vil det bli oppfatta av
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> som <quote>reint</quote>, dvs. at det
            kjem ikkje opp noe åtvaring dersom du lukkar det. Sidan
            JPEG-formatet ikkje lagrar alle opplysningane om biletet, kan
            dette vere ein ulempe. Treng du å lagra alle opplysningane om
            biletet, bør du lagre det først i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt
            eige <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF-format</link>.
          </para>
        </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        Mange digitalkamera nyttar JPEG-formatet med ekstra informasjonar om
        dato, kamerainnstillingar osv. Desse såkalla EXIF-data blir ikkje
        støtta utan vidare av <acronym>GIMP</acronym> i normalinstallasjonen.
        Har du lagt til biblioteket <quote>libexif</quote> i systemet ditt,
        kan <acronym>GIMP</acronym> lasta inn og lagra filer med EXIF-data
        utan å forandra dataane, men kan ikkje gjere seg nytte av dei.
      </para>
      <para><note>
          <para>Litt om dei avanserte innstillingane:</para>
          <formalpara>
            <title>DCT-metoden</title>
            <para>
              DCT står for "discrete cosine transform", og er første steget
              i JPEG-algoritmen. Dette er rein matematikk, og vala du har er
              <quote>Desimaltal</quote>, <quote>Heiltal</quote>
              (normalinnstillinga) og <quote>Raske heiltal</quote>.
              Desimaltala er litt betre enn heiltala, men er merkbart
              seinare dersom maskinen din ikkje er utstyrt meg ein god
              matematikkprosessor.
              Metoden kan også gi eit litt varierande resultat frå maskin til
              maskin. Heiltalmetoden skal gi same resultatet uavhengig av
              maskintype. Dei raske heiltala gir dårlegare resultat enn dei to
              andre metodane.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </note></para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        该文件格式支持压缩和全部颜色深度。色彩压缩是可以调节的，不过要注意：由于 JPEG 压缩是有损压缩，一个太高的压缩率会导致图形质量变差。JPEG 被用作创建真彩色网页图形或节约图像所占空间，同时它也是数码照相时保存的格式。
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG 文件扩展名一般为.jpg，.JPG 或.jpeg。它使用非常广泛因为它压缩图像非常有效，并且最小化图像质量损失。没有其它格式能够达到一样的压缩程度。不过它不支持透明或多图层，这就意味着，图像常常需要导出后才能保存为 JPEG 格式。
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="zh_CN">JPEG 保存对话框</phrase>
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='../images/using/jpeg-save-dialog.png'
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        当您保存一个文件为 JPEG 格式时，会出现一个允许输入1到100的质量等级的对话框。默认85常常产生最完美的效果，不过一些情况下，大幅度降低质量值也不会明显降低图像质量，而95以上的值常被认为是没用的。您可以勾选 JPEG 对话框中的“Preview in image window”来测试不同的效果，它使任何对质量(或其它任何 JPEG 参数)的更改立即在图像显示上反映出来。(它不会改变图像内容：当 JPEG 对话框关闭时，图像将回到原来的状态。)
      </para>
      <para>
        JPEG 算法相当复杂，有一系列让人迷惑的选项，这些已经不在该文档讨论范围内。除非您是个 JPEG 专家，不然也许调节质量参数是唯一能让您受益的参数。
      </para>
      <para>
      <caution>
        <para>
        在保存一个图像为 JPEG 文件后，GIMP 不再认为图像是“脏”的了，因此您关闭它时不会有任何提示信息。由于 JPEG 是有损的而且不支持透明或多图层，可能图像中有些信息就在丢失。要保存图像中所有信息就需要使用 GIMP 内建的 <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF 格式</link>。
        </para>
      </caution>
      </para>
      <para>
        从许多数码相机中保存的 JPEG 文件包含相机设置和图像创建的细节的附加信息，叫做 EXIF 数据。GIMP 处理 EXIF 数据的能力依赖“libexif”这个函数库，它需要单独安装。如果 GIMP 被编译为支持 libexif，则在您打开 JPEG 文件，处理最终图像和另存为 JPEG 时 EXIF 数据都被保留。EXIF 数据在您做这些事时不会有任何改变(也就是说它的一定地方不再有效)。如果编译 GIMP 时没加入 EXIF 支持，虽然并不影响带 EXIF 数据的文件被打开，但是当最终图像被另存时 EXIF 数据就没有了。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
