<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2007-02-06 alessandro falappa: added some italian content
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-05-21 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050826 de added L*a*b colo model by axel.wernicke
  050613 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title><anchor id="glossary-l" />L</title>

  <!-- FIXME fr: enable glossentry below? -->
  <glossentry id="glossary-lab" lang="en;de;it">
    <glossterm lang="en;de;fr;it">L*a*b</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        The Lab color space (also called the L*a*b color space) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        developed in the beginning of the 1930s by the Commission
        Internationale d`Eclairage (CIE). It includes all the colors that
        the human eye can perceive. That contains the colors of the
        RGB and the CMYK color spaces, among others. In Lab, a color is
        indicated by three values: L, a and b. Here, the L stands for the
        luminance component — corresponding to the gray value — and a and b
        represent the red-green and blue-yellow parts of the color,
        respectively.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Lab-Farbraum (auch L*a*b-Farbraum) ist ein Anfang der 30er Jahre
        des 20. Jahrhunderts von der Commission Internationale d`Eclairage
        (CIE) entwickeltes Farbmodell. Es schließt alle Farben ein, die das
        menschliche Auge wahrnehmen kann. Darin enthalten sind unter anderem
        die Farben des RGB- und des CMYK-Farbraumes. In Lab wird eine Farbe
        durch die drei Werte L, a und b angegeben. Hierbei steht das L für
        die Helligkeitskomponente (luminance) - entsprechend dem Grauwert -
        und a und b repräsentieren den rot-grün- beziehungsweise blau-gelb-Anteile der
        Farbe.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le mode de couleurs Lab (aussi appelé espace de couleurs L*a*b) est un
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Modèle de couleurs</link>
        développé au début des années 1930 par la Commission Internationale
        d'Éclairage (CIE). Elle comprend toutes les couleurs que l'œil humain
        peut percevoir, entre autres les espaces RVB et CMJN. Dans ce système,
        les couleurs sont représentées par trois valeurs: L, a et b. Le L
        représente la composante Luminance (correspondant aux valeurs de gris).
        Le a et le b représentent respectivement le rouge-vert et le bleu-jaune
        de la couleur.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Lo spazio di colore Lab (anche denominato spazio di colore L*a*b) è un
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">modello di colore</link>
        sviluppato nei primi anni 30 dalla Commissione Internazionale del
        Colore (CIE dal francese Commission Internationale d`Eclairage).
        Include tutti i colori percepibili dall'occhio umano. Contiene i
        colori degli spazi di colore RGB e CMYK, tra gli altri. Nel Lab un
        colore è definito da tre valori: L, a e b. L sta per la componente
        di luminanza — corrispondente al valore del livello di grigio — mentre
        a e b rappresentano rispettivamente le componenti rosso-verde e
        blu-giallo del colore.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        In contrast to RGB or CMYK, Lab is not dependent upon the
        various input and output devices. For that reason, it is used as an
        exchange format between devices. Lab is also the internal color
        model of PostScript Level II.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Im Gegensatz zum RGB oder CMYK ist Lab nicht von den
        unterschiedlichen Ein- und Ausgabegeräten abhängig. Deshalb benutzt
        man dieses Format als Austauschformat zwischen den Geräten. Lab ist
        auch das interne Farbmodell von PostScript Level II.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        (Quelle: <ulink url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lab-Farbraum">Wikipedia</ulink>)
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Contrairement à RVB et CMJN, Lab ne dépend pas des divers périphériques
        d'entrée et de sortie. C'est pourquoi on l'utilise pour les échanges
        entre les périphériques. Lab est aussi le modèle de couleur interne de
        Postscript Niveau II.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Al contrario dei modelli RGB e CMYK il modello Lab non dipende dai
        vari dispositivi di ingresso e uscita. Per questa caratteristica è
        utilizzato come spazio di transizione per scambi di formato tra
        dispositivi. Il Lab è anche il modello di colore di base del
        linguaggio Postscript Livello 2.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        (Approfondimenti:
        <ulink url="http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spazio_dei_colori">Wikipedia
        </ulink>)
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-antialiasing-fr" lang="fr">
    <glossterm lang="fr">Lissage</glossterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Lissage</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Anti-crénelage</primary></indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Aussi appelé <quote>Anti-crénelage</quote>.
        Méthode permettant de réaliser une transition plus douce avec
        l'arrière plan. Cette transition est obtenue par l'ajustement de la
        frontière entre la région traitée et le fond.
      </para>
      <para>
        Ne confondez pas l'anticrénelage et l'adoucissement:
        <figure>
          <title>Comparaison lissage-adoucissement</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/alias-feather.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>
                De gauche à droite, une sélection elliptique sans lissage ni
                adoucissement, avec lissage, avec adoucissement.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
        Le lissage peut agir sur le bord des sélections et sur les bords des
        traits de brosse.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-marching-ants" lang="de">
    <glossterm lang="de">Laufende Ameisen</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="de">
        Der Begriff bezeichnet die gestrichelte Linie, mit der eine Auswahl
        umrandet ist. Die Begrenzungslinie ist animiert, so dass sie aussieht,
        wie kleine Ameisen, die hintereinander herlaufen.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-layer" lang="en;es;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Layer</phrase>
      <!-- cs MARK: see phrase "Vrstva" -->
      <!-- de MARK: see phrase "Ebene" -->
      <!-- es MARK: see phrase "Capa" -->
      <!-- fr MARK: see phrase "Calque" -->
      <phrase lang="es">Capa</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Livelli</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">레이어(Layer)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Lag</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Layer(图层)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm lang="en"><primary>Layer</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="es"><primary>Capa</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="it"><primary>Livelli</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="no"><primary>Lag</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        You can think of layers as being a stack of slides which are more or
        less transparent. Each layer represents an aspect of the image and
        the image is the sum of all of these aspects. The layer at the bottom
        of the stack is the background layer. The layers above it are the
        components of the foreground.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can view and manage the layers of the image through the
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers dialog</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        레이어는 쌓여있는 판자나 입고 있는 옷을 생각해보면 된다. 입고 있는
        옷의 각 부분은
        <!--PENDING: ko <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">레이어 대화상자</link>
        --> 레이어 대화상자
        에 있는 각 레이어와 같다. 그리고 레이어는 각각 다른 것들의 위에
        쌓여져 있다. 제일 아래의 레이어는 이미지의 배경으로 이미지의 다른
        성분들이 그 위에 놓여지게 된다.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Puedes pensar a las capas de una imagen como una pila de
        filminas o como la ropa sobre tu cuerpo.  Cada elemento que
        vistes es una capa en el <!--link
        linkend="gimp-layer-dialog"-->diálogo de capas<!--/link-->.
        Las capas se apilan una sobre otra.  La capa de más abajo es
        el fondo de la imagen y las demás se superponen para formar la
        imagen.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Si può pensare ai livelli come ad una pila di diapositive o a degli
        strati di vestiti indossati. Ogni indumento indossato è un livello
        nella <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">finestra dei livelli</link>.
        I livelli sono posizionati uno sopra l'altro. Il livello in fondo a
        tutti è lo sfondo dell'immagine e i componenti in primo piano sono
        sopra di esso.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Laga i eit bilete kan samanliknast med plastfoliane i ein stabel med
        filmark. Kvart ark, altså kvart lag, kan innehalde informasjon om
        deler av biletet. Når du ser heile stabelen ovanfrå, vil du sjå
        totalbiletet sett saman av alle laga. Bakgrunnslaget ligg alltid på
        botnen, nedst i stabelen. Elles kan du stokka laga som du ønskjer.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        您可以认为图层是身上的衣服。您穿的每一件衣服都
        是<link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">图层对话框</link>中的一个图层。
        图层都是从上到下堆叠起来的，最底下的是图像背景，图像的前景部分则在其
        上。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">Representation of an image with layers:</para>
      <para lang="es">Representación de una imagen con capas:</para>
      <para lang="ko">이미지의 레이어 모습 :</para>
      <para lang="it">Rappresentazione di un'immagine con livelli:</para>
      <para lang="no">Her ser du laga i biletet:</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">表现一个带图层的图像：</para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/layers_overview.png"
            format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

      <para lang="en">The final image:</para>
      <para lang="es">La imagen final:</para>
      <para lang="it">L'immagine finale:</para>
      <para lang="ko">최종 이미지:</para>
      <para lang="no">og her det endelege biletet:</para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">最终图像：</para>

      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/dialogs/layers_example.png"
            format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>

    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

</glossdiv>
