<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-07-21 alex falappa : updated mask description
  2007-06-15 j.h : changed mask description
  2007-02-15 ciampix: moved it layer-modes to concepts/layer-modes.xml
  2007-01-19 lexa: moved en layer-modes to concepts/layer-modes.xml
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-24 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-06-05 add in marching ants by j.h
  2006-05-21 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050617 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>M</title><anchor id="glossary-m"/>

  


  

  <glossentry id="glossary-marching-ants">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Marching Ants</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see phrase "Laufende Ameisen" -->
      
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossentry "Pointillés mobiles (défilants)" -->
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Marching ants is a term which describes the dotted line which
        surrounds a selection. The line is animated, so it looks as if
        little ants are running around behind each other.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can disable the marching ants by unchecking the
        <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
          <guimenu moreinfo="none"><accel>V</accel>iew</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Show <accel>S</accel>election</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        option or by using the keyboard shortcut
        <keycombo moreinfo="none"><keycap moreinfo="none">Ctrl</keycap><keycap moreinfo="none">T</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>

      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  


  <glossentry id="glossary-masks">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Masks</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Masks</primary><secondary>Overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    
    
    
    

    
    
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para> <!--changed 070615-->
        <!-- TODO: es ko update content -->
        A mask is like a veil put over a layer (layer mask) or all the layers
        of an image (selection mask). You can remove this mask by painting
        with white color, and you can complete it by painting with black
        color. When the mask is <quote>applied</quote>, non masked pixels
        will remain visible (the others will be transparent) or will be
        selected, according to the type of mask.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>There are two types of masks:</para>
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Layer Mask</emphasis>
            : Every layer can have its own mask. The layer mask represents the
            Alpha channel of the layer and allows you to manage its
            transparency. By painting on the layer mask, you can make parts of
            the layer opaque or transparent: painting with black makes the
            layer transparent, painting with white makes the layer opaque and
            painting with shades of gray makes the layer semi-transparent. You
            can use all paint tools to paint on the mask. You can also apply a
            filter or copy-paste. You can use the Layer mask for transition
            effects, volume effects, merging elements from another image, etc.
            See the <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask">Layer Mask</link>
            section for more details.
          </para>
          
          
          
          
          
          
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Channel Mask</emphasis>, also called
            <emphasis>Selection Mask</emphasis>:
            Channel Masks determine the transparency of a selection. By
            painting on a Channel Mask with white, you remove the mask and
            increase the selection; with black, you reduce the selection.
            This procedure lets you create a selection very precisely. You
            can also save your selections to a Channel Mask with the
            <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">Save to Channel</link>
             command. You can retrieve it later by using the
             <quote>Channel to selection</quote> command from the
             <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">Channel menu</link>. Channel
             masks are so important in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that a
             special type has been implemented: the
             <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quick mask</link>. See the
             <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Selection mask</link>
             section for more details.
          </para>
          
          
          
          
          
          
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
<!--Sorry for introducing new id, but get validating errors without it -->
  

  


  <glossentry id="glossary-moire">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Moiré Effect</phrase>
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Moiré</primary></indexterm>
    

    <glossdef>
      
      <para>
        The moiré effect (pronounce <quote>Moa-ray</quote>)is an unintended
        pattern which appears when a regular pattern of grids or lines
        interferes with another regular pattern placed over it. This can
        happen, for example, when you are scanning an image with a periodic
        structure (such as a checkered shirt or a half-toned image), scanning
        a digital image, taking a digital photograph of a periodic pattern,
        or even when silkscreening.
       </para>
       <para>
         If you discover the problem in time, the best solution is to move
         the original image a little bit in the scanner or to change the
         camera angle slightly.
       </para>
       <para>
         If you cannot re-create the image file, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
         offers some filters which may help you with the problem. For more
         information, see the
         <link linkend="plug-in-despeckle">Despeckle</link> and
         <link linkend="plug-in-nlfilt">NL Filter</link> (Non-Linear)
         filters.
      </para>

      
      
      

      
       
       
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  
</glossdiv>
