<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
     2006-05-22 added Korean translation by Dust
     2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
     050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
     -->
<glossdiv lang="cs;de;es;fr;en;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title>P</title>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-path' lang="de;en;ko;zh_CN">
    <glossterm lang='en'>Path</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang='de'>Pfad</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="ko">경로(Path)</glossterm>
    <!-- es MARK: see glossterm "Ruta" -->
    <glossterm lang="zh_CN">Path(路径)</glossterm>
    <glossdef lang='en'>
      <para>
        A <emphasis>path</emphasis> is a one-dimensional tracing, either
        polygonal, or curved, or a mixture of segments of both types.
        In GIMP, the main uses of paths are either to form the
        boundaries of selections, or to be <emphasis>stroked</emphasis>
        to create visible curves on an image.  See the <link
        linkend='gimp-concepts-paths'>Paths</link> section for basic
        information on paths, and the <link linkend='gimp-tool-path'>Path
          Tool</link> section for information on how paths can be created
        and edited.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang='de'>
      <para>
        Ein Pfad ist eine eindimensionale Kurve. <!-- XXX -->
        Ihre Hauptanwendung finden Pfade in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> vor
        allem um Auswahlen oder schwierige Formen zu Erstellen, die dann
        nachgezeichnet werden können. Für weitere Informationen zu Pfaden
        können Sie die <link linkend='gimp-concepts-paths'>Einführung</link>
        anschauen. Das Kapitel
        <link linkend='gimp-tool-path'>Pfadwerkzeug</link> erklärt wie Pfade
        erstellt werden.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="ko">
      <para>
        <emphasis>경로</emphasis> 는 다각형이나, 곡선 등 1차원의 흔적이다.
        김프에서 경로의 주 용도는 선택의 외각을 만들거나,
        <emphasis>테두리를 그려</emphasis> 곡선을 만드는 것이다.
        경로에 대한 기본 정보는 
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend='gimp-concepts-paths'>경로</link>
        --> 경로
        섹션을 참고하면 되고, 경로를 만들고 편집하는 방법에 대해서는
        <!-- PENDING: ko <link linkend='gimp-tool-path'>경로 도구</link>
        --> 경로 도구 
        섹션을 참고하면 된다.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        FIXME
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-pdb' lang='de'>
    <glossterm lang="de">PDB</glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="de">
      <para>
        In der Prozeduren Datenbank (kurz: PDB) sind alle Funktionen
        registriert die GIMP und die Erweiterungen zur Verfügung stellen.
        Entwickler können in der Datenbank nach nützliche
        Programmierinformationen über die bereitgestellten Funktionen
        nachschlagen.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id='glossary-marching-ants-fr' lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang='fr'>Pointillés mobiles (défilants)</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang='fr'>
        Nom des lignes tiretées animées qui délimitent une sélection.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="file-pdf-save" lang="de;fr;en;es;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      PDF
      <anchor id="file-pdf-load" />
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        The PDF format was developed by Adobe to address some of the
        deficiencies of Postscript: most importantly, PDF files tend to
        be much smaller than equivalent Postscript files.  As with
        Postscript, Gimp's support of the PDF format is via
        Ghostscript.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="de">
      <para>
        Das Portable Document Format wurde durch Adobe entwickelt, um
        Defizite von Postscript abzustellen. Die Unterstützung von PDF
        (genauso wie Postscript) wird durch die freien Ghostscript
        Bibliotheken erreicht.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        El formato PDF fue desarrollado por Adobe para mejorar algunas
        de las deficiencias de Postcript: la más importante es que los
        archivos PDF tienden a ser mucho más pequeños que sus
        equivalentes Postcript.  Así como con Postcript,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puede usar el formato PDF mediante
        Ghostscript.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        Le format PDF a été développé par Adobe pour s'attaquer à certains
        défauts de Postscript: surtout, les fichiers PDF sont beaucoup plus
        petits que leur équivalent Postscript. Comme avec Postscript, la
        gestion du format PDF se fait à travers Ghostscript.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="ko">
      <para> 
        PDF 포맷은 포스트스크립트(Postscript)의 부족한 부분을 채우기 위해
        어도비(Adobe) 사에 의해 개발되었다. PDF 파일은 포스트스크립트 
        파일보다 상당히 작다. 김프에서는 고스트스크립트(Ghostscript)를 통해
        포스트스트립트와 함께 PDF 포맷을 지원한다.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        PDF-formatet blei utvikla av Adobe for å retta opp noen av manglane
        ved Postscript. Det viktigaste er at PDF-filene stort sett blir
        mykje mindre enn tilsvarande Postscript-filer.
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> støtter både Postscript og PDF ved hjelp av
        gratisskriptet Ghostscript.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        PDF 格式由 Adobe 发明来填补 Postscript 的不足之处：最重要的是，在相同情况下，PDF 文件比 Postscript 文件要小。和 Postscript 一样，Gimp 是通过 Ghostscript 来支持 PDF 格式的。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <!-- XXX commented out, because it's causing validity errors
       If you edit this glossentry and add text to it, please also add an
       empty glossdef with an empty para, to get it valid also for other
       languages
       
       <glossentry id="file-psp-save">
         <glossterm>PSP</glossterm>
         <anchor id="file-psp-load" />
         <glossdef lang="en">
         </glossdef>
       </glossentry>
       -->

  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard" lang="es">
    <glossterm lang="es">Portapapeles</glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        Portapapeles es el término usado para describir el área
        temporal de memoria usado para transferir datos entre
        documentos o aplicaciones.  El <acronym>GIMP</acronym> utiliza
        métodos un poco diferentes bajo los distintos sistemas
        operativos.  Bajo Linux/XFree, el portapapeles de XFree es
        usado para el texto y el portapapeles interno del
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> es usado para imágenes transferidas
        entre documentos.  Cuando el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> es
        utilizado bajo otros sistemas operativos, las diferencias se
        pueden tornar significativas.  Cualquier diferencia debería
        ser remarcada en la documentación específica del
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> para cada sistema.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
       
  <glossentry id="file-ps-save" lang="de;fr;en;es;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      Postscript
      <anchor id="file-ps-load" />
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        Created by Adobe, PostScript is a page description language
        mainly used by printers and other output devices. It's also an
        excellent way to distribute documents.  Gimp does not support
        Postscript directly:  it depends on a powerful free software
        program called Ghostscript.
      </para>
      <para>
        The great power of Postscript is its ability to represent vector
        graphics–lines, curves, text, paths, etc–in a
        resolution-independent way.  Postscript is not very efficient,
        though, when it comes to representing pixel-based raster
        graphics.  For this reason, postscript is not a good format to
        use for saving images that are later going to be edited using
        Gimp or another graphics program.
      </para>
      <para>
        Linux distributions almost always come with Ghostscript already
        installed (not necessarily the most recent version).  For other
        operating systems, you may have to install it yourself.  Here are
        instructions for installing it on Windows:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Go to the <ulink
            url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ghostscript">Ghostscript
              project page on Sourceforge</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Look for package gnu-gs or ghostscript (non-commercial use
            only) and go to the download section.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Download a prepared Windows distribution like gs650w32.exe
            or gs700w32.exe.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Start the executable and follow the instructions of the
            installation procedure.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Copy the executable gswin32c.exe from the directory bin of
            the ghostscript installation to the Windows directory (or
            any other directory that is contained in the PATH).  As an
            alternative, advanced users can set an environment variable
            GS_PROG to point to gswin32c.exe
            (e.g. c:\gs\gsX.YY\bin\gswin32c.exe)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Now you should be able to read PostScript files with GIMP.
        Please note that you must not move the directories of
        ghostscript once the installation has finished. Registry entries
        have been created that allow ghostscript to find libraries.
        (These instructions courtesy of http://www.kirchgessner.net.)
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="de">
      <para>
        Postscript ist eine sogenannte Seitenbeschreibungssprache udn wurde
        von Adobe vorwiegend für Drucker oder andere
        Ausgabegeräte entwickelt. So beschreibt Postscript das Aussehen
        einer Grafik, anstatt die Selbige zu speichern. Um die Grafik
        wieder anschauen zu können muss sie durch einen
        Postscript-Interpreter geladen werden. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        unterstützt Postscript nur indirekt durch das frei verfügbare
        Ghostscript. Ghostscript interpretiert eine mit Postscript
        formatierte Datei und wandelt es in ein Pixelformat um. Deshalb
        eignet sich <acronym>GIMP</acronym> schlecht um wiederum im
        Postscript Format abzuspeichern.
      </para>
      <para>
        Formate zur Beschreibung von Grafiken werden allgemein als
        Vektorformate bezeichnet. Zur Beschreibung werden geometrische
        Primitiven wie Linien, Kreise, Text und Pfade verwendet. Der
        Vorteil bei dieser Vorgehensweise ist die Unabhängigkeit von der
        Auslösung der Grafik jedoch lassen sich mit Vektorformate sehr
        schwierig kleinste Details beschreiben.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        Creado por Adobe, PostScript es un lenguaje de descripción de
        páginas utilizado principalmente por impresoras y otros
        dispositivos de salida.  Es también un excelente formato para
        distribuír documentos.  El <acronym>GIMP</acronym> no admite
        documentos Postscript directamente: depende de un poderoso
        programa que es software libre llamado Ghostscript.
      </para>
      <para>
        El gran poder de Postscript reside en su habilidad para
        representar gráficos vectoriales como líneas, texto, rutas,
        etc, siempre de la misma forma, independientemente de la
        resolución.  No obstante, Postscript no es muy eficiente a la
        hora de representar gráficos de pixeles.  Es por esta razón
        que Postscript no es un buen formato para guardar imágenes que
        luego serán editadas con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> o con otro
        programa para gráficos.
      </para>
      <para>
        Las distribuciones de Linux casi siempre vienen con
        Ghostscript previamente instalado (no necesariamente en su
        versión más reciente).  Para otros sistemas operativos, puedes
        instalarlo tú misma.  Aquí hay instrucciones para instalarlo
        en Windows:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="es">
            Ve al<ulink
            url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ghostscript">sitio
            del proyecto de Ghostscript project en
            Sourceforge</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="es">
            Busca el paquete gnu-gs o ghostscript (sólo para uso no
            comercial) y ve a la sección de descarga.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="es">
            Descarga la distribución preparada para Windows como por
            ejemplo gs650w32.exe o gs700w32.exe.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="es">
            Inicia el ejecutable y sigue las instrucciones para el
            proceso de instalación.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="es">
            Copia el ejecutable gswin32c.exe desde el directorio bin
            de la instalación de ghostscript hasta el directorio
            Windows (o cualquier otro directorio que esté contenido en
            el PATH).  Como alternativa, los usuarios avanzados pueden
            hacer que la variable de entorno GS_PROG apunte a
            gswin32c.exe (por ej. c:\gs\gsX.YY\bin\gswin32c.exe)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Ahora deberías ser capaz de leer archivos PostScript con el
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Por favor nota que no debes mover
        los directorios de ghostscript una vez que la instalación ha
        terminado.  Las entradas al registro han sido creadas para
        encontrar las bibliotecas de ghostscript (estas instrucciones
        son cortesía de http://www.kirchgessner.net).
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        Créé par Adobe, Postscript est un langage de description de page
        surtout utilisé par les imprimantes et autres périphériques de
        sortie. C'est aussi un bon moyen pour diffuser des documents.
        GIMP ne gère pas Postscript directement mais fait appel à un
        puissant logiciel libre appelé Ghostscript.
      </para>
      <para>
        La caractéristique la plus puissante de Postscript est sa
        capacité à représenter les dessins, courbes, textes, chemins...
        vectoriels de manière indépendante de la résolution. Postscript
        n'est pas très efficace toutefois pour représenter des images
        tramées à base de pixels. Pour cette raison, Postscript n'est
        pas le bon format à utiliser pour sauvegarder des images qui
        seront ensuite éditées avec GIMP ou un autre programme graphique.
      </para>
      <para>
        La plupart des distributions Linux sont livrées avec Ghostscript
        déjà installé (pas forcément la version la plus récente). Pour
        les autres systèmes opératoires, vous vous aurez sûrement à les
        installer vous-même. Voici les instructions pour l'installation
        sur Windows:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Aller sur  http://sourceforge.net/projects/ghostscript.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Chercher le paquetage gnu-gs ou ghostscript (usage non
            commercial seulement) et aller à la section Téléchargement
            (Download).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Télécharger une distribution préparée pour Windows, par
            exemple gs650w32.exe ou gs700w32.exe.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Lancer l'exécutable et suivre les instructions de la
            procédure d'installation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Copier l'exécutable gswin32c.exe obtenu du répertoire bin du
            dossier d'installation de Ghostscript dans le dossier Windows
            (ou dans tout autre dossier contenu dans le PATH). Autre
            possibilité pour les utilisateurs confirmés: établir une
            variable d'environnement GS_PROG pointant sur gswin32c
            (p.e c:\gs\gsX.YY\bin\gswin32c.exe).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Vous devriez être maintenant capable de lire des fichiers
        Postscript avec GIMP. Notez que vous ne devez pas déplacer les
        répertoires de Ghostscript une fois l'installation terminée:
        des entrées ont été créées dans le registre pour permettre à
        Ghostscript de retrouver les librairies. (Informations fournies
        avec l'aimable autorisation de http://www.kirchgessner.net.)
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="ko">
      <para>
        어도비(Adobe) 사에 의해 개발된 포스트스크립트(PostScript)는 
        프린터 등 여러 출력장치에 널리 사용된 페이지 표현 언어이다.
        이것은 문서들을 배치하는데 좋은 방법이다. 하지만 김프에서는
        이를 직접 지원하지 않고 포스트스크립트를 지원하는 강력한 자유 
        프로그램인 고스트스크립트(Ghostscript)를 통해 간접 지원한다.
      </para>
      <para> 
        포스트스크립트의 가장 큰 장점은 벡터 그래픽라인, 곡선, 문자, 경로
        등을 해상도와 관계없이 표현할 수 있다라는 점이다. 포스트스크립트는
        픽셀기반의 래스터 그래픽스로 표현될때 다소 효율적이지는 않다.
        그런 까닭에 포스트스크립트는 후에 김프와 같은 그래픽스
        프로그램으로 편집하기 위해 저장하는 포맷으로는 적당하지 않다.
      </para>
      <para>
 
        리눅스 배포판에는 대부분 고스트스크립트가 포함되어 있다. 하지만 
        다른 운영 체제에서는 직접 설치해야 한다. 아래는 윈도우즈에서의
        설치 방법이다.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="ko">
            <ulink
            url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ghostscript">
            고스트스크립트(Ghostscript) 프로젝트 페이지
 소스사이트</ulink>
            를 방문한다.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="ko">
 
            gnu-gs 혹은 ghostscript(비상업용) 패키지를 찾아 다운로드한다.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="ko">
 
            gs650w32.exe이나 gs700w32.exe 와 같은 윈도우즈용 설치파일을
            받는다.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="ko">
            파일을 실행하고 설치 과정을 따라한다.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="ko"> 
            고스트스크립트 설치 디렉토리에서 gswin32c.exe 파일을 복사해
            윈도우즈 디렉토리(혹은 PATH 로 지정된 디렉토리)에 붙여넣는다.
            
참고로 고급 사용자일 경우 gswin32c.exe 를 가리키는 GS_PROG
            환경변수를 설정해 사용할 수도 있다.
            (예. c:\gs\gsX.YY\bin\gswin32c.exe)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        이제 김프에서 포스트스크립트 파일을 읽을 수 있게 되었다. 주의할 
        점은 고스트스크립트를 설치한 후에 해당 디렉토리를 이동시켜서는
        안된다라는 것이다. 설치할 당시 상항에 맞춰 레지스트리 값들이 
        기록되었기 때문이다. (이 과정의 원문은 http://www.kirchgessner.net
        에 있다.)
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        Postscript er utvikla av Adobe, og er eit språk som kanskje er
        mest kjent i samband med overføring av data til skrivarar, men
        er faktisk også svært brukbart til å distribuera vanlege
        dokument. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har ikkje direktestøtte for
        Postscript, men er avhengig av eit fritt program kalla
        <acronym>Ghostscript</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Den store fordelen med Postscript er at det kan handtera
        vektorgrafikk, kurver, tekst, banar osv. uavhengig av
        oppløysinga. Derimot er Postscript ikkje så effektivt i
        behandlinga av pikselbasert rastergrafikk. Difor er det ikkje
        så lurt å lagre denne type bilete med Postscript dersom dei
        seinare skal redigerast i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eller andre
        biletbehandlingsprogram.
      </para>
      <para>
        Som oftast kjem dei ulike versjonane av Linux med Ghostscript
        ferdiginstallert (om ikkje alltid siste versjon). Bruker du andre
        operativsystem, må du installera programmet sjølv. I Windows
        kan du gjere det slik:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="no">
            Gå til <ulink
            url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/ghostscript">Ghostscript
              project page on Sourceforge</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="no">
            Finn fram til gnu-gs eller ghostscript (non-commercial use
            only) og gå vidare til nedlasting (download).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="no">
            Last ned ein klargjort Windows-distribusjon som for eksempel
            <filename>gs650w32.exe</filename>,
            <filename>gs700w32.exe</filename> eller noe liknande.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="no">
            Køyr programmet og følj instruksjonane som dukkar opp etter
            kvart.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="no">
            Kopier fila <filename>gswin32c.exe</filename> frå bin-mappa
            der Ghostscript blei installert og over i Windows-mappa
            (eller ei anna mappe som er inkludert i oppstartstigen
            (path) for Windows). Dersom du kjenner til måten å gjere
            det på, kan du setje omgivnadsvariabelen (environment
            variable) GS_PROG til å peika til  gswin32c.exe (for
            eksempel c:\gs\gsX.YY\bin\gswin32c.exe).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Dersom alt har gått bra, skal du nå vere i stand til å lese
        PostScript-filer i <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Hugs på at du ikkje
        må flytte på mapper og filer som høyrer til PostScript etter at
        programmet er installert. Windows har sett opp registra sine
        etter plasseringa mappene fekk under installeringa. (Denne
        instruksjonen erhenta frå http://www.kirchgessner.net).
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        FIXME
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="file-png-save-defaults" lang="cs;de;es;fr;en;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      PNG
      <anchor id="file-png-load" />
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="cs">
      <para>
        PNG je grafický formát vytvořený jako dokonalejší a patenty nezatížená
        náhrada <link linkend="file-gif-save">formátu GIF</link>. PNG podporuje
        obrázky v indexovaných barvách a stupních šedi, ale navíc i obrázky v
        pravých barvách a alfa kanál (částečnou průhlednost). PNG používá
        kompresi, narozdíl od <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link>
        neztrátovou.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        The format that is supposed to replace the
        <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF format</link> and thus
        provide a solution to GIF's trademark and patent issues.
        Indexed color, grayscale, and truecolor images are supported,
        plus an optional alpha channel. PNG also uses compression, but
        unlike <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link> it
        doesn't lose image information.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="de">
      <para>
        PNG (Portable Network Graphics) sollte einst das
        <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF Format</link>
        ablösen, um Patentschwierigkeiten aus dem Wege zu gehen. Das
        Format selber unterstützt Indexierte, Graustufen und RGB Farben,
        sowie einen optionalen Alphakanal. PNG benutzt ein
        Kompressionsverfahren ohne dabei Bildinformationen zu verlieren.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        El formato que supuestamente reemplazará al <link
        linkend="file-gif-save">formato GIF</link> dando una solución
        a los problemas de marca registrada y patente que este último
        presenta.  Imágenes en color indexado, escala de grises, y
        color verdadero son admisibles, además de un canal alfa
        opcional.  PNG también usa compresión, pero al contrario de
        <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link> la realiza sin
        pérdida de información.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        Le format PNG (Portable Network Graphics) devrait remplacer le
        format <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF</link> et régler ainsi
        les problèmes de marque commerciale et de licence. Il accepte
        les couleurs indexées, les niveaux de gris et les images en
        Vraies Couleurs avec en plus un canal Alpha pour la
        transparence. Il utilise aussi la compression, avec l'avantage
        d'être sans perte d'information à la différence du
        <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="ko">
      <para> 
        이 포맷은 
        <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF 포맷</link> 
        의 대안으로 제시된 것이다. 따라서 GIF의 상표권과 특허권에 대한
        대책을 가지고 있다. 그리고 인덱스 색상, 그레이스케일, 트루컬러 
        이미지 등을 지원하며, 알파채널도 지원한다. PNG 역시 압축기법을
        사용하지만 
        <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link>
        과는 달리 정보 손실이 없다.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        Dette formatet er tenkt å skulle erstatta
        <link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF</link>, som er noe
        problematisk på grunn av varemerke- og patentrettar som er
        knytt til GIF. PNG har støtte for indekserte fargekart,
        gråskala, fullfarge og alfakanalar.
        Også PNG-formatet kan komprimerast, men i motsetnad til
        <link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link> misser ikkje PNG
        informasjonar om biletet.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        该格式作为<link linkend="file-gif-save">GIF格式</link>的替代者解决 GIF 的商标和专利方面的问题。它支持索引色，灰度和真彩色，外加一个可选的 alpha 通道。PNG 也使用压缩，不过不象<link linkend="file-jpeg-save">JPEG</link>，它并不损失图像信息。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="file-psd-save" lang="de;fr;en;es;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      PSD
      <anchor id="file-psd-load" />
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        PSD is Adobe Photoshop's native file format, and thus is
        comparable to <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>in
        complexity.  Gimp's ability to handle PSD files is sophisticated
        but limited:  some features of PSD files are not loaded, and
        only PSD versions XX or less are supported.  Unfortunately,
        Adobe has now made the Photoshop Software Development
        Kit ­ which includes their file format
        specifications ­ proprietary, and only available to a limited
        set of developers blessed by Adobe.  This does not include the
        Gimp development team; and the lack of information makes it very
        difficult to maintain up-to-date support for PSD files.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="de">
      <para>
        PSD ist das hauseigene Dateiformat von <trademark>Adobe
          Photoshop</trademark>, vergleichbar mit dem
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigenen <link
        linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>. Es ist leider nicht immer
        möglich Photoshop Dateien lesen zu können und vor allem, alle
        abgespeicherten Informationen auch in GIMP um zu setzen (z.B.
        Ebeneneffekte). Leider ist der Zugang zu den Informationen für
        Entwickler, um einen guten Im- und Export des Dateiformates zu
        ermöglichen, nur für ausgewählte Personen erreichbar. GIMP
        Entwickler gehören leider nicht zum ausgewählten Personenkreis,
        so dass auch in Zukunft nicht mit einer Unterstützung aktueller
        Photoshop Versionen zu rechnen ist.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        PSD es el formato de archivo nativo de Adobe Photoshop, y por
        lo tanto es comparable al <!--link
        linkend="gimp-xcf-save"-->XCF<!--/link--> en cuanto a
        complejidad.  La habilidad del <acronym>GIMP</acronym> de
        manejar archivos PSD es sofisticada pero a la vez limitada:
        algunas capacidades de los archivos PSD no serán cargadas, y
        sólo las versiones XX de PSD o anteriores están comprendidas.
        Desafortunadamente, Adobe ha hecho ahora al Photoshop Software
        Development Kit (que incluye a las especificaciones de sus
        formatos de archivo) propietarias, y sólo disponibles para un
        conjunto limitado de desarrolladores bendecidos por Adobe.
        Éste no incluye al grupo de desarrolladores del
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, y la falta de información dificulta
        mucho mantener al día el soporte de archivos PSD.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        PSD est le format natif de Photoshop et est comparable au format
        <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link> en termes de complexité.
        La capacité de GIMP à gérer le format PSD est assez développée
        mais limitée: seules les anciennes versions sont acceptées car
        Photoshop a développé un Kit propriétaire auquel seuls ont
        accès les développeurs adoubés par Adobe. L'équipe de
        développement de GIMP n'en fait pas partie, et ce manque
        d'information rend quasi impossible le maintien d'une mise à
        jour pour les fichiers PSD.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="ko">
      <para> 
        PSD 는 어도비 포토샵의 전용 파일 포맷으로 김프의
        <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>
        와 비교되는 포맷이다. 김프에서는 PDS 파일을 지능적으로 다루지만 
        한계가 있다. PDS 파일의 몇몇 기능은 읽을 수 없으며, PDS 특정 
        버전이나 그 이하의 버전만을 지원한다. 그런데 안타깝게도 어도비는
        포토샵 개발도구-파일 포맷 설계를 포함한-를 독점하고 있기 때문에
        이에 대해서는 어도비에 관계된 개발자만이 사용가능하다. 그리고
        여기에 김프 개발팀은 포함되어 있지 않기 때문에, 정보부족으로
        인해 최신 버전의 PSD 파일을 지원하는 것이 쉽지 않다.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        PSD er det originale filformatet for <trademark>Adobe
          Photoshop</trademark> og er like komplekst som
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt eige format
        <link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>. Diverre er Adobe
        sine filspesifikasjonar nå bare tilgjengelege for utvalde
        personar, og utviklarane av <acronym>GIMP</acronym> høyrer ikkje
        med til desse. Difor er det vanskeleg å lage oppdatert støtte
        for PSD-filene. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> har difor bare støtte for
        eldre PSD-filer.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        PSD 是 Adobe Photoshop 的内建文件格式，和<link linkend="gimp-xcf-save">XCF</link>的复杂程度相当。GIMP 处理 PSD 文件的能力是高深而有限的：一些 PSD 文件的特性无法支持，而且只有 XX 版本及其以前的 PSD 才能支持。不幸的是，Adobe 现在使用 Photoshop Software Development Kit - 其中包括它们的专利的文件格式规范，只对一部分 Adobe 的开发者开放。而这不包括 GIMP 开发小组，由于缺乏信息使得保持对 PSD 文件的支持非常困难。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard-fr" lang='fr'>
    <glossterm lang="fr">Presse-papier</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Le presse-papier est une zone de la mémoire utilisée pour stocker
        temporairement des données en attendant de les transférer dans un
        autre document. La façon dont GIMP utilise le presse-papier
        dépend de la plateforme sur laquelle il est installé. Sous
        Linux/XFree, le presse-papier XFree est utilisé pour le texte,
        et les tampons internes à GIMP sont utilisés pour les
        transferts d'image entre images. Quand GIMP est utilisé sur
        d'autres plateformes, ce peut être différent et ces différences
        devraient être soulignées dans la documentation pour le
        paquetage GIMP spécifique de cette plateforme.
      </para>
      <para>
        Voyez aussi <link linkend='gimp-buffer-dialog'>Tampons</link>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id='glossary-bitmap-no' lang="no">
    <glossterm lang="no">Punktgrafikk</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="no">
        Det biletet du ser på skjermen, eller på papiret, er sett saman
        av mange biletpunkt. Når du lagrar dette biletet i ei fil, er
        den vanlegaste måten å lagra biletet piksel for piksel, eventuelt
        med noen ekstra data om lysstyrke, farge osv. for kvart
        biletpunkt.
        Denne måten å laga og lagra bilete på, blir kalla punktgrafikk
        (eng.: bitmap), i motsetnad til vektorgrafikk der biletdata blir
        lagra som matematiske funksjonar. Dei fleste av dei mest brukte
        biletformata er i punktgrafikk.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
