<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-25 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050826 de added rgb by axel.wernicke
  050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="en;cs;de;es;no;it">
  <title>R</title>

  <glossentry id="glossary-dithering-cs" lang="cs">
    <glossterm>Rozptylování</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Rozptylování (používá se i anglický termín
        <foreignphrase>dithering</foreignphrase>) označuje černou magii
        potřebnou k tomu, aby obrázek obsahující ve skutečnosti malé množství
        barev vypadal, jako kdyby barev obsahoval mnoho.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-rgb" lang="en;de;no;it">

    <glossterm>RGB</glossterm>
    <indexterm><primary>RGB</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <figure>
        <title>
          <phrase lang="en">Additive color model</phrase>
          <phrase lang="de">Additives Farbmodell</phrase>
          <phrase lang="no">Det additive fargesystemet</phrase>
          <phrase lang="it">Modello di colore additivo</phrase>
        </title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/color-model-additive.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang="en">
        RGB is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Red, Green and Blue. These colors are
        emitted by screen elements and not reflected as they are with paint.
        The resulting color is a combination of the three primary RGB colors,
        with different degrees of lightness. If you look closely at your
        television screen, whose pitch is less than that of a computer
        screen, you can see the red, green and blue elements lit with
        different intensities. The RGB color model is
        <emphasis>additive</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses eight bits per channel for each primary
        color. That means there are 256 intensities (Values) available,
        resulting in 256×256×256 = 16,777,216 colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        It is not obvious why a given combination of primary colors produces a
        particular color. Why, for instance, does 229R+205G+229B give a shade
        of pink? This depends upon the human eye and brain. There is no color
        in nature, only a continuous spectrum of wavelengths of light. There
        are three kinds of cones in the retina. The same wavelength of light
        acting upon the three types of cones stimulates each of them
        differently, and the mind has learned, after several million years of
        evolution, how to recognize a color from these differences.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        It is easy to see that no light (0R+0G+0B) produces complete darkness,
        black, and that full light (255R+255G+255B) produces white. Equal
        intensity on all color channels produces a level of gray. That is why
        there can only be 256 gray levels in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Mixing two <emphasis>Primary colors</emphasis> in RGB mode
        gives a <emphasis>Secondary color</emphasis>, that is, a
        color in the CMY model. Thus combining Red and Green gives
        Yellow, Green and Blue give Cyan, Blue and Red give Magenta.
        Don't confuse secondary colors with
        <emphasis>Complementary colors</emphasis> which are
        directly opposite a primary color in the chromatic
        circle:
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/colorcircle.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        Mixing a primary color with its complementary color gives gray (a
        neutral color).
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        It is important to know what happens when you are dealing with colors
        in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
        The most important rule to remember is that decreasing the intensity
        of a primary color results in increasing the intensity of the
        complementary color (and vice versa). This is because when you
        decrease the value of a channel, for instance Green, you automatically
        increase the relative importance of the other two, here Red and Blue.
        The combination of these two channels gives the secondary color,
        Magenta, which is the complementary color of Green.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Exercise</emphasis>:
        You can check this out. Create a new image with only a white
        background (255R+255G+255B). Open the
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Color Tools</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Levels</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        dialog and select the Red channel. If necessary, check the
        preview box. Move the white slider to the left to decrease the
        Red value. You will notice that the background of your image
        gets closer and closer to Cyan. Now, decrease the Blue channel:
        only the Green will remain. For practice, go backwards, add a
        color and try to guess what hue will appear.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link>
        tool lets you find out the RGB values of a pixel and the
        <link linkend="glossary-hextriplet">hextriplet</link>
        for the color.
      </para>

      <para lang="de">
        RGB ist ein Akronym für Rot, Grün, Blau. Es bezeichnet ein
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Farbmodell</link>,
        welches verwendet wird, um Farben auf Computern und Fernsehgeräten
        darzustellen. Die Farben werden von den Geräten ausgesendet und nicht
        wie bei Gemälden reflektiert. Die sich ergebende Farbe ist eine
        Kombination der Primärfarben Rot, Grün und Blau mit jeweils
        unterschiedlicher Helligkeit. Wenn Sie ganz nah an einen Fernsehschirm
        herangehen, können Sie die einzelnen roten, grünen und blauen Elemente
        in unterschiedlichen Helligkeiten leuchten sehen. Das Farbmodell RGB
        ist ein <emphasis>additives</emphasis> Farbmodell.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        verwendet 8 Bit pro Kanal für jede Primärfarbe. Daraus ergeben sich
        256 verschiedene Werte (Helligkeiten) für jede Primärfarbe, welche
        insgesamt zu 256x256x256 = 16,777,216 verschiedenen Farben gemischt
        werden können.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Es ist nicht offensichtlich warum Kombinationen der Primärfarben
        gelegentlich unerwartete Farben ergeben. Warum entsteht zum Beispiel
        aus der Kombination 229R+205G+229B die Farbe Pink? Das Ganze hängt vom
        menschlichen Auge und dem Gehirn ab. Es gibt in der Natur keine
        Farben, sondern lediglich ein kontinuierliches Spektrum der
        Wellenlänge des Lichtes. In der
        <ulink url="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netzhaut">Retina</ulink>,
        der Netzhaut des Auges, befinden sich drei verschiedene Arten von
        Zapfen. Eine konstante Wellenlänge regt diese drei Arten von Zapfen
        unterschiedlich an. Das Gehirn hat nach einigen Millionen Jahren
        Evolution gelernt, diese Unterschiede als Farben zu erkennen.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Es ist leicht einzusehen, dass kein Licht (0R+0G+0B) Dunkelheit,
        bzw. Schwarz ergibt, während volles Licht (255R+255G+255B) weiss
        erzeugt. Eine gleiche Hellikeit aller Kanäle ergibt einen
        Grauwert. Daraus ergibt sich, dass in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        lediglich 256 verschiedene Graustufen existieren.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Werden im RGB-Modus zwei <emphasis>Primärfarben</emphasis>
        gemischt, ergibt dies eine <emphasis>Sekundärfarbe</emphasis>,
        also eine Farbe des CMY Modells. Die Kombination von Rot und
        Grün ergibt Gelb (Yellow), Grün und Blau ergeben Cyan, und Blau
        und Rot ergeben Magenta. Verwechseln Sie diese dabei bitte nicht
        mit den sogenannten <emphasis>Komplementärfarben</emphasis>,
        welche die Farben sind, die sich im Farbkreis gegenüberstehen:
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/colorcircle.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        Das Mischen einer Primärfarbe mit seiner Komplementärfarbe
        ergibt Grau.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Es ist sehr wichtig zu verstehen, was passiert wenn Sie in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> mit Fargen hantieren. Die wichtigste
        Regel, welche Sie sich merken sollten ist, dass die Verminderung
        der Intensität einer Primärfarbe automatisch eine Erhöhung der
        Intensität der Komplementärfarben bewirkt. Dies gilt natürlich
        auch in umgekehrter Richtung. Warum ist das so? - Nun, wenn Sie
        den Wert für einen Kanal, beispielsweise Grün, verringern, wird
        automatisch die relative Wichtigkeit der Rot und Blauanteile
        erhöht. Die Kombination dieser beiden Kanäle ergibt wiederum die
        Sekundärfarbe Magenta, welche gleichzeitig die Komplementärfarbe
        zu Grün ist.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Der <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Farbwähler</link>
        gibt Ihnen jederzeit Auskunft über den RGB Wert eines Pixels und
        den zugehörigen HTML <link
        linkend="glossary-hextriplet">hextriplet</link> Wert der Farbe.
      </para>

      <para lang="it">
        RGB è un acronimo inglese per Rosso, Verde e Blu. Questi sono i tre
        colori primari additivi. Mescolando insieme tre <emphasis>sorgenti
          di luce</emphasis> con questi colori con differenti intensità
        relative, è possibile ottenere qualsiasi combinazione di colore
        visibile a partire dal nero (tutte le luci spente) fino al bianco
        (tutte e tre le luci al massimo e con intensità uguale). Per
        informazioni aggiuntive consultare la voce
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">Modello di colore</link> in
        questo glossario.
      </para>

      <para lang="no">
        RGB er forkorting for Raud, Grøn og Blå, og er eit vanleg namne på
        ein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel-no">fargemodus</link> som blir
        brukt for å vise fargar på data- og TV-skjermar. Fargane blir laga
        av fosforiserande punkt på skjermen, og ikkje med reflektert lys
        slik som dei blir laga t.d. når du ser på maling. Den fargen du ser,
        er ein kombinasjon av dei primære RGB-fargane, med ulike grader av
        lysstyrke. Du kan faktisk sjå dei ulike fargeprikkane dersom du
        kikkar nærare etter på TV-skjermen. (Denne skjermen har noe grovare
        fargeprikkar enn dataskjermen. Difor lettast på TV-skjermen).
        Sidan fargane blir laga ved å legge saman primærfargane, blir denne
        måten å blanda fargar på kalla <emphasis>additiv</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> bruker ein åtte bits (8-bit) kanal for kvar
        primærfarge. Difor kan kvar farge ha 256 ulike lysstyrkar (verdiar).
        Til saman gir dette 256 × 256 × 256 = 16 777 216 ulike fargar. (Det
        er dette Windows kallar <quote>millionar av fargar</quote>).
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Det er ikkje så innlysande kvifor kombinasjonane av primærfargane
        ofte gir uventa resultat. Kvifor gir 229R + 205G + 229B ein
        lyseraud farge? Svaret ligg i måten auget vårt og hjernen vår
        oppfattar fargar. I naturen er det eigentleg ikkje fargar, bare ulike
        bølgjelengder av lys. Når desse lysstrålane treff auget vårt, vil noen
        såkalla stavar i netthinna i auget bli påverka ulikt av ulike
        bølgjelengder. Gjennom noen millionar års utvikling, har vi lært oss
        korleis desse signala frå stavane skal oppfattast som fargar og kva
        fargar dei ulike bølgjelengdene skal oppfattast som.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Det er kanskje enklare å forstå at fullstendig mangel på lys (0R + 0G
        + 0B) gir fullstendig mørke, altså svart, og at fullt lys (256R + 256G
        + 256B) blir oppfatta som kvitfarge. Alle andre blandingar med like
        mengder av kvar farge gir grått. Du kan altså bare ha 256 ulike
        gråtonar i dette systemet.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Blandar du to <emphasis>primærfargar</emphasis> i RGB-modus får du
        ein <emphasis>sekundærfarge</emphasis> som er ein farge i såkalla
        CMY-modus (dvs. <quote>Trykkfargane</quote>). Kombinasjonen raud og
        grøn gir gul, grøn og blå gir cyan medan blå og raud gir magenta.
        Sekundærfargane er ikkje det same som
        <emphasis>komplementærfargane</emphasis>, som er fargar som står
        diametralt motsett kvarandre på fargesirkelen:
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/colorcircle.png"
              format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        Blandar du ein primærfarge med ein komplementærfarge blir
        resultatet grått (nøytral farga).
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Det er viktig å kjenne til kva som skjer når du steller med fargar.
        Ein av reglane du bør hugsa, er at dersom du minskar ein primærfarge
        aukar du metninga til komplementærfargen, og omvendt. Forklaringa er
        at når du reduserer verdien av til dømes grøn, så gjer du dei to andre
        relativt viktigare, i dette tilfellet raud og blå. Kombinasjonen av
        raud og blå gir sekundærfargen magenta, som er komplimentærfargen til
        grøn.
      </para>
      <para lang="no"><!--
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">-->Fargepipetta<!--</link>-->
        gir deg høve til å sjå RGB-verdien til eit fargepunkt, og gir deg
        samstundes <link linkend="glossary-hextriplet">hexverdien</link> for
        fargen til bruk i HTML.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dersom du har lyst, kan du kontrollera påstanden. Lag eit nytt bilete
        med kvit (255R + 255G + 255B) bakgrunn. Opna dialogen
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Verktøy</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Fargeverktøy</guimenuitem>
          <guimenuitem>Nivå</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        og vel den raude kanalen. Om nødvendig, ta fram førehandsvisinga.
        Flytt den vesle kvite glidebrytaren for nivå ut mot venstre for å
        minska mengda av raudt i biletet. Du vil sjå at bakgrunnen blir meir
        og meir cyan etter som mengda av raudt minkar. Gjer det same med
        blåkanalen, og du vil sjå at du sit igjen med ein grøn bakgrunn. Som
        ei lita ekstraøving, kan du legga til fargar og prøve å gissa kva
        farge du endar opp med.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-path" lang="es">
    <glossterm lang="es">Ruta</glossterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Ruta</primary></indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="es">
        Una <emphasis>ruta</emphasis> es una línea, ya sea poligonal,
        curva, o una combinación de segmentos de ambos tipos.  En
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, los principales usos de las rutas son
        para definir la frontera de una selección, o para ser
        <emphasis>trazada</emphasis> y así crear curvas visibles sobre
        la imagen.  Vea la sección sobre <!--link
        linkend="gimp-concepts-paths"-->Rutas<!--/link--> para
        información básica, y la sección sobre la <!--link
        linkend="gimp-tool-path"-->Herramienta de ruta<!--/link-->
        para saber cómo pueden ser creadas y editadas.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

</glossdiv>
