<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-12-27 lexa: added rendering intent for en, de
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-25 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050826 de added rgb by axel.wernicke
  050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>R</title><anchor id="glossary-r"/>

  


  <glossentry id="glossary-rgb">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>RGB</phrase>
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>RGB</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Color</primary><secondary>Additive color model</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <figure float="0">
        <title>
          <phrase>Additive color model</phrase>
          
          
          
          
          
        </title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/color-model-additive.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        RGB is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Red, Green and Blue. These colors are
        emitted by screen elements and not reflected as they are with paint.
        The resulting color is a combination of the three primary RGB colors,
        with different degrees of lightness. If you look closely at your
        television screen, whose pitch is less than that of a computer
        screen, you can see the red, green and blue elements lit with
        different intensities. The RGB color model is
        <emphasis>additive</emphasis>.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses eight bits per channel for each primary
        color. That means there are 256 intensities (Values) available,
        resulting in 256×256×256 = 16,777,216 colors.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        It is not obvious why a given combination of primary colors produces a
        particular color. Why, for instance, does 229R+205G+229B give a shade
        of pink? This depends upon the human eye and brain. There is no color
        in nature, only a continuous spectrum of wavelengths of light. There
        are three kinds of cones in the retina. The same wavelength of light
        acting upon the three types of cones stimulates each of them
        differently, and the mind has learned, after several million years of
        evolution, how to recognize a color from these differences.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        It is easy to see that no light (0R+0G+0B) produces complete darkness,
        black, and that full light (255R+255G+255B) produces white. Equal
        intensity on all color channels produces a level of gray. That is why
        there can only be 256 gray levels in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        Mixing two <emphasis>Primary colors</emphasis> in RGB mode
        gives a <emphasis>Secondary color</emphasis>, that is, a
        color in the CMY model. Thus combining Red and Green gives
        Yellow, Green and Blue give Cyan, Blue and Red give Magenta.
        Don't confuse secondary colors with
        <emphasis>Complementary colors</emphasis> which are
        directly opposite a primary color in the chromatic
        circle:
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <figure float="0">
        <title>
          <phrase>Colorcircle</phrase>
          
          
          
          
          
        </title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/glossary/colorcircle.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>

          <caption>
            <para>
              Mixing a primary color with its complementary color gives gray
              (a neutral color).
            </para>
            
            
            
            
            
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        It is important to know what happens when you are dealing with colors
        in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
        The most important rule to remember is that decreasing the intensity
        of a primary color results in increasing the intensity of the
        complementary color (and vice versa). This is because when you
        decrease the value of a channel, for instance Green, you automatically
        increase the relative importance of the other two, here Red and Blue.
        The combination of these two channels gives the secondary color,
        Magenta, which is the complementary color of Green.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        <emphasis>Exercise</emphasis>
        : You can check this out. Create a new image with only a white
        background (255R+255G+255B). Open the
        <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
          <guimenu moreinfo="none">Tools</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Color Tools</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Levels</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        dialog and select the Red channel. If necessary, check the preview
        box. Move the white slider to the left to decrease the Red value. You
        will notice that the background of your image gets closer and closer
        to Cyan. Now, decrease the Blue channel: only the Green will remain.
        For practice, go backwards, add a color and try to guess what hue will
        appear.
      </para>
      <!-- TODO: de  add this paragraph!?
      <para lang="de">
      </para>
      -->
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        The <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link>
        tool lets you find out the RGB values of a pixel and the
        <link linkend="glossary-html-notation">hextriplet</link>
        for the color.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-rendering-intent">
    <glossterm>Rendering Intent</glossterm>
    
     <!-- it MARK: see glossterm "Intento di rendering" -->
     <!-- no MARK: see glossterm "Fargetilpassing" -->

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Color Management</primary></indexterm>
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Rendering intents are ways of dealing with colors that are
        out-of-<xref linkend="glossary-gamut"/> colors present in the source
        space that the destination space is incapable of producing. There are
        four rendering intents defined by the ICC:
      </para>
      
      

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Perceptual</term>
          
          

          <listitem>
            <para>
              This rendering intent is typically used for photographic
              content. It scales one gamut to fit into the other while
              maintaining the relative position of colors.
            </para>
            
            
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Relative colorimetric</term>
          
          

          <listitem>
            <para>
              This rendering intent is typically used for spot colors. Colors
              that are not out of gamut are left unchanged. Colors outside the
              gamut are converted to colors with the same lightness, but
              different saturation, at the edge of the gamut.
            </para>
            
            
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Saturation</term>
          
          

          <listitem>
            <para>
              This method is typically used for business graphics. The
              relative saturation of colors is mostly maintained, but
              lightning is usually changed.
            </para>
            
            
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Absolute colorimetric</term>
          
          

          <listitem>
            <para>
              This rendering intent is most often used in proofing. It
              preserves the native device white point of the source image.
            </para>
            
            
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  

</glossdiv>
