<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-25 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-06-30 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-23 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;ko;it;no;zh_CN">
  <title>S</title>
  
  <glossentry id="glossary-samplemerge" lang="cs;de;en;ko;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="cs">Sloučený vzorek</phrase>
      <phrase lang="en">Sample Merge</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Vereinigung abtasten</phrase>
      <!-- es MARK: see phrase "Muestreo, unión de"-->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossentry "Échantillonner sur tous les calques" -->
      <!-- it MARK: see phrase "Campionamento diffuso" -->
      <phrase lang="ko">표본 합치기(Sample Merge)</phrase>
      <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Markeringsfletting" -->
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Sample Merge(位样合并)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Funkce některých nástrojů, například plechovky, závisí na barevnosti
        pixelů ve vrstvě, na kterou je nástroj použit. V případě, že je však
        použita funkce sloučený vzorek, však nástroj využívá barevná data ze
        všech vrstev, tak jak jsou viditelná (tedy bere například v úvahu
        prosvítající pixely z vrstvy umístěné níže).
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Sample Merged is an option you can set when you use the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket Fill</link> tool, the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link> tool and
        various selection tools. It is useful when you are working on an
        image with several layers and the active layer is either
        semi-transparent or has a
        <link linkend="glossary-modes">Layer Mode</link> which is not set
        to Normal. When you check the Sample Merged option, the color which
        is used for the operation is the composite color of all the visible
        layers. When the Sample Merged option is not checked, the color used
        is the color of the active layer itself.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        <guilabel>Vereinigung abtasten</guilabel> ist eine nützlich wenn
        Sie mit mehr als einer Ebene arbeiten und Pixelinformationen der
        anderen Ebenen mit hinzuziehen wollen.  Beispielsweise kann die
        Farbe eines Pixels von einer aktuellen Ebene gemessen werden,
        oder unter Hinzunahme von <emphasis>Vereinigung
        abtasten</emphasis> die gemischte Farbe aller darunter liegender
        Ebenen gemessen werden.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        표본 합치기는 하나 이상의 레이어에 효과를 미치는 작업에 유용한 
        기술이다. 이는 보이는 모든 레이어에 대한 색상 및 픽셀 정보를 얻을 
        수 있다. 색깔에 의한 선택과 같은 예처럼 이 기능은 상당히 유용하다.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        位样合并是一种针对多图层的，影响所有可见图层而不是一个图层上颜色或像
        素信息的技术。可以想象下比如在按颜色选择中该功能是多么有用。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-fileformat-cs" lang="cs">
    <glossterm>Souborový formát</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Způsob zápisu dat, v našem případě obrázku. Existuje řada různých
        souborových formátů pro zápis obrázků z Gimpu. Mají různé vlastnosti,
        výhody a nevýhody, proto je důležité zvolit vhodný formát podle
        situace a určení obrázku. Příkladem obrazových souborových formátů je
        JPEG, PNG nebo XCF.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-supersampling" lang="cs;de;en;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="cs">Supersampling</phrase>
      <phrase lang="de">Supersampling</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see also glossentry "Hochrechnung (Anpassende)" -->
      <phrase lang="en">Supersampling</phrase>
      <phrase lang="es">Supermuestreo</phrase>
      <phrase lang="fr">Suréchantillonnage</phrase>
      <phrase lang="it">Supercampionamento</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ko">슈퍼샘플링(Supersampling)</phrase>
      <phrase lang="no">Superutjamning</phrase>
      <phrase lang="zh_CN">Supersampling(超级采样)</phrase>
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">
        Technika vylepšující kvalitu vykreslování.<!-- FIXME: cs -->
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Mit dieser Technik verwendet <acronym>GIMP</acronym> mehr Pixel
        zur Berechnung eines
        Farbübergangs, zum Beispiel für eine Interpolation. Diese Technik
        führt zu sehr guten Ergebnissen, erfordert allerdings mehr
        Rechenaufwand und damit eine längere Zeit zur Berechnung.
      </para>
      
      <para lang="en">
        Supersampling is a more sophisticated antialiasing technique, that
        is, a method of reducing jagged and stair-stepped edges along a
        slanted or curved line. Samples are taken at several locations
        <emphasis>within</emphasis> each pixel, not just at the center, and
        an average color is calculated. This is done by rendering the image
        at a much higher resolution than the one being displayed and then
        shrinking it to the desired size, using the extra pixels for
        calculation. The result is a smoother transition from one line of
        pixels to another along the edges of objects.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The quality of the result depends on the number of samples.
        Supersampling is often performed at a range of 2× to 16× the
        original size. It greatly increases the amount of time needed to
        draw the image and also the amount of space needed to store the
        image in memory.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One way to reduce the space and time requirement is to use Adaptive
        Supersampling. This method takes advantage of the fact that very few
        pixels are actually on an object boundary, so only those pixels need
        to be supersampled. At first, only a few samples are taken within a
        pixel. If the colors are very similar to each other, only those
        samples are used to calculate the final color. If not, more samples
        are used. This means that the higher number of samples is calculated
        only where necessary, which improves performance.
      </para>

      <para lang="es">
        Utilizando esta técnica el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> toma más
        pixeles de alrededor para calcular un nuevo color, por ejemplo
        para hacer interpolación.  El resultado es mejor pero toma más
        tiempo.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Avec cette technique, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> utilise plus de
        pixels aux alentours pour
        calculer une couleur de transition, par exemple lors d'une
        interpolation. Le rendu est meilleur mais le temps de traitement est
        allongé.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Con questa tecnica <acronym>GIMP</acronym> preleva più pixel attorno
        per calcolare un
        colore di transizione come prova di iterpolazione. Il risultato è
        migliore ma l'elaborazione risulta più lunga.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이 기술은 김프로 하여금 보간법보다 더 많은 주변의 픽셀들을 가지고
        변할 색을 계산하는 것이다. 화질은 좋아지는 대신 조금 더 많은 시간을
        필요로 한다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Som <link linkend="glossary-samplemerge-no">Markeringsfletting</link>,
        markeringsfletting, men nå bruker <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        opplysningar frå fleire pikslar for eksempel ved interpolering.
        Resultatet blir betre enn med markeringsfletting, men tar meir tid.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        GIMP 使用该技术处理多个像素从而产生过渡的颜色(比如在插值中使用)。虽
        然用绘制效果更好，但要花更多时间。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  

  <glossentry lang="fr" id="glossary-floatingselection-fr">
    <glossterm lang="fr">Sélection Flottante</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les sélections flottantes peuvent être assimilées à des calques sauf
        que les sélections flottantes doivent être ancrées avant que l'on
        puisse travailler sur tout autre calque de l'image. Tant qu'une
        sélection est flottante toutes les fonctions appliquées pour modifier
        les données de l'image agiront sur la sélection. Il y a 2 méthodes
        pour ancrer une sélection flottante. La première, qui est aussi la
        plus utilisée, est de transformer la sélection flottante en un nouveau
        calque. Cela se fait en créant un nouveau calque pendant que la
        sélection flottante est active. La seconde méthode consiste à ancrer
        la sélection flottante dans un calque existant. Cela se fait en
        cliquant dans l'image en dehors de la sélection. Ainsi, la sélection
        est fondue dans le calque d'arrière plan.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Tout objet collé sera d'abord affiché en tant que sélection flottante.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
