<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-04-26 jh : created SVG entry en;fr
  2007-02-06 alessandro falappa: updated supersampling section
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-25 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-06-30 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-23 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-15 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>S</title><anchor id="glossary-s"/>

  <glossentry id="glossary-samplemerge">
    <glossterm>
      
      <phrase>Sample Merge</phrase>
      <!-- de MARK: see glossentry "Vereinigung prüfen"-->
      <!-- es MARK: see phrase "Muestreo, unión de"-->
      <!-- fr MARK: see glossentry "Échantillonner sur tous les calques" -->
      <!-- it MARK: see phrase "Campionamento diffuso" -->
      
      <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Utvalsfletting" -->
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      
      <para>
        Sample Merged is an option you can set when you use the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket Fill</link>
        tool, the <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link>
        tool and various selection tools. It is useful when you are working on
        an image with several layers and the active layer is either
        semi-transparent or has a
        <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Layer Mode</link>
        which is not set to Normal. When you check the Sample Merged option,
        the color which is used for the operation is the composite color of
        all the visible layers. When the Sample Merged option is not checked,
        the color used is the color of the active layer itself.
      </para>
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-saturation">
    <!--TODO cs es nl ru-->
    <glossterm>Saturation</glossterm>
    
    
    <!-- no MARK: see glossentry "Fargemetning" -->
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Saturation</primary></indexterm>
    
    
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Saturation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        This term refers to color purity. Imagine you add pigment to white
        paint. Saturation varies from 0 (white, fully toned down, fully
        diluted) to 100 (pure color).
      </para>
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  


  


  <glossentry id="glossary-supersampling">
    <glossterm>
      
      
      <!-- de MARK: see also glossentry "Hochrechnung" -->
      <phrase>Supersampling</phrase>
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Supersampling</primary></indexterm>
    
    
    
    
    
    

  <!-- FIXME cs es ko zh_CN: update translations -->
  <glossdef>
    <para>
      Supersampling is a more sophisticated antialiasing technique, that
      is, a method of reducing jagged and stair-stepped edges along a
      slanted or curved line. Samples are taken at several locations
      <emphasis>within</emphasis> each pixel, not just at the center, and
      an average color is calculated. This is done by rendering the image
      at a much higher resolution than the one being displayed and then
      shrinking it to the desired size, using the extra pixels for
      calculation. The result is a smoother transition from one line of
      pixels to another along the edges of objects.
    </para>
    <para>
      The quality of the result depends on the number of samples.
      Supersampling is often performed at a range of 2× to 16× the original
      size. It greatly increases the amount of time needed to draw the image
      and also the amount of space needed to store the image in memory.
    </para>
    <para>
      One way to reduce the space and time requirement is to use Adaptive
      Supersampling. This method takes advantage of the fact that very few
      pixels are actually on an object boundary, so only those pixels need to
      be supersampled. At first, only a few samples are taken within a pixel.
      If the colors are very similar to each other, only those samples are
      used to calculate the final color. If not, more samples are used. This
      means that the higher number of samples is calculated only where
      necessary, which improves performance.
    </para>

    
    
    

    
    
    

    
    
    
    
    
    
    

    
  </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  

  

  <!--TODO cs;es;ko;zh_CN: glossentry SVG-->
  <glossentry id="glossary-svg">
    <glossterm>SVG</glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>SVG</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>SVG</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        SVG stands for Scalable Vector Graphics. It a format for
        two-dimensional vector graphics, both static and animated. You can
        export GIMP paths to SVG and you can import SVG documents into GIMP
        from a vector graphic software. See
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-svg"/> for more details.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
