<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2006-09-20 scb: added tile; translated to fr by j.h
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-27 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-06-29 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-24 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>T</title><anchor id="glossary-t"/>

  <glossentry id="file-tga-save">
    <glossterm>TGA
      <anchor id="file-tga-load"/>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>TGA</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>TARGA</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>TGA</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      
      <para>
        TGA (TARGA Image File) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which
        supports 8, 16, 24 or 32 bits per pixel and optional RLE compression.
        It was originally developed by the Truevision company.
        <quote>TGA</quote> stands for Truevision Graphics Adapter and
        <quote>TARGA</quote> stands for Truevision Advanced Raster Graphics
        Adapter.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-tiff">
    <glossterm>TIFF
      <anchor id="file-tiff-load"/>
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>TIFF</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      
      <para>
        TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which was
        developed primarily for scanned
        raster graphics for color separation. Six different encoding routines
        are supported, each with one of three different image modes: black and
        white, grayscale and color. Uncompressed TIFF images may be 1, 4, 8 or
        24 bits per pixel. TIFF images compressed using the LZW algorithm may
        be 6, 8 or 24 bits per pixel. Besides Postscript format, TIFF is one
        of the most important formats for preliminary stages of printing. It
        is a high quality file format, which is perfect for images you want to
        import to other programs like FrameMaker or CorelDRAW.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <!-- FIXME cs es ko nl no ru sv zh_CN  translate glossary-tile -->
  <glossentry id="glossary-tile"> <!--added 060920-->
    <glossterm>Tile</glossterm>
    
    <!-- de MARK: see glossentry "Kachel" -->
    <!-- it MARK: see glossentry "Piastrella" -->

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A Tile is a part of an image which <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        currently has open. In order to avoid having to store an
        entire image in memory at the same time,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> divides it into smaller pieces.
        A tile is usually a square of 64 x 64 pixels, although tiles at
        the edges of an image may be smaller than that.
      </para>
      <para>
        At any time, a tile may be in main memory, in the tile cache
        in RAM, or on disk. Tiles which are currently being worked on are
        in main memory. Tiles which have been used recently are in RAM.
        When the tile cache in RAM is full, tiles which have been used
        least recently are written to disk. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        can retrieve the tiles from RAM or disk when they are needed.
      </para>
      <para>
        Do not confuse these tiles with those in the
        <link linkend="plug-in-tile">Tile Filter</link>
      </para>

      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  


  


  

</glossdiv>
