<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-09-20 scb: added tile; translated to fr by j.h
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-27 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-06-29 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-24 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-08 norwegian added by kolbjørn
  050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title>T</title>

  <glossentry id="file-tga-save" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>TGA
      <anchor id="file-tga-load" />
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>TGA</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>TARGA</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">Targa je souborový formát pro ukládání obrázků.</para>
      <para lang="en">
        TGA (TARGA Image File) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which
        supports 8, 16, 24 or 32 bits per pixel and optional RLE compression.
        It was originally developed by the Truevision company.
        <quote>TGA</quote> stands for Truevision Graphics Adapter and
        <quote>TARGA</quote> stands for Truevision Advanced Raster Graphics
        Adapter.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Das TGA (Targa Image File) ist ein Dateiformat, welches eine
        Kompression von 8, 16, 24 und 32 Bits je Pixel unterstützt. Es wurde
        ursprünglich von der Firma Truevision entwickelt.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        El formato de archivo Targa admite compresión a 8, 16, 24 o 32 bits
        por pixel.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le format de fichier TGA, ou Targa, permet un encodage  8,16, 24 ou
        32 bits des pixels et une compression RLE optionnelle.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Il formato file Targa supporta compressioni a 8, 16, 24 o 32 bit per
        pixel.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">Targa 파일 포맷은 픽셀당 8, 16, 24, 32 비트의 압축을 지원한다.</para>
      <para lang="no">
        TGA (Targa Image File) er eit filformat med støtte for 8, 16, 24 og 32
        bits per piksel. Opphavleg utvikla av firmaet Truevision.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">Targe 文件格式支持每像素 8，16 或 32 位压缩。</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-tiff" lang="en;cs;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>TIFF
      <anchor id="file-tiff-load" />
      <anchor id="file-tiff-save" />
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>TIFF</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="cs">Standardní grafický souborový formát.</para>
      <para lang="en">
        TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which was
        developed primarily for scanned
        raster graphics for color separation. Six different encoding routines
        are supported, each with one of three different image modes: black and
        white, grayscale and color. Uncompressed TIFF images may be 1, 4, 8 or
        24 bits per pixel. TIFF images compressed using the LZW algorithm may
        be 6, 8 or 24 bits per pixel. Besides Postscript format, TIFF is one
        of the most important formats for preliminary stages of printing. It
        is a high quality file format, which is perfect for images you want to
        import to other programs like FrameMaker or CorelDRAW.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Das Dateiformat TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) wurde vor allem für
        gescannte Rastergrafiken für die Farbseparation entwickelt. Sechs
        verschiedene Kodierungsarten werden unterstützt, wobei jede nochmals
        verschiedene Bildmodi unterstützen: Schwarz/Weiß, Graustufen und
        Echtfarben. TIFF ist neben dem Postscript-Format eines der wichtigen
        Formate für die Druckvorstufe.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Diseñado para convertirse en estándar, los archivos TIFF (Tagged Image
        File Format) vienen de muy variadas formas. Hay seis rutinas de
        codificación diferentes, cada una con tres modos de imagen: blanco y
        negro, escala de grises, y color. Las imágenes TIFF sin comprimir
        pueden ser de 1, 4, 8 o 24 bits por pixel. Las imágenes TIFF
        comprimidas que utilizan el algoritmo LZW pueden ser de 6, 8 o 24 bits
        por pixel. Este es un formato de alta calidad, perfecto para imágenes
        que se quieran importar a otros programas como FrameMaker o CorelDRAW.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Destiné à devenir un standard, le format TIFF (Tagged Image File
        Format) se présente avec différentes nuances. Ce format gère six
        routines d'encodage, chacune ayant trois modes d'images possibles:
        noir et blanc, niveaux de gris et couleur. Les images TIFF non
        comprimées peuvent avoir des pixels de 1, 4, 8 ou 24 bits. Les images
        TIFF comprimées avec l'algorithme LZW ont 6, 8, ou 24 bits par pixel.
        C'est un format de haute qualité, parfait pour les images que vous
        voulez importer dans d'autres programmes tels FrameMaker ou
        CorelDRAW.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Progettato per essere uno standard di riferimento i file in formato
        TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) sono di molti tipi differenti. Sei
        tipi di algoritmi di codifica supportati, ognuno dei quali con tre
        differenti possibilità di modalità immagine: bianco e nero, in scala
        di grigi e a colori. Le immagini TIFF non compresse possono essere di
        1, 4, 8 o 24 bit per pixel. Le immagini TIFF compresse usano
        l'algoritmo di compressione LZW possono essere di 6, 8 o 24 bit per
        pixel. Questo è un formato di file immagine di alta qualità, perfetto
        per esportare immagini ad altri programmi come FrameMaker o CorelDRAW.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        표준 TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) 은 다양한 특성을 가진다. 여섯 개의 인코딩 방법을 지원하며,
        각각 검정과 흰색, 그레이스케일, 색상 등 3가지의 이미지 모드를 지원한다. 비압축 TIFF 이미지는 픽셀당 1, 4, 8,
        24 비트를 사용할 수 있다. 이는 굉장히 높은 화질의 파일 포맷으로 FrameMaker 이나 CorelDRAW 등의 다른
        프로그램으로 보내는데 아주 좋다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) var eigentleg meint å vere eit
        standardformat for lagring av skanna biletfiler med full
        fargeseparasjon. Etter kvart har det utvikla seg fleire ulike format
        av TIFF, kvart av desse med tre ulike modus: Svart/kvit, gråskala og
        farge. Ukomprimerte TIFF-bilete kan ha 1, 4, 8 eller 24 bits per
        piksel. Komprimerte TIFF-bilete 6, 8 eller 24 bits per piksel. TIFF
        gir svært gode biletfiler, og er mykje brukt for bilete som skal
        trykkast profesjonelt. Formatet er også godt eigna for å overføra
        bilete til andre biletbehandlingsprogram.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        作为一个标准，TIFF 文件有多种选择。支持六种不同的编码标准，而每一种 都有三种不同的图像模式：黑白，灰度和彩色。非压缩 TIFF
        图像每像素可以 是 1，4，8 或 24 位。TIFF 压缩则使用 LZW 算法可以是 6，8 或 24 位每
        像素。这是一种高质量的图像格式，可以完美地导入到其它程序如 FrameMaker 或 CorelDRAW。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <!-- FIXME to translate -->
  <glossentry id="glossary-tile" lang="en"> <!--added 060920-->
    <glossterm lang="en">Tile</glossterm>
    <!-- it MARK: see glossentry "Piastrella" -->
    
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A Tile is a part of an image which <application>GIMP</application>
        currently has open. In order to avoid having to store an
        entire image in memory at the same time,
        <application>GIMP</application> divides it into smaller pieces.
        A tile is usually a square of 64 x 64 pixels, although tiles at
        the edges of an image may be smaller than that.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        At any time, a tile may be in main memory, in the tile cache
        in RAM, or on disk. Tiles which are currently being worked on are
        in main memory. Tiles which have been used recently are in RAM.
        When the tile cache in RAM is full, tiles which have been used
        least recently are written to disk. <application>GIMP</application>
        can retrieve the tiles from RAM or disk when they are needed.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Do not confuse these tiles with those in the
        <link linkend="plug-in-tile">Tile Filter</link>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-path" lang="it">
    <glossterm lang="it">Tracciati</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="it">
        Un <emphasis>tracciato</emphasis>
        è una linea monodimensionale curva, poligonale o mista o un insieme di
        segmenti con tali caratteristiche. In
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, l'uso principale dei
        tracciati è sia per creare dei limiti alle selezioni che per
        <emphasis>tratteggiare</emphasis>
        curve con grande precisione su di un'immagine. Vedere la sezione
        <link linkend="gimp-concepts-paths">Tracciati</link>
        per un'informazione basilare su questo argomento e la sezione
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Strumento tracciati</link>
        per apprendere come come crearli e modificarli.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-dithering-fr" lang="fr">
    <glossterm lang="fr">Tramage</glossterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Principe mathématique permettant d'afficher une image avec peu de
        couleurs comme s'il y en avait beaucoup. Cette opération peut-être
        exécutée de différentes manières selon le périphérique de sortie et le
        programme. L'une des techniques consiste à mélanger des pixels de
        couleur pour simuler une autre couleur. C'est ce que l'oeil humain à
        tendance à faire lorsqu'il observe des motifs colorés et complexes.
        L'écran de télévision et les journaux utilisent ce principe - de loin
        l'image semble être composée d'une multitude de couleurs ou de nuances
        de gris, mais de près ce n'est plus du tout le cas. Une télévision
        couleur n'utilise que 3 couleurs mélangées dans diverses combinaisons.
        Un journal noir et blanc n'utilise que l'encre noire alors que les
        photos y apparaissent en tons de gris. Il existe des techniques plus
        perfectionnées donnant de meilleurs résultats.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> peut utiliser la technique de tramage
        couleur de Floyd-Steinberg
        par exemple. Cette méthode est simplement une technique mathématique
        de mélange de pixels qui donne de meilleurs résultats que d'autres
        méthodes. Bien sûr, il existe des exceptions et il existe bien
        d'autres techniques utilisées de nos jours.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        L'outil Dégradé utilise le tramage. Vous pouvez choisir le tramage
        quand vous créez une image indexée
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry lang="fr" id="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering-fr">
    <glossterm lang="fr">Tramage couleur de Floyd-Steinberg</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="fr">
        Cette méthode cherche les couleurs de la palette les plus proches de
        celle du pixel courant. Ces couleurs sont alors réparties sur les
        pixels juste en dessous et à droite du pixel originel.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

</glossdiv>
