<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-05-24 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-08-01 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
  <title>X</title>

  <anchor id="gimp-xcf-open" />
  <anchor id="gimp-file-open-xcf" />
  <anchor id="gimp-file-save-xcf" />

  <glossentry id="gimp-xcf-save" lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;it;ko;no;zh_CN">
    <glossterm>XCF</glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>XCF</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        XCF is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which is
        special because it is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
        native file format: that is, it was designed specifically to store all
        of the data that goes to make up a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image.
        Because of this, XCF files may be quite complicated, and there are
        few programs other than <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that can read them.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        XCF je nativní souborový formát GIMPu, to znamená, že byl navržen
        pro uložení <emphasis>všech dat</emphasis>, která tvoří obrázek
        v GIMPu. Je to proto ideální formát pro ukládání rozpracovaných
        obrázků (běžnější souborové formáty většinou nezachovají složitější
        struktury v obrázku, například vrstvy). Jeho nevýhodou je naopak to,
        že kvůli jeho složitosti ho kromě GIMPu umí zpracovat jen velmi málo
        dalších programů.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        XCF ist das <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigene Dateiformat;
        entwickelt um alle <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigenen Informationen
        zu speichern.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        El tipo de archivo XCF es especial porque es el formato nativo
        del <acronym>GIMP</acronym>: esto es, fue diseñado
        específicamente para guardar todos los datos que puede tener
        una imagen del <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Por esto, los
        archivos XCF pueden ser un poco complicados, y hay unos pocos
        programas sin contar el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> que pueden
        leerlos.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le type de fichier XCF est spécial: c'est le format natif de
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> et il est spécifiquement destiné à conserver
        toutes les données dont <acronym>GIMP</acronym> a besoin pour créer
        une image. Rares sont les programmes autres que
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> capables de le lire.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Il tipo file XCF è un tipo speciale dato che è il file nativo di
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>: cioè è stato specificatamente progettato
        per memorizzare tutte le informazioni che compongono un'immagine di
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Per questa ragione i file in formato XCF
        possono essere molto complessi e ci sono pochi programmi, a parte
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, che sono in grado di leggerli.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        XCF 파일 형식은 김프 전용 파일 형식이다. 이는 김프로 작업한
        이미지의 모든 정보를 저장할 수 있도록 설계되었다. 따라서 XCF 파일은
        상당히 복잡하며 김프외의 몇가지 프로그램만이 이 포맷을 읽을 수
        있다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dette er <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt eige format for biletfiler,
        laga spesielt for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Formatet blir støtta av
        få andre program, om noen i det heile.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        XCF 文件格式比较特殊因为它是 GIMP 的内部格式：也就是，它被专用来保存
        GIMP 图像中所用数据。所以 XCF 文件可能比较复杂，很少有其它程序能够读
        取它。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        When an image is stored as an XCF file, the file encodes nearly
        everything there is to know about the image:  the pixel data for
        each of the layers, the current selection, additional channels
        if there are any, paths if there are any, and guides.  The most
        important thing that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> saved in an XCF
        file is the undo history.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Uložením obrázku do XCF souboru zachováte téměř všechny informace,
        které jsou o obrázku známé: obrazová data všech vrstev, aktuální
        výběr, případné další kanály, cesty a vodítka. Nejpodstatnější
        informace, která se do souboru ve formátu XCF
        <emphasis>neukládá</emphasis>, je historie změn (Vrátit/Znovu).
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Wenn <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ein Bild als XCF speichert, werden
        alle Informationen zum Bild abgespeichert: Pixeldaten für jede
        Ebene, aktuelle Auswahlen, zusätzliche Kanäle, Pfade und vieles
        mehr. Die Informationen zum Rückgängig machen von Operationen
        werden jedoch nicht gespeichert.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Cuando una imagen es guardada como archivo XCF, en el archivo
        se codifica todo lo que se conoce de la misma: los datos de
        pixeles de cada capa, la selección actual, canales adicionales
        si es que los hay, rutas si hay alguna, y guías.  La única
        cosa importante que <emphasis>no</emphasis> se guarda en un
        archivo XCF es el historial de deshacer.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Quand une image est enregistrée au format .xcf, le fichier encode
        toutes les données de l'image: les calques, les chemins, les
        sélections, les guides...etc. La seule chose qu'il NE conserve PAS est
        l'Historique d'Annulation.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Quando un'immagine viene memorizzata in un file XCF, il file codifica
        quasi ogni informazione riguardante l'immagine: i pixel che compongono
        ogni livello, la selezione corrente, i canali aggiuntivi se ne
        esistono, i tracciati se esistono e le guide. La cosa più importante
        che <emphasis>non</emphasis>
        viene salvata in un file in formato XCF è la cronologia degli
        annullamenti.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        이미지를 XCF 파일로 저장을 하면, 파일은 각 레이어의 픽셀 데이터,
        현재 선택, 추가된 채널, 경로, 안내선 등 이미지에 대한 거의 모든
        정보를 저장하게 된다. 단, 실행 취소 이력은
        <emphasis>저장하지 않는다.</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Når eit bilete blir lagra i XCF-format, blir omtrent alt som finst
        i biletet lagra: data for kvart av laga, den aktive markeringa,
        kanalar, banar, hjelpelinjer osv. Det viktigaste som
        <emphasis>ikkje</emphasis> blir lagra er opplysningane om
        angreloggen.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        当一个图像被保存为 XCF 文件，文件编码几乎包括了解图像所需的所有信息：
        各个图层中的像素数据，当前选区，附加通道，路径和参考线。<emphasis>没
        有</emphasis>保存在一个 XCF 文件中最重要的东西是撤消历史。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The pixel data in an XCF file is represented
        in a lossless compressed form: the image byte blocks are compressed
        using the lossless RLE algorithm. This means that no matter how many
        times you load and save an image using this format, not a single
        pixel or other image data is lost or modified because of this format.
        XCF files can become very large, however <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        allows you to compress the files themselves, using either the gzip
        or bzip2 compression methods, both of which are fast, efficient, and
        freely available. Compressing an XCF file will often shrink it by a
        factor of 10 or more.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs"> <!-- FIXME -->
        Rastrová obrazová data (údaje o jednotlivých pixelech) jsou ve formátu
        XCF komprimována neztrátovou RLE kompresí, která je u obrázků
        obsahujících hodně barevné informace neefektivní; proto mohou být XCF
        soubory velmi velké. Například RGB obrázek o rozměrech 1000×1000
        pixelů a třech vrstvách může mít přes 10 megabajtů. V praxi nejsou
        vzácné XCF soubory větší než 100 megabajtů.
      </para>
      <para lang="de"> <!--FIXME -->
        Pixeldaten werden in unkomprimierter Form gespeichert: jedes Byte der
        Bildaten is gleich jedem Byte der Datei. Somit können XCF Dateien, in
        Abhängigkeit der Bildgröße in Pixel, verwendetem Farbraum und
        verwendeten Ebenen, sehr groß werden. Beispielsweise ein 1000x1000
        Pixel grosses Bild im RGB Format mit drei Kanälen kann ein
        abgespeichertes XCF mit 100 Megabyte ergeben. Um die Dateigrössen
        dennoch etwas zu verkleinen, ist es möglich externe programme zum
        Komprimieren der Daten zu verwenden. Hierfür kann GZIP oder BZIP2
        benutzt werden, welche schnell, effizient und frei verfügbar sind.
        Durch die Benutzung dieser Kompressionsprogramme werden die
        Dateigrößen meist um den Faktor 10 verringert.
      </para>
      <para lang="es"> <!--FIXME -->
        Los datos de pixeles en un archivo XCF son representados en
        forma cruda, sin comprimir: cada byte de la imagen equivale a
        un byte en el archivo XCF.  Por esto, incluso los archivos XCF
        de imágenes modestamente pequeñas pueden ser bastante grandes:
        por ejemplo, una imagen RGB de 1000x1000 con tres capas
        producirá un archivo XCF de más de 10 megabytes.  No es para
        nada fantástico obtener archivos XCF de más de 100 megabytes.
        Afortunadamente, aunque los archivos XCF no comprimen los
        datos, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> permite comprimir los archivos
        mismos, usando los métodos gzip o bzip2.  Ambos son rápidos,
        eficientes, y libremente disponibles.  Usualmente al comprimir
        un archivo XCF se reduce su tamaño por un factor de 10 o más.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les fichiers .xcf sont comprimés sans perte grâce à l'algorithme RLE.
        Vous pouvez les enregistrer aussi souvent que vous le voulez sans que
        cela détériore l'image. Malgré tout, une image RVB de 1000x1000 pixels
        avec 3 calques produira un fichier XCF de 10 Mo et vous pouvez
        facilement obtenir des fichiers de plus de 100Mo. Heureusement, vous
        pouvez les comprimer en utilisant gzip ou bzip2 qui sont des méthodes
        très efficaces et disponibles gratuitement. Le fait de comprimer un
        fichier XCF peut le réduire d'un facteur 10 ou plus.
      </para>
      <para lang="it"><!-- it FIXME: -->
        I dati immagine in un file XCF sono rappresentati in formato compresso
        senza perdite: l'algoritmo di compressione utilizzato è di tipo RLE.
        Ciò significa che non è importante quante volte un'immagine viene
        scritta e riletta da disco: non verrà perso neanche un pixel o un dato
        dell'immagine a causa del formato utilizzato.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        <!-- FIXME: ko Someone said
          "This is not true, RLE compression is used in XCF. I have rewritten
          it in the Czech version already" So please translate that to
          English.p
        -->
        XCF의 픽셀 데이터는 비압축 상태로 표현된다. 이미지의 각 바이트는 XCF 파일의 각 바이트와 일치한다. 따라서 XCF
        파일은 다소 큰 편이다. 예를 들어 세 개의 레이러를 가진 1000x1000 사이즈의 RGB 이미지를 XCF로 저장하면 10
        메가바이트가 된다. 100 메가바이트 이상의 XCF 파일이 만들어지는 것또한 놀라운 일은 아니다. 다행스럽게도, XCF 파일이
        기본적으로 데이터를 압축하지 않는 대신, 김프를 통해 이들을 gzip 이나 bzip2 로 압축할 수 있다. 이 두 압축 방법은
        상당히 빠르고, 효율적이며, 자유롭게 사용할 수 있다. 압축된 XCF 파일은 그 크기가 1/10 이하로 줄어든다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no"> <!-- FIXME: no -->
        <!-- FIXME: no This is not true, RLE compression is used in XCF. I have
          rewritten it in the Czech version already. Somebody
          translating it to english?
        -->
        Pikseldata blir lagra i rå og ukomprimert form. Difor kan XCF-filene
        sjølv for eit enkelt lite bilete bli nokså store. Eit 1000 × 1000
        piksels bilete i RGB-format med tre lag vil lage ei XCF-fil på over
        100 mb. Det er heller ikkje vanskeleg å få filer på over 100 mb. Har
        du behov for det, kan du komprimera XCF-filene med eit eller anna
        komprimeringsprogram, t.d. gzip eller bzip2, som er fritt
        tilgjengelege. Slike program kan ofte komprimera filene med ein faktor
        på 10 eller meir.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN"> <!-- FIXME -->
        一个 XCF 文件中的像素信息保存为一种未加工的，非压缩的形式：所以 XCF
        文件常常比较大：比如，一个 1000x1000 的带3个图层的 RGB 图像将生成大
        于 10 兆的 XCF 文件。要产生于大于 100 兆的 XCF 文件也不难。幸运的是，
        虽然 XCF 文件本身不支持压缩其数据，但 GIMP 允许您自己用 gzip 或
        bzip2(都快速而有效，并且可免费获得)压缩方式来压缩文件。压缩一个 XCF
        文件通常能减少 10 倍或更多。
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developers have made a great effort to
        keep the XCF file format compatible across versions. If you create a
        file using <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0, it ought to be possible to
        open the file in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2. However, some of the
        information in the file may not be usable: for example,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 has a much more sophisticated way of
        handling text than <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, so a text layer
        from a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 XCF file will appear as an
        ordinary image layer if the file is opened in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
      </para>
      <para lang="cs">
        Vývojáři GIMPu se velmi snaží, aby zachovali kompatibilitu XCF formátu
        mezi jednotlivými verzemi. Pokud vytvoříte XCF soubor v GIMPu 2.2,
        mělo by být možné otevřít ho i GIMPem 1.2. Nicméně část informací
        nemusí být ve staré verzi použitelná; GIMP 2.2 má například mnohem
        pokročilejší možnosti práce s textem, takže textová vrstva Gimpu 2.2
        se v Gimpu zobrazí jako obyčejná vrstva obrázku.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Entwickler haben sich viel Mühe
        gegeben, das Format in jeder (älteren) <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        Version lesbar zu halten. Jedoch steht einiges der neuen
        Funktionalität in älteren <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Versionen
        nicht mehr zur Verfügung, wie z.B. Textebenen. Solche speziellen
        Informationen werden einfach als normale Ebene importiert.
      </para>
      <para lang="es">
        Los desarrolladores del <acronym>GIMP</acronym> han hecho un
        gran esfuerzo en mantener los archivos XCF compatibles entre
        versiones.  Si creas un archivo usando <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        2.0, será posible abrirlo con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2. De
        todas formas, algo de la información del archivo no será
        disponible: por ejemplo, el manejo del texto en la versión 2-0
        es mucho más sofisticado que en la versión 1.2, así que una
        capa de texto desde la nueva versión a la antigüa aparecerá
        como una capa de imagen ordinaria.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les développeurs de <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ont fait de gros efforts
        pour garder à XCF une compatibilité avec les versions antérieures de
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Toutefois, certaines informations peuvent
        être perdues. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 a ainsi une gestion
        perfectionnée des textes, et, dans <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, un
        calque texte provenant de 2.0 apparaîtra comme une image ordinaire.
      </para>
      <para lang="it">
        Gli sviluppatori di <acronym>GIMP</acronym> hanno fatto un grande
        sforzo per mantenere il formato XCF compatibile attraverso le
        versioni. Se si crea un file usando <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0
        dovrebbe essere ancora possibile aprire il file con
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2. Comunque, alcune informazioni nel file
        saranno inutilizzabili: per esempio <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0
        possiede un metodo di gestione del testo molto più sofisticato di
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, perciò un livello di testo proveniente
        da un file immagine scritto da <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 apparirà
        semplicemente come un normale livello immagine una volta aperto con
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
      </para>
      <para lang="ko">
        김프 개발자들은 XCF 파일이 다양한 버전에 대해 호환성을 유지하도록
        많은 노력을 해왔다. 즉, 김프 2.0 에서 만들어진 파일을 김프 1.2
        에서도 읽을 수 있도록 하는 것이다. 하지만 몇몇 정보들은 사용할 수
        없을 것이다. 예를 들어 김프 2.0 은 김프 1.2 에 비해 보다 나은
        텍스트 관리 방법을 가지고 있는데, 김프 2.0 의 XCF 파일은 이를 텍스트
        레이어로 표현하는데, 이를 김프 1.2 에서 읽어들일 경우 그저 일반적인
        레이어로 표현할 수밖에 없다.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dei som har utvikla <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, har streva hardt for å
        gjere formatet kompatibelt gjennom ulike versjonar. Dersom du lagar
        ei fil med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 kan det godt hende at ho kan
        opnast i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, men ofte vil noe av
        informasjonen bli borte. T.d. har <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 ein heilt
        annan måte å behandla tekst på enn <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. Difor
        vil eit tekstlag i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 bli vist som eit ordinært
        biletlag i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
      </para>
      <para lang="zh_CN">
        GIMP 开发者在保持 XCF 文件格式在各个版本间兼容上花了很大的力气。比如
        您在 GIMP 2.0 中创建一个文件，它也应该可以在 GIMP 1.2中打开。不过，
        文件中的一些信息可能不能用：比如，GIMP 2.0 有比 GIMP 1.2 更复杂地处
        理文字的方式，因此，GIMP 2.0 中的文字图层在 GIMP 1.2 中打开后，这些
        文字就和原图像作为图像图层而混在一起了。
      </para>

      <para lang="cs">
        Název <acronym>XCF</acronym> je historického původu. Je to zkratka
        <foreignphrase>eXperimental Computer Facility</foreignphrase>, což
        je studentská pracovní skupina na Kalifornské univerzitě v Berkeley,
        kde kdysi GIMP i XCF formát vznikly.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
