<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2006-05-24 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-08-01 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>X</title><anchor id="glossary-x"/>


  <glossentry id="glossary-xcf">
    <glossterm>
      <anchor id="gimp-xcf-open" xreflabel="XCF"/>
      <anchor id="gimp-xcf-save" xreflabel="XCF"/>
      <anchor id="gimp-file-open-xcf" xreflabel="XCF"/>
      <anchor id="gimp-file-save-xcf" xreflabel="XCF"/>
      XCF
    </glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>XCF</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>.xcf</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>.xcf.gz</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Formats</primary><secondary>XCF</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        XCF is a <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        which is special because it is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
        native file format: that is, it was designed specifically to store all
        of the data that goes to make up a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image.
        Because of this, XCF files may be quite complicated, and there are
        few programs other than <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that can read them.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        When an image is stored as an XCF file, the file encodes nearly
        everything there is to know about the image: the pixel data for each
        of the layers, the current selection, additional channels if there are
        any, paths if there are any, and guides. The most important thing that
        is <emphasis>not</emphasis> saved in an XCF file is the undo history.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

        <!-- FIXME: es  ko zh_CN review needed
          Someone said "This is not true, RLE compression is used in XCF. I
          have rewritten it in the Czech version already" So please translate
          that to English.p
        -->
      <para>
        The pixel data in an XCF file is represented
        in a lossless compressed form: the image byte blocks are compressed
        using the lossless RLE algorithm. This means that no matter how many
        times you load and save an image using this format, not a single
        pixel or other image data is lost or modified because of this format.
        XCF files can become very large, however <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        allows you to compress the files themselves, using either the gzip
        or bzip2 compression methods, both of which are fast, efficient, and
        freely available. Compressing an XCF file will often shrink it by a
        factor of 10 or more.
      </para>
      

      

      
      
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developers have made a great effort to
        keep the XCF file format compatible across versions. If you create a
        file using <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0, it ought to be possible to
        open the file in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2. However, some of the
        information in the file may not be usable: for example,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 has a much more sophisticated way of
        handling text than <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, so a text layer
        from a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 XCF file will appear as an
        ordinary image layer if the file is opened in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      

      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
