<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history: -->
<!-- 050801 de reviewed by axel.wernicke -->
<glossdiv lang="cs;en;de;es;fr;no;zh_CN">
  <title>X</title>

  <anchor id="gimp-xcf-open" />
  <anchor id='gimp-file-open-xcf' />
  <anchor id='gimp-file-save-xcf' />

  <glossentry id="gimp-xcf-save">
    <glossterm>XCF</glossterm>
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        The XCF file type is special because it is Gimp's native file
        type:  that is, it was designed specifically to store all of the
        data that goes to make up a Gimp image.  Because of this,
        XCF files may be quite complicated, and there are few programs
        other than Gimp that can read them.  
      </para>
      <para>
        When an image is stored as an XCF file, the file encodes nearly
        everything there is to know about the image:  the pixel data for
        each of the layers, the current selection, additional channels
        if there are any, paths if there are any, and guides.  The most
        important thing that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> saved in an XCF
        file is the undo history.
      </para>
      <para>
<!--    This is not true, RLE compression is used in XCF. I have rewritten
        it in the Czech version already
-->
        The pixel data in an XCF file is represented in a raw,
        uncompressed form: each byte of image data equals one byte in
        the XCF file.  Thus, XCF files for even modestly sized images
        can be quite large:  for example, a 1000x1000 RGB image with 3
        layers will produce an XCF file of over 10 megabytes.  It is not
        at all difficult to get XCF files of over 100 megabytes.
        Fortunately, although XCF files do not intrinsically compress
        their data, Gimp allows you to compress the files themselves,
        using either the gzip or bzip2 compression methods, both of
        which are fast, efficient, and freely available.  Compressingan
        XCF file will often shrink it by a factor of 10 or more.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Gimp developers have made a great effort to keep the XCF
        file format compatible across versions.  If you create a file
        using Gimp 2.0, it ought to be possible to open the file in Gimp
        1.2.  However, some of the information in the file may not be
        usable:  for example, Gimp 2.0 has a much more sophisticated way
        of handling text than Gimp 1.2, so a text layer from a Gimp 2.0
        XCF file will appear as an ordinary image layer if the file is
        opened in Gimp 1.2.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="cs">
      <para>
        XCF je nativní souborový formát GIMPu, to znamená, že byl navržen
        pro uložení <emphasis>všech dat</emphasis>, která tvoří obrázek
        v GIMPu. Je to proto ideální formát pro ukládání rozpracovaných
        obrázků (běžnější souborové formáty většinou nezachovají složitější
        struktury v obrázku, například vrstvy). Jeho nevýhodou je naopak to,
        že kvůli jeho složitosti ho kromě GIMPu umí zpracovat jen velmi málo
        dalších programů.
      </para>
      <para>
        Uložením obrázku do XCF souboru zachováte téměř všechny informace,
        které jsou o obrázku známé: obrazová data všech vrstev, aktuální
        výběr, případné další kanály, cesty a vodítka. Nejpodstatnější
        informace, která se do souboru ve formátu XCF
        <emphasis>neukládá</emphasis>, je historie změn (Vrátit/Znovu).
      </para>
      <para>
        Rastrová obrazová data (údaje o jednotlivých pixelech) jsou ve
        formátu XCF komprimována neztrátovou RLE kompresí, která je u obrázků
        obsahujících hodně barevné informace neefektivní; proto mohou být
        XCF soubory velmi velké. Například RGB obrázek o rozměrech 1000×1000
        pixelů a třech vrstvách může mít přes 10 megabajtů. V praxi nejsou
        vzácné XCF soubory větší než 100 megabajtů.
      </para>
      <para>
        Vývojáři GIMPu se velmi snaží, aby zachovali kompatibilitu XCF formátu
        mezi jednotlivými verzemi. Pokud vytvoříte XCF soubor v GIMPu 2.2,
        mělo by být možné otevřít ho i GIMPem 1.2. Nicméně část informací
        nemusí být ve staré verzi použitelná; Gimp 2.2 má například mnohem
        pokročilejší možnosti práce s textem, takže textová vrstva Gimpu 2.2
        se v Gimpu zobrazí jako obyčejná vrstva obrázku.
      </para>
      <para>
        Název <acronym>XCF</acronym> je historického původu. Je to zkratka
        <foreignphrase>eXperimental Computer Facility</foreignphrase>, což
        je studentská pracovní skupina na Kalifornské univerzitě v Berkeley,
        kde kdysi Gimp i XCF formát vznikly.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang='de'>
      <para>
        XCF ist das <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigene Dateiformat;
        entwickelt um alle <acronym>GIMP</acronym> eigenen Informationen
        zu speichern.
      </para>
      <para>
        Wenn <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ein Bild als XCF speichert, werden
        alle Informationen zum Bild abgespeichert: Pixeldaten für jede
        Ebene, aktuelle Auswahlen, zusätzliche Kanäle, Pfade und vieles
        mehr. Die Informationen zum Rückgängig machen von Operationen
        werden jedoch nicht gespeichert.
      </para>
      <para>
        Pixeldaten werden in unkomprimierter Form gespeichert: jedes
        Byte der Bildaten is gleich jedem Byte der Datei. Somit können
        XCF Dateien, in Abhängigkeit der Bildgröße in Pixel, verwendetem
        Farbraum und verwendeten Ebenen, sehr groß werden.
        Beispielsweise ein 1000x1000 Pixel grosses Bild im RGB Format
        mit drei Kanälen kann ein abgespeichertes XCF mit 100 Megabyte
        ergeben.
        Um die Dateigrössen dennoch etwas zu verkleinen, is es möglich
        externe programme zum Komprimieren der Daten zu verwenden.
        Hierfür kann GZIP oder BZIP2 benutzt werden, welche schnell,
        effizient und frei verfügbar sind. Durch die Benutzung dieser
        Kompressionsprogramme werden die Dateigrößen meist um den Faktor
        10 verringert.
      </para>
      <para>
        Die <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Entwickler haben sich viel Mühe
        gegeben, das Format in jeder (älteren) <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        Version lesbar zu halten. Jedoch steht einiges der neuen
        Funktionalität in älteren <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Versionen
        nicht mehr zur Verfügung, wie z.B. Textebenen. Solche speziellen
        Informationen werden einfach als normale Ebene importiert.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="es">
      <para>
        El tipo de archivo XCF es especial porque es el formato nativo
        del <acronym>GIMP</acronym>: esto es, fue diseñado
        específicamente para guardar todos los datos que puede tener
        una imagen del <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Por esto, los
        archivos XCF pueden ser un poco complicados, y hay unos pocos
        programas sin contar el <acronym>GIMP</acronym> que pueden
        leerlos.
      </para>
      <para>
        Cuando una imagen es guardada como archivo XCF, en el archivo
        se codifica todo lo que se conoce de la misma: los datos de
        pixeles de cada capa, la selección actual, canales adicionales
        si es que los hay, rutas si hay alguna, y guías.  La única
        cosa importante que <emphasis>no</emphasis> se guarda en un
        archivo XCF es el historial de deshacer.
      </para>
      <para>
        Los datos de pixeles en un archivo XCF son representados en
        forma cruda, sin comprimir: cada byte de la imagen equivale a
        un byte en el archivo XCF.  Por esto, incluso los archivos XCF
        de imágenes modestamente pequeñas pueden ser bastante grandes:
        por ejemplo, una imagen RGB de 1000x1000 con tres capas
        producirá un archivo XCF de más de 10 megabytes.  No es para
        nada fantástico obtener archivos XCF de más de 100 megabytes.
        Afortunadamente, aunque los archivos XCF no comprimen los
        datos, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> permite comprimir los archivos
        mismos, usando los métodos gzip o bzip2.  Ambos son rápidos,
        eficientes, y libremente disponibles.  Usualmente al comprimir
        un archivo XCF se reduce su tamaño por un factor de 10 o más.
      </para>
      <para>
        Los desarrolladores del <acronym>GIMP</acronym> han hecho un
        gran esfuerzo en mantener los archivos XCF compatibles entre
        versiones.  Si creas un archivo usando <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        2.0, será posible abrirlo con <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2. De
        todas formas, algo de la información del archivo no será
        disponible: por ejemplo, el manejo del texto en la versión 2-0
        es mucho más sofisticado que en la versión 1.2, así que una
        capa de texto desde la nueva versión a la antigüa aparecerá
        como una capa de imagen ordinaria.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="fr">
      <para>
        Le type de ficier XCF est spécial: c'est le format natif de GIMP 
        et il est spécifiquement destiné a conserver toutes les données 
        dont GIMP a besoin pour créer une image. Peu d'autres programmes 
        que GIMP sont capables de le lire.
      </para>
      <para>
        Quand une image est enregistrée au format .xcf, le fichier encode 
        toutes les données de l'image: les calques, les chemins, les 
        sélections, les guides...etc. La seule chose qu'il NE conserve PAS 
        est l'Historique d'Annulation.
      </para>
      <para>
        Dans un fichier .xcf, les pixels sont représentés à l'état brut, 
        sans aucune compression: à chaque octet de l'image correspond un 
        octet dans le fichier XCF. Ainsi une image RVB de 1000x1000 pixels 
        avec 3 calques produira un fichier XCF de 10 Mo et vous pouvez 
        facilement obtenir des fichiers de plus de 100Mo. Heureusement, 
        bien que Les fichiers XCF ne sont pas intrinsèquement comprimés, 
        vous pouvez les comprimer en utilisant gzip ou bzip2 qui sont des 
        methodes très efficaces et disponibles gratuitement. Le fait de 
        comprimer un fichier XCF peut le réduire d'un facteur 10 ou plus.
      </para>
      <para>
        Les développeurs de GIMP ont fait de gros efforts pour garder à XCF 
        une compatibilité avec les versions antérieures de GIMP. Toutefois, 
        certaines informations peuvent être perdues. GIMP-2.0 a ainsi une 
        gestion perfectionnée des textes, et, dans GIMP-1.2, un calque texte 
        provenant de 2.0 apparaîtra comme une image ordinaire.
      </para>
    </glossdef>

    <glossdef lang="no">
      <para>
        Dette er <acronym>GIMP</acronym> sitt eige format for biletfiler,
        laga spesielt for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Formatet blir støtta av
        få andre program, om noen i det heile.
      </para>
      <para>
        Når eit bilete blir lagra i XCF-format, blir omtrent alt som finst
        i biletet lagra: data for kvart av laga, den aktive markeringa,
        kanalar, banar, hjelpelinjer osv. Det viktigaste som
        <emphasis>ikkje</emphasis> blir lagra er opplysningane om
        angreloggen.
      </para>
      <para>
        <!--    This is not true, RLE compression is used in XCF. I have rewritten
                it in the Czech version already. Somebody translating it to english?
                -->
        Pikseldata blir lagra i rå og ukomprimert form. Difor kan
        XCF-filene sjølv for eit enkelt lite bilete bli nokså store. Eit
        1000 × 1000 piksels bilete i RGB-format med tre lag vil lage ei
        XCF-fil på over 100 mb. Det er heller ikkje vanskeleg å få filer på
        over 100 mb. Har du behov for det, kan du komprimera XCF-filene med
        eit eller anna komprimeringsprogram, t.d. gzip eller bzip2, som er
        fritt tilgjengelege. Slike program kan ofte komprimera filene med
        ein faktor på 10 eller meir.
      </para>
      <para>
        Dei som har utvikla <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, har streva hardt for å
        gjere formatet kompatibelt gjennom ulike versjonar. Dersom du lagar
        ei fil med <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 kan det godt hende at ho kan
        opnast i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, men ofte vil noe av
        informasjonen bli borte. T.d. har <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 ein heilt
        annan måte å behandla tekst på enn <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1. Difor
        vil eit tekstlag i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1 bli vist som eit ordinært
        biletlag i <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
    
    <glossdef lang="zh_CN">
      <para>
        XCF 文件格式比较特殊因为它是 GIMP 的内部格式：也就是，它被专用来保存 GIMP 图像中所用数据。所以 XCF 文件可能比较复杂，很少有其它程序能够读取它。
      </para>
      <para>
        当一个图像被保存为 XCF 文件，文件编码几乎包括了解图像所需的所有信息：各个图层中的像素数据，当前选区，附加通道，路径和参考线。<emphasis>没有</emphasis>保存在一个 XCF 文件中最重要的东西是撤消历史。
      </para>
      <para>
        一个 XCF 文件中的像素信息保存为一种未加工的，非压缩的形式：所以 XCF 文件常常比较大：比如，一个 1000x1000 的带3个图层的 RGB 图像将生成大于 10 兆的 XCF 文件。要产生于大于 100 兆的 XCF 文件也不难。幸运的是，虽然 XCF 文件本身不支持压缩其数据，但 GIMP 允许您自己用 gzip 或 bzip2(都快速而有效，并且可免费获得)压缩方式来压缩文件。压缩一个 XCF 文件通常能减少 10 倍或更多。
      </para>
      <para>
        GIMP 开发者在保持 XCF 文件格式在各个版本间兼容上花了很大的力气。比如您在 GIMP 2.0 中创建一个文件，它也应该可以在 GIMP 1.2中打开。不过，文件中的一些信息可能不能用：比如，GIMP 2.0 有比 GIMP 1.2 更复杂地处理文字的方式，因此，GIMP 2.0 中的文字图层在 GIMP 1.2 中打开后，这些文字就和原图像作为图像图层而混在一起了。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
