<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<glossdiv>
  <title>X</title>
  <glossentry id="gimp-xcf-save">
    <glossterm>XCF</glossterm>
    <anchor id="gimp-xcf-open" />
    <glossdef lang="en">
      <para>
        The XCF file type is special because it is Gimp's native file
        type:  that is, it was designed specifically to store all ofthe
        data that goes to make up a Gimp image.  Because of this,
        XCF files may be quite complicated, and there are few programs
        other than Gimp that can read them.  
      </para>
      <para>
        When an image is stored as an XCF file, the file encodes nearly
        everything there is to know about the image:  the pixel datafor
        each of the layers, the current selection, additional channels
        if there are any, paths if there are any, and guides.  The most
        important thing that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> saved in anXCF
        file is the undo history.
      </para>
      <para>
        The pixel data in an XCF file is represented in a raw,
        uncompressed form: each byte of image data equals one byte in
        the XCF file.  Thus, XCF files for even modestly sized images
        can be quite large:  for example, a 1000x1000 RGB image with 3
        layers will produce an XCF file of over 10 megabytes.  It isnot
        at all difficult to get XCF files of over 100 megabytes.
        Fortunately, although XCF files do not intrinsically compress
        their data, Gimp allows you to compress the files themselves,
        using either the gzip or bzip2 compression methods, both of
        which are fast, efficient, and freely available.  Compressingan
        XCF file will often shrink it by a factor of 10 or more.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Gimp developers have made a great effort to keep the XCF
        file format compatible across versions.  If you create a file
        using Gimp 2.0, it ought to be possible to open the file inGimp
        1.2.  However, some of the information in the file may not be
        usable:  for example, Gimp 2.0 has a much more sophisticatedway
        of handling text than Gimp 1.2, so a text layer from a Gimp 2.0
        XCF file will appear as an ordinary image layer if the file is
        opened in Gimp 1.2.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
