<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-09-01 AntI: added es
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2005-08-26 de added YUV and YCbCr by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv>
  <title>Y</title><anchor id="glossary-y" xreflabel="Y"/>

  <glossentry id="glossary-ycbcr">
    <glossterm>YCbCr</glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>YCbCr</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        YCbCr is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which was developed for the PAL television standard as a simple
        modification to the YUV color model. In the
        meantime, it has become the CCIR-601 standard for image and video
        recording. For example, it is used for JPEG pictures and MPEG videos,
        and therefore also on DVDs, video CDs and for most other widespread
        digital video standards. Note that a color model is still not a color
        space, since it doesn't determine which colors are actually meant by
        <quote>red</quote>, <quote>green</quote> and <quote>blue</quote>.
        For a color space, there must still be a reference to a specific
        absolute color value.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        There are color models which do not express a color by the additive
        basic colors, red, green and blue (RGB), but by other properties, for
        example, the brightness-color model. Here, the criteria are the basic
        brightness of the colors (from black, through gray, to white), the
        colors with the largest portion (red, orange, yellow, green, blue,
        violet, or other pure colors that lie between them) and the saturation
        of the colors (<quote>gaudy</quote> to pale). This color model is
        based on the
        ability of the eye to recognize small differences in luminosity
        better than small color differences, and to recognize those better
        than small differences in saturation. That makes gray text written on
        a black background easy to read, but blue text on a red background
        very hard to read, even with the same basic brightness. Such color
        models are called brightness-color models.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        The YCbCr model is a slight adaptation of such a brightness-color
        model. An RBG color value is divided into a basic brightness, Y, and
        two components, Cb and Cr, where Cb is a measurement of the deviation
        from gray in the blue direction, or if it is less that 0.5, in the
        direction of yellow. Cr is the corresponding measurement for the
        difference in the direction of red or turquoise. This representation
        uses the peculiarity of the eye of being especially sensitive to green
        light. That is why most of the information about the proportion of
        green is in the basic brightness, Y, an only the deviations for the
        red and blue portions need to be represented. The Y values have twice
        the resolution of the other two values, Cb and Cr, in most practical
        applications, such as on DVDs.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-yuv">
    <glossterm>YUV</glossterm>

    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>YUV</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para>
        YUV is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which uses two components to represent the color
        information, luma (the strength of the light per area) and the
        chrominance, or proportion of color (chroma), where the chrominance
        again consists of two components. The development of the YUV color
        model also goes back to the development of color television (PAL),
        where ways were sought for transmitting the color information
        along with the black-and-white signal, in order to achieve backwards
        compatibility with old black and white televisions without having to
        increase the available transmission bandwidth. From the YUV color
        model of the analog television techiques, the YCrCb color model was
        developed, which is used for most kinds of digital image and video
        compression. Erroneously, the YUV color model is also often spoken
        about in those fields, although the YCbCr model is actually used.
        This often causes confusion.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        For the calculation of the luma signals, the underlying RGB data is
        first adjusted with the <link linkend="glossary-gamma">gamma</link>
        value of the output device, and an R'G'B' signal is obtained. The
        three individual components are added together with different
        weights, to form the brightness information, which also functions as
        the VBS signal (Video Baseband Signal, the black-and-white signal)
        for the old black and white televisions.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>Y=R+G+B</para>

      <para>
        The exact calculation is more complicated, however, since some aspects
        of the color perception of the human eye have to be taken into
        account. For example, green is perceived to be lighter than red, and
        this is perceived to be lighter than blue. Furthermore, in some
        systems gamma correction of the basic color is first performed.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>
        The chrominance signals, and the color difference signals also,
        contain the color information. They are formed by the difference of
        blue minus luma or red minus luma.
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>U=B-Y</para>
      <para>V=R-Y</para>

      <para>
        From the three generated components, Y, U and V, the individual
        color proportions of the basic color can be calculated again later:
      </para>
      
      
      
      

      <para>Y + U = Y + ( B - Y ) = Y - Y + B = B</para>
      <para>Y + V = Y + ( R - Y ) = Y - Y + R = R</para>
      <para>Y - B - R = ( R + G + B ) - B - R = G</para>

      <para>
        Furthermore, because of the structure of the retina of the human
        eye, it turns out that the brightness information is perceived at a
        higher resolution than the color, so that many formats based on
        the YUV color model compress the chrominance to save bandwidth
        during transmission.
      </para>
      
      
      
      
      
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
