<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE glossdiv PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- section history:
  2006-09-06 scb: thorough review and/or rewrite of English
  2006-07-29 lexa: applied changes suggested by Sally
  2005-08-26 de added YUV and YCbCr by axel.wernicke
-->
<glossdiv lang="en;de;fr;no">
  <title>Y</title><anchor id="glossary-y" xreflabel="Y" />

  <glossentry id="glossary-ycbcr" lang="de;en;fr;no">
    <glossterm lang="en;de;fr;no">YCbCr</glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>YCbCr</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        YCbCr is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which was developed for the PAL television standard as a simple
        modification to the YUV color model. In the
        meantime, it has become the CCIR-601 standard for image and video
        recording. For example, it is used for JPEG pictures and MPEG videos,
        and therefore also on DVDs, video CDs and for most other widespread
        digital video standards. Note that a color model is still not a color
        space, since it doesn't determine which colors are actually meant by
        <quote>red</quote>, <quote>green</quote> and <quote>blue</quote>.
        For a color space, there must still be a reference to a specific
        absolute color value.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Das YCbCr-Farbmodell wurde für die PAL-Fernsehnorm als ein leicht vom
        YUV-Farbmodell abweichendes Farbmodell entwickelt. Es wurde inzwischen
        zum CCIR-601-Standard für digitale Bild- und Videoaufzeichnung. Es
        wird beispielsweise für JPEG-Bilder und MPEG-Videos verwendet, und
        damit auch auf DVDs, Video CDs und bei meisten anderen verbreiteten
        digitalen Videonormen. Man beachte, dass ein Farbmodell noch kein
        Farbraum ist, denn es legt noch nicht fest, welche Farben eigentlich
        mit "Rot", "Grün" und "Blau" genau gemeint sind. Für einen Farbraum
        bedarf es noch des Bezuges auf bestimmte absolute Farbwerte.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        YCbCr est un modèle de couleurs développé pour le standard de
        télévision PAL. Il s'agit d'une simple modification du modèle de
        couleur YUV. Depuis, il est devenu le standard CCIR-601 pour les
        images et le vidéos. Il est utilisé entre autre pour les images JPEG
        et les vidéos MPEG, et donc pour les CD et les DVD. Notez qu'un modèle
        de couleur n'est pas un espace de couleur puisqu'il ne détermine pas
        ce que sont effectivement les couleurs Rouge, Vert et Bleu. Un espace
        de couleur doit se référer à une valeur de couleur absolue.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        YCbCr er ein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">fargemodell</link>
        som blei utvikla for PAL televisjonstandard som ein enkel modifikasjon
        til YUV fargemodellen. I mellomtida har modellen blitt til 
        CCIR-601-standarden for opptak av digitalbilete og video. For
        eksempel blir det brukt i JPEG-bilete og MPEG-videoar, og difor også
        på DVD-ar og CD-ar og andre videoprodukt. Merk at ein fargemodell
        ikkje er det same som eit fargerom i og med at grunnfargane
        <quote>raud</quote>, <quote>grøn</quote> og <quote>blå</quote>
        ikkje er definerte. For eit fargerom må desse fargane vere
        absolutt og eintydig definerte.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        There are color models which do not express a color by the additive
        basic colors, red, green and blue (RGB), but by other properties, for
        example, the brightness-color model. Here, the criteria are the basic
        brightness of the colors (from black, through gray, to white), the
        colors with the largest portion (red, orange, yellow, green, blue,
        violet, or other pure colors that lie between them) and the saturation
        of the colors (<quote>gaudy</quote> to pale). This color model is
        based on the
        ability of the eye to recognize small differences in luminosity
        better than small color differences, and to recognize those better
        than small differences in saturation. That makes gray text written on
        a black background easy to read, but blue text on a red background
        very hard to read, even with the same basic brightness. Such color
        models are called brightness-color models.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Es gibt Farbmodelle, die eine Farbe nicht durch die additiven
        Grundfarben Rot, Grün und Blau (kurz RGB), sondern durch andere
        Eigenschaften ausdrücken. So zum Beispiel das
        Helligkeit-Farbigkeit-Modell. Hier sind die Kriterien die
        Grundhelligkeit der Farbe (von Schwarz über Grau bis Weiß), die Farbe
        mit dem größten Anteil (Rot, Orange, Gelb, Grün, Blau, Violett, bzw.
        weitere dazwischen liegende reine Farben) und die Sättigung der
        Farbe, ( <quote>knallig</quote>
        gegenüber blass). Dieses Farbmodell beruht auf der Fähigkeit des
        Auges, geringe Luminanzunterschiede (Helligkeitsunterschiede) besser
        zu erkennen als kleine Farbtonunterschiede, und diese wiederum besser
        als kleine Farbsättigungsunterschiede. So ist ein grau auf schwarz
        geschriebener Text sehr gut zu lesen, ein blau auf rot geschriebener,
        bei gleicher Grundhelligkeit der Farben, allerdings sehr schlecht.
        Solche Farbmodelle nennt man Helligkeit-Farbigkeit-Modelle.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Il existe des modèles de couleurs qui n'expriment pas les couleurs
        par additions des trois composantes Rouge, Vert et Bleu, mais par
        d'autres propriétés, par exemple la Luminosité. L'avantage, dans ce
        cas, est que l'œil humain distingue mieux les différences de
        luminosité que les différences de teintes. Un texte gris sur un
        fond noir sera mieux vu avec un tel modèle, mais un texte bleu sur
        un fond rouge sera difficile à voir.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Ikkje alle fargesystema definerer fargane ved hjelp av dei
        additive grunnfargane raud, grøn og blå (RGB). Noen fargesystem
        bruker andre kriteriar som t.d. kor lys fargen er på ein skala frå
        svart via grå til kvit. Andre system bruker den fargen, eller dei
        fargane, som det er mest av, t.d. raud, oransje, gul, grøn, blå, fiolett
        eller andre reine fargar mellom desse. Endeleg finst det også
        fargesystem som bygger på fargemetninga. Desse er baserte på at
        auget vårt oppfattar små skilnader i lysstyrke betre enn små
        skilnader i metning. Det er dette som gjer at ein raud tekst på
        grå bakgrunn er lettare å lese enn ein blå tekst på raud bakgrunn,
        sjølv om lystilhøva er dei same. Fargemodellar som er bygd på
        lysstyrke blir gjerne kalla lysstyrkemodellar.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The YCbCr model is a slight adaptation of such a brightness-color
        model. An RBG color value is divided into a basic brightness, Y, and
        two components, Cb and Cr, where Cb is a measurement of the deviation
        from gray in the blue direction, or if it is less that 0.5, in the
        direction of yellow. Cr is the corresponding measurement for the
        difference in the direction of red or turquoise. This representation
        uses the peculiarity of the eye of being especially sensitive to green
        light. That is why most of the information about the proportion of
        green is in the basic brightness, Y, an only the deviations for the
        red and blue portions need to be represented. The Y values have twice
        the resolution of the other two values, Cb and Cr, in most practical
        applications, such as on DVDs.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Das YCbCr-Modell ist ein leichte Abwandlung eines solchen
        Helligkeit-Farbigkeits-Modells. Es wird ein RGB-Farbwert in eine
        Grundhelligkeit Y und zwei Komponenten Cb und Cr aufgeteilt, wobei Cb
        ein Maß für die Abweichung von Grau in Richtung Blau ist bzw., wenn es
        kleiner als 0,5 ist, in Richtung Gelb. Cr ist die entsprechende
        Maßzahl für Differenz in Richtung Rot bzw. Türkis. Diese Darstellung
        verwendet die Besonderheit des Auges, für grünes Licht besonders
        empfindlich zu sein. Daher steckt die meiste Information über den
        Grünanteil in der Grundhelligkeit Y und man braucht daneben nur noch
        die Abweichungen beim Rot- oder Blauanteil darzustellen. Die Y-Werte
        werden dann in den meisten praktischen Anwendungen, etwa auf DVDs,
        doppelt so fein aufgelöst wie die beiden Werte Cb und Cr
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-ycbcr" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le modèle YCbCr fait partie de ces modèles basés sur la luminosité.
        Une couleur RVB est divisée en luminosité, Y, et deux autres
        composants, Cb et Cr. Cb est la mesure de la déviation du gris dans
        la direction du bleu, ou du jaune si elle est inférieure à 0,5. Cr
        est la mesure correspondante pour la différence dans la direction du
        rouge ou du turquoise. Cette représentation utilise le fait que
        l'œil humain voit mieux dans le vert. C'est pourquoi l'information
        sur le vert se trouve dans Y, et que seules les déviations du rouge
        et du bleu doivent être mentionnées. Les valeurs Y ont une
        résolution deux fois plus grande que Cb et Cr.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        YCbCr er ein slik lysstyrkemodell. Ein RGB-fargeverdi blir broten opp
        i grunnleggande lyssttyrke Y og dei to komponentane Cb og Cr. Cb
        er eit mål for avviket frå grå i retning blå, eller dersom avviket er
        mindre enn 0,5 i retning mot gult. Cr er det same i retning raud
        eller turkis. Denne modellen tar omsyn til at auget vårt er spesielt
        følsamt for grønt lys. Difor kan informasjonen om mengda av grønt
        leggast saman med lysstyrke i Y. For raud og blå er det nok å vise
        avvika. I praktisk bruk, som t.d. på DVD-ar, har Y gjerne dobbelt
        så stor verdi som dei to andre.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>


  <glossentry id="glossary-yuv" lang="de;en;fr;no">
    <glossterm lang="de;en;fr;no">YUV</glossterm>

    <indexterm><primary>YUV</primary></indexterm>

    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        YUV is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which uses two components to represent the color
        information, luma (the strength of the light per area) and the
        chrominance, or proportion of color (chroma), where the chrominance
        again consists of two components. The development of the YUV color
        model also goes back to the development of color television (PAL),
        where ways were sought for transmitting the color information
        along with the black-and-white signal, in order to achieve backwards
        compatibility with old black and white televisions without having to
        increase the available transmission bandwidth. From the YUV color
        model of the analog television techiques, the YCrCb color model was
        developed, which is used for most kinds of digital image and video
        compression. Erroneously, the YUV color model is also often spoken
        about in those fields, although the YCbCr model is actually used.
        This often causes confusion.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Das YUV-Farbmodell verwendet zur Darstellung der Farbinformation zwei
        Komponenten, die Luma (Lichtstärke pro Fläche) und die Chrominanz oder
        Farbanteil (chroma), wobei die Chrominanz wiederum aus zwei
        Komponenten besteht. Die Entwicklung des YUV-Farbmodells geht auf die
        Entwicklung des Farbfernsehens (PAL) zurück, wo nach Wegen gesucht
        wurde, zusätzlich zum Schwarzweiß-Signal die Farbinformation zu
        übertragen, um eine Abwärtskompatibilität mit alten
        Schwarzweiß-Fernsehgeräten zu erreichen, ohne die zur Verfügung
        stehende Übertragungsbandbreite erhöhen zu müssen. Aus dem
        YUV-Farbmodell der analogen Fernsehtechnik wurde das YCbCr-Farbmodell
        entwickelt, das bei den meisten Arten der digitalen Bild- und
        Videokompression eingesetzt wird. Fälschlicherweise wird in jenem
        Bereich auch oft vom YUV-Farbmodell gesprochen, obwohl eigentlich das
        YCbCr-Modell benutzt wird. Dies sorgt oft für Verwirrung.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        YUV est un modèle de couleur qui utilise deux composants pour
        représenter les couleurs: la luminance (la force de la lumière émise
        par unité de surface) et la chrominance (information sur la couleur)
        composée de deux paramètres, U et V. On pourrait bien sûr utiliser
        directement les valeurs R, V, B, mais le système YUV permet
        d'économiser un signal, ce qui est important dans la transmission des
        couleurs en télévision. Dans le modèle YCrCb, seules les informations
        du rouge et du bleu sont transmises, l'information du vert étant
        re-calculée à partir du rouge, du bleu et de la luminance. Le modèle
        YUV a aussi permis de conserver la compatiblité avec les téléviseurs
        noir et blanc au début de la télévision couleur. Ce modèle YUV est
        actuellement très utilisé dans toutes sortes de compressions d'images
        numériques et de vidéos. On a tendance à utiliser indifféremment les
        termes YUV et YCrCb, ce qui peut être source de confusion.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        YUV er ein <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">fargemodell</link>
        som bruker bare to komponentar for å representere
        fargeinformasjonen, <emphasis>luma</emphasis>, dvs. lysstyrke
        per arealeining, og <emphasis>krominans</emphasis>, dvs.
        fargetone og fargemetning. Utviklinga av YUV-modellen er eit
        resultat av eit ønskje om å kunne sende fargesignal saman med
        svart/kvit-signala på ein slik måte at dei kunne lesast av både
        svart/kvit-TV og farge-TV utan å auke bandbreidda. Den analoge
        YUV-modellen blei seinare utvida til YCrCb-modellen (sjå ovanfor).
        Av gammal vane blir ofte YCrCb-modellen omtalt som YUV, 
        sjølv om dette eigentleg er feil.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        For the calculation of the luma signals, the underlying RGB data is
        first adjusted with the <link linkend="glossary-gamma">gamma</link>
        value of the output device, and an R'G'B' signal is obtained. The
        three individual components are added together with different
        weights, to form the brightness information, which also functions as
        the VBS signal (Video Baseband Signal, the black-and-white signal)
        for the old black and white televisions.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Zur Berechnung des Luma-Signals (auch Leuchtdichte-Signal) werden die
        zugrundeliegenden RGB-Daten zunächst mit dem Gamma-Wert des
        Ausgabegerätes verrechnet, man erhält ein R'G'B'-Signal. Die drei
        Einzelkomponenten werden mit unterschiedlicher Gewichtung addiert, um
        die Helligkeitsinformation zu bilden, die als BAS-Signal auch bei
        alten Schwarzweiß-Fernsehgeräten funktioniert.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Pour le calcul du signal de luminance, les valeurs RVB sont d'abord
        ajustées à partir de la valeur
        <link linkend="glossary-gamma">gamma</link> du périphérique de
        sortie. Ces trois valeurs sont alors ajoutées, constituant le Y,
        utilisé dans les téléviseurs noir et blanc.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        For å rekne ut lumasignala, blir verdiane for RGB justerte i høve til
        <link linkend="glossary-gamma">gammaverdien</link> til det
        utstyret signala skal brukast på. Resultatet blir eit R'G'B'-signal.
        Verdiane frå dette signalet blir så lagt saman med ulike vektingar
        for dei tre komponentane. Resultatverdien fortel kor lyssterkt
        biletpunktet skal vere. Denne informasjonen fungerer også som
        VBS (Video Baseband Signal, svart/kvit-signalet) for svart/kvit-TV.
      </para>

      <para lang="de;en;fr;no">Y=R+G+B</para>

      <para lang="en">
        The exact calculation is more complicated, however, since some aspects
        of the color perception of the human eye have to be taken into
        account. For example, green is perceived to be lighter than red, and
        this is perceived to be lighter than blue. Furthermore, in some
        systems gamma correction of the basic color is first performed.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die genaue Berechnung ist jedoch komplizierter, da einige Aspekte des
        Farbensehens des menschlichen Auges berücksichtigt werden müssen. So
        wird beispielsweise Grün heller wahrgenommen als Rot, und dieses
        heller als Blau. Weiterhin wird bei einigen Systemen zunächst eine
        Gammakorrektur der Grundfarben vorgenommen.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Le calcul exact est en fait plus compliqué, pour tenir compte des
        caractéristiques de l'œil humain, qui ne perçoit pas avec la même
        intensité des couleurs ayant pourtant la même intensité physique.
        Par exemple, le vert est perçu plus clair que le rouge, lui-même plus
        clair que le bleu. C'est pourquoi une correction de gamma est
        appliquée par certains systèmes.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Formelen ovanfor er ikkje heilt korrekt for det blir i tillegg tatt 
        omsyn til at menneskeauget oppfattar grønt som lysare enn raudt,
        som igjen blir oppfatta lysare enn blått. Som nemnd tidlegare,
        kan det også vere behov for gammakorrigering av grunnfargane.
      </para>

      <para lang="en">
        The chrominance signals, and the color difference signals also,
        contain the color information. They are formed by the difference of
        blue minus luma or red minus luma.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Die Chrominanzsignale, auch Farbdifferenzsignale enthalten die
        Farbinformation. Sie entstehen aus der Differenz Blau minus Luma bzw.
        Rot minus Luma.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Les signaux de chrominance sont dérivés des valeurs du rouge et du
        bleu, et de la luminance:
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Krominanssignala og signala for fargedifferanse inneheld
        fargeinformasjonen. Desse blir rekna ut som skilnaden mellom
        blå og luma eller raud og luma:
      </para>

      <para lang="en;de;fr;no">U=B-Y</para>
      <para lang="en;de;fr;no">V=R-Y</para>

      <para lang="en">
        From the three generated components, Y, U and V, the individual
        color proportions of the basic color can be calculated again later:
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Aus den drei erzeugten Komponenten Y, U und V können später wieder die
        einzelnen Farbanteile der Grundfarben berechnet werden:
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Par la suite, les trois signaux R,V,B sont recalculés à partir des
        trois signaux Y, U et V:
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        Dei individuelle fargeproporsjonane blir rekna ut frå dei tre
        komponentane Y, U og V:
      </para>

      <para lang="en;de;fr;no">Y + U = Y + ( B - Y ) = Y - Y + B = B</para>
      <para lang="en;de;fr;no">Y + V = Y + ( R - Y ) = Y - Y + R = R</para>
      <para lang="en;de;fr;no">Y - B - R = ( R + G + B ) - B - R = G</para>

      <para lang="en">
        Furthermore, because of the structure of the retina of the human
        eye, it turns out that the brightness information is perceived at a
        higher resolution than the color, so that many formats based on
        the YUV color model compress the chrominance to save bandwidth
        during transmission.
      </para>
      <para lang="de">
        Weiterhin ergibt sich durch den Aufbau der Netzhaut des menschlichen
        Auges, dass die Helligkeitsinformation in einer höheren Auflösung
        wahrgenommen wird als die Farbe, so dass viele auf dem YUV-Farbmodell
        aufbauende Formate eine Komprimierung der Chrominanz vornehmen, um
        Bandbreite bei der Übertragung einsparen zu können
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-yuv" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        En outre, comme l'œil humain a une meilleure résolution dans la
        luminance que dans les couleurs, beaucoup de systèmes basés sur YUV
        en profitent pour comprimer le signal de luminance pour économiser la
        bande passante lors de la transmission.
      </para>
      <para lang="fr">
        Plus détails sur Wikipedia
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-yuv" />.
      </para>
      <para lang="no">
        På grunn av måten auget vårt oppfattar informasjonen om lysmengda
        betre enn fargane, vil mange av modellane baserte på YUV-modellen
        komprimera krominanssignala for å spare bandbreidde i overføringa.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
