<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-08-17 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-04-09 KoSt: added 'no'
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050930 de replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
  050829 de added by axel.wernicke
-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-dog">
  <title>
    Difference of Gaussians
  </title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Edge Detect</secondary>
    <tertiary>Difference of Gaussians</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Difference of Gaussians</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      Overview
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
          Applying example for the <quote>Difference of Gaussians</quote>
          filter
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg" format="JPG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Original image</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/edge-taj-dog.jpg" format="JPG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Filter <quote>Difference of Gaussians</quote>
          applied</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      This filter does edge detection using the
      so-called <quote>Difference of Gaussians</quote>
      algorithm, which works by performing two different Gaussian blurs on the
      image, with a different blurring radius for each, and subtracting them
      to yield the result. This algorithm is very widely used in artificial
      vision (maybe in biological vision as well!), and is pretty fast because
      there are very efficient methods for doing Gaussian blurs. The most
      important parameters are the blurring radii for the two Gaussian blurs.
      It is probably easiest to set them using the preview, but it may help to
      know that increasing the smaller radius tends to give thicker-appearing
      edges, and decreasing the larger radius tends to increase the
      <quote>threshold</quote>
      for recognizing something as an edge. In most cases you will get nicer
      results if Radius 2 is smaller than Radius 1, but nothing prevents you
      from reversing them, and in situations where you have a light figure on
      the dark background, reversing them may actually improve the result.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      Activating the filter
    </title>
    <para>
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Edge detect</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Difference of Gaussians</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>
      Options
    </title>
    <figure>
      <title>
        Gaussian Difference filter options
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/diff-gauss-options.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Smoothing parameters</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Radius 1 and Radius 2 are the blurring radii for the two Gaussian
            blurs. The only constraints on them is that they cannot be equal,
            or else the result will be a blank image. If you want to produce
            something that looks like a sketch, in most cases setting Radius 2
            smaller than Radius 1 will give better results.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Normalize</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Checking this box causes the brightness range in the result to be
            stretched as much as possible, increasing contrast. Note that in
            the preview, only the part of the image that is shown is taken
            into account, so with <guilabel>Normalize</guilabel>
            checked the preview is not completely accurate. (It is accurate
            except in terms of global contrast, though.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Invert</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Checking this box inverts the result, so that you see dark edges
            on a white background, giving something that looks more like a
            drawing.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
