<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<sect2 id='plug-in-dog' lang="en;fr">
  <title lang="en">Difference of Gaussians</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Difference of Gaussians</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <mediaobject lang="en">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref='../images/filters/filters-edgedetect-dog.png' format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="fr">Généralités</title>   
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is located at
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Edge detect</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Difference of Gaussians</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      This filter is new in GIMP 2.2.  It does edge detection using
      the so-called "Difference of Gaussians" algorithm, which works
      by performing two different Gaussian blurs on the image, with a
      different blurring radius for each, and subtracting them to
      yield the result.  This algorithm is very widely used in
      artificial vision (maybe in biological vision as well!), and is
      pretty fast because there are very efficient methods for doing
      Gaussian blurs. The most important parameters are the blurring
      radii for the two Gaussian blurs.  It is probably easiest to set
      them using the preview, but it may help to know that increasing
      the smaller radius tends to give thicker-appearing edges, and
      decreasing the larger radius tends to increase the "threshold"
      for recognizing something as an edge.  In most cases you will
      get nicer results if Radius 2 is smaller than Radius 1, but
      nothing prevents you from reversing them, and in 
      situations where you have a light figure on the dark background,
      reversing them may actually improve the result. 
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Smoothing parameters</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Radius 1 and Radius 2 are the blurring radii for the two
            Gaussian blurs.  The only constraints on them is that they
            cannot be equal, or else the result will be a blank
            image.  If you want to produce something that looks like a
            sketch, in most cases setting Radius 2 smaller than
            Radius 1 will give better results.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Normalize</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Checking this box causes the brightness range in the
            result to be stretched as much as possible.  Note that in
            the preview, only the part of the image that is shown is
            taken into account, so with "Normalize" checked the
            preview is not completely accurate.  (It is accurate
            except in terms of global contrast, though.)  
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Invert</term>
        <listitem lang="en">
          <para>
            Checking this box inverts the result, so that you see dark
            edges on a white background, giving something that looks
            more like a drawing.  
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </simplesect>

</sect2>
