<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<sect2 id="gimp-tool-cage">
  <title>Cage Transform</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Cage Transform</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Cage</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
    The Cage tool is a special transforming tool allowing you to select the
    transforming area by setting anchor points by free hand drawing similar
    to the way you do it with the Free Select tool. The tool adds
    nothing to the image until you confirm the transformation by pressing the
    <keycap>Enter</keycap> key.
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>

    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Transform Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Cage Transform</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-cage.svg" contentwidth="16px" />
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap>
            <keycap>G</keycap>
          </keycombo>
          keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-cage.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Normally, tool options are displayed in a window attached under the
      Toolbox as soon as you activate a tool. If they are not, you can access
      them from the main menu through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Windows</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tool Options</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      which opens the option window of the selected tool.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Create or adjust the cage</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When activating the Cage Tool this option is selected. You can now
            click in the image to make anchor points around the desired area.
            If you need to add anchor points at a later stage, you click on
            this option.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Deform the cage to deform the image</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> switch to this option automatically when the
            cage outline is finished. Now you are able to drag the anchor points
            around in the image and even outside it to transform the picture.
            The transforming starts when you release the mouse button.
          </para>
          <para>
            You can activate more than one anchor point by holding down the
            <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while clicking on the points. You can
            also select more points by holding down the mouse button while
            drawing a rectangle around the desired points.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fill the original position of the cage with a color</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the transforming action results in empty areas these areas will
            be filled with color if this option is checked. It looks like the
            color is picked from the start pixel of the cage line.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Using the <quote>Cage Transform</quote> tool</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Cage Transform Tool example</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/cage-1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>The cage area selected</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/cage-2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>Transformed</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      When clicking on the cage icon in the toolbox the cage option is set to
      <quote>Create or adjust the cage</quote>. You are now able to draw a cage
      outline in the image by successively clicking around the area you want to
      transform. Click on the starting point to finish the selection.
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> will then do some mathematics and activate the
      <quote>Deform the cage to deform the image</quote> to allow you to drag
      the points on the line to deform the cage and the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      The selected point(s) turns to a square. Drag the points around in the
      image to transform it. The transforming will occur every time you release
      the press on the mouse button. The transforming may take some time so be
      patient especially when working with large images.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you desire to add more points to the line you have to select the
      <quote>Create or adjust the cage</quote> in the tool options dialog.
      Put the points on the line and switch back to the <quote>Deform the cage
      to deform the image</quote> to transform the image or layer.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the work is done, press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key to confirm it.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
