<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2019-05-05 j.h: add Highlight opacity cursor
  -->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-crop">
  <title>Crop</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>Crop</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Crop</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Image</primary>
    <secondary>Crop</secondary>
    <tertiary>Tool</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The Crop Tool is used to crop or clip an image. It works on all the
    layers of the image, visible and invisible. This tool is often used
    to remove borders, or to eliminate unwanted areas to provide you with a
    more focused working area. It is also useful if you need a specific image
    size that does not match the original dimensions of your image.
  </para>
  <para>
    To define the crop area click and drag with the mouse. A highlighted area
    will appear that shows the crop boundaries. To move the whole crop area,
    click in the middle and drag the rectangle. Resizing can be done by moving
    close to the borders. The mouse cursor will change and you can drag either
    one side, if you are in the middle, or two sides, if you are in a corner.
    While you are changing the drag area, the size of the cropped area and
    the aspect ratio will be shown in the status bar.
  </para>
  <para>
    When the mouse becomes the moving cross-hair, you can use the keyboard
    arrow keys to move the crop rectangle. Holding the
    <keycap>Shift</keycap> key down allows to move by increments of 25 pixels.
  </para>
  <para>
    To finalize cropping, click inside the crop rectangle or press the
    <keycap>Enter</keycap> key.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      By default the image canvas size
      isn't changed after cropping. The Tool Options of the Crop Tool have a
      setting <guilabel>Delete cropped pixels</guilabel> that can be checked
      to make sure the canvas size is also adjusted to the cropped area.
    </para>
  </note>
  <tip>
    <para>
      You can use <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-guides">Guides</link> to
      position the crop area. Make sure that the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Snap to Guides</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      option is checked.
    </para>
  </tip>

  <sect3>
    <title>Activating the Tool</title>
    <para>
      There are different possibilities to activate the tool:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From the main menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Transform tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Crop</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                  fileref="images/stock-icons/gimp-tool-crop.svg" contentwidth="16px"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          in the Toolbox.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By pressing the <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
          keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Key modifiers</title>
    <para>
      When you maintain click on the crop rectangle, handles
      disappear and
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key toggles to the
          <guilabel>Extend from Center</guilabel> option,
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          holding down the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key toggles to the
          <guilabel>Fixed</guilabel> option, which makes some
          dimensions fixed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>Options</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Tool Options Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-crop.png" 
format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="../about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Selected layers only</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option will make crop affect only the selected layers.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Delete cropped pixels</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When checked, the canvas size is adjusted to the cropped area. By
            default this is not checked, which means that after cropping the
            layers have been adjusted, but the canvas size is still the same.
            This is to make sure you don't remove anything by accident.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Allow Growing</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option allows the crop or resize to take place outside the
            image (or layer), and even the canvas. So, you can give the size
            you want to the resulting image. Transparency will be used if
            there is no material to crop.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Example for <quote>Allow Growing</quote></title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/crop-grow-1.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>An image on a big canvas</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/crop-grow-2.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  The option is checked. The crop rectangle extends outside
                  the canvas.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/crop-grow-3.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>The resulting image.</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Expand from Center</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this option is checked, the crop rectangle expands from
            the first pixel you clicked taken for center. You can toggle
            this option with <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> while drawing the crop
            rectangle.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Fixed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can also access this option by holding down the
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while drawing the crop rectangle.
            This option offers you several to make drawing
            the crop rectangle respect fixed dimensions, or their ratio:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Aspect ratio</guilabel>: That's the default
                possibility. Width and Height keep the same ratio they have
                in the original image, when drawing the crop rectangle.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Width / Height</guilabel>: Only Width or Height
                will remain fixed. The value of this dimension can be set in
                the text box below; it defaults to 100 pixels.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <guilabel>Size</guilabel>: Both Width and Height will be
                fixed. Their values can be set in the text box below, in the
                form <quote>150×100</quote> for example. The crop rectangle
                will adopt these values as soon as you click the image. On the
                right, two buttons let you choose a
                <guibutton>Landscape</guibutton> (widthwise) or
                <guibutton>Portrait</guibutton> (upright) format for the
                crop rectangle.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Position</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These two text fields contain the current horizontal and vertical
            coordinates of the upper left corner of the selection. You can use
            these fields to adjust the selection position precisely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Size</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These two text fields contain the current width and height of
            the selection. You can use these fields to adjust the selection
            size precisely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Highlight</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you enable this option, the selected area is emphasized by a
            surrounding mask to make visual selection much easier.
          </para>
          <para>
            The dark area opacity can be set using the <guilabel>Highlight 
            opacity</guilabel> cursor.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Guides</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With this menu you can select the type of guides that is shown
            within the selection to make the creation of a selection easier,
            respecting <emphasis>Photo composition rules</emphasis>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Six options are available:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>No Guides</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Center lines</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Rule of thirds</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Rule of fifths</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Golden sections</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Diagonal lines</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Auto Shrink</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Auto Shrink button will attempt to locate a border, in the
            active layer, from which to draw dimensions from. This option
            only works well with isolated objects contrasting sharply with
            background.
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title>Auto Shrink example</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/toolbox/autoshrink-1.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  An image with a sharp limit in it and a crop rectangle.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/toolbox/autoshrink-2.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para>
                  After clicking the Autoshrink button, the crop rectangle
                  has been shrunk to fit the sharp limits.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shrink merged</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option works the same, with Auto Shrink or not. It uses the
            pixel information from all <emphasis>visible</emphasis> layers,
            rather than just from the active layer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
