<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.5.0//EN"
          "website.dtd" >
<webpage id="help">

  <head>
    <title>Help us</title>
    <keywords>GIMP, Manual</keywords>
  </head>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      There are several ways to get involved by helping us improve
      GIMP's documentation.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url='#translate'>Translate</ulink> the User Manual.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write new or improved <ulink url='#content'>content</ulink> for the
          User Manual.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write <ulink url='https://www.gimp.org/tutorials/'>tutorials</ulink>
          for the website.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Give feedback on the current User Manual and
          <ulink url='https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help/issues'>
          report</ulink> incorrect or missing documentation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <note>
      <para>
        More information on helping out with GIMP in general is available
        <ulink url='https://www.gimp.org/develop/'>here</ulink>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="translate">
    <title>Translating</title>
    <para>
      If you are interested in translating the manual the best way to start is
      going to <ulink url="https://l10n.gnome.org/module/gimp-help/"
      title="Damned Lies">Damned Lies</ulink>, register an account and apply to
      be a member of the language team for the language you want to translate.
      You can then start translating the po files of GIMP's manual found
      on that website.
    </para>
    <para>
      The current progress of each translation can be found on our
      <ulink url='index.html#gimp-latest-online'>main page</ulink>.
      Detailed information about the progress for each separate file is
      available on the already mentioned
      <ulink url="https://l10n.gnome.org/module/gimp-help/">gimp-help</ulink>
      page of Damned Lies.
    </para>
    <para>
      If your language isn't listed yet as being translated, then please
      contact us on
      <ulink url='https://www.gimp.org/discuss.html'>IRC</ulink>,
      or open an issue on our
      <ulink url='https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help/issues'>issue tracker</ulink>.
      We will then add your language and shortly after the relevant files to
      translate will turn up on Damned Lies.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="content">
    <title>Improving the User Manual</title>
    <para>
      If you would like to help out writing and improving our documentation,
      then our <ulink url='https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help'>gimp-help</ulink>
      repository is the right place to start.
    </para>
    <para>
      Preferably you build the most up to date manual yourself, or check
      the latest <ulink url='https://docs.gimp.org/2.10/en/'>online version</ulink>.
      The source of the manual can be found in XML files in the
      <ulink url='https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help/-/tree/master/src'>/src</ulink>
      directory. Find a topic that interests you or that needs updating and
      start writing.
    </para>
    <para>
      You could also take a look at our
      <ulink url='https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help/issues'>issue tracker</ulink>
      to see which documentation issues you can help with.
    </para>
    <para>
      Our User Manual is written in Docbook XML files. Some knowledge of
      Docbook and XML in general is useful, but if you look at the structure
      of the documents that are already written, it should not be too
      difficult. If you are uncertain about something, you can always ask, see
      the links below on how to contact us.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="contact">
    <title>Contacting the Documentation Team</title>
    <para>
      It would be a good idea to subscribe to messages that have the GIMP or
      documentation tags on
      <ulink url='https://discourse.gnome.org/'>Gnome's Discourse server</ulink>.
      Note: when asking a question on Discourse make sure you add tags for GIMP
      and documentation (or i18n if it is related to translations), or we may
      not see your message.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most of the GIMP developers can also be reached on the
      <ulink url='https://www.gimp.org/discuss.html#irc-matrix'>#gimp IRC channel</ulink>
      on irc.gimp.org. The best chances to talk are usually during European
      evening hours, but be patient, getting an answer can take a while. Note
      that there is no need to ask if you can ask a question: just ask.
    </para>
    <para>
      For specific documentation questions you can also open a new issue or
      comment on an open issue.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="submissions">
    <title>Submitting your changes</title>
    <para>
      Before you can send us your changes you should have a Gnome Gitlab
      account and fork the gimp-help repository. For each new issue you work
      on, please make a separate branch. When ready push your changes to
      your branch and then open a merge request (MR).
    </para>
    <para>
      We will then look at your changes and possibly suggest or request further
      changes. If everything looks fine, your MR will be merged into our
      documentation. Note: we are all volunteers here, so be patient. Getting
      back to you can take time. Most of the time we will get back to you
      within a week, but sometimes it will take considerably longer.
    </para>
    <para>
      Make sure that the e-mail address connected to your Gnome GitLab account
      receives notifications when someone comments on your MR. Notification
      settings can be changed in your Gnome GitLab account.
    </para>
    <para>
      More info on
      <ulink url='https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp-help/-/tree/master#tips-for-contribution'>
      contributing</ulink> can be found in our repository.
    </para>
  </section>

</webpage>
